yep
can anybody people hear what i'm saying
or you're good
awesome so i just want to get started
with similar to last week where we asked
you about
the util lab i just want to get started
by asking a little bit about cisco lab
since that was due
on thursday so if anybody just has
like something particularly interesting
they found about the lab or a nasty bug
that they found or
just a silly mistake they made anything
you want to share about the syscall lab
that'd be
that'd be great i somehow managed to
delete the part
from where from fork where you have to
copy over the mask so i had that working
and then i changed something else and
then i tested it
your audio is like cutting out i think
oh it is sorry
you heard me
i hear you oh okay um
yeah i guess so basically i deleted
somehow
the copy of the mask and then my my fork
didn't work anymore so then i was just
like i did that
how does it not work so spend a lot of
time figuring out
what i did wrong and i realized i just
deleted that line somehow
is anybody having trouble hearing luca
or is that on my end
i think it's on your end yeah i hear him
fine
this must be on my end
sorry maybe that'll work better now
can you hear me now perfect okay great
i was worried that i was just talking no
no no
it seems to be on my end all right
awesome will anybody else have anything
they'd like to share about you
our a syscall
anything particularly interesting or was
the lab
absolutely horrendous and you think we
should cut it out of the class
never do it again i have something
apparently the order of things matters
which is a general statement
uh so i tried to determine
the mass computation inside the syscall
function
before determining whether i actually
needed to do the tracing
and so all the sys calls were getting
correctly traced except the trace call
and i was really getting disturbed by
that until i think it was david who
pointed out you know you should do the
computation after you
you should trace she's like ah that's
all right i'm glad you were able to
catch that
uh yeah order does matter um especially
for page tables you'll find i think that
order
matters there as well and generally
throughout the class
paying attention to the order of things
will be important
it's good to not overwrite things in
page table
also had something which i'm actually
still
confused about um well i
had a lot of debugging print statements
in the kernel code
i then ran the trace thing with
all of the bits set so basically tracing
all the system calls and
i think i saw a lot of
tracing for the print statements in the
kernel and then
because and then i assumed that my
prints
my print apps were trying to
read and write to the console but that
to write to the console but then
i was wondering why are we
i guess i'm just confused why we're able
to use printf in the kernel
yeah i'm not uh i haven't looked at the
printf code
recently but i think there's a file uh
printf.c that you might be able to look
at if you want to
figure out what was going on there so i
think the printf function should be
implemented in there
at least our version of it i don't know
perhaps one of the
one of some of the other core staff
might know what's going on
the the print ups in the kernel
shouldn't show up as
in your traces because printf in the
kernel doesn't call any system
calls yeah that's what i
thought maybe then maybe the tracing was
not from that
yeah i don't think it is from your
printers in the kernel
okay
okay well unless anybody has any other
burning comments about uh cisco i think
we can
uh get started with lecture for today
we'll be talking a little bit about
the uh process of converting c2 assembly
and processors and this is more of kind
of a practical lecture today or at least
that's the aim so the goal here is
to get you all familiarized with
risk five the processor the assembly
language
and the calling conventions for risk
five
and this will be important in not not
super important for a page table but
certainly for the traps lab which is
will be assigned later this week this
will be essential for
debugging and implementing things
because you'll be working
quite intimately with trap frames and
the stack and things like that
so that's the that's kind of the goal
for today and
my first aim was to and this might be a
little bit of review
from 6004 or any other computer
architecture theme classes that you may
have taken in the past
but i just want to go over briefly kind
of
see the c language how we get to
assembly
and maybe a little bit about processor
so throughout and then
of course throughout this lecture feel
free to interrupt uh with any
questions that you have so
uh you know we have our normal main
functions in c
you know they do something maybe they
print something
then they exit and this all looks
uh well and good but as any of you are
aware from 6004
processors don't actually understand the
c
language rather they understand what we
call
assembly or more specifically they
understand the binary encodings of
assembly
and so this here i've circled a picture
of an actual risk five processor from a
sci-5 board
and when we say a processor is risk 5
that means that it understands the risk
5 instruction set
so every processor has an associated isa
or instruction and that's kind of the
set of instructions that make sense to
that processor so
every instruction has an associated
binary encoding or an op code
and when a processor is running and it
sees a particular
encoding it knows what to do and so
you know this processor on this board
happens to
understand the risk 5 assembly which is
what c code is compiled to so the
general process of getting
c code to actually run on your processor
is we start with c
it gets compiled to assembly and there's
some linking and things like that that
happen between the step but that's
we're not a compilers class so and then
the assembly will
then be translated into binary and so
this is
the object or
dot o files that you see
so if you've ever paid attention to
what's inside of your lab directory
after you run make qmu you'll see a
bunch of dot o files lying around
and those are the actual object files
that the processor understands
and the asm files you've also seen um
you haven't really written any but
if you recall from syscall usas.pl is
compiled to a file called
usys.s and so dot s files
are assembly language and so you've seen
you've certainly seen some risk five
assembly and if you took double 04
i believe you you've also seen a good
amount of assembly language
and assembly looks in general much less
structured than
c so you'll just see lines after line
after line
of instructions you know you'll see
simple things like add
malt etc
and so on and so forth and this doesn't
have there's no
um nice control flow there's no loops
there are functions but not in the sense
that you might remember know from c
you know we see labels as opposed to
true function definitions
and assembly so it's it's a much lower
language and there are plenty of other
languages that are also compiled to
assembly so
um the same process holds true for
things like c
plus plus um
you know any any language that's
compiled will go to the same
assembly language at the base
and uh and so that's that's kind of the
basic process of getting our
computer to actually understand the c
code that we're writing
but you'll notice that we've been
referring to
risk five assembly
throughout the course and the processor
is risk five and that's because
uh it's important because there's many
different kinds of assembly so
it's unlikely that you're using risk
five
yourself like you're not going to be
running linux on it
uh instead most modern computers will
run
on what's called x86 or you'll sometimes
see it as x86 64.
and this is this is a different isa
this is a different instruction set it
looks pretty similar to risk five
but this is what you see in kind of your
personal computers often
so if you use an intel so
intel cpus implement x86
and i believe amd also do
and this is a relatively important
distinction between the two they're not
quite as similar as they may
look at first and that comes down to the
fact that risk five is what we call
as a risk the risk part of risk five
refers to
a reduced instruction set and
x86 64 is what's called a cisc
or complex instruction set
and there's a couple of key differences
here one
is just the number of instructions that
are present in x86
64 in fact one of the big motivations
for writing um for for
making risk five was how
many uh instructions we we actually have
in the intel kind of handbook so for
reference there's
three full books
that encompass the isa and
some statistics i think there's
new instructions have been added at a
rate of three instructions
per month since x86 64 was added
it was uh first published in the 70s so
i
believe there's like north of uh 15 000
instructions
in x 86 64. and risk five on the other
hand
the assembly for risk five can be nicely
contained within two documents and so
kind of going off of that we don't
expect you
in this course to memorize every single
risk five instruction
but if you are interested or you ever
find yourself confused by what a
specific instruction
is or does if you go to the course
website
and we look under the references tab
under risk five we give you the links to
both the privileged
and unprivileged instruction sets so
this is kind of the document
that gives you a whole bunch of
information about the isa
but you'll note that like this is 240
pages
and this is 135 pages so it's
significantly significantly smaller
than uh the x86 instruction set that's
one of the the nice things about
about risk five so we have
in risk five we have uh fewer
instructions
and not only that the instructions are
simpler
so what i mean by that is that
there are many instructions in x8664 and
by instruction i'm referring to
something like at or malt or sub
um in x8664 there's plenty of
instructions that do
more than one thing so they perform some
complicated
uh set of operations and then get you
the result
and that's uh not not the case with risk
five uh risk five instructions tend to
be
smaller in scope and so they take you
know it's less cycles to run each
instruction than maybe x8664 is and this
is just a trade-off that the designers
chose to uh
chose to undertake um there's nothing
or you know there's no
canonical reason why a reduced
instruction set
is better than you know a complex
induction
instruction set they each have their own
uses
um and so on and so forth and another
another cool thing about risk five as
opposed to
x86 is that this is open source
so it's one of the only open source
instruction sets on the market so that
means anybody can develop a board for
risk five
and it was it came out of a research
project from
uc berkeley and so that's kind of where
risk five started
and since then it's been picked up and
supported by a number of companies
uh you can find the list online but you
know there's tons of big companies that
are interested in supporting an open
instruction set and actually i think
quite recently there was an announcement
made by
sci-5 who are sort of the premier
board manufacturer for risk 5 processors
that they will
be releasing a board for
personal computers that should
ostensibly you know a risk five
processor designed to run linux for
personal computers
and i think that that's been released in
the last week or two the
announcement about it um so if you're if
you're curious if you're
find yourself you know absolutely you
know i want to use risk 5 after i finish
6s081
hopefully by that time there will be a
processor available that you can run
linux on on your own computer
but even in your day to day lives you're
most likely using reduced instruction
sets even if you don't realize it so
the arm assembly so that's
arm this is also a reduced instruction
set
and arm is implemented by
qualcomm the the snapdragon series of
processors
so if you have an android phone
you are most likely
running a reduced instruction set
and even if you're using ios ios i think
i forget what the name of it is but
apple
has some has some version
of of arm that they also implement in
their own processors
that runs on ipads iphones and most
mobile apple devices so you know reduced
instruction sets are present
all over the place and if you're looking
for a risk five in the real world
uh you know outside of your qmu
you'll be able to find that in uh like
integrated devices so it is present
it's not as it's certainly not as
ubiquitous as something like x8664
but it's it's uh yes i
yes i think apple is as lucas just said
in the chat i think apple is moving max
to arm i believe that's also the case
there's been in the last few years
there's definitely been a push towards
reduced instruction sets
given given how big the intel isa has
gotten
and the reason why intel's isa is so big
is because they're
very concerned with backwards
compatibility so if you write
you know a modern intel processor can
run the same
instructions that intel code from you
know
30 40 years ago was written in so they
don't really deprecate any instruction
so that they maintain backwards
compatibility
and risk five is more modern so that's
not a worry risk five is also so if we
jump back to those manuals risk five is
unique in that it's divided we have
what's called the base integer
instruction set which all risk five
processors
uh if we have fifth so gabriel asks in
the chat if we have 15 000 instructions
is it nearly impossible to efficiently
pipeline them
why do we need so many i like i was
saying we need so many for backwards
compatibility reasons it's up to you to
decide you know whether you
think that that's super important but
many of those instructions i think a ton
of them are also
eaten up by cmd instructions which are
their own
kind of special class of things um
you won't i i've never seen intel
assembly code that makes full uses
full usage out of the 15 000
instructions but mostly this comes from
from a need for backwards compatibility
and cmd but
like i was saying so risk five has uh
what's called the base
integer instruction set which uh
contains all of the normal add and
multiply
things and then processors can choose to
implement a number of other modules
which you can see along the side here
it's probably impossible to read on your
screen but for example
if you want a processor you know that
supports standard extension for single
precision floating point
then you can include the f module and
this makes it easier for risk five to
support
um backwards compatibility because if uh
you can just say you know what set of
the modules do i include and support
and the compiler can choose then the
compiler can say okay you know
this processor is telling me it supports
these modules so i can only compile this
code with these modules
okay bibx says it seems that the only
advantage of using x86 instead of risk
five processors is the kind of
performance you can get
however that performance comes as a
massive cost and complexity and
potential security
my question is why are we still using
x86 instead of moving to something like
risk five
uh well the big answer is that is the
world has run on x86
for i i don't have a great answer for
why
risk five is pretty modern too so
the world as a whole pretty much runs on
x86 so if you suddenly
start converting your processors
to risk five you run the risk of uh
you know losing support for a bunch of
important things
also there are like intel does do
interesting things within their
processors
it's like security wise there are
enclaves and intel processors and
there's things that um
they've been doing in recent years to
try to try and give you extra
added security and uh some of those
instructions that intel does implement
which are hyper-specific
can be really efficient for certain
computations uh and so they have so many
instructions that there's often you know
a perfect instruction for a situation
that may be more efficient than
than what exists within risk five but a
more practical answer is that risk five
is relatively new and we just don't
you know nobody's really making
processors for personal computers i
think the
sci 5 announcement is super recent um
and
they're kind of the first people to be
doing that so on a practical level
that and the inability to run all the
software design for intel
is is my best answer
so we've been now chatting a little bit
about assembly so i just wanted to
take a look at some actual assembly code
so here is uh the
c code for what's below so this is a
simple function that has an accumulator
we loop from zero to n and we
sum up all the numbers from uh from zero
to n
and then return that value and uh
at its simplest level you know this is
the easiest kind of assembly that you
can get out of compiling that program
if you actually go into your own
computer and you write the c
code and you try to compile it you will
end up with something
that likely looks quite different and
that's true for a variety of reasons we
haven't
some of which we'll get to and some of
which are compiler specific
so modern compilers make a large number
of optimizations
um within when they compile your c2
assembly and so your assembly
instructions may look different
for instance while you're debugging in
gdv you may come across something that
tells you that it's
some variable has been optimized out and
that means that the compiler decided it
didn't need that variable
uh and so that'll be gone effectively
from the program
but yeah and it's at its most
straightforward
we're moving uh the value that's in a
zero to t
zero we're setting a zero to zero and
then
we are just adding what's in t zero to a
zero
for every iteration of a loop until t
zero reaches zero
and that's all that's going on in this
piece uh amir your hands erased
yeah i was wondering what dot section
dot text
and dot global do global means that you
can
include this from other files so if we
actually hop into
uh let's see def.h
this is the file that you're uh will if
you aren't already you will become quite
familiar with this
includes basically all of the functions
within the kernel that you may want to
be using
and uh within here you know we can see
that in my
my file i've included the definitions to
these functions
and so that dot global make sure that
that these these functions can be called
from other places
and dot text just says this is code
so if you recall from figure 3.4
in the book so that's if we go
to the book
and we go into page tables
process address space so in here in this
diagram
that's the same thing this is text so it
just means code
that answer your question okay thanks
and so if we want to run let's say we
have some assembly
also if you ever find yourself
interested in
what the kernel looks like we can go
inside the after you compile you can
look in the file kernel
kernel.asm and this is the full kind of
assembly for the kernel
of xv6 and each of these numbers on the
left here
is a label that tells you where in
memory this
in this instruction will be and that'll
come in quite handy
and so here is the here's the actual uh
here's the actual assembly code and you
can see the labels for the functions
and where they're declared so this is
this is a can be really really useful as
we're debugging code
and hopefully i'll be able to show that
in a second
but for now we'll jump back to this
first function
sum2 and we'll just see how we can
examine that
inside of gdd so the first step is i
have my two windows here
what's the difference between asm and s
files
um i'm not 100
certain they're both assembly i think
the dot asm file includes a bunch of
extra annotations that aren't included
in dot
s so usually when you compile your c
code to
dot s you'll end up with something that
doesn't include all of those line
numbers and things like that so
if you're curious about how we get the
dot asm file i think the makefile
um will tell you the exact steps used to
get that and so
if we're we're in our terminal we have
our two uh two windows
so the first thing to do is of course uh
get qmu up and running so we can
start it within gdb mode so now we're
we're frozen here
and then we can start gdb uh
and what uh what what what uh professor
crasher showed last week
and which i think some people were
excited about if you type tui
enable you get this nice window which is
empty for now but will come in
quite useful as you're debugging so we
can set a breakpoint and i should note
that all this code is living inside the
kernel none of this is in user space
so we don't have any of those annoying
problems setting breakpoints so i can
set a breakpoint
in the function sum2 and then just
continue running
and run that function and now
so the first window that you see in tui
is the source window
uh yes as david is saying those those
numbers on the left of kernel.asm
are really useful when you're debugging
things and you get an address
it'll tell you so you can see now even
here we can see that the program so pc
here in gdb
is the program counter so we can see
this address 8 0 0
so on and so forth if we go into
kernel.asm
and we search for that specific address
we can see that it's the
uh well it comes up twice because it's a
function call but if we look here this
is that address
it's the top of the sum2 function so
if you see any time you see one of these
um
all the kernel addresses will look
something like 0x8000
some numbers those uh those addresses
you can jump straight into kernel.asm
and find the exact
line of assembly where the problem is
occurring and then you can set your
breakpoints accordingly
but for now uh that top window in tui
is source and if we want to look at
specifically the assembly we can do
layout ngdasm
and that'll give us all of the assembly
instructions
and we can also look at the registers if
we type layout reg we'll get assembly
and registers and if you find yourself
you know wanting to scroll through
things
now that we have three windows we need
to specify which one is focused so if i
want to look through all the registers
i'm going to focus
reg and now my focus is on the register
window so if i
move the arrow keys or scroll it'll
start scrolling that window
so for now we can focus on the assembly
window
and once we're here we can see all of
the things uh
so let's see we can see in the registry
register window we can see that t
0 contains this value we can see that a0
contains this value
and as we step through the assembly we
can watch
see okay t 0 just got the value of a0
which was
5 and it's nicely highlighted the
register that's changed
here and we can just keep remember if we
if we push enter we get the
most recently executed instructions so
we can go through
all right we set a0 to 0 and now we can
just kind of watch ourselves go through
this loop
and sum up the values
and again this is like a complete you
know toy function
and then we can continue and you know
live our lives and if you're ever
curious about
what kind of breakpoints you've set or
you lose track of what you were doing
if you type info break or break points
you can see all of the breakpoints that
you've set in your code
and you can even see okay this
breakpoint has already been hit one time
and you get lots of useful information
doing that
if you don't want to have the register
window but you do want to look at the
registers
info reg or info registers or ireg or
any of the
numerous gdb shortenings
will bring up the register window as
well
um so with that is there any are there
any questions about
gdd um simple ones i know it's been
um there's been lots of post sump shots
about it so
now is a good time to just ask uh some
straightforward we'll i'll be showing
more
usage of ddb what command did you use to
open the multiple windows so i use tmux
so i can show just from scratch uh if we
go
here and i open a new terminal so here's
just a blank terminal
if you type tmux and this is available
on athena
i'll address the next question in a
second so now i'm in tmux which you can
tell by this
green bar at the bottom and if you want
to
get so there's a couple ways you can do
multiple windows in tebow tmux
uh if you're so you can type control bc
and uh i know that's sometimes if you're
used to using emacs that will make a lot
of sense but
um normal people who don't use emacs
that's hitting control and then d and
then hitting
c on its own afterwards that will get
you a second window which you can then
navigate between with control b
and then p control b and then n to go
previous and next
yeah and david just posted a t-much
cheat sheet which is useful
and if you want to split the windows i
think it's ctrl b and then
the percent sign will split them um
vertically and then sing a double
control b
and then double quote we'll split them
uh horizontally
and so that's how we get them and if
we're in this state we can use control b
and o to jump between our windows
so that's what's that's how i got the
multiple windows yeah i don't care
um and then ahmed asked
why is this displaying assembly
addresses again instead of c line
numbers
ah so because the the function
so if we go back to the assembly
function
this is implemented entirely in assembly
and not at all in c
and so there just aren't any associated
c line numbers for this
um if we were to
set a breakpoint so if you type delete
you'll delete all your breakpoints uh so
i cleared the old one if i now set a
breakpoint in
demo one so that's a c breakpoint and
continue
and run this now if i go here and type
layout split
i'll get the c and the assembly um or if
i just want the c
source i can do layout source and i'll
just get the c
so that's uh that's what's going on it's
just a quirk of the fact that this
doesn't have associated c code and so we
don't see seedline numbers
any other any other questions about gdb
tmox and that that sort of thing
so layout split is the one that you use
to bring up this extra window of the
source and assembly and so on right
yes yes so layout uh if you do layout
split that'll get you
source and assembly layout source will
get you just source
asm we'll get you just assembly and the
registers are their own thing where if
you type layout reg
i think yeah that'll bring up the
registers but
unfortunately i don't know of a way to
get
the register of the assembly and the c
code all at the same time outside of
using inforeg with layout split
i have a question um so when we set the
break point uh add a line right it
displays the address of the like in this
case break point to add
0x 354. um
what any instruction might have multiple
uh
any like line of code in c might have
multiple instructions
so which one does its uh show i believe
it shows the first one
and uh it's to you for the person who
asked to
start the tui it's i think it's tui
enable not enable to ui sorry i think
um yeah again there's like a hundred
cheat sheets out here for gdb
and for tmux as well so if you ever find
yourself lost
i t gdp even has its own inbuilt um
its own thing called apropos so if you
look for apropos
tui it will actually show you all of the
commands that involve tui
so yeah uh this can be quite useful but
it can also be a little bit overwhelming
um if you do apropos dash b it'll give
you even more information i think
um i don't remember i i don't use it
often myself but if you if you do
find or if you forget the exact way to
type the command in in gdb and you don't
feel like googling it apropos
will will uh often be able to find
exactly what you're looking for in
addition to a whole bunch of stuff you
weren't looking for
um yeah so
that can be quite useful gdp is
extremely well documented as well
so um yeah if you ever find yourself
lost
you know google is your friend um
so now that we we've kind of been over
assembly and
and risk five and these sort of things i
want to dive a little bit more into the
specifics
um of what you you really need to know
for the
lab coming up and also is this will be a
little bit of review from the document
that you've all
of course as diligent students read
through thoroughly
uh in preparation for this lecture
um so you know this table will of course
be uh wildly familiar to you all
and uh from from both double o4
and from what you've read and this is
the table of registers and
registers are little you know locations
on the cpu or on the processor
pre-defined that it can use to store
values
and this is important because assembly
operations
if we remember from the assembly code
the assembly doesn't operate on memory
it operates on registers so when we do
add when we do subtract
we're operating on registers um
and so what you'll often see as the
pattern for
for writing assembly is we'll have some
kind of a load
so we'll load some value
to a register and that value can be from
memory
or it can be from another uh register
and and here i'm referring to load in
general not the load instruction
um and then we'll operate
so we'll perform some operation on the
register
and then if we care about the result of
that operation outside of the return
address
we will um will store that
register to somewhere
to some locate that will store that
register to some location
do that in memory or to another register
and so that's that's uh generally the
way things work and and registers are
the absolute fastest way to perform
any sort of calculation uh or to access
any value and that's why
um it's important to use them and also
why
we prefer using registers over using
memory so if you remember from
the reading when we call functions so
you can see here that registers
a0 to 7 and
in general when we speak about registers
we
we will be referring to them by their
abi name um
not only is it less confusing it's just
a standard and it's also the way that
you'll write assembly code
um this you know these actual numbers
are not super important
the only case where it does matter is
for the compressed version of risk 5
instructions
and if you want to know more about that
feel free to read up about it the basic
idea is that risk
5 normal instructions are 64 bits
but there's also a compressed version in
which instructions are 16 bits
and we use less registers and the
registers we use in that case
are 8 through 15. those are the
registers that are available to us
so i think somebody had a question about
you know why is this s1 register
x9 why is it separated from all of the
other s
registers and my guess is that that's
why
that we separated from all of the other
ones because it's available
in compressed instruction mode whereas
s2 to 11 or not
and so that's the idea so that's that's
for compressed but outside of that
registers will always be referred to by
their
abi name and so a0 to a7 are used for
function arguments
but if we have a function that takes
more than the eight arguments that those
registers give us access to
we do need to use memory but that's this
is kind of an illustration of the fact
that we don't want to use memory when we
can use registers
we only we only use a memory if we have
to
and this uh this column here the saver
column
this is also extremely important when
we're discussing registers caller versus
callee saved
and um the terms are
i confuse them regularly caller and
callie they only differ by one letter
the easiest way that i found to remember
them is that
caller saved registers are not
preserved
across a function call
so and callee saved registers
are preserved what i mean by this
is that
a caller saved register can be
overwritten
by the function so let's say i have
function a
which calls function b any registers
being used by function a
that are caller saved call function b
can overwrite when it gets called and i
think a good illustration of this
is the return address because you know
you can see that the return address is
caller saved
and that's important because every
function needs to use the return address
so when a calls b it's important that b
be able to
overwrite the value in the return
address hence why it's caller saved
and callee saved registers are just our
convention that we use
the frame pointer is important for that
reason
and those are preserved across the
function calls so basically any register
that is caller saved
the function that is making the call
needs to worry about those registers
and if they're calling saved the
function that is being called
needs to worry about preserving the
value in those registers
and again you know i i regularly confuse
the two
and find myself returning to this table
to remind myself about what they do
and so you know you if you remember from
the reading
all of these registers are 64 bits wide
so they have 64
places where we can put things and
the various data types are made to fit
into those 64 bits
based on the calling convention so if we
have a 32-bit integer
depending on how it's whether or not
it's sign extended you know we'll either
add zeros or ones to the front of that
integer
in order to make it 64 bits to put in
these registers
so before we move on uh does anybody
have questions about
registers or things things of that
nature
i have a question can you have a
can you put a return value in a1
yes it's a good question so um i think
in theory
you can the reason why we say a0 to a1
is if a function returns a long long
which is 128 bits
so if you remember from the reading if a
function argument is 100 is more than
a pointer word and so when we refer to
the prior word size we're saying 64 bits
so if we have something that is twice
the size of a pointer word
um we can put that in a register pair
and so the same convention holds true
for return addresses where if we have
something that's
the size of twice a pointer word we can
stick that in a0 and
a1 and use that as the return address i
think you'll run into problems if you
only try to put something in a1
make sense thanks
why are the registers not like
continuous
so why is like a zero and one separate
from sorry no that's a that's a bad
example what's why is s1
separate from s2 why are the a's in
between like is there any point in that
yeah so uh i mentioned this briefly
earlier but there is a
compressed this is a guess i don't i
don't know for sure
but there's a compressed version of the
risc 5
instructions which are 16 bits in size
as opposed to 64.
and you would use that to try and
make your code take less space in memory
and when you use those 16-bit
instructions you only have
accesses to registers 8 through 15.
so i think s1 is separate from s2 to 11
because they want to make it clear that
s1 is available to you
in the compressed instruction mode
whereas s2 to 11 aren't
um and the reason you know i don't know
why they picked x
x eight to 15 but i suspect that that's
just they looked at a bunch of code and
we're like oh these are the most
commonly used registers
[Music]
any other questions
i had a question um besides the frame
pointer the stack pointer and all
uh i i don't know why we would need more
call
callista registers but we do have
like a bunch of them yeah the s1s
to 11s those are just for i believe used
there for freedom for the compiler
or for the programmer to use um so there
are maybe there are certain cases where
you want
you want to guarantee that something is
still around
after after your function call the
compiler can choose to use
s1 211 to do that
i don't have like on hand a specific
example of where that's useful
but i'm sure it shows up where
having a callee save value is important
but these are basically basically you
know programmer or compiler's choice to
use
that's 1 to 11.
and i should note that these these
floating point registers they're for
floating point arithmetic
i as far as i'm aware you won't see them
in this class
and so you don't really need to worry
about them
okay so we started talking a little bit
about function calls
and so with that i want to
move us into discussion of the stack
so this is this is
we're talking about the stack and
the stack if you've seen it likely
before
the reason why the stack is important is
it
it's what keeps our functions
organized and sane and it's what allows
and what makes functions work it what
it's what makes return
work and it's also uh where often we'll
find ourselves
saving our registers and things like
that
um
so here i've
given just a pretty simple um
[Music]
layout of what a stack looks like and so
each of these
boxes here is what we refer to
as a stack frame
and every time we get
which are generated by function calls
um every time we call a function
that function makes for itself its own
stack frame
and which is in which it uses itself and
does that by moving around the stack
pointer
so here's the stack pointer and this is
uh
and it's very important to remember with
stacks
we start from high addresses
and we grow downwards to
low addresses so the stack grows down
always
and so you'll see that the arithmetic
for a stack pointer is uh
is usually done via subtraction when we
want to make a new stack frame
in assembly so the stack grows downwards
and stack frames for a function contain
saved registers local variables
um also like i like i was saying if you
run out
of argument registers additional
arguments will show up on the stack
and so not at stack frames are not all
the same size
even though they are in this diagram
that's not the case different functions
have different numbers of local
variables different safe registers
so on and so forth and so stack frames
will be different sizes but the two
things that you can definitely count on
which are important is that uh the
return address will always be
on the first thing and the frame pointer
the previous frames frame pointer is
also going to show up on the stack
at a predictable location so
the two important registers here are sp
which you know as we discussed
is used for this is the bottom of the
stack
or generally you know it's the location
of the stack
and then fp is our also important
register and this points to the top of
the current
frame and this is important because
that means that the return address and
the previous fp
will always be at a fixed location
from the current frame pointer so that
means that
if i want to find my return address or i
want to find the previous frame
i can always get to those values by
looking at the current frame pointer
and the reason why we store the previous
frame pointer is to allow us
to jump back so once this function
returns we can move this into fp
and all of a sudden fp again will go
from pointing to this
this stack frame to now pointing to this
stack frame
and so we use the frame pointer to
manipulate our stack frames
and make sure we're always pointing to
the one corresponding
to the correct function
and that's that's kind of how things uh
how things are done
and uh the these pieces of the stack
um need to be created by assembly
and so everything's everything in that
calling conventions
document that you read about that's all
um enforced by
effectively by the compiler so the
compiler adheres to
the calling convention and it's what
generates the stack frame
it generates the assembly code that
makes our stack frames look
correct so often at the top of a
function you'll see what's called
a function prolog
and then there will be the body of the
function
and then there will be an epilogue
that shows up after that so this is kind
of like
what an assembly uh
function will often look like and we'll
take a look at that
now so here i have another function
something so you you'll you'll note that
studently that sum2 did not have
any of these things that it it should if
it was a proper function
and this works fine because it's simple
enough so it does all of its
computations on
a0 and so things are things are good and
we're also not it's a it's a leaf
function
so you'll see if you see the term leaf
function that's a function that doesn't
call another function
and the functions are special in that
they don't need to
worry about saving their own return
address
or saving really any of the caller saved
registers
because they're going to they're not
going to make another function call so
they don't have to be
as careful some then double on the other
hand
is not a leaf function so you can see
here it calls
um sum2 and so it does need to include
that
that prolog and so we see here that we
are subtracting
16 from the stack pointer so we're
making space
on our stack we're storing the return
address
for something double on the stack and
then we make our call to sum2
and after that all this this function
does is it calls sum2 and then
doubles the result doubles the result
turned by some two and here you can see
the
epilog so we load the return address
back in to ra and
delete our stack frame and then jump out
of the function
and so we can run that to make sure it
does what we would expect
we can go here
we can run so if we run demo2 or demo
one we got a result of 15
for the sum and i'll tell you that demo
two just uh just calls something double
and indeed
you know it happily doubles the sum
returned by some two and
so a question i have for for anybody
what happens if we uh delete
this prologue and f so what happens
if we just have this as our function
something double can anybody predict
what's going to happen
i mean one thing is that some then
double wouldn't know
the return address that it should return
to so upon calling
sum to that's going to override the
return address to be
some then double so at the end of thumb
then double
it's not going to return to its original
call
yeah exactly um and we can see that
that's what happens
again so if we
exit out of this and we exit out of this
and we recompile with now with our
broken function
we can take a look at exactly what's
going to happen so we can actually
set our breakpoint for something double
and set up tui and let it continue so if
we now run demo 2
okay we're at some then double and
again this is an assembly only function
so we're going to want to look at it in
assembly so we'll do layout asm layout
reg because it's important what's in the
registers in this case
and you'll see that gdb knows a whole
bunch of extra information
and so we can see that
we can see that ra currently so the
return address currently points to demo2
the plus 18 so
it points effectively into the function
demo2
and now we can run um we can just kind
of step through our function and see
what happens so we've called sum2
and immediately we can see that the
return address was
overwritten by sum 2 to now point to sum
then double plus 4
which makes sense you know that's what
we'd expect if we go back into our code
we call sum 2
and so sum2 should return to uh to here
and now we can step through
[Music]
you know so on up and uh
then we get back into
whoops the wrong s
okay so now we're here and now when sum
then double returns
as exactly as amir pointed out um its
return it has not restored its own
return address
and instead its return address is still
the one that was used by
um sum two and so we will
get into an infinite loop where we just
keep doing this over and over and over
again and we'll never terminate from it
and so this is a i think this is a good
illustration of why it's important to
keep track of our caller versus callee
saved registers
and hopefully this also shows that you
can use kind of gdb to
debug these sorts of these sorts of
problems so let's
restore what we had and we'll go
into some other demos to talk about
to illustrate uh somebody asked why are
we subtracting 16
that's to put space to get our stack
frame
so this is subtracting 16 from the stack
pointer so it's moving it down basically
in memory
um moving it down so that we now have
space for our own stack frame and then
we can stick stuff there
so because uh at this point in fact we
don't want to override what's at the
stack pointer uh
why not four is just um
well four
we need to do 16 because instructions
are 64.
uh yeah i guess i guess we wouldn't
don't actually need to do 16 but that's
generally what you'll see
um you'll generally just see i don't
think yeah
you you can't you can't do four because
uh you need eight so four doesn't work
but i think you can do
uh you need the instruction size
and the size of the register right so
registers are 64.
yeah and then so the convention why you
usually see 16 is because if we jump
back to our document
usually we have the return address and
the frame pointer
uh but we're not doing that here because
we're being uh
not super careful with our assembly
so normally if we if we look in
i'm sure if we look in kernel.asm we'll
see
yeah so if we look in kernel. we see
it's also you know 16 this is generally
what you'll see with the compiler
um okay so
now we can go back to this
fixed our function and now we can look
at some c
code
all right so here we have demo four
which is just basically um a copy of a
main function
like a imitation of the main function
so we have our args
which is an array of strings and we have
dummy main which takes
uh the number of arguments and the
arguments frame
and just prints it out um for us
and so that's all that's that's all
that's happening here it's pretty
straightforward
uh if we set a breakpoint in
dummy main
and we pop over let this
okay we let this continue and we we
start this
we run down four okay so we now we've
hit
um dummy main and there's a couple of uh
important things to uh remember about
uh that you can use gdp for regarding
stack frames
so if we type i so again that's info
if we type iframe we can see a whole
bunch of uh
useful information about the current
stack frame
so we can see we're at stack level zero
level zero means
it's uh earth is down in the call stack
that we can go
and the frame is at this address
the program counter which is okay that's
all well and good
we have a save program counter as well
and if we
again if we take this address and we
jump
into kernel.asm
[Music]
and we search for that address we can
indeed see
that that address is inside of
inside of demo form which is exactly
where we expect
the program to return to and it was
called by a frame at this address source
language c
you know that's that's nice to know and
then we have the argument list
also starts at this address of course
in this case we have most of our
arguments in
registers uh and then we can even see
what
args are we mean rxc is three
and rv is this address
and if we want to more in depth examine
things we can look at things like
info arcs which will tell us information
about the arguments of the function
we can look at but more importantly
we can type if we type back trace or bt
works as well
we get a full back trace of all of the
stacks uh the all of the stack frames
from the call stack so you can see you
know something questionable happened
here that's when we invoked a system
call um then we get to the user track
function
then to the syscall function then to
sysdemo
then to demo four and then finally to
dummy main
and if we want to investigate any of
these stack frames
more in depth we can do frame and then
whatever number
uh is along the side here so let's say i
want to look at what was my stack frame
when six calls are called i can go to
frame three and so now i'm
inside of gdb i'm looking at that stack
frame so if i type info frame
i can get this and here we get a lot
more
a lot more information we have a bunch
of saved registers
we have some local variables we don't
have any arguments to this function
we can see where the program counter
where we're supposed to jump back to
um all kinds of things like that so this
is super super useful for
if you're debugging things and in fact
it's so useful we make you implement
um your own version not nowhere near and
as
in depth as what udb tells you but we're
one of the exercises on the next lab
will be to implement your own
backtrace helper function for use when
debugging things inside the lab
and so back back traces uh is quite
useful and then if we type frame 0 or we
go back to
where we were supposed to be
and if we want to investigate you
probably noticed it's not super helpful
you know rv is a string
as an array of strings and so we just
get a ref we just get a
an address for where that's actually
stored
and if we want to look at what's in
there there's a couple ways of doing
this
uh the easiest is uh if we type print p
is for print and then if we d
uh dereference the address so we go look
at what's at the
address we can do that and
you know as you would expect we get the
first element of that array because
when it tries to print a string it'll go
you know as c says it'll go in until it
hits the null character
so we get foo which is the first element
that array and if we want to get more
things
we can put in the length so if we do
and then a number it'll go up to a
certain index so then we can see
both of the strings here and
you know again gdb is quite smart so we
can even
use rxe to print out the whole argument
array
and so all of that information is
available to you
however you you want to get it so gdp is
a super powerful tool
why does gdb or sorry why does the
compiler sometimes
optimize out rg c
and rgb that has happened to be before
yeah uh that just means that the
compiler found a more efficient way
likely it just got rid of the variable
and it's doing all of its operations
um directly you know via regis it might
be doing all of its operations on a0 for
example
it might just be doing all of its
computations on the return address
it's pretty common to see something like
that if you um
if it's a variable that's not you know
necessary uh if you you know we don't
let
we don't give you control over the
compiler but if you ever find that in
your day-to-day
you can try setting the optimization
flag for the compiler to zero
um but even then you know the compiler
will do we'll do its we'll do some level
of optimization
uh your hand is raised yeah
um what's the address besides
that dollar one or dollar two you know
like before foo
or bar uh dollar this
yeah so what's that address is that the
address where
foo is probably yeah
but but then rv points to some other
address shouldn't those be the same
uh so our rv is on the stack
and it'll so the reason why
you know if you look at these addresses
we can see that they're in the kernel
uh just by the eight zero zero zero
um which makes sense because we they're
declared statically right so in demos if
i go here they're declared here
and so they're basically they're sitting
somewhere in the kernel and they're all
car stars
args arcs or rv is an array of car stars
and so i imagine that each element
points to points to
its own string right so it's an array of
pointers
crazy
i also have a question about this uh the
dollar three version of
the array has if i look
at these addresses the first one is
suffixed by
38. second one is suffixed by 40.
the third one is 48 which is
not uniform even though the length of
each of the three arguments
is three so why why are they different
uh not in i'm not 100
certain my guess is that this is an
attempt to align things
um right so to get them on a reasonable
alignment and it is uniform in hex as
people are pointing out
oh right yeah yeah that makes sense
oh oh yes i see it now yeah right
thanks so you'll sometimes see where
straight things are
laid out strangely where there might be
two things at strange offsets and that's
just
because not everything is uh naturally
the same size
um okay any other questions
okay uh we can skip the fifth demo
and so another useful function that we
get
from gdb are
instead of just break points uh there
are also watch points and we can also
set
conditional break points so
i'll just briefly go over that
we run demo six so we can set
inside this function we can watch so we
can set a watch point
um i think here you'll see um
yeah so here you'll see what uh luca was
talking about where
we see that sum has been optimized out
likely because it's just being
put in a zero or something we can look
even at the assembly for this right so
we can do layout
splits and yeah indeed we can see that
it all just being uh
it's all just being done on the stack it
looks like to me
oh no it's all just being done in s0
s013
so here you can see that the the
compiler decided even to use the quality
saved registers
and so we can set things like we can do
watch
on i
or we haven't declared i yet because
we're not inside
we're not inside the for loop so if we
step through the c instructions now if
we do information for the locals we see
we get i
we can even watch um watchpoint on
sum so now anytime that sum changes
we'll actually get a notification so we
can continue
and then we'll get a delete here because
some
has been removed so we can't we can't
actually watch it
we can even do things like break points
on sum2 so this is a conditional
breakpoint
if well let's actually see what is i
currently so i is currently one let's
say
i think my loop is breaking and whenever
i is five
well if i want to specifically debug
that case i can set a breakpoint
on sum2
if i equals five
so now we have this breakpoint and if we
continue along
we'll get to some two and uh we can see
that it actually printed out
the first couple values and so we only
break now on some two
if if i if we hit that breakpoint
condition
and so that's uh this can be again this
can be useful if you want to debug
specific edge cases of your code
and watch points can be useful if for
instance you think that something
shouldn't be changing
but you suspect that it is or you think
that something is going wrong
every time you change a certain variable
and so that's that's uh that's one one
usage for that
and uh the last thing i want to talk
about today is structs
structs are pretty important and they'll
come up in
um in the labs often
and also so what asks
i'll talk a little bit about the way
structs are laid out in memory
and so a struct is basically um it's a
continuous contiguous area of memory so
if we have some struct
and we have like field one field two
field three when we make that struck
those fields are going to be
aligned next to each other in memories
and you can kind of think of this
like an array but f1 f2 and f3 can all
be different types
and uh we can uh
pass them as functions usually they're
past uh pass them as arguments to
functions
usually they're passed by reference so
here i've made a struct person
with two integer arguments and
i'm passing them passing a person as an
argument to print person
and uh printing out some of that
information
so if we hop into gdb and let's delete
all of our breakpoints and watch points
and now we can set a breakpoint at
person and let's continue
and run seventh demo
we can see that now we're here and so if
we type iframe
we can see that we have an argument p
and indeed we can if we do print
p if we can even tell that it's a struct
person
at this address and
we can if we dereference it
gdb will tell us exactly what p looks
like it has id 1215
age is 22 and just to show kind of how
things are
laid out we can take this address
and we do x hd at this
i address exactly
so if we again so we can use this to
debug
our structures in
in the code we can take a look at what's
going on
with structures this way so gdb is a
super powerful tool
not just for you know stepping through
code but also for examining
all kinds of potentially problematic
pieces in your code and looking at
arguments and stack frames and things
like that
and this will be hopefully will be
useful in the next lab
when you have to work with um with stack
frames and with assembly code
so that's that's mostly what i wanted to
talk about today so
with the last kind of seven minutes of
lecture
i'll open it up to any any other
questions that you guys have
i had a bit of a tangential question who
is in who manages the the creation of
compilers
from like to get from c to various uh
instruction set architectures is that
the creator of the instruction set
architecture is it a third party
something like that
um i believe that it is
not the creator of the instruction set
so it's often a third party
so the two big c compilers that you'll
see refer to are gcc
which is maintained by i think the gnu
foundation
and uh c lang or llvm
which is its own thing so i think you
know you can find
i believe lovm is even open source so
you can find
um you can you can find the code
specifically that does this
uh when a new instruction set is
released such as risk five
that calling convention document as well
as all of those instruction documents
uh i think you're careful but i assume
there's like a high level of cooperation
between the compiler designer and the
instruction set designer
um but yeah short answer is i i believe
it's a third
third party who does it likely with a
lot of cooperation from the people who
make the instruction set
risk five is probably risk five might be
an exception where because it came out
of a research project
they may have written the the compiler
for it themselves
as well i i don't think intel has
for example has input in uh in gcc or
llvm
other questions
okay well uh thanks
for listening in that case and i guess
we can uh
we can end the lecture here uh with five
minutes to spare so
have a nice rest of