all right um
welcome to six s081 operating systems
um i'm robert i'll be co-lecturing with
franz
and david and nicholas for the tas
please during these zoom lectures ask
questions you can either
interrupt me by audio or enter something
into the chat window and
one of the staff will see an ask
question for you and by the way we'll be
recording these lectures
and we'll post the recordings later so
you can review them or for
people who can't make this time so they
can never like see the lectures
all right i want to start by um
laying out some of the goals of the
course so
number one is to um understand
uh the design and implementation of
operating systems
and you know the uh
design is sort of high-level structure
and implementation is really about what
the code looks like
and we'll be spending a lot of time with
both um
and in the interest of
getting a deep understanding of what's
going on you'll get hands-on experience
with a small
with a small operating system the xv6
operating system
and in addition to actually looking at
an existing operating system
you'll be in the labs get a bunch of
experience
extending the operating system modifying
improving its behavior
and writing system software that um it
uses the operating system
interfaces if it works an application
so um so this is what you're going to be
doing in the course
we're also interested in what the
purpose of the operating system itself
is as well as of the course
so for that i have a sort of list of a
couple of things which
um you know there's lots of operating
system
different operating systems out there
they typically have a common set of
purposes
one of them is to abstract the hardware
um that is you know what you're given
typically as a kind of starting point is
you buy a computer a computer as a cpu
in memory
but that's a very low level uh set of
resources
it's fantastic to have much higher level
um interfaces and abstractions that
applications can use
such as processes or file systems both
for convenience
and for portability another very
important
task of an operating system is to
multiplex the hardware
among many applications you might be
running
a text editor and a compiler or
maybe multiple different database
servers or something on your operating
system
it's fantastic to be able to have the
operating system run both of them at the
same time or all the things are going on
at the same time
without having them interfere that's
often called multiplexing
um because there may be a lot of things
happening on the operating system at the
same time it's it's critical that they
not interfere
unintentionally even if they have bugs
and that's
a task is called isolation the idea that
different activities should not be
allowed to interfere on the other hand
there are times when
different activities would like to
interfere we'd like to interact or
cooperate so
for example if i create a file with a
text editor
and i'd like my compiler to read the
file we definitely want to allow that
kind of sharing
so we want to allow sharing when it's
sort of what the user has in mind um
but in many circumstances the user
doesn't want sharing maybe you're logged
into
a time sharing machine like athena and
you don't want other people to read your
files
so we also need as well as sharing we
want to not share when we don't want to
which we could call security or a
permission system
or an access control system
another thing that people value in
operating systems is if you spend a lot
of money on hardware on a computer
you'd like your application to be able
to get the sort of full performance
that the hardware ought to be able to
provide
and you know a lot of that is just
application programming
but inevitably unfortunately some of it
is the operating system has to make sure
that
whatever services it provides
don't get in the way of applications
getting high performance
so you want to at least not get in the
way and maybe even help
applications achieve good performance
finally with most operating systems
have to support a wide range of
different applications maybe it's a
laptop
running a text editor maybe it's running
games
maybe your operating system needs to
support database servers or
cloud computation and usually because
operating systems are
quite expensive to design and build
people use the same operating systems
for many different tasks like linux for
example which
i'm sure many of you are running is used
in all of the situations i mentioned so
the same operating system really has to
be able to support
a range of often quite different uses
so we're hoping to be able to support um
sort of all these different goals
uh simultaneously um and we'll hear more
about all of them
during the course all right uh operating
systems
uh sort of people worked out a set of um
design ideas over the decades that have
worked pretty well
sort of ways of organizing things and
i'm going to lay out for you the sort of
classic
organization it's a sort of standard
deal for
uh for this course and
um is actually quite common around for
many operating systems so this is sort
of
you know os internal organization or
um the way i think about it is a
in terms of a draw a box for the
computer
um the computer sort of
comes with a bunch of hardware resources
which i'll put at the bottom maybe
there's cpu
and ram and a disk for storage
and maybe a network interface so this
sort of hardware that's
the lowest layer um so if at the top
we want to run various applications
maybe a text editor i happen to use
vi as a text editor if you're going to
run a c compiler
say cc you know if you run lots of other
things we're going to talk a lot today
about the shell which is the
command line interface so we have all
these different programs that are
running
and this is the sort of world in which
applications run is usually called user
space
and as distinct from that there's a
single program
um a special program that's always
running called the kernel and the kernel
is sort of the
guardian of the resources of the
computer it's what first
boots up you turn on the computer
there's just one of it it maintains data
to help it manage each of these
processes and the kernel also maintains
lots of data structures to help it
interface and all the different kinds of
hardware that
uh these user programs need to use
the kernel also has built in a bunch of
services um
and so for example there's typically a
file system implementation inside the
kernel that
implements things like file names and
file contents
and directories and understands how to
store
the files in the disk so your programs
are going to talk to the files inside
the kernel and the file system
implementation is going to
talk to the disk and in this course
what we mostly focus on is all the
things that have to happen inside the
kernel
and on the interfaces between user
programs and the kernel
as well as the sort of structure of the
software
inside the kernel so we care a lot about
these
services inside the kernel
[Music]
one of them is the file system i
mentioned there's also uh
management of processes each of these
running programs
is called a process and it has things
like its own memory for example
as well as a share of the cpu time
so kernel manages
processes as a kernel service
[Music]
the kernel manages the allocation of
memory the different processes need
different amounts of memory the kernel
multiplexes and divides up the memory
allocates the memory
among all the different processes
um the kernel as i mentioned
influenced the file system file system
really comes in two or three
logical or a bunch of logical parts but
for now we can think of it in terms of
managing file content that's what's
inside files figuring out where on disk
each file's content ought to live the
file system also somewhat separately
manages a name space each file has a
name
and there's a hierarchy of directories
every directory has a bunch of files in
it all that's managed
by the file system there's typically
some sort of security arrangement
maybe we'll call it access control
by which the colonel decides that you
know when a given process wants to read
use some resource maybe read something
from the disk or use some memory
the access control machinery inside the
kernel is what gets to decide yes is
that allowed is that not allowed
and that can get pretty complicated if
we're talking about time sharing systems
like athena systems where there's
you know each of these processes may be
run by a different user and
have different access control rules
applied to what it's allowed
to get at and in a real
full-blown operating system there's
turns out to be many many other services
you know there's typically some way for
different processes to talk to each
other
called inter-process communication
there's typically a whole bunch of
software associated with the network
things like the tcp ip protocols for
talking in the network
there's typically support for sound
cards there may be drivers for hundreds
of different disks and hundreds of
different network cards
so in a full blown operating system
there's a huge amount of stuff here and
this may run to millions of lines of
code
inside the kernel
so that's sort of a quick overview of
what's inside the kernel
we're also interested in how
applications interact with the kernel
and what that interface looks like
the
usual so this is the api
for the kernel
how applications get at the kernel
typically that's done with something
called system calls and these are things
that
look like function calls that programs
can make
but actually jump into the kernel and
execute a
system called implementation in the
kernel i'll talk a
bunch about that in the latter part of
this lecture for now just to give you a
flavor here
what a couple of different system calls
might look like in the source code
of an application
one might be that if you want if an
application wants to open a file
it make it calls the open system call
and tells the open system called the
name of the file
so maybe it wants to open a file for
writing called
out and it would be an extra argument
here saying one in this case saying i
want to write that file
and so this thing that looks like a
function call
if opens the system calls actually
special code that jumps into the kernel
and the kernel can retrieve these
arguments
execute some kernel code that implements
open maybe talks to the disk
and then returns a value and that's this
file descriptor
as fd stands for file descriptor which
is
the program can then use as sort of a
handle to refer
to this open file
if you want to write to a file the
system called
to do that is called write you have to
pass it one of these file descriptors
the same as was returned by open
um these are now arguments that are
passed in the system call
from the program into the kernel you
give it a pointer
to a buffer of characters so an easy way
to do that in the c
programming language which these
examples are written by is the double
quotes and then
the string the bytes of the string this
backslash n is a new line
and the third argument is the count of
characters
that you want to write and so this
really gets point passed as an address
in memory
so you're telling the kernel look please
write six bytes from this address
to the file that this file descriptor
refers to
a much more exciting uh system call that
you encounter is the fork system call
fork is the system call that creates a
new process
um and it returns actually creates a
process that's identical to the caller
and fork returns the an identifier the
process identifier or pid
of the new process it's actually a
little more complicated than that and
we'll
hear more about this so again these are
all look like function calls
but the system calls are special because
they jump into the kernel
that's just taste i'll see more later
well that is a sort of quick overview um
i want to just mention why i find
operating the study of operating systems
to be
both challenging and interesting
why you know why it's maybe worth
intellectually worth taking a course in
this area so one reason why it's hard is
that the
environment's unforgiving the
programming environment inside the
kernel is unforgiving because
you're
you're when you're programming when
you're modifying the kernel or extending
the kernel writing a new operating
system kernel
you're providing the infrastructure that
everybody else assumes is already
present to run their programs
right and everybody else gets an
operating system under their program
when they write ordinary application
programs but
when we build operating systems what we
get is the hardware underneath
our operating system which turns out to
be
more difficult to deal with in this
course we
we get to use a hardware simulator
called qmu
that you know simulates a cpu and a
computer and that makes life a little
bit better but
it's it's still a kind of a difficult
environment to program it
another reason why it's hard and
interesting is because if you're
designing an operating system you have
to satisfy a bunch of
tensions that require real design
thought
so one is that you'd like your operating
system to be both efficient
which often means that it sort of
operates at a low level close to the
hardware
but for ease of use and because real
live people have to write programs
that use your operating system we'd like
it also to be
provide abstract high-level portable
interfaces
and it's a neat trick to provide
abstract interfaces that are simple
um affordable but that are also
efficient
another tension is that we'd like to
provide a very powerful
operating system services so that the
operating system can shoulder a lot of
the burden
of running programs we'd like to
powerful
operating system services
but we also want to have simple
interfaces
that is we don't want tremendously
complex hard to understand interfaces
for programmers to use because
they're not going to understand them and
they may find it hard to use
um so this is really simple api and so
this is possible to do to provide simple
interfaces that have powerful machinery
inside them and so we'll always be
searching for
sort of simple interfaces that provide
powerful services hey robert we have a
question in the chat
uh what is unique slash different about
saying system calls jump into the kernel
i.e as opposed to a standard function
call that jumps to another function
well the colonel has the kernels um
a piece of code that's always resident
that has special privileges
that were that because it booted the
machine booted the kernel
um the kernel has special inter
privileges that can get directly at
all kinds of hardware like the disk
device that ordinary user programs can't
get at
so if you make a fun an ordinary
function call um
the the function you're calling doesn't
get it just doesn't get any special
privileges with respect to the hardware
whereas if you make a system call into
the kernel um
we'll talk about how this works but that
ends up um
as it when it jumps into when the system
call jumps into the kernel
the system call implementation in the
kernel then gets all these special
privileges so that it
it can modify all kinds of
sensitive and protected uh hardware
resources like for example getting
directly at the
hard disk we'll see a lot more detail
for all this
uh shortly okay so
a final tension that we wanna that all
operating systems need to satisfy is you
wanna give programs as much flexibility
as you can you don't want to constrain
them so you want to have very flexible
interfaces but you do need to constrain
programs somewhat because you absolutely
have to have some notion of security
you can't you we'd love for programs to
give programmers complete freedom but it
can't be complete can't be really
complete
because we don't want programs to get
directly at the hardware or to interfere
with other programs
or to sort of be able to interfere with
the operation of the
operating system itself so these are all
you know it's possible to do a good job
and we'll talk a lot about it but
it's always a bit of a puzzle to provide
sort of both of these
the properties in both of these columns
another thing that makes os design hard
and interesting is that
operating systems provide a lot of
features and a lot of services but they
actually tend to interact
and sometimes in odd ways they require a
lot of thought so even in the simple
examples i gave
with open and fork those two interact
actually if a program
allocates a file descriptor with the
open system call
and then that same program
forks and the semantics of fork
just turn out to be that you create a
new process that's a copy of the current
process
this file descriptor you opened
if that's truly to be a copy this file
descriptor still has to
um be present and usable in the child
and you know so that's to be thought
through that is the files the open and
filed scripters interact with fork in
this interesting way
and somebody has to figure out oh should
the child be able to
get at the file descriptors created
before fork was called
and the answer happens to be yes in the
operating systems we're going to look at
all right and so other things that are
turned out to be interesting
i already mentioned that operating
systems have to cater to a wide variety
of uses
the same os used both for database
servers and and smartphones for example
and operating systems as time goes on
the hardware that you run the hardware
you get with typical computers changes
maybe you get super fast ssd storage
instead of mechanical hard drives for
example
about 15 years ago multi-core computers
went from being rare curiosities to
being
pervasive and recently we've seen you
know order of magnitude speedups in how
fast networks operate
and so all these require rethinks um
periodically of how operating systems
are designed
now um so so those are those are sort of
intellectually why you might take the
course there's also some even more
practical reasons why you might be glad
to have taken this course one is if
you're interested in what happens inside
computers what goes on under
and saw under the hood sort of in secret
when you turn on your computer
this is a good course to take similarly
if you like infrastructure that is if if
you enjoy
building uh sort of services that other
programs can then use
this is of course essentially all about
infrastructure because that's that's
what operating systems are
if you ever need to spend a lot of time
tracking down bugs in
application code or tracking down
security problems
often that um involves understanding
what was going on inside the operating
system
because it's ultimately the operating
system that enforces a lot of security
and
when things go wrong it's sort of the
operating system that has to pick up the
pieces so
that's often involved in uh tracking
down bugs
and finally yes two more questions from
the chat so
the first is how important is it for
application developers to truly deeply
understand the operating systems they're
developing their applications for
do they necessarily need to be experts
you don't have to be an expert but if
you spend
um a lot of time developing and
maintaining and debugging applications
you'll eventually end up knowing a lot
about the operating system
whether you whether you meant to or not
it just
it just comes up and you're often forced
to understand
and the second question is do high-level
programming languages like
python use system calls directly are
there built-ins
slash wrappers for convenience a lot of
high-level languages are
sort of at one remove from system calls
that's absolutely true so
partially because a lot of languages
want to provide
portable a portable environment that
works on many different operating
systems so they can't necessarily commit
to the specific system calls of any one
operating system
um so i'm the answer the question i
think is if you use python
uh you're somewhat insulated from the
system call interface you know
internally of course python makes
has to make system calls to get its work
done and
certainly in python and many other
languages there is usually a way to get
directly at the system calls of whatever
your
operating system you're running on
and folks for questions you can just
feel free to jump in yourself and ask
questions you don't need to go through
the chat
okay um all right
sorry um
i'm going to spend a couple of minutes
now talking about
the class structure of
6 s081
before switching back to actual
technical content
so the uh there's a website for the
course which i don't want to write out
just now but it's
um you can find it by looking for 6s 081
on google
and the website um has
um the schedule uh
it has the assignments on the schedule
it has the lab assignments
um and it has the sort of information
about course structure like
the grading policy on it the other big
resource you're gonna want to keep track
of is piazza
i guess everybody who's here got here by
the way piazza but
as well as so we use piazza really for
two main things one is
as a way of people to be able to ask
questions about the lab assignments and
uh course staff will try to answer these
questions but
you should feel absolutely free to
answer each other's questions as well
and the other big thing that happens on
piazza if there's announcements if
there's any announcements about the
course
we'll put the announcements on piazza so
you should keep an eye on piazza for
announcements even if
you're not using it for lab help
the one of the big parts of the course
is that these lectures
the lectures will
cover basic ideas in operating systems
some of the lectures will be devoted to
detailed
study of the code in xv6 which is our
small teaching operating system
and so talk about how it works we'll
look at the code and sort of show the
code executing during lectures
and in addition before many of the
lectures there'll be assignments
reading assignments from a book that
sort of describes how
xv6 operates and why it's designed that
way
so you should do the readings before the
class so that you'll understand
the discussion in the class some of the
lectures are devoted to
background to help you do the labs sort
of explanations about c works of how the
risc 5 which is the microprocessor that
we'll be using
that you'll find helpful in in
understanding how to do the labs
and towards the end of the course i will
spend some lectures
discussing some operating system papers
um
research papers and and some classic
papers in the field
which uh you know we'll ask that you
read before the lectures and then we'll
sort of talk about the
papers in during the lecture for all the
lectures or almost all the lectures
we ask that you submit a question about
the reading
for the lecture before the actual time
of the lecture
which many or all of you did for this
lecture for which thank you
and we will read those questions to help
us
guide us about what to talk about and
we'll try to answer
as many of the questions as we can
although there's rarely time
unfortunately for us to answer all of
them
the next big part the course of the labs
there's a programming lab
do almost every week
and the point of the labs is to help you
get hands-on experience with
implementing and using operating systems
um the lab that's due next week
is actually about using using about
writing applications that
make the call the system calls we'll be
talking about um
whereas most of those labs after that
are involve you
either implementing basic operating
system features or adding
uh kernel extensions to the xv6
uh operating system the very last slab
and
one in which you actually add a network
stack and a network driver so you'll be
able to connect in over the network
to the operating system that you run um
you should if you have problems with the
labs uh there'll be office hours
that the um tas will hold in addition
you can
post questions to piazza and very often
you'll be able to get useful answers
from piazza
more quickly than from office hours
we welcome you discussing the labs
talking about the labs talking about how
to
design the lab solutions but we ask you
please do not look at other people's
solutions
for the labs please all the code you
write should be your own and
you shouldn't share code or look at
other solutions
the grading
for the course will be mostly determined
from the labs this year so 70 of the
grade will be
um uh based on
whether or not that your lab the lab you
submit passes the tests and we for
grading we run the same tests
um that we supply you so if your lab
passes the all the tests that we give
you then chances are you get full credit
for the lab
um 20 of the grade
um is going to be from lab check off
meetings
uh we'll for each of you we'll pick a
couple of randomly selected labs
and one of the teams will talk to you
and ask you questions about your
implementation just to make sure that
you really understand what's going on so
this
lab check-offs
there's um ten percent remaining
there's a question be like a
yes or no one or zero type of thing or
would they be
like could someone get like if they
answered some of the questions right but
not all the questions right would they
get
in between so they're great you know i
haven't thought this through
um there's certainly room for partial
credit but
it's not a it won't be binary it'll
definitely be
you can receive partial credit okay
all right um the last 10 is going to be
driven by the homework
and participation during lecture and in
piazza
there'll be no exam or quizzes
this year um and so what that means is
that most of the
you know ninety percent of the grade is
being driven by the lab so
you know you should spend a lot of time
in the labs
make sure that you start early and have
enough time to
complete them and work out bugs in order
to get full credit
and you know as a result of that this is
going to be a very kind of hands-on
software oriented course or any
questions about the
machinery of the course
uh we've got a couple questions in chat
so the first is a logistical question
currently 6s081 isn't listed as usable
for the systems concentration in the
are there plans added to the list of
classes later i think for that
because it's not an aags it's an aus
it can't be used to fulfill mn
requirements as it's not a graduate
level
class but
um and then we have is the only homework
to submit questions looking at the
calendar that appears to be the case
unless i'm forgetting something i think
that's the case
yes so
have uh are there gonna be cutoffs for
grades like x percent gets an a
y percent gets a b etc
no no um
you know we're going to try to
free student estimate um
our impression of how well you've
understood the material
and assign a grade based on that so
there's there's no predetermined cutoffs
all right anything else
all right just real quick for folks
in the chat uh asking about the
concentration requirement i'm not a
hundred percent certain
uh but six soa one is not it's like a
temporary number
before the class gets this official one
so it certainly won't be
uh listed anywhere if you needed to
fulfill a concentration i think your
best bet is probably to fill out a
petition
or to email somebody like katrina
lakerts
to see what the status is we don't
control
you know what what classes fill these
kind of requirements
unfortunately and for what language
we'll be using the class will be in c
all right um
all right for the rest of the lecture i
want to uh talk about how
um house what system calls look like to
applications
and you know since the system calls are
the
interface to the services that the
operating system provides it
it's actually pretty important what
those system files look like what
applications expect from system calls
and how they behave so it's sort of
worth understanding what the interface
looks like
you'll be using the system calls we talk
about in the first lab
and extending and improving the
implementation
internal implementation of these system
calls in subsequent labs
what i'm going to do is show some simple
examples
of little programs
that call system calls and then i'll run
them
and and next v6 for you um
i'm going to run them the xv6 is a it's
a unix
a simplified unix-like operating system
unix is a
old operating system sort of at least
intellectual basis for many
present day operating systems such as
linux and os x
so it's in very common use
xv6 our teaching operating system is
much simpler
it's sort of inspired by unix and has
the same overall structure but is
dramatically simpler than any real unix
operating system
and it's simple enough that hopefully um
you know
it would be relatively straightforward
for you to read all the source code
as well as read the book um in a couple
of weeks certainly during the semester
in order to
kind of understand all of what happens
inside xv6
x86 runs on the risc-5 processor
risc-5 microprocessor and this is the
same microprocessor that's the focus of
recent 6004
so many of you may actually know quite a
bit about the risk 5 instruction set
in theory you could run xv6 on top of a
risk 5 computer
and people have done that
but we're going to run it under the qmu
machine emulator so just to write this
down we got
our operating system is xv6
it runs on risk 5 microprocessor
and not just risk 5 microprocessor but
we assume a certain amount of
surrounding hardware like
memory and a disk and a console
interface for us to talk to it um but we
actually run
under the qmu
machine simulator so that which
runs under linux so that all of you can
actually
run xv6 without having to have hardware
okay
so i'm gonna switch to uh showing you
code
all right so um first thing is
i've uh set up xv6 on my laptop
um and i'm going to run it and type make
qmu which you'll find yourself doing
quite a bit during the labs
um which compiles xv6 it's written in c
so it's compiled with a
c compiler maybe i'll make
clean for you so you can see the actual
compilation
and i might type make qmu which has the
effect of
compiling and building xv6 kernel and
all the user
processes and then running them under
the qmu emulator
it takes a moment to run the compiles
and now we're up and running xv6 and the
dollar sign prompt you see is the shell
which is the command line interface to
xv6
modeled after the shell on unix which is
if you log into an athena workstation
it's the
it's like the shell that athena shows
you
x36 is itself tiny and it comes with a
small number of utility programs
and including for example the ls program
which i'm about to run
run ls and it gives me a list of all the
files in xv6 of which there are only
about two dozen
including things like grep and kill and
make deer
and rn which may be familiar to you as
uh as unix utilities
okay the first program i'm going to show
you to illustrate system calls
is um program called copy
um here's the source it's just a page
and so what you're seeing here is a
program that starts on line eight and
main
there's the sort of convention for c
programs it sits in a loop at line 12.
and over and over again it reads some
data
as input and on line 13 and then writes
the data just read
to its output on line 16. if i run copy
uh in xv6 just waiting to read input if
i
type some input and reads it and spits
it back out to me
so it's very simple program just does i
out
it's written in c as i mentioned um if
you're you don't already know c it's
worthwhile getting the
um standard c programming language book
by kernhan and ritchie
and i think there's a more full
reference to it on the
course website which explains to you in
a
very straightforward way how to program
and see
as i mentioned before read and write
this this program makes
two really three system calls read write
and exit are
system calls if you look at the call to
read on line 13
it takes three arguments the first
argument is a file descriptor which is
really a reference to a previously open
file
and the shell uh ensures that
when a program starts by default its
file descriptor 0 is connected to the
console input and its file
descriptive 1 is connected to the
console output and that's why i was able
to type to
this copy program and see the output
of course you know these file
descriptors are expected the program
expects these file descriptors have been
previously opened and set
up by the shell for it and this this
zero
one file descriptors is a pervasive unix
convention many many unix programs
expect to read
and file descriptor one and read file
scripture zero and write to file
description one
um the second argument to read is a
pointer to some memory
um where the program is asking the
operating system to read data
into that address and memory so that's
the buff argument
and line 10 allocates 64 bytes of memory
on the stack per read to read into
and the third argument to read is the
maximum number of bytes that the program
wants to read
and the size of buff says just 60
maximum
64 buckets so the recall reads up to 64
bytes from whatever
is connected to file descriptor zero and
that was my terminal in this example
the return value from read it either
repeat
it which may return the number of bytes
read
which would be six in the case of
me typing xyz y um
lead might be reading from a file if it
gets to the end of the file there's no
more bytes read will return zero
i know some other error occurred like
the file descriptor doesn't exist
read may return minus one and so
in many of these examples like on line
16 there
i don't my example code doesn't check
system call returns for errors
um but you should be more careful than
me um
uh the you should figure out how system
calls reflect errors is usually a minus
one return value
and check all system call returns for
errors
and if if you want to know what the
system call arguments and return values
are there's a table and
i think chapter 2 in the book that
explains all of the xv6
system call arguments and
return values the question regarding the
resist call what if we set the max read
bytes to
size of buff to one plus size of buff or
bigger
so what if we try to read more than the
size yeah then if there was
65 bytes to read then the operating
system would happily
we'll just copy those 65 bytes
to the memory that you provide and of
course
there's something else on the stack up
there maybe the return program encounter
or an argument or something
and so if you pass 65 then you're
inviting the colonel to
write junk um to an unexpected place in
your stack
and so that's a bug and it may cause you
for him to crash
or do something else unexpected um
so as a programmer you're you have to be
careful here there's nobody
writing in c with these kind of
interfaces there's
it's very very easy to write code that
the compiler is happy with and will run
but
absolutely does the wrong thing
so that's too bad but um that's the way
it is
okay uh one thing to note is that this
copy program and indeed the read and
write system calls
they don't care about the format of data
they're reading or writing
they just read them write and read and
write and this copy program
just deal with 8-bit bytes with streams
of 8-bit bytes
how you interpret them is totally up to
the application so the application maybe
parse these as data records or as c
source code or who knows what
the operating system um
it only thinks in terms of a stream of
8-bit bytes
okay so copy assume this code my copy
program assumed that the file
descriptors were already set up
um but we need to we need to have a way
to create file descriptors
and the most straightforward way to do
that is um
with the open system call and so here's
the source for a program that
called open that
uses the open system call a question
from the chat
what do you mean by a stream of bytes
i i i just mean that if a file contains
a bunch of bytes
then read and successive yes building a
file contains a million bytes
if you make a sequence of recalls each
for 100 bytes
it'll just read the first hundred bytes
and then the second hundred bytes and
then
the third hundred bytes um
that's all i mean
all right so this program um called open
first i'll run it for you
what it does is uh opens creates a new
file called output.txt and then writes
some
bytes to it and then it finishes so we
don't see anything because it
broke data to this file it opened but we
can look at this output.txt file that it
created
and see the ooo that it
wrote there so line 11 in the program is
makes the open system call gives it a
file name output.text and
the o underscore stuff um in the second
argument to open are
flags that tell the open system call
implementation in the kernel that we'd
like to create a file with its name
and that we're going to write it open
returns a newly allocated file
descriptor
and the file the script is just a small
number it's probably two or three or
four or something
and then we pass that same file
descriptor to write along with a buffer
and a number of bytes to write that
writes data to
the file that the file descriptor refers
to
what that file descriptor is actually
doing is indexing into a little table
inside the kernel the kernel maintains
state for each
process that's running each program that
you run and among other things the
kernel remembers a table for every
running process of index by file
descriptors
and the table sort of tells the kernel
what each file descriptor
refers to
a critical point is that each process
has its own
sort of space of file descriptors so uh
before running two different
processes two different programs and
different processes and they both open a
file they may actually get the same
number back as a file descriptor
but because the kernel maintains a
separate file descriptor for each
process
the same file descriptor number may
refer to different files
in different processes
any questions about open about this
little program
yeah we got a question in the chat a
question from someone not familiar with
c
uh how are these files being described
different from normalc
programs is it because we're only using
kernel calls i.e couldn't we also
open or write a file in python
i don't think i understand that it's a c
program that's opening and writing a
file
um okay
i think i'm gonna move on um
all right so
you um ask what actually happens when uh
maybe
the question is whether someone is doing
it in c
any different than doing it in python
minus the syntax
well it's it's not really um
there's certainly ways to um
python provides nice function calls for
opening
and doing all these things or opening
files for example
in reading writing files um they're sort
of a layer of
they're higher somewhat higher level
functions typically um not you know
pointers to memory for example um
and python does more error checking for
you
but when you open a file in python or
write a file in python the
python calls you make boil down
to system calls just like these
is that a good answer
i think so all right
all right um all right i've been
over here talking to the uh
xv6s unix like
shell and the shells what people often
call the command line interface
as opposed to some more graphical user
interface
the shell turns if you haven't used the
cell the shell turns out to be
a pretty useful interface for things
like system management of unix systems
it provides a lot of utilities for uh
messing around with files
and for programming development and for
writing scripts
to do all these things so you saw me
before run
i just want to demonstrate a few shell
features ordinarily when you type things
um you're telling the shell to run a
program so when i type ls what that
means is
i'm asking the shell to run the program
whose name is ls and what that really
means is there's a file
in the file system called ls that
contains some instructions
some machine instructions and i'm asking
the shell to run
the instructions that are in the file
called ls
run ls now ls what it actually does is
get a listing of the files in the
current directory and you can see up
there on the fourth line
that among the other files that
ls says exists in this list is a file
called
ls which is in fact the file containing
the instructions i just ran
the shell does a few other things for
you other than running programs
it allows you to redirect io so for
example if i say ls greater than out
what that means is
i'm asking the shell to run the ls
command but with its output redirected
to the file called
out and i run ls
we don't see any output because the
output all went out
um now i can out contains a bunch of
data
um we could the cat command
reads a file and displays the contents
of the file so
i say cat out i'm just going to see now
the now this is the saved output
of ls you can also run a command like
grep and i can give it an argument x and
what
grep x is the grep command searches for
patterns
again um if i run grep
x it's going to search for lines of
input that contain
x i can redirect tell the shell to
redirect its input from the file out
in order to look for instances of x in
that saved ls output
and turns out there's three files um
whose names
contain x's
um we're going to spend a bunch of time
with the shell
um it the shell is sort of the most
traditional
um and fundamental interface to uh to
unix
because when units was first developed
all there was was simple terminal
interfaces like the one we're using
and the main use of unix originally was
time
sharing a bunch of people logging into
the same machine much like athena
and talking to shells
a question about system calls and the
compiler
how does a compiler handle system calls
does assembly generated make a procedure
call to some code segment
uh defined by the operating system
uh there's a special risk five
instruction that a program can call that
transfers control into the kernel
so indeed when you write c code that
makes the system called like open or
right
i mean technically what actually happens
is open is a c
function in the c library
but the instructions in that function
are really
machine instructions it's not you know
open
the open function that we're calling
isn't a c function it's implemented
assembler
and the assembly code
consists of this special instruction
it's actually called e-call
on the risk 5 the special instruction
that transfers control
into the kernel and then the kernel
looks at the
process's memory and registers to figure
out what the
arguments were
all right um the next example i want to
look at is
an example program that calls fork
to create a new process um
so this is the very simple use of fork
at line 12
we're calling fork and what fork does is
creates a copy
of the memory of instructions and data
of the
calling process now we have two
processes with identical
memory fork the fork system called
returns
in both processes in the original
process
the fork system call returns the process
id which is a
an integer greater than zero for in the
original process
fork returns the process id of the newly
created process
and in the newly created process fork
returns
zero so we sort of break even though the
processes of identical memory
can break the symmetry of old versus new
process by the return value from fork
then in line 16 you can see code that
checks and says if
process id is equal 0 must be the child
we must now be running in the child
the course is two processes and in the
other process
in the calling process which is usually
called the parent the process id is
greater than zero
so the child will print child and the
parent a good parent
and then they'll both exit so when i run
for
um here's what we get
so it may look like garbage but what's
actually happening is that
after the fork both of these processes
are running they're both running at the
same time
um and qmu is actually emulating a multi
a multi-core microprocessor for me so
they really are running
at the very same time and so when they
produce output they're producing each
byte of their output at the same time as
the other process
is producing the corresponding byte of
its output so the outputs and the two
processes are
interleaved um you can see that they're
both typing f
um they're both going to type fork
returned
um so you can see the f from both of
them and the o for both of them and they
are for both them and so on
and one of them uh you can see the zero
at the end of that first line is
in the child fourth return zero um and
i'm guessing that the
in the parent four return 19 that is the
child's
process id is nineteen under exit six
that basically means the 19th process
that
was created since boot um and then one
of them prints
child and you can see the ch ild
and interleave with that is the other
one pretty parent
so this is sort of a silly use
of fork but we can see so vividly in
this output that
it's created two processes that are and
both of them are running
we're fork returning both processes and
they're both running
but also note that one printed child and
the other parent
so it's important that fork returns
differently
in the two processes
the question is the child process as a
result of fork always identical to the
parent process or could they be
different
i um
in xv6 are identical
except for the return value from fork
you know so the instructions are the
same the data's the same the stack is
is the same um and also both
processes you know the processes are
copies and
they both have their own separate
address spaces that is
you know they both have they both think
that their memory starts at zero and
goes on up from there
um but but it's different it's different
different memory um for the two of them
in a more sophisticated operating system
there are some details which we
definitely don't care about
um that may occasionally cause parent
and child to differ but in xv6 they're
the same except the return value
so the memory is the same in addition
the
file descriptor table is copied
so if the parent had some files open
then the child sees the same set of file
descriptors
although the child is seeing them in a
copy
of the table of file descriptor
information
and so we'll see in a moment that it's
quite important that
fork copies the table of open file
descriptors as well as the memory
okay so uh port creates a new process
but
when we run stuff in the shell um
the shell indeed creates a new process
to run each command that you type
but it needs to actually run the command
in it so you know if i type ls
we need to the shell forks to create a
process to run ls but
there needs to be some way for this for
that
new process actually run the
instructions from the ls program
to load those instructions from the file
called lx um
and the example program i mean i'll show
you in a minute
uh uses echo echo is a very simple
command that
just takes whatever arguments you pass
to it and writes them into its output
and i prepared for you a program called
exec
um which
uh run which makes the exact system
called which
replaces the calling process with the
instructions read from a
particular from the file you specify and
loads the instructions from that file
over the current process sort of discard
it discarding its current memory
and then starts executing those
instructions so
the call to exec the system call exec on
line 12.
it's going to have the effect of the
operating system loading the
instructions from the file called
echo into the current process sort of
replacing
the memory of the current process and
then starting to
execute uh those instructions and in
addition you can pass arguments command
line arguments echo
exec allows you to pass an array of
command line arguments
with just an array of pointers and see
line 10
set sets up an array of character
pointers which are essentially strings
and initializes that array to be
to contain the strings echo this is echo
and that's equivalent to calling running
the act with command with
the three arguments this is echo and so
when i want exec
indeed um i see this output this is echo
but
even though i ran the exact command the
exact program what the exact program
does is call it
the exact system call to replace itself
with echo and so it was really the echo
program
um producing this output
and uh something about the exact system
call that's
important for us is that um it exec
preserves
the current table of file descriptors so
whatever files descriptor zero one two
etc were referred to before exec they
refer to the same thing
in this new program whose instructions
we've loaded
another point is ordinarily exec does
not return
because exec replaces the current
is memory entirely um there's nothing
for exec to return to
so exact you know reads the instructions
from that file and executes them and
then that's it
um the only time exec returns is if some
error occurred
that prevented the operating system from
running that program for you
so for example if the program doesn't
exist at all
since the exec can't find a file called
echo for example
then exec would return negative one to
signal that you know something i'm wrong
it couldn't
couldn't find a file so ordinarily exact
does not return it only returns if
um the kernel couldn't actually run the
file for you
questions about exec one question in the
chat is what is the last
zero for in arc v
it marks the end of the array um
c is so low level that
there's no the c array
scheme doesn't have a way
for code to find out how long the array
is
and so to tell the kernel that um
you know we meant that the array
contains echo this is echo and nothing
more
um we put a zero as the last
strip as the last pointer each of those
strings in double quotes is actually a
pointer to some memory that contains
those bytes
that fifth element of the array is a
pointer whose value is zero
the convention is that a pointer whose
value is zero or what's called a null
pointer um
sort of signifies nothing um with it
you know we're done and so the code in
the kernel has actually
walks through this array until it finds
the element
whose value is zero
okay um right so this is how a program
can replace itself
um with another program from a file but
actually when we run stuff in the shell
like echo abc
or ls or anything else um
we don't want to replace the shell we
don't want to have the shell just
call exact um because that would replace
the shell with the echo command and then
when echo exited
that would be it you know we don't want
echo to replace the shell so
what the shell actually does is fork and
then the child calls it zac
and that's an extremely common unix
idiom
these programs that um want to run a
program but regain control what they do
is call
fork and have the child call exact so
here's a
simple example this fork exact program
so in this program um called fork on
line 12
and the child started line 14 we call
exec much like before
the child process um
has to replace itself with the echo
command
and echo does this thing and then exits
and then the parent process regains
control
because um when the fork returns
the greater than zero value in the
parent process so the parent process
then continues to execute at 19
and unix provides a weight system called
line
20 for a process to wait for one of the
for a
child that it created with four because
when i run a command
um here on the command line
we want uh we want the shell to wait
for the command to finish before it
prints the prop again
before it prints this dollar sign prompt
asking me for more input
and so it's the wait system call that
allows the process to wait for
any of its children to return and this
status argument is a
way for an exiting child
to communicate one integer
32-bit value from the exiting child um
to the waiting parent so in line 17 that
argument to exit
that one that's the argument to exit the
operating system
passes that one from the exiting child
um to the call to wait at line 20. so
weight that the ampersand and weight
is passing the address of the status
variable
to the kernel the colonel fills in that
address with the
child's argument to exit and the
convention in unix is that
if a program completes successfully it
exit with exits
with state of zero but if if it
encountered an error
as it lines 17 um then the unix
convention is that you pass
one to exit and so if you care the
calling process can look at the status
from weight
and decide whether the
child completed successfully enough
professor morris quick question yes
about
the exact call on 9 15. uh we mentioned
not
a bit ago that exec will completely go
into the echo program and not return
to fork exec so
would it ever reach lines 16 and 17
well not for this exact code because
there happens to be
a program called echo but but you know
if i modified that code here let me let
me just modify this code for you
okay so first let me just run fork exact
right it actually does execute echo with
those arguments we see the output this
is echo
and we see the child exited to show that
uh
echo exited successfully and the parent
waited for it
let me just modify the program for you
um instead of echo i'm going to run some
command that doesn't exist
i actually have to exit out of uh qmu
with control a x and then rebuild the
whole thing in order to recompile
my modified four gigs and i run four
pixel yen after modifying and compiling
it
and this time because the program we're
asking to
actually
the program we're asking to execute
doesn't exist
exec does return we see the exec failed
output
and the exit one you see the one there
is communicated back to the parent which
says the child exited the status one
so exec returns back to the calling
function
when something went wrong yes
okay
all right um something that uh something
to note here that
actually i think many of you have
already noted is that
uh this is a common idiom here this fork
followed by an exec and a child um and
it's potentially a bit wasteful the fork
copies the entire parent process but
exec
throws away all that copied memory and
replaces it with whatever is in the um
file that you're running so you know if
you're worried about this kind of stuff
the
copy implied by the fork
is in some sense mostly wasted because
all that copied memory is just thrown
away and replaced by the
exact um and this effects actually would
be significant for big programs if you
have a multi-gigabyte program that calls
fork
uh and it did indeed copy all the memory
would actually uh take a fair fraction
of a second
perhaps to do the copy which could be a
problem
um
but later in the course you'll actually
implement some optimizations in
particular something called
copy on right fork which will eliminate
almost
all of the apparent inefficiency of fork
copying only to have exact throw away
the copy
it turns out with a bunch of tricks
involving a virtual memory system
you can build a fork that's lazy about
the copy and that doesn't do in the
common case of fork immediately followed
by exact um where you don't actually
have to do the copy because the child
doesn't actually use most of the memory
um i think you'll find that's a fun and
interesting lab
question from chat why does the parent
process print parent waiting completely
before the child calls exec
it's just chance
the is it that you know the
the observation is that um you know
uh it could be that the parent's output
could be interleaved with the child's
output in the same area that we saw
before with the simpler fork example
it just happens not to be there's no
guarantee that this is the output we
would see
in fact we shouldn't be surprised if we
saw the lines of the output in the other
order
or interleaved i suspect what's going on
is that it takes a bit of time and
effort
now the exact system calls a little bit
expensive because it has to
load all those instructions to access
the file system and access the disk and
read the contents of a file called echo
off the disk into memory after
allocating some memory and that even
after freeing some memory from the old
process so
there's quite a bit of machinery
involved in the exact system call
and apparently that takes long enough
that the parent can complete
producing the output before the exec has
finished and started running echo
does that make sense
i have another question is it convention
that the child can't wait for the parent
there's not a way unix doesn't have a
way for the child
there's no straightforward way for the
child to wait for the parent
the weight system call is sort of
the only mechanism available well the
weight system call
waits for your children and that's it
and so what weight is what weight does
is um
if you have any children and one of them
has already exited
or does exit then weight will return
but you know if you don't have any
children say because you are
because in this simple case
um whether it was just a parent and a
child
if the child called weight the child
doesn't have any children
and in that case weight just returns
immediately with a minus one
error return saying this process doesn't
have any children
anyway the short answer is there's no
way for a child
to wait for its parent to exit
another question when we say the child
copies all the memory
from the parent process what i what
exactly do we refer to by that
i thought the child is going to divide
define the variables again
um well when you compile us you know
um
after compilation your c program
is just a bunch of instructions in
memory that live in ram
um and so those can be copied
because they're just bytes living in ram
those can be copied somewhere else
um and with appropriate tricks having to
do with setting up
a sort of virtual memory mappings um
and make the mappings look the same with
the child as an apparent you can just
copy the parent's memory image to the
child
and execute it in the child
i mean even though we're looking at c
programs you should think of them as
just a bunch of us
machine instructions um
which are just bytes in memory that can
be copied
if a parent has multiple children would
wait just return as soon as the first
child finishes
meaning that there could be some more
interleaving with the parent and
unfinished children
would there need to be multiple separate
weights to ensure all children finish
yes if you call forth more than one if a
sin if a given process
calls for twice um
then and it wants to wait for both
children it has to call weight
twice and each call to wait will return
as soon as
one of the children exits so you don't
when weight returns you don't
necessarily know which
child is exited the weight returns the
child's process id as its return value
so you can tell
after weight returns you know which one
it was that exited
as a final example um
i'd like to show
how all of these facilities combine
to implement i o redirection so
if you remember the shell provides us
with this handy syntax
and i can say echo hello greater than
out
and that runs the echo command that
argument sending its
first that sends this output to the file
out and we look it out
or better yet run the cap command with
its input
connected from the out file
we can see that saved output from the
echo command
um the way the shell sets this up
is as follows
um it uh the shell
first forks like on line 13 and then
in the child the shell changes the way
the file descriptors are set up so that
the child's
file descriptor one which by convention
most programs use for their output
the shell changes the child's file
descriptor to one to refer
to this output file and then runs
whatever command
you wanted and that leaves the parent
shells file descriptor one
unchanged so this idiom of forking and
in the child
um changing around the file descriptors
is the usual way in
to sort of redirect input and output for
a command that you run but not affect
the input and output
for the calling program because we don't
want to redirect the shell's output
we only want to redirect the child
programs output
anyway the way this works we call fork
in the usual way
line 15 only executes in the child the
reason for the close one
on line 15 is that in this program
we're redirecting just the output of the
echo command so
when i run this redirect program
produces no output itself but it ran
echo with this output directed to
output.txt
so when i look at output.txt
i see this expected output the reason
for the close one on line 15
is that we want one
sort of conventional output file
descriptor to refer to something else it
happens
so we don't from the child we don't want
to use the file descriptor one that the
shell had that's connected to the
console
um the call to open on line 16 is
guaranteed to return one because
the semantics of open are that open
returns the lowest
file descriptor number that's not
currently in use
um in the calling process since we just
closed one
and file descriptor 0 is
still connected to the console that mean
um
open is guaranteed to return one so
after the
line 16 file descriptor 1 is connected
to this file
when we exec echo echo just writes its
output to file scripter one
um and now it goes to this file and the
cool thing about this is echo had no
idea what's going on
echo doesn't need to know about io
redirection at all it just
writes its output to file descriptor one
only the shell knows about
io redirection
this example also illustrates the sort
of
kind of neatness of the separation
between
fork and exec the fact that fork and
exact are separate system calls
separate uh functions
means that there's a period of time but
in the child between the fork
between fork returns and the child and
exact in which
we're still running the calling
processes instructions so the
calling process even though it's running
even though its instructions are running
in the child
it's still the calling processes
instructions that are executing
and so the calling process is still able
to change
things um still in control up until line
and this sort of interval between fork
and sec uh gives the shell a chance to
change what the file descriptors refer
to for example
any questions about this redirect
example
all right um got out of time
i'll just wrap up we looked at unix's
a bunch of the interfaces to unix's i o
and process abstractions a thing to take
away from this is that the interfaces
are relatively simple
you just pass integers like file
descriptors and process ids back and
forth across
as arguments to these system calls um
but
sort of all the functionality inside the
interfaces is relatively
sophisticated like creating new
processes and
copying the current process and
furthermore
i showed some examples of ways in which
the abstractions though individually
simple
combine in useful ways for example
to produce iod direction
there's a lab due at the end of next
week and that lab involves writing
more simple utilities like the ones i
showed that use the system calls that we
discussed
so have fun with that lab and i'll see
you in class next week
and that's it
since i'm the one recording um how do i
end this
first time recording is in lecture i
think we exit
okay and nothing special i can just exit
and it'll be saved somewhere
yes awesome
and zoom will create some directory and
stick the vowel in that directory
there's also office hours right after
this right
yes perfect okay
cool
all right all right thank you and
i'll see you next week thanks