okay
quick sound check can everybody hear me
yep okay good uh anyway let's
get let's get going um you know good
afternoon or good evening or good
morning
uh whatever good night wherever you are
uh
so today's lecture uh is going to be
about the page faults
and a particular uh we're gonna
uh the plan is to
[Music]
cover or implement
you know implement a number
virtual memory features
using page faults
um and the features that we're going to
be looking at are
lazy allocation which is the uh topic of
the next lab
um yeah we're going to look at the
demand
copy and write fork
demand paging
and memory map files or map
and almost
you know sort of a series operating
system actually implements all these
features so if you look inside of linux
you'll see all these features actually
uh
are implemented uh in xc6 as it stands
none of them are implemented
and uh and the fact that what a page
fault does in xc6
if the page vault happens in user phase
basis basically kill the process
but nothing interesting uh and so in
this lecture we're going to explore
again what interesting things you could
do in the page fault handler
to actually implement these three
features so this lecture is a little bit
less
walking through code and understanding
uh existing code
a little bit more design level uh in the
sense
we don't even have code to look at uh
another thing that's important to
mention is that lazy allocation is the
topic of the next lap and
hopefully it will push out today um and
copy and write fork it's going to be a
topic of one of the labs
and uh map is going to be another topic
of one of the subsequent labs
so this is going to you know this is one
of the interesting parts of an operating
system
and we're going to be spending quite a
bit of time on it in the labs
now you know before diving sort of into
details
it is probably helpful to take a little
bit of a
step back and so you can think about
virtual memory having
two major benefits
one is isolation so
isolation in the sense that uh virtual
memory allows the operating system to
give every application its own address
space
and so it's impossible for you know one
application to muck
you know or by accident or maliciously
to modify another application's address
space
uh it also provides isolation between
the user and kernel address space as we
talked about quite a bit and as you've
seen in the page table lab
but sort of another view or another
benefit
of you know virtual memory that you know
i alluded to a couple times
earlier is that it provides a level of
interaction
now the processor the instructions you
can all use virtual addresses
uh but the kernel gets to sort of define
the mapping
from virtual addresses to physical
addresses
and that allows all kinds of interesting
uh
uh interesting features
like the ones i'm going to be talking
about in the in this lecture um
the second
kernel has controls this particular
mapping from a virtual to
a physical address space and most so far
in excuses that mapping has to be
quite boring you know in fact in the
kernel it's mostly direct mapping
and a couple sort of interesting things
that we do with the x26 kernel does you
know with this mapping one as we've seen
is the trampoline page allowed the
kernel to map
one page into many address spaces
another interesting case that we have
seen
is the you know guard protect
the stack uh both in the kernel and both
and in kernel space both in user space
any kernel space
but if you sort of think about it you
know so far that mapping
you know has been relatively static you
know the
you we set it up once you know maybe per
user uh with the kernel page table
mapping we set up once in the beginning
and for processes once at fork and there
sort of
the kernel doesn't really do anything
else with this mapping
and what page fault gives us is actually
to make these mappings
dynamic so i'm using page faults
yeah we can change or the kernel can
change
the mapping
so dynamically on the fly and this turns
out to be an extra
extremely uh powerful uh
mechanism so if you can combine page
tables
and page faults uh you uh have an
enormous
the kernel has an enormous amount of
flexibility and the flexibility comes
down because you can
change this level of direction on on the
fly
and so what we're going to be doing is
basically looking at all kinds of
usages of this dynamic remapping or
dynamic changing of the page tables that
gives us
interesting features
um so the first thing we may want to
think about is a little bit
uh is you know what information is
needed you know so if you're in the
page vault happens um
and uh you know the kernel wants to
respond to this page fault you know what
you know information doesn't need
to actually be able to respond and you
know sort of quite
know obviously you know we'd like to
have the virtual dress
off uh the virtual address with
defaulting
uh or the cost of page fault
uh let me not say it actually i want to
say is
the folding virtual dress
and you know you've seen presumably some
of these panic uh calls in
your page fault lab uh and you know the
kernel actually has access to them
uh in fact it prints them out when
actually page fold happens
and uh you know it happens to be sitting
in the st
valley register
so when a user application
causes a paid fault the paid fall
basically invokes the same
track machinery that robert discussed in
the last lecture
it's almost completely identical but in
the case of a page fault it also will
put the defaulting address
into that st valve register
so that is uh one thing that we probably
want to know
the second thing that we probably want
to know is the type of default
uh because it may be in terms of uh uh
we may want to do
respond differently differently in terms
of to
uh a page fault due to a load
instruction
or a page filter due to store
instruction or page fall due to like a
jump instruction
um and so in fact you know if you look
in the risc 5
documentation um
here's the race 5 documentation in here
in the s-cause register that we was
mentioned in the track lecture
there are a number of uh
causes that actually related to page
faults so example if you look at
number 13 is a load page fault number 15
is the store page fault and the number
12 is in the instruction page fault
so these are the uh in the s cause
register
and we get that information
and so there's three different types you
know the read
write and uh instruction
and just going back you know the the one
uh s know that actually uh was caused by
uh the ecal instruction to do actually a
kernel transfer
is number eight right so that's the one
that we saw in
the trap lecture that we spent a lot of
time thinking about in the trap lecture
but basically all the other page faults
or exceptions
use the same you know mechanism to
transfer from user space to kernel
transfer
to kernel space and um
once given the kernel space in the case
of the page fault you know the std value
is
set yes cause register set then the
third thing
that we probably want to know is the
instruction
or to address the virtual address of the
that cost the page fault
and you know anybody remember where you
know from the trap lecture where that
where the instruction is where that
address is
anybody is it uh sepsi
yeah exactly and there was this regisepc
correct the supervisor exception
exception program counter
uh there is where it is and where is
that saved
as part of the trap handling code
in the trap frame yeah it ends up in the
trap frame correct there's a trap frame
epc actually has the exception program
camera
so we sort of think about the hardware
mechanism and what xv6 does
uh we have free piece of information
they're probably extremely valuable to
us when we get actually paid for namely
the the drastic cost default the type of
default
and the exception program counter like
where how did it happen in user space
and the reason that we care a lot about
the exception program counter correct is
because
uh when that we probably want to repair
you know in the handler we're going to
repair
the page table and then we're going to
basically restart the same instruction
and you know hopefully the after
repairing the page fault or
repairing the page tables that
instruction can just run without any
trouble
and so it's important that we can be
able to resume the instruction that
actually
that we that cost default
does that all make sense
okay um so now i want to look at
you know also the basic mechanism and
the basic information that the risk 5 is
actually giving us
and i want to look at a basically go
through a list of
uh you know features uh that will help
us you know
understand actually how we can uh use
the patrol handler to
uh repair the page table and
do interesting things so the first thing
i want to look at
is allocation
in particular you know s-break
so fast break is the system call that
xv6 provides
that uh allows an application to
basically grow
grow its heap right so when the
application uh
starts uh you know s break uh points
here
you know at the bottom of the heap you
know at the top of the stack
and in fact you know it's the same place
where you know p
size basically you know points to and so
when s break is called uh for example
aspect is called with like one two three
four five you know the number of pages
that you know you want to allocate
the uh aspect system call it basically
bumps up
you know this boundary
do something there and then that uh
and so what that means that when the s
break actually happens
or the aspect system call is called the
kernel will allocate some physical
memory
uh map it into the address space of
the user application uh zero the memory
and then basically return it from the
system call
and you know every time it's just and
the application can grow
you know that physical memory that or
memory that it needs
or it might want uh by just calling
multiple times to uh
s-brick uh the application can also
decrease or
shrink in its address phase by calling
estimate with a negative number
but i want to focus on the case where
we're growing uh the address space
and in xy6 as it is uh
the uh this break is eager
and or does what we're going to call
eager allocation
namely as soon as the uh
s-break is called the kernel will
immediately allocate
the physical memory that the application
is asking for
and now it turns out that in practice
it's actually hard for applications to
predict
uh how much memory they need so
typically applications
tend to over ask
and so they ask a lot more than they
really need uh and
uh often that will which means that
basically you know the address space uh
will grow quite a bit
uh even with memory that's actually
never used by the application
you might think like oh that's stupid uh
how could that happen
well you know think about like if you
write an application program
and uh the typical application program
maybe it read some input or you know it
has a matrix something that
uses for some computation um
and often the application writers sort
of plans for the worst case you know
it you know allocates memory for the
biggest matrix that you know the
application
might never ever need but in the common
case
the application may be computed with a
much smaller you know input or a much
smaller
matrix and so it's quite common
in fact for application programmers and
probably if you know you think about
your own application you've written
to actually over ask and actually under
use
uh and again we'd like to in principle
not a big
problem but you know using actually uh
virtual memory and page fault handlers
we can actually totally
totally respond to that in sort of an
intelligent manner
and by basically doing lazy allocation
and then the basic idea is very simple
and s break
we're basically going to do almost
nothing and the only thing that we need
to know remember is of course that we
did grow the address space so the only
thing really what we're going to be
doing
is actually bumping up you know p size
you know whatever with the number uh
you know set two sides to whatever the
new size plus you know n
and where n is the amount of memory
that's allocated and then
you know so that but we don't allocate
the kernel doesn't allocate any physical
memory at that particular point of time
it doesn't zero it that there's
absolutely nothing
um then at some point the application
will use or might use that memory
correctly if
it's actually one of the pieces of
memory that it really needs uh
and that will cause a page fault
because we didn't map that memory
actually into the page map yet
and so if we dereference a virtual dress
you know above you know this piece size
uh but below
pcs plus n uh what we like to be
happening
is that you know the kernel will
allocate a page and uh restarts
instruction
so if we get a page fault and we see
that the virtual address
is you know bigger than pizza uh it is
below
sorry it's a little key size
for p size then we know that this must
be a virtual address and i guess above
the stack
you know that this is a an address that
actually comes out of the heap
but for which we the kernel hasn't
allocated any
uh physical memory yet and so the
response to this paid fault you know
could be reasonable straightforward you
know in the patrol panel itself
we can allocate a page and using k alec
allocate one page zero to page
map the page into the page table so
updating the page tables
and then basically restart the
instruction
so for example if there was a load
instruction or store instruction
that wrote where i was trying to read
you know from that uh not
allocated you know piece of memory that
actually the process has
uh now after we mapped in this you know
physical page
uh the restarting instructions should
just work
i'm here go ahead
right so i was wondering in in the case
where we're doing eager
allocation uh and there comes a point
where a process consumes so much memory
that it actually exhausts the physical
memory
resource uh if we don't do eager
allocation
we do lazy instead at what point would
the application know that there's no
physical memory
ah that's a great question uh well
basically you know
it almost looks through the application
there there's this illusion of
unlimited physical about memory you know
at some point of course you know
it you know might use so much you know
that basically okay so
it may use all physical memory and so if
then it touches one more page
which there's no physical memory present
at that particular point in time
then you know there's a couple of
actions that the colonel can take and
i'll talk about
the more sophisticated ones later uh
what you're going to be doing in the
lazy lab is you know if the is uh up
and there's no no more free memory uh
you just
return an error or actually you kill the
process in that particular case
uh and so because you're out of memory
so there's nothing the kernel can do
and at that point you know you return or
kill the process
yeah that's a that you're going to do in
the lazy lab we'll see
later in this lecture you could be more
sophisticated than that
uh i think this is generally brings up a
topic that is if we have a collection of
processes running on
an operating system there is a limited
amount of physical memory and that
limited
physical memory must be shared in some
way between the applications
and so i'll talk a little bit much more
about it in
10-20 minutes
okay uh there's a question to check uh
in the chat
why is the condition virtual address uh
virtual justice loans next we start at
zero
okay this is a question about this
particular check here
so remember
we have our stack here and
we have our data here and we have our
text
in the user process and basically we
bumped up
you know p size to something bigger
uh we've dumped it up the growth we
haven't allocated memory here yet so
this memory has
not been physically allocated yet so
this check just checks
if the address falls below p size and it
actually is a valid you know address
in the user address space if it were
above p size presumably that's a
programming error
in the program or the user application
who's trying to dereference a memory
that actually doesn't have
hopefully that answers the question
yeah thank you okay good so
to get a little bit of a feel uh you
know for what that actually
means uh in uh this lazy allocation
uh and that's probably uh the only
uh sort of programming or tooth uh
things that we're gonna be doing
today is uh let's try to sort of uh
sketch out or look actually how it would
look in
in code and the two holes you'll see
that it will be surprising
easy and furthermore it's probably a big
help
for the lazy lab and so that hopefully
that will help you
get going pretty straightforwardly
and it allows us also to look at a
couple uh page fault
um i had a question actually regarding a
point that i made in chat
why do we actually need to kill the
application couldn't the operating
system just return like a narrative
you are out of memory try and do
something else
let's respond that question to a little
bit later you know
in the page fault we're going to just
kill the process uh but you know we can
be more sophisticated
uh in pixel lab real kernels are more
sophisticated
okay uh although in the end they might
still kill us you know if there's just
no more memory what whatsoever to be
gotten you know there's basically no
choice
um okay uh so the first thing uh we're
gonna do we're gonna modify so
you remember that cis practice you know
actually grows the address space of the
application allocates memory and all
that kind of stuff
we're just not going to do that we're
just going to set p size you know to
p size plus n
so let's assume that we're only growing
and not worry about uh shrinking for now
and that is what we're going to be doing
so this grows the virtual dress space
uh by end and that's all all we're going
to be doing
let's see if i can make no programming
mistakes i did make a programming
mistake
uh i guess i don't have product key here
so i'll like proc
it's good yeah so the program just runs
uh or at least we boot
uh i think if we do like echo high uh
we're gonna get actually a page fault
and the reason that we get a paid fault
is because uh
the shell uh who's gonna fork you know
echo and
then you know the child is gonna exec
echo uh the shell actually allocates
some memory
and so the shell calls s-break and
things are not looking good
but it's sort of interesting to look at
you know the
uh information here so here's our it
prints out the s-cos
uh register uh when the value in s-cos
and we see it's 15.
uh anybody remember what 15 is
you know from the table i just showed
you a little bit a while ago that
actually is the write
or store page fault we see that is
process free that's probably the shell
and we actually see the
exception program encounter it's one two
a four and we see the address given the
virtual address on which we fault which
is four thousand eight
and so let's uh look at the you know we
can look at the
assembly of the shell the make files
nice of us nice enough for us to
actually generate that
and we can look at the address uh
1284 and
you know we see indeed you know there
there's a story instruction correct the
store instruction
and uh it looks like that's where we're
faulting
uh so if you scroll back a little bit
and look at this assembly here
uh you know we see uh that actually this
is in part of the implementation of
malloc
so that seems uh totally reasonable
correct here's the malek implementation
not surprising that we presumably use
s-break to get some
memory for implementing the user malloc
and we're basically initializing the
free list of
using the memory that we've just gotten
from the kernel
and this line 12 a4
joomla writes you know i guess it's
right something in size
and uh but we we're writing to memory
that actually hasn't been allocated
another reason that we can see that the
memory is probably not allocated is
uh the i think the shell actually has
four pages
of text and data and we're basically
sitting just above the fourth
page in the fifth page in fact we're
sitting eight bytes above it
that sort of makes sense uh we look at
the instruction again where's 1284
you see here that basically probably a
user general holds
you know four thousand and eight is the
uh additional offset you know that we're
actually dereferencing
so that's the default and now what we
like to do is you know
do something slightly more sophisticated
than we're currently doing and so let's
go to proc
trap.c
and uh look at user trap right because
this happens in user trap
uh mutual trap is the function that we
uh that robert discussed uh a week ago
uh and you know just go through the
different causes
and perform some action so we're a
little bit here
uh this line is s-class is eight and you
know that's the point we're gonna do
process system calls
uh then there's a line that checks
whether it was any uh device interrupt
and processes inside of the device
interrupt
and if there's none of those to happen
then basically we get this trap
and the process is being killed and
basically what we need to do
is you know we need to add some code
here that you know checks
uh for another case right basically i
guess the case that we want to look for
outlet is if
uh our s cos is causing a
is 15
we want to do something else
does that make sense so what do you want
to do here
what is sort of the plan for attack you
know for these couple lines of code
we want to check if p size
is more than the virtual address
not um in
sd val perhaps yeah
yeah yeah oh and this is the case then
do something like uv
um um malloc i think
there's one way we could do it uh so i'm
going to cut some corners just
for the demo and uh presumably in the in
the lab itself you will need to do a
little bit more work
uh but basically here's the sort of i
think the
frequent segment of code that we need
so let's see where i was
here's usually trap
let me just kind of paste it into it
and then we can look at it you know just
a print statement for debugging uh and
basically
what i'm going to do in this handler i'm
going to allocate the physical page
uh if there's no physical pace meaning
we're out of memory i'm just
we're going to kill the process for now
uh if there's a physical page you know
we'll zero the page
and then we just map the page at the
appropriate address
in the uh address space of the user
in particular we map it on the rounded
down virtual address
right so the faulting address is 4008
here
uh and so that's eight bytes into you
know the fifth page
and we want to map that physical page at
the bottom of the physical
the virtual page so at four thousand so
round it down to four thousand and then
we map four files into this physical
page
and then of course we have to set the
usual permission bits you know the ubid
the read and write
does that make sense
yeah i guess i can get rid of this line
uh so let's see let's try this out
and i guess i made some mistakes
i think that on the else you don't have
an opening bracket at the bottom
oh yeah
[Music]
no i do have it do i need one more oh
yeah
[Music]
oh sorry i meant on the ls right here
you don't have an opening bracket
right like uh lenses else printf user
trap
unexpected cause thank you thank you
hopefully it'll help a lot with
excellence so echo high
uh now of course we're going to be
optimistic and we hope that works uh
i'll tell you it won't work but
uh but we did get two page faults right
we got a page filled at four thousand
eight you know apparently we practiced
them because we got another page fault
and so we only problem that we've left
is there's a
uvm app you know comes complaining that
um
it's complaining that there's some page
that we're uh
trying to unmap is actually not mapped
and what could that be
why would you think even we get this
panic
anybody
what memory is being unmapped here most
likely
the one that was lazily allocated and
not actually allocated
yeah exactly you know the memory that
was lazily allocated but actually
hasn't been used yet right and so there
is no physical page for that particular
laserly memory
and so uh this case when the pt is zero
you know there's no mapping yet it's not
really a panic you know this is actually
what we expected you know it could
happen
right and in fact for that page we just
don't have to do anything
right we can just continue you know go
to the next page
does that make sense so let's do that
and now let's do the echo high and boom
we got two page faults and but high
works
and so we're basically uh uh
you know have sort of a very basic
minimal
lazy allocation scheme working
any questions about this sorry i didn't
really follow
why you could just continue uh could you
explain that again
yeah um so the
the bug indicated that we had that we're
trying to free page
that actually is not mapped and
you know how could that happen well the
only reason that could happen is because
s-break moved up key size
but never used the application never
used in that memory and so
it actually has no mapping yet because
it was actually not allocated
right because we're lazily allocating
we're only allocating physical memory
for those pages
when we need it if we didn't need it
then there will be no mapping and so
it's totally reasonable that there
actually is going to be a case
where there's no mapping for a virtual
address because it actually wasn't
allocated yet
and for that case we just have to do
nothing you know
uh we can't free the page correctly
there is no free page and so the best
thing is to do continue and just go to
the next page and
look okay that makes sense
thank you yeah we didn't know do
continue but basically
you know just kept going then we would
actually free the page and i'll be
that's why it continues there makes
sense
uh another question in
uvm on map i assume the panic was that
was there
was there for a reason so a more correct
a more reasonable implementation is to
have two versions
and we would use the one that doesn't
panic yeah okay
why was the uvm the panic there well
there was basically an invariant
that used to be true for the unmodified
xv6
right actually unmodified xc6 should
never have a case where there's user
memory that was not mapped
and so therefore the panel goes up we
now changed the design of xc6
and so we have to just uh and this
invariant is just not
no longer true and so we've got to
remove the panic and you know
uh because anybody is just not true
legitimately not true anymore
i see thanks
does this make sense so um
so a couple of comments
this will hopefully help a lot with the
next lap in fact this is like one of the
three components of the labs of the next
lap so it's one of the first things you
have to do
and hopefully this will save you some
time uh maybe make up for
you know all the pain that you went
through in the patrol to
lab but clearly it's not enough
right so like what things are you know
we made these changes but more things
are still probably broken
now one radio was mentioned i actually
didn't do the check whether actually the
virtual address
was below p size correct which we
probably should do
any other things that might be broken
anybody
the number of bytes to grow the process
by an s break
is an int and not an unsigned end so
negative numbers could be used
yes and then negative numbers can use
and that means shrinking the address
space
right and so we shrink the address space
we also have to be a little bit careful
uh so it turns out there's a whole bunch
of as usual uh
in an operating system there are a whole
bunch of different cases right where in
which
uh we're going to be looking at this
particular page table entry
and for all those different cases we
might actually have to modify xj6
slightly
and and that's exactly what basically
the lab is about is you know doing good
enough job that basically you can pass
user tests
and user tests will stress a whole bunch
of other cases that
you will need to deal with
okay
any questions so far
okay let me uh in that case i want to
talk about a bunch of
other usages or cool
things you can do once you have page
faults and page tables and you update
them dynamically
another one that is almost trivial
but you know commonly used is
what's called zero fill
zero fill on demand
uh it turns out that in uh
operating systems you know there are
many null pages um
and uh so for example if you look at the
uh
an address space in user space uh
you know xp6 doesn't really is not
advanced uh but like if you look at the
layout of the binary
uh and ain't it out you know there's
some text there's what's called the data
segment
and there is typically also about
something that's called the bss segment
and so when the compiler you know
produces uh
the binary you know basically fills in
these three segments the text is you
know the instructions
no the data is basically global
variables that actually have a value
that is not zero so an initialized uh
data
and bbzs is basically a description that
says
well there's a whole bunch of variables
and at least basically their sizes
and they also be zero and the reason
that they're basically not
listed out you know or the memory is not
right there in the file is because you
know that'll save
a lot of you know for example if you
declare a big matrix in c
on the top of the file as a global
variable and it's automatically going to
distribute all zeros
why allocate all that space in the file
uh just like note that basically you
know for this particular variable
you know the in the content should be
zero
and then basically on exec on a normal
operating system on exec
you know we'll look at these three uh uh
segments and that's the usual thing that
xv6 does you know for text and data
but they're from bess you know it will
allocate you know
memory uh to hold the bss and basically
stick zeros in there
so you know allocate an address space
takes the data in it and sticks to avoid
it and then you know basically
uh you know the equivalent of the bzs
you know all the global
variables that are basically zero and
there may be many many pages
and all those pages basically have to
have the content zero
so that's the virtual address space and
so typical trick you know to do is to
say like wow
i got so many pages that need to have
zero what i'm going to do
in physical memory this is the virtual
address space
and it's the physical address you know
memory uh what i'm going to really do is
i'm just going to allocate one zero page
i fill it with zeros and basically map
all the other pages
to that one page
you know saving myself you know lots you
know lots of physical memory at least at
startup
um and of course those mappings has to
be limit care uh dominance care
we can't market you know we cannot allow
rights to it right because everybody's
relying on the fact that it actually
stays zero
so we just map it read only
and then at some point when an
application starts writing to one of you
know the
basically starts it doesn't load or
store to one of the
pages that actually are part of the vess
so because it wants you to you know
whatever store one or two variable
content in there
and we're going to get a page fault
and so what should we do on the page
fault
in this particular case
anybody
go ahead anybody idea what should we do
in the page fault here
i think we should make a new page
and uh write zeros there and rerun the
instruction
yeah exactly so let's let's assume this
for my drawing that actually the
uh store instruction happened to the one
at the top
and what we really want to do basically
is allocate a new physical page a new
page in memory you know catalog put
zeros in there because
that's what we're expecting and then we
can change the top
mapping right for the one for this
particular because for this guy
uh or let me assume that this is this
one we can change this mapping you know
to be
read write and point it to
the new page
and then you know basically so copy
let's update pte and then restart the
structure
and that's it why is this ineffective
why do you think this is actually in
good optimization
why do operating systems do it
anybody
you don't need it yeah um
you don't need to use as much memory as
the user requested so it's just better
to um
bill it when it when you need it yeah
actually
similar like to the lazy allocation
basically if the
program say allocated a huge array you
know for the worst possible input
it's a global array it all has to be
zeros but maybe the only fraction is
being used
right what's the second advantage
second advantage you have to do less
work in exec right and so
the program may start quicker and get
basically better interactive performance
okay because you don't really have to
allocate memory you don't really have a
zero memory you only have to allocate
the zero to one page
and the rest is you know you're just
mapping the page table so you just have
to write the pte entries
does that make sense but aren't
updates or writes
so they will become slower because every
time
a page fall will occur and yeah so you
know there's absolutely a good point
uh so we basically postpone some of the
cost to later
right um at the point that we do the
page fault
and you know we're partially relying or
hoping that maybe not all the pages are
being used
uh but like for example if the page is
496 496 bytes
uh you know basically we're gonna take
one page wall per four thousand ninety
six
zeros right and so do some rotation
there
but it's a good great point you know
certainly we have made paint we have
income
we have added the cost of the page fault
how much is the cost of the page fault
how
how should we think about that is that
comparable to
store instruction or is much more
expensive
more expensive right yeah why
well a store will just uh
like need to require it will take some
time to
get through the to ram but the
fault will have to go to the cornell
yeah
so in fact how many store instructions
were there even in the
uh the trap handling code that robert
showed you last week
or actually that you're doing currently
in the uh trap block
uh well oh at least like a hundred yeah
at least a hundred current used to save
restore registers
uh so there's quite a bit and so there's
the both the overhead of
transferring from user space to kernel
space as well like all the instructions
that are being executed
uh to save and restore state so the page
fault is definitely not
free so the question that was asked
earlier is a very good question
okay so let's uh look at some more
uh optimizations that one can do
these ones are sort of reasonably boring
or maybe reasonable straightforward
uh and we're gonna hopefully get a
little bit more
a couple more exciting ones
let's see what's next one i wanted to do
uh
next one is a very common one uh
many operating systems implemented and
in fact it will also be one of the
topics in
one of the labs so let's do the next one
uh and that is copy
on the right fork
or something it's called cow fork
um and you know the uh
the observation uh is you know pretty
straightforward in fact we made
this observation a couple times in
lecture um
but when uh
let's say you know the shell right there
we were in fact shot in a second ago
it's like if the shell runs
and it processes a command it actually
does a fork
to create a child and so the fork you
know basically creates a copy of the
shell
and so we've got a parent and we've got
the child and then the child of almost
one of the first things it does is an
exit
and then you execute a couple
instructions and then it actually exits
you know for example to run echo
and as we now know uh
in the last lap you know the fork
creates a complete duplicate
of the shell address space and then
exactly the first thing it basically
does it you know throws that away
and then replaces it with an address
face you know containing echo
and so it seems slightly wasteful right
like you know so here let's say we have
our
parent virtual dress space
and then here we have the child
and what we're actually doing and here's
physical memory
and in the normal case in xv6 or in
unmodified xv6
you know there's a bunch of like there
were four pages we saw
that the shell has one two three four
and
uh you know when we start when a fork
uh runs it basically gets a duplicate of
those four pages one
two three four and copies all the
content
you know from those pages the parenting
to the child
um and you know then as soon as exit
happens basically we're going to free
these pages
and allocate new pages to actually have
the content of echo in it
so a good optimization one that actually
tends to be very effective
for this particular sequence is that you
know if we
uh if the parent has these four mappings
you know in its address space
you know going from whatever the zero
goes here the first one goes there
and whatever instead you know when we
create the child address space instead
of creating copying and allocating new
physical memory
what we could do is just share the
physical pages
that the parent actually already has
allocated
and so we can just set the pte's for the
child you know to the same
pointing to the same physical pages as
in the parent
and we're going to be a little bit
careful again correct because if the
child
wants to modify one of these pages that
update should not be
visible to the parent because we want
strong isolation between the parent and
child so we need to be a little bit more
careful
so to be a little bit more careful now
what we can do is just map those pages
both in the child and in the parent
read-only
and then of course we're going to get a
page fault at some point
because the parent is going to run or
the child is going to run
and uh and maybe you know the child or
the parent will
do a store instruction to maybe save the
data
to some global variable or somewhere and
at that point you know where
the that will cause a page fault because
you know we're writing to a page that is
mapped
only so we get a page fault and so what
do we need to do well we need to make a
copy of the page
so let's assume that it's the child that
actually uh
does the story instruction so we
allocate a new page
uh we copy you know the content
uh off the page that were faulted on
into this new page
we mapped that page into the child and
this time we can
happen to read write because it's now
private page only you know visible in
the child's address space
and in fact the page that will actually
be folded on we can also now map read
write
into the parent and so we copy the page
map it and restart the instruction
and when restarting instruction really
means you know doing user read you know
the same way that uh we returned to user
space
uh in uh last week's lecture
does this make sense any questions about
this one
i'm sorry um when you say we mapped the
parents
um virtual address to we also
read write uh how do we find it out is
it the same as
the child's oh yeah because the the
dress space of the child is a duplicate
of the
apparent address space right so if we
fall to the particular virtual dress
since the address spaces are equal you
know the it's the same virtual address
both in the parent's
address space and in the child's address
space
makes sense thank you
another question for let's say
like some parentless process maybe like
the first one that launches
does it use its pages
does it set just read permissions or
does it start off with read
write well we can and when it forks it
modifies
yeah okay it's up to you in fact
this is also one lap uh you're gonna
implement copy and write
uh after the lazy lab uh and you know
you have some freedom you know the easy
thing to do is just also map it read
only
you will get a page fault and then
you'll do whatever you normally also
would do in the copy and write
so you can use the same mechanism in
both cases
there's no reason to actually specialize
or do something
separate for the first process
okay thanks so um
i also have a question um given that we
like kind of copy
whole tables sorry whole pages around
pretty often um does
any like memory hardware implement
like a specific instruction because
basically memory
hardware will usually just have like
some data lines to say
read me or store this memory
because we have like oh copy page a to
page b
yeah there's a x86 for example has uh
hardware instructions for copying
rangers memory
uh you know vs5 doesn't uh
uh but of course you know in a very high
performance implementation
uh the all these recent rights will be
pipelined
and you know hopefully run at the speed
of the memory bandwidth
note that actually uh you know in
principle we might be lucky and we're
saving correct on
loads and stores or copies because in
this particular picture
i made only one copy and in the
unmodified case we would have copied all
four pages
and so hopefully you know this is just
like strictly better both in terms of
memory consumption and
in terms of performance you know fork
will just be faster
i have a quick question um when
when the page fault occurs and and we
see that
like it was it was essentially like we
were trying to write to a read-only
address
um how does the colonel tell uh like
that this is a
situation where it's copy on right fork
versus just a situation where the memory
it was trying to write was was marked as
read only for some
like legitimate reason other than copy
on right fork is it just kind of an
invariant
that if if uh if it's user memory then
it will be mapped read write unless it
was a result of copy on port
yeah right so it is a an invariant that
needs to be maintained in the kernel and
the
kernel must recognize in some way that
this is a copy and write page if you
will
um and so i'm very glad you asked a
question because uh turns out you know
the risk five hardware almost all page
table hardware
actually has support for this uh and we
didn't mention that earlier but here's
our
you know our usual you know whatever two
level uh or multi-level uh page table
here's our pte
and if you look at the pte you know i
talked about the bits you know
one zero through seven but not about
these two bits
rsw and
they are reserved for supervisor
software so
the supervisor software you know this is
the kernel uh
can use these bits at its own free will
and so one thing one could do is like
say decide that bit a basically means
this is a copy and write page or copy to
write fault
and so when the kernel programs you know
these page tables
for you know copy and write you know you
can just pull to on the pte's you know
for these particular pages
the bits you know set a bit uh copy and
write so that when the
page fault happens and we see that the
copy and right bit is set
then we just go off and do this and
otherwise we do something else
for example maybe it's a lazy allocation
does that make sense yeah thank you
and in fact in uh in the lab you know
one of the things you will be doing is
probably use that bit
you know set a copy and write bit in the
pte
there's one more wrinkle that will show
up in the copy and write lab is that
there's some currently in xg6 basically
a physical page more or less only
belongs to one
process with the exception of the
trampoline page
which is the family page we're never
free so that is not really a particular
big issue
but for these pages you know now we have
multiple processes or multiple dress
spaces pointing to the same physical
address
and so for example if the parent exits
right away we got a little bit care and
be careful correct because
can we free that page immediately if the
parent exits
oh maybe not because there may be
multiple
children processes yeah there might be a
child correct using that page and so
we if the colonel would free that page
then
uh you know we're going to be in trouble
because basically the
if you look at k3 k3 actually uh writes
all kinds of ones on
three page and so then the child runs
with that page you know all kinds of
bizarre things are going to happen
so what should the rule be now for
freeing
i'm free if you don't have children
i guess yeah maybe a better way or sort
of a more general version of that
statement is to say well what we really
need to do
is we need to ref count
every physical page and when we free the
page
we decrease the ref count by one and if
the ref ground reaches zero then
actually we can free the page
and so you will have to introduce uh
some additional data structure or some
meta information in the copy and write a
lot to actually do that ref counting
where can we store this because this if
we ever have to ref count every single
page that could be a lot
yeah we well for every physical page of
memory we you'll have to do a rough
count yeah
you can get away with a little bit less
but then we're in the for the for
simplification in lab we're going to use
that for every one
physical so for every 496 bytes we need
to maintain a reference count
can we write that down in those other
two free
bits and say that no more
for um good good
yeah i'm
not unreasonable but uh you know if you
reform it multiple times
that'd be too bad right and after three
times your four times you can't don't
you can't do the optimization anymore
but yeah you know there's some freedom
here uh
also um do you really need to use that
bit to specify if it's a copy on write
because
the kernel could also uh maintain some
information about the processes that
yes yeah yeah yeah you could you could
maintain some other meta information
along with the process address days to
say basically well
virtual addresses between this and that
are text addresses so we have a page
fault there and
it must be copyright or something
and in fact one of the later labs you
know you you will certainly extend
uh the meta information that xv6
maintains
exactly for that reason
there's a bit of freedom here when you
start implementing these labs
any further questions about this
okay uh then let's go to the next one uh
this is something that's called
uh demand paging
another very popular one and most
operating systems implemented
um and so the the uh you know it just
goes back basically to
exec
so currently in unmodified xv6 you know
x6 actually loads
the text segment
and the data segment from file and maps
it in
eagerly in basically
into the page table
and basically the same observation that
we made for lazy
and zero filled is that well what we
could do is like why do it eagerly
why not let's wait a little while uh
until to see if actually the application
really needs you know those particular
set of instructions you know the
the binary might be very big uh and
instead of actually uh loading it all
in you know from disk it tends to be
expensive operation uh
maybe the data segment is much bigger
than it really needs than the typical
use case
uh requires we don't really have to do
that
and so instead of uh on exec
instead of actually you know we allocate
the virtual address space you know we'll
allocate the
address base for the text and the data
uh that's it in the file but in the ptes
we're going to not map them at all you
know it's going to keep you know in the
pte
for one of these pages you know we're
just going to not set the valid bit so
the validated to zero
uh and of course you know when we're
going to get our first
page fault if we do this
in exec and let's say we modify xc6 to
do this
when will our first default happen
what's the first instruction that is
being run for user address
or user program
where does the user program start is it
loading the
initial code newbie a minute yeah yeah
okay we were just keeping that
piece correct that's the whole point of
like modifying exec and not called the
uvm
in it where
so most you know when we actually if you
remember from four regret or something
like that you know that place where an
application starts is exactly address
zero so
my picture is a little bit you know he's
leading here but so here's text here's
zero
it goes up to some number and basically
the first instruction whatever sits here
that's the first instruction that we're
going to actually that address that's
the first instruction we're going to get
a page folder
right because we have not loaded it
so what to do on the page fault
well what we're going to do in the page
fault is basically we'll note
ah this is uh what's one of these uh uh
on demand pages
uh we have to remember somewhere earlier
that you know this corresponds to
some uh that this corresponds to some
file
and basically what we're going to do in
the patrol handler is read
you know that block or page
from file
into memory
map that memory
into the page table
and restart the instruction
and then we're off and running right and
so we're going to get
in the worst case if the user program
uses all of its text
uses all of this data then we're going
to get a page fault for every page you
know in
uh in the program
but you know we get lucky and the
program know doesn't use all of its
data segment or doesn't use all of this
text segment then you know we might save
some memory and uh we certainly make
exact you know perform you know
much quicker and so be a little bit more
interactive and as soon as the program
starts boom it's running
my we hardly have to do any work in
exactly
does that make this optimization make
sense
okay so then there's a sort of a slight
extension to demand paging
so this is the second part of the net
paging
yeah sorry right there more
[Music]
so part two demand paging this principle
there's a little bit of a problem here
that we haven't really discussed it
might be the case you know maybe the
file that we're actually reading or the
text and data segment are even bigger
than what actually is in physical memory
or
if multiple applications uh started with
demand paging
maybe their sum of their binaries
is basically bigger than actually it's a
physical memory
and so uh the typical thing you know
what
if you go down this demand paging uh
round
is to actually if you run out of memory
so if caliber returns zero if out of
memory
so for example you know your demand page
you get a page fault at some
uh page that needs to be uh paged in
from the file system but you don't have
any more free pages
you need to do something and so the
typical and this comes back
to an earlier question example the same
is true for lazy or
you know what to do if you run out of
memory so if you run out of memory
one option that you really clearly have
is to
evict a pitch
you can example instead of you know you
can for example invicta page and write
it you know
to the file back so for example if it's
a
data page that got modified you know you
can write it back you know to the file
system
um and then once you've hit the page
then you have a new free page
and you can put the uh use that you know
use the new the just free page
to satisfy you know the fault that you
had
and then basically restart the
instruction again
again restart the instruction is a
little bit more complicated because the
whole
machinery to basically do useret and
uh start it and transfer back to user
space etc
uh and so this is a you know typical
operating system we'll do this um
and of course the key question is like
what page to evict
which one to choose so what are what are
some candidates you know what
what would be your reasonable policy for
choosing a page to evict
least recently used yeah so this is the
most commonly used strategy least
recently used
or lru
and that is the page that uh that's
typically yours
is thrown out there's a couple sort of
twists that typically are
small optimizations that do if you have
to evict the page and
um you have a choice between a dirty
page and a non-dirty page so dirty page
is a page where there was a store to
and the non-dirty page is a store page
that basically only has been read but
not written to
which one would you prefer to vic first
a three one because you would have to
write the dirty one at some point anyway
yeah uh so so we're gonna say again
actually
double check there um i said dirty
because
30 pages would need to be written to
memory at some point
yeah that's true uh but then maybe now
you have to write it twice
you know once you write it maybe it's
modified later again
and so actually typically when an
operator oh i see okay the dropping
system is exactly the opposite
uh they choose a page that actually has
not been written or is not dirty because
you don't have to do anything
you can just reuse it you can just take
uh
if it was present in pt in page table
one your market there is non-valid
and then uh you're done and then you can
reuse that page in another page table
and so the preference and typically take
pages that have been
uh not you know non-dirty ones first
can i just ask for a clarification on
the 30
pages so
um i i know like in a cache
when we have memory and then we say okay
a line is dirty because it hasn't been
written to memory
but what about a page in memory like
what does it correspond to like how is
it dirty where does it have to be
written back to
it just exists in memory right isn't
that the whole whole thing like it
doesn't exist anywhere else really
so when can it be dirty yeah okay so for
example if it's the demand page file
page
uh actually we'll talk about this in a
second like in the next uh
maybe a prefetch a little bit too much
but if you uh with memory map files
where you map a file into uh
memory uh and then the restore to it
then you would dirty that page
okay so that only applies when like a
page actually responds not just to some
memory but also to a file or something
else
exactly okay okay that makes sense yeah
okay so just to uh you know just to make
one more two more points
related to this uh if you look at this
uh the ptes again so we saw this irish w
bit
uh and you'll notice there actually is a
bit seven that is the dirty bit
so when the paging hardware when the
hardware ever writes you know to a page
and watches at the dirty bits so the
operating system later can see you ah
this actually page
can easily see this page that's actually
written to
and similarly there is a uh an a bit
uh that stands for access and so
whenever a page is either written
or written either read or written the
access bit will be set
and uh and why is that useful to know
in what way could that help the colonel
well the ones that haven't been
accessed you can you can evict right
yeah like another way of saying that if
you want to implement these recently
used
uh if uh you find a page that basically
hasn't been accessed in some period of
time you know it actually hasn't been
recently used so it actually is a
candidate for eviction
while the pages that have the access bit
set are not really candidates for
eviction
and so the abit is typically used or the
actual bit is typically used
to actually implement this lru strategy
okay but would you have to reset um
the accessed bits to not accessed every
once in a while or
yeah exactly that's exactly what the
typical operating system will do
and if they don't do it maybe for all
memory they sweep through memory
that's a little you know there's some
famous algorithm for this called the
clock algorithm that is like one way of
doing it
very well would you need to set it why
would you need to reset it
well if you want to know whether page is
recently used uh
you need and you make a periodic
decision uh then say maybe every 100
milliseconds or whatever every second
you know you clear the axis bit
and if it then gets accessed in the next
hundred milliseconds you know it was
used in the last hundred milliseconds
and the pages that don't have the axis
bit set were not used in the last in the
milliseconds
and so then you can keep counters of
like how intentionally they're used and
what is the and throughout the really
it's basically the stepping stone to
build a sort of sophisticated lru
implementation
okay um i want to talk about one more
just to uh
and then that's the last one actually
that you also will be implementing in
uh one of the labs and that is
memory map files
and the idea is that uh you know here we
have
our address space what we really want to
do is basically be able to
load a whole file or parts of the file
into the address space
so that we can just manipulate you know
the content of the file using load and
store instructions
instead of read you know lc can write
and to be able to support that you know
a typical operating system
amongst modern operating systems could
provide a system call called nmap
and basically mf takes a virtual address
or you know pixel virtual address
length uh protection
from flags which we're not going to talk
about and then a file descriptor of an
open file
and then offset and basically what this
says is like you should you know map
you know this file descriptor if this is
address you know the virtual address
you know the file descriptor starting
from offset
you know in the file f you know map that
in
add to address at the virtual address va
and do that we have some protection like
read write etc
and so let's say it's a read write then
you know the
kernel uh when so the way the kernel
implements nmap
is you know if it does it eagerly uh
which is like most
the system don't do it easily you know
basically copy
read all the bytes they're starting from
offset uh lang bytes starting from
offset into
uh memory sets up the uh ptes
to point to the physical memory for
where their blocks are located and then
basically from then on
the uh application can usually should
use load and store instructions to
actually modify
the file and then maybe when they uh
where we're all done
there's typically a corresponding
unmapped call
that an app length
that allows the application to say like
okay i'm done with this particular file
and at the point of the unmapped and we
need to write back the dirty blocks
and we can easily figure out which
blocks are dirty because
they have to d bit set in the pte
now of course in any memory
sophisticated memory
uh implementation uh this is all done
lately you know you just don't map the
file immediately
uh you just keep a record somewhere on
the site saying like well you know this
pte
you know really belongs to this
particular file descriptor so there's
some
information maintained on the site which
is typically called
in the structure called the vma or the
virtual memory area
and for example for this file f that
would be one vma and in a vma we record
you know the file descriptor the offset
et cetera where the actual content of
that memory
lists and so when we uh get a page fault
for a particular address that sits in
this you know dma
and we can go off and the kernel can
read it from disk
and uh bring it into memory
and uh in response to an early question
this is like one of the reasons that
this dirty bit is important because at
the
map you have to write back the dirty
blocks
does this make sense
um i have a quick question yeah uh
maybe this is a more general issue but
could it ever be an issue if say
multiple processes are
memory mapping the same file on
secondary storage
and then they like like synchronization
issues yeah
good question uh so what is the
semantics in units in general like what
happens if multiple processes are read
or write to the same file using reading
over the right system calls
does unix guarantee anything
oh it's undefined yeah this is like no
the right the reason right will show up
in some order or the rights will show up
in some order so if two processes you
write to the same block off the file you
know
either the first process writes go or
the second process rights go
one of the two and so here's basically
the same thing you know we don't really
have to guarantee anything
if you want to do a more sophisticated
unix operating system support file
walking
where you can lock files and then you
can
properly synchronize but by default
there's no synchronization
or no synchronization at this level
makes sense i'm sorry what is length
and what is flags oh flags uh ling
is the length of the you know the area
you want to map the files the number of
bytes
uh prod is read write x flags you know
is you'll see that when you do the map
uh
i think this has to do with whether the
area is mapped private or shared
uh if it's not shared then you know it
can be shared among multiple processes
any further questions about this
if some other process modifies the file
and disk that means that this will not
be reflected here right
uh that's correct uh unless i think if
it's not
shared then you're supposed to reflect
those changes
right but then they would be using the
same file descriptor right
[Music]
i'm hazy on the exact you know semantics
of
nmap when things are shared and what
exactly happens there
okay i get so i guess in like the
idiomatic case yeah and the shared
they would have to reflect it but
if a process just like actually opened
the same file name
completely set separately i think
it could be unsynced even if it's shared
yeah that's correct
okay so uh so this is after the file
system lab
you actually do memory map files and
that will be our last
virtual memory sort of laugh unless you
decide at the end to do more virtual
memory uh
uh features or exercises uh whatever you
want to do uh
anyway so the main choice this will
conclude this lecture um
the you know sort of summary
you know we have loot in the past you
know sort of in great uh detail
exactly you know uh page tables work
uh you've done a couple laps and one lap
the page tables we've looked a lot at
like how traps work
and and you know page faults and it
turns out you know if you combine the
two
you know you're going to get you can
implement very powerful
and elegant
uh virtual memory features
and you know went through a whole list
of them uh
mostly focusing on the ones that
actually going to be implementing in
future labs
uh but you know this is only a subset
very sample
of the ones that you know some operating
systems implemented and the typical
operating systems implement all the ones
that actually discussed today
so you look at linux it has all of them
and many more interesting other tricks
but this hopefully gives you a good
sense you know sort of how the power of
virtual memory
uh once you dynamically can change the
page tables uh in the page fault
headline
i think this is exactly that 25 so maybe
it is a good point to
stop but if you have any questions you
know feel free to ask them
and if not you know we should good luck
finishing uh the trap lab
and i hope it's not as painful as the uh
or not as hard as the page table lab
oh sorry i had another question when you
map in the
in the previous slide um when you map
the whole file or like when you put it
into memory
and it turns out to be longer than
length um
then what happens so if the file doesn't
fit in the virtual address space
oh i guess so like length is how
much of the file we want yes
yeah so length is just like we want to
map like 10 bytes
out of the file descriptor starting and
offset off
oh okay okay so if the file is longer
then we're not gonna
put all of it into memory yeah yeah we
can always yeah exactly
okay i see thank you
um thank you i've got a question i've
got a question about
[Music]
evicting pages so
so we talked about it under like the man
caging part two but is that like a
general
procedure we would use in any of these
techniques if we discover that we're out
of
physical boundary yeah as the common
basically mechanisms like so even in
lazy allocation we run at the point
where uh
there's no memory available anymore to
allocate to the page
and you know we support demand paging or
whatever we use evict you know some page
you know
typically using lru okay and one way to
think about it is that in the steady
state the operating system basically
runs
uh with all memory in use at any time
and want to use old memory
and so when we start something new you
know we have to make some room
and you know lru is basically a way to
do it
okay make sense thank you