valid address yeah he had to be not so
good
good how about erica how's the
lazy life for you um i also thought it
was okay
and um i also had a bug with the coffee
and coffee app but uh
got that result so yeah yeah i think
it's one of those
tricky cases that you might not think
about when you start programming
but luckily user tests will find it for
you
caroline ortega
the lab is going good um i haven't
finished yet actually
all right so worry about copying i guess
how about kendall garner
i think for the most part it was
not too bad for me probably the weirdest
part was just trying to figure out when
it went
below bounds of the stack
ah yeah into the guard page basically
good okay well
uh so it's about time to get started uh
so welcome to the next lecture in
s081 wherever you are in whatever time
zone
so today's lecture is about locks
and you probably have seen locks in
previous classes
or at least i've been in touch with them
in some way or another uh
and so this lecture's a little bit of a
conceptual lecture uh may overlap a
little bit with some uh
things you've seen before for locks but
we'll uh have a little bit more of a
kernel and os focus
and that changes a couple things um so
just to get started you know let's just
remind ourselves
uh why we need locks um you know and i
guess the starting point is really that
applications
uh want to use multiple cores
they want to use multiple cores to get
performance
and so if an application actually
wants to do runs on multiple cores and
presumably once the in
this course or the parts of the
application may invoke system calls
and so the kernel must be able to handle
uh you must handle parallel system calls
uh and that means that you know if these
system calls run in parallel on
different course
they may actually access shared data
structures
the instructions in parallel
and as you've seen by now actually x6
has quite a number of
you know shared data structures you know
whether it's the proc structures or
uh you know ticks or you know
later we'll see the buffer cache you
know there's actually a ton of shared
data structures
um and so if you have parallaxis you
know through
a data structure and one of the you know
course is a writer and the other course
is a reader
uh you know we need basically blocks you
know to coordinate these updates to the
shared data structure so that
readers see a consistent view so we'll
need logs
you know to you know for controlled
sharing
or for correct sharing
now this is in some sense a little bit
of a bummer
because you know we want this parallexis
we want to run multiple uh consistent
calls in
uh in parallel on a different course
but unfortunately you know if they share
the data structures you know they need
locks and locks no serialize
basically operations and so in fact you
know locks in the end can limit
performance
and so we're sort of in a tricky
situation where you know for correctness
we need locks
you know but for performance uh they're
not good
uh but you know sort of it's going to be
sort of a fact of life and
uh you know we'll see what we can do
about it
but that's sort of the top-level uh
scenario here
and you know maybe just to really you
know uh
bring this point why do applications
actually want to uh
multiple course and now that really has
to do with your technology trends you
know over the last you know a couple
decades
uh and you know there's sort of this
classic graph that sort of make these
points
uh so let me you know pull up one of
them there's a little bit of a
complicated graph
uh but you know there's years on the
x-axis and y-axis there's you know units
uh they're different types of units
depending on you know which line we're
looking at
uh but the thing that really to look at
is that uh
what has happened in the last couple
years is that over the last decades is
that
[Music]
starting in the 2000s that the clock
frequency
hasn't really increased anymore uh so
basically this has you know
plateaued or constant
um and as a result you know basically
single
threat performance of the core also you
know basically
uh has reached you know sort of a limit
you know or plotted
uh and yet on the other hand given the
minimum course of the number transistors
still has been increasing over the same
time period so if you can't like you
know use transistors to make a single
core sort of run faster
uh you know the only other option
basically have is you know i have
multiple cores and you see indeed that's
starting from 2001 or from the early
2000s you know the number of course has
gone up
and so there's an application once more
performance you know
uh you know can rely on the single core
it basically has to explode multiple
cores
and also this means if an application is
you know kernel intensive os
intensive you know whereas like a server
then that means that the operating
system also has to be
run efficiently on multiple cores and so
that's the main reason
uh you know that we're sort of very
interested in
you know parallelism you know within the
in the kernel
any questions about this
okay i've seen i i assume that you've
seen some of these graphs uh before but
it's
good to remind us you know what the
starting point of all the discussion is
um so why logs
you know already hinted at this you know
they're there for uh correctness
uh you know if we have you know readers
and writers you know
exiting a shared data structure and you
know the thing that goes wrong
is that we want to avoid race conditions
so if you don't have locks you know we
run the risk you know
we have shear data structures that we're
going to have uh
we're going to have raised detect
conditions and it turns out that the
race conditions are
uh pretty annoying um and so just
first can we get a little bit of sense
of what it actually is let's look at the
let's just let's create a race condition
in xv6 and
sort of see how it actually shows up and
then understand like look what actually
happened
uh so here's uh
our function k3 uh in calc.c you know so
this is the function that frees
after you free page it puts it on the
free list you know the
kernel has a very simple data structure
to keep the free list of all three pages
uh so that one calendar needs a page
that actually can grab it from the free
glitch
you see here the uh
allocation has one uh the the
the memory allocator has one lock came
in lock
and uh here it actually updates the free
list
uh within page that just has been
treated or the argument to three
so we're gonna do is like just comment
out these two
acquire releases that basically uh mark
you know the
acquiring of the lock and then releasing
the lock you know and so this this
this this piece of code that sits in the
middle uh that used to be
uh there's now not more it's not being
executed anymore
atomically uh
so let's do that uh
and then run uh
qmu so we'll compile it
and you know before i run it in a notice
actually we already booted
and actually uh presumably have made
some calls probably to
k3 as you probably as you know and so
effective things seem to be working fine
so let's run user tests and maybe you
know it's interesting to think a little
bit about this now what do you expect
will this
work will this not work
anybody who tried it out
i think it could potentially lose some
pages
but maybe it will not because
uh maybe a race condition wouldn't occur
yeah so one of the things is that these
uh with race conditions they might not
happen so let's
run the user test and see actually what
happens
um so here we start it up
uh take a little while zoom might
complain a little bit because you know
running a lot of put a lot of load in my
machine here correctly if you probably
know
the q mu simulating free cores here and
the discrete course might run in
parallel
and you know so far so good you know
we're starting to pass
tests
that's a little bit slower because i'm
running zoom at the same time
let's wait a couple more and just uh see
what's going on
okay well uh
let's uh just go back to the slides and
then we'll check back in in a little
while so to see what actually happens
uh but you know as pointed out you know
these race conditions may appear may not
appear right because
it is always the case that you know
every core or every time we call k3
these two u lines are executed
atomically
uh as as they would have done with the
lock
then there's no problem and the only
problem is like between two frets or two
processors executed
at the same time and so becomes in
between
look at this actually you know while i'm
talking you know we see actually there
is a panic and so there is some race
condition that can actually cause a
panic
there are other race conditions that
will show up as indeed as uh
as mentioned or as well answered that
will show up as like
not enough you know some free pages
where some pages get lost so basically
user test runs fine until the very end
where it complains saying well you lost
some pages during uh all usual
all of the rounds of user test okay so
these race conditions can show up in
different ways
uh they may happen they may not happen
uh clearly something happened here
uh so let's try to understand you know
what what what actually
uh what goes wrong
back to the slides
so the picture you should have in your
head like so there's this
multiple cores that we're running so
here's cpu0
so cpu0 is executing instructions and
cpu one
is executing instructions and
they're both connected you know to a
memory right if you're
looking back think back up at the scheme
schematics you know that we've shown a
couple times before
in fact there's a dram controller you
know that actually
uh connects you know to the drm chips
where all the stage is living
uh or all the memory is living so i'm
going to make that memory a little bit
bigger because i want to
have some place to draw and so basically
our tree list
you know lives in
in memory and let's say there's a free
list with two pages on it
and you know both
both cpus you know call k3 roughly at
the same time
and so look at a little bit of the code
again just to make sure that we
have this variable in our head so we
look at k3 uh
you know they're get passed in some pa a
physical address
that we're going to use to actually hook
up you know into the free list
so you know cpu 0 has uh
you know an r uh and
that's pointing to to some you know free
page
and uh maybe yeah and
cpu one has one let me actually use
another column for cpu 1.
so cpu knows it has an r it also is pin
pointing to some page
you know that we want to hook into the
free list make sense
and so you know we look back at the code
uh
you know the first thing they do is you
know update our next to point to
uh to point to the to the free list
so let's assume you know that cpu one
runs
uh first and you know what it will do
is we'll put its pointer you know to
the beginning of the uh you know to
wherever freelance is pointing to
and if you know cpr and runs exactly at
the same time
then uh you know
it could run you know before you know
cpu0 executes a second instruction
and so it actually might do the same
thing you know it might actually also
run that first instruction
and update um
and update the pointer 2. so now both
are you know one from cpu 1 and from cpu
zero one for cpo one are pointing to the
beginning of the free list and the free
list is also pointing to the
beginning of the field list and so now
there are two remaining instructions
that are being executed in parallel
so we'll go back again you know the code
you know the remaining instruction is
being executed
is actually updating the free list to
point to r you know uh
and so uh you know cpu you know zero and
one going to execute these instructions
maybe
exactly in the same uh rapidly at the
same time but one is going to go first
correct there's only one single shared
memory
and so one update is going to go first
and the other one is going to go second
so let's say cpu one you know goes first
and now
what will then happen well the cpu one
goes first the three list is gonna be
pointing to sr
right and then cpu 2
runs so now cp2 runs actually this x
instruction
and so what it's going to do it is going
to actually update
you know pre-list two-point
so here's a free list and
it's actually going to point to the r
that actually get passed in and so you
know we have a setting now correct we're
we've lost you know basically one page
the
r you know that actually cpu zero
actually three
actually ended up not being on the free
list at all so
we lost the page
um and that's one you know bad
particular outcome of course it could be
more bad outcomes because there could be
more cpus after trying to do this three
list
uh they may observe the new one of the
my observed three lists pointing
temporarily to the cpu
to zeros r uh and so we start using that
uh well then immediately the freelancer
is updated you know by
uh the second cpu so the more cpu's
involved you know presumably we could
actually get more bizarre outcomes than
just the loss page does this make sense
any questions
okay um so the way
you know ask you know the code does you
know the way to address this uh
one way and a very common way uh is to
address this problem
is to use a lock so let me talk a little
bit about locks
in more detail
so what is a you know what's the lock
abstraction
well uh it is just an object like any
other sort of
uh object in the kernel and then it has
a
there's in fact there's something called
strut lock you know that has some fields
you know to maintain state about locks
and it has a pretty straightforward api
you know there's a
acquired in fact there are only two
calls into this
abstraction uh which
require which takes the uh a pointer to
uh a lock struck and and a release
uh you know that actually uh
also takes a point through the log
struct uh to basically update you know
the lock object
and then basically the rule of the
lighting you know the rule here is that
uh the choir
enforces this uh following rule that
only one
process
you know can enter or can acquire the
lock
so at any particular point in time
there's only going to be one process
that is able to actually
successfully acquire the lock and the
other process the business is trying to
acquire the lock at the same time
has to wait until the first process
actually calls a release
and so this sequence you know the the
instructions you know between
you know the choir and release are often
called the critical section
and one reason it's called the critical
section is because this is sort of the
uh diffused instruction together that do
the uh you know
need to do the update you know to our
whatever data structure that's protected
by the lock
in an atomic fashion uh and then ensures
that basically
if you have multiple instructions in
this you know between the car and
release
that they all are executed all together
or none and so there's never the case
that basically these instructions in the
critical section
are interleaved as in the way that we
saw in the race condition
and actually exactly that is what avoids
these race conditions
any questions about the lock abstraction
now programs typically have
many locks in fact xv6 has many locks
and the reason to have many locks is
because you know even the you know the
the the
walk serializes you know the execution
right the two processes you know want to
enter this critical section only one
succeeds then the other one
runs that critical section after the
first one
finishes so there's no sort of
parallelism at all
so if the kernel had only one lock you
know which is typically called the
big kernel lock then basically every
system call
uh in this uh in the kernel would be
serialized you know you would
assist the call which one start gets the
one the big kernel lock you know does
whatever it needs to do
and then releases the big kernel lock
and then basically research use space
and then the second system called the
drum so we have an apparel application
that runs you know once we run system
calls in parallel
suddenly you know all the system calls
actually run serially if we had only one
lock
and so typically a program like you know
xp6 has
you know many locks because at least you
know when you get some parallelism
because
you know if you have two system calls
for example use two different locks
uh then you know they can actually run
uh completely in parallel
uh without any uh you know serialization
uh because they're basically you know uh
using diff blocks to serialize
now uh there's
sort of a couple of important points uh
the nobody really sort of enforces in
this interface
you know that you put in the acquires
and releases you know it's up to the
program to do so
so if you want some particular piece of
code to be
atomic then it's up to the developer to
actually
put these acquire releases in and you
know clearly as we'll see
if you can imagine um and that is a
little bit uh
it can be tricky and so it's important
to realize that you know the locking is
not actually done automatically for you
uh it's all up to the developer to
figure out to
associate with data structures
and ensuring that you know the
appropriate acquired releases
are dead
um so clearly it's the case like you
know the the
uh blocks limit imperialism and
therefore their limit performance
uh and so then i mean this raises the
question when to lock
and you know i'm going to give you sort
of a very conservative rule
but that's a good one as a starting
point to think about things
so to conserve the rule
or maybe guideline is a better uh
phrasing is that if you know two
processes
two processes access
a shared data structure
and one is a and one of them is a
writer or an updater so meaning it's
actually going to modify the shared data
structure
then you need a lock for that data
uh so this is a conservative rule sort
of like a red flag you know when you're
programming
and you have a data structure that was
accessed by multiple processes and one
can be a writer
at that point you should be thinking
okay there's a possibility of a race
condition
we want to avoid this in a race
condition i'll just stick it in lock
i will use a lock to guarantee that this
race condition can't happen
but you know there's rulers uh in some
ways too strict
uh there are cases where you know it's
okay if two processes actually share
data structure and one is a writer
in particular there are sort of styles
of programming called block free
programming
that actually totally were just where
these kinds of scenarios actually do
happen
you might want to do log free
programming just basically to get better
performance or
more parallelism uh
mark free program is tricky uh even more
tricky than programming with locks
and you know we'll talk about it at the
end of the semester we'll to study some
lock-free styles of the programming that
particularly are
common in operating system kernels but
basically for this lecture
and for most of the rest of the semester
we're going to be thinking about the
case where
uh using locks you know to uh
control uh sharing um and that's hard
enough
you know just using locks it's not that
straightforward either
um so it's in one hand a little bit uh
too strict
uh because it's not always the case that
you uh needed also some cases to lose
uh you might just
um you might even
lose you want to actually maybe want to
use locks you know to enforce some other
uh properties like if you look at printf
uh
if we pass a stream to printf uh you
know the
xv6 kernel tries to at least you know
get the whole string
to be printed atomically and you know
there's no shared data structure
involved
but it's still useful to actually use a
lock in that particular case
because we want the output to be
serialized so
this rule is not you know perfect but
it's a pretty good guideline
any questions about this rule
um i had a question not about this rule
but
isn't it possible that two processes
could acquire the lock at the same time
and so
would be able to modify the structure
yeah no so so part of the sort of
contract of the lock abstraction is is
that it's impossible for two
uh processes to acquire a lock at the
same time
uh if uh the the rule is that there's
ever there's no there's never a case
where two
processes actually acquire the lock uh
can hold the lock at the same time
we'll see in a second how to implement
that but the api or the specification
for require
is there's only one lock holder at any
given point in time or zero
nice
um okay so uh you know if you see
the programming block is here slightly
uh it could be
problematic because of these race
conditions um
yeah now of course the particular race
condition that we looked at
uh in k3 or that we created in crayfi
which are like easily spottable in some
ways and the fact you know if you use a
race detection tool
uh it would immediately find it um but
you know they're more tricky
cases and so you may want to wonder like
why couldn't you like make you know
could you make locks
or could we make locking automatic
so like if you follow this sort of
simple rule that i just stated you know
then if ever we see a shared data
structure
then you know operations and that shared
data structure basically should require
a walk you know we should
we should associate a lot with the data
structure and then every operation
actually uh uh uh that is uh
that's performed on that uh uh
on that data structure basically
required to release the lock so
one way to think about it maybe in xv6
terms like every struct
you know has a lock
and uh and that lock is automatically
required when we do anything related to
that struct
and this turns out to be too rigid and
this is why you know
walking can not really be uh automatic
so so we've been operating systems an
example from one operating system is the
following
let's say we have a call like rename
that moves a file name from one
directory to another directory so let's
say we have d1x
and we rename it to you know d2
y right so we have a file name in the
directory
uh d1 x and you know we rename it to
d2 slash y so the way uh
you presumably if we follow the rigid
rule or like this
rule of automatic locking now what would
happen is uh
you know that rule up soon we have two
objects we have d1 and d2
right and so we follow the rule then
basically the automatic rule then you
know we lock d1
you know erase x
and release
the lock for uh d1
and then you know we do the second part
update you know d2
lock d2 at
yeah y and release
d2 um
and then we're done so this would be the
sort of hypothetical scheme
uh sort of you imagine
uh would happen if we did automatic
walking and
uh and the point of this example is that
you know we will have the wrong outcome
and why why is this a problematic scheme
why is this not gonna work
and so think about like the thing to
think about is like this
period so we have done the first step
step one we've not done step two yet
what could another process observe
anybody
the file would just be gone yeah you
know this
between step one and two the file
doesn't exist
i mean that is clearly wrong because the
file does exist
it's just being renamed uh and another
point of time really that it didn't
exist
but by implementing this in this way it
just appears that the file might
actually not exist even though it does
so the really right you know solution to
this is what we need
is that we actually lock d1
and d2 first at the beginning of rename
then erase and add
and then release
the locks for d1 and d2
so that makes sense so here's sort of an
example where
we have an operation that regression
needs multiple locks
and uh and the locks can not really be
associated with the
two objects that are the arguments of
this operation uh it has to be the case
that actually the operation itself first
requires to both blocks then performs
the operations
so this automatic locking is not sort of
you know directly possible
uh there's gonna be cases where that
just is not gonna run
to the or this native scheme at least
will run into a problem
problems any questions about this
yeah so could we just say that um
when we're accessing a data structure we
just have to access or we have to
acquire all of the locks associated with
all of the data structures we need at
the beginning
yeah so that'll be one way doing it and
i think that this quickly will
uh sort of come down to basically having
a big kernel lock
oh i think okay and then you're on the
wrist basically you have no parallelism
anymore
and so you want to do better than that
right yeah and i think this is always
the tension you know you can make things
simpler
by basically what's called your coarse
grain blocking
but then you know you're loose there's
performance
or you may lose performance depending if
the lock is contented or not
yep makes sense thank you
so lock perspective so there's different
ways
uh to think about locks
and you know there are three common ones
and
uh you know go for all three of them and
just maybe that may help you
to think about locks and maybe one of
them is your favorite and you can use
that one
as your way of thinking about it but
it's probably helpful to see that there
are actually different ways of thinking
about logs
so first of all you know one other way
to think about it is actually a lot
avoid
uh lost updates or help
if you use logs correctly you know
lock's going to help avoiding
lost updates
and if you think about uh our early
example in the catalog.c
you know the lost update is basically
the we lose one update to
the k3 and by putting walks in it you
know where actually we
didn't lose that update so that's one
way you're thinking about it
it's a very low level way uh another way
to think about it
is you know you can make locked blocks
make multi-step operations
atomic
and so there's sort of the view of a
critical section you know we have a
required walk we do a whole bunch of
steps or instructions we executed all
the instructions then release
and basically that whole critical
section execute as an atomic operation
and that's sort of the uh and also a
fine way you know to think about locks
and then the third one uh you know that
may be helpful is that
really what locks do is locks health
maintain an invariant
data structure that you know it's
protecting and
uh what really is going on is that uh
at the before a choir if there's no lock
holder you know
that invariant holds uh when we acquire
the lock and we do some operations then
temporarily that invariant may be
uh violated but at the point that we do
the release
and so if you think about our free list
uh
case you know the invariant is there uh
you know
the three pointer points to uh one other
next pointer
and all the three pages are on a single
list
uh and that's temporarily violated uh
at the point uh
in the middle of the k3 because like
multiple
pointers actually point to the beginning
of the free list
and then it's established at the end of
it so and you know for
you know the free list it has a not so
complicated variant but like for more
uh complicated shared data structures
you know it can be a helpful way of
thinking actually what the lock is doing
for you
and so see even in this kind of the k3
case you know all three lock perspective
for reasonable perspective
um and uh you know one of them
you know uh brings more with you than so
than one of the other ones and you know
use that as your way to think about
locks
any questions about this point
okay so i'm gonna now run for a couple
things
uh uh sort of uh
you know undesirable properties or that
can actually happen with locks
and you know we know like locks are uh
necessary to fix a correctness problem
you know to avoid these race conditions
blocks themselves in
when inappropriate inappropriately used
can also introduce their own set of
problems
and so i want to talk a little bit about
that and so the obvious one
of course is deadlock
you know for example you know the the
simplest case you know was a little bit
boring but i mean you
worthwhile thinking about you know if
you do an acquire
you know a lock and so you start the
critical section
and in the critical section you do
another acquire
of the same lock
what will happen
can the second acquirer succeed
well with the spec that we've given
early on uh you know
this should be not allowed and so
basically the second acquirer must block
until the first acquire release the lock
but that was
you know the process itself so basically
this resulted in a deadlock
now this is a trivial example of a
deadlock uh maybe now there's
interesting in fact this is a deadlock
that xv6 detects you know because when
it sees that the same process requires
the same walk again uh it actually
causes a panic the more interesting
cases are
when multiple locks are involved so
let's
go to our previous example let's say we
have the following
uh we have core one or maybe
cpu one
we have cpu two
and cpu 1 you know executes
vname directory1x
to directory2 y
and cpu 2 executes at the same time
uh rename
uh in the other way in the other
direction
you know d2 a to
the one you know why i say b
just to make the names different so the
critical
thing to observe here is that cpu1 you
know runs a rename from d1 to d2
and cpu uh two does exactly the opposite
that doesn't rename from d2 to d1
so let's assume that we actually
acquired the locks in the order of their
arguments
and so what will happen rick is that uh
in this case
you know we'll acquire both locks we
know from our previous example that is
actually
important so we'll acquire
v1 lock
and you know let's say they really run
they're truly concurrent
so at that point you know this other guy
might actually this other cpu might
acquire
d2 first because that is its first
argument
and now of course d2 d1 wants to acquire
d2
so i'll try to acquire d2 will it
succeed
i won't succeed because you know the
other guy you know actually has the lock
and so this guy will stop here and not
proceed
now let's look at the other cpu cpu2
acquired d2
it's not going to require d1 for its
secondary argument
he's going to try to call it's going to
call acquire d1
and will it be able to proceed no it
won't be able to proceed
right because the cpu one actually has
to walk in d1
and so here we you know sometimes this
is called the deadly embrace
you know uh where you know the
because in the way we acquired the
ordering which we ordered which we quite
unlocked results actually in deadlock
does that make sense this example
this is like a little bit of a more
endangering example correct of deadlock
you know it's not an obvious
problem and the solution turns out in
some sense reasonably simple
the solution is that you know if you
have multiple locks then
you have to order the locks
and all operations have to acquire
locks in that order
so if you're a system designer you have
to decide you know what the
global order is for all log objects
and so for example in this case we may
want to decide that d1
should be always ordered before d2 and
that means that
when we execute a rename the rule of
life is we always acquire
uh the lower numbered uh
directories first before we acquire the
higher order directory numbers
and that will ensure that basically uh
there's a global order
and you know this particular case you
just cannot happen
uh because you know the block order is
going to be then
for v1 d2 for this guy
and this guy will acquire the locks
exactly in the same global order you
know d1 d2
and then we don't have this deadline
bridge
this makes sense
any questions about this
so this uh indicates a little bit of a a
problem
even though like okay so it fixes you
know this sort of deadlock problem by
having global order
notice this order is global
and this is uh
an issue a little bit when designing a
system because
um hold on
uh so if you think about the sort of
walk ordering
you know that has to be sort of global
and so if one module one m you know
calls a method in marshall
two um
and the collar you know and one g you
know might actually
needs to be aware or could be you need
to be aware actually or what locks
f acquires award walks you know and two
uses
uh because uh if you know and two
uh uses some set of locks uh then
you know if we follow our walk ordering
rule uh jesus got to make sure that you
know if it has some locks
that it acquires all locks you know from
f and g together actually in some
uh global order and so that really means
that these are the internals
the internals of m2 at least in terms of
locks
must be visible to m1
so that you know and one can ensure that
actually you know uh calls
uh at uh n2 in the in in the appropriate
way
uh and you know in some ways that is you
know sort of an abstraction violation
you know abstractions work out perfectly
you know m1 doesn't really know you need
to know anything about how m2 is
implemented
and unfortunately logs are a common
example where some of the internals you
know of m2 might actually leak out to m1
because m1 really needs to know and so
you know when you design a bigger system
uh you know
this makes the modularity more
complicated
um oh sorry i was just wondering does it
need to be
a complete um ordering of locks or
can there be some blocks that are um
like that can be ordered in whatever way
they yeah it depends if like f and g
you know share any locks right so for
example if you like and look at xv6
uh there uh are sort of multiple strands
of lock orderings because some
blockchain have nothing to do with other
locks and so they know
they're never required together and so
if they're never acquired together
they're just joined block sets if you
will
and then only you have to make sure that
the ordering in one particular lock set
is global
and the ordering in the other lock sets
is completely independent of the other
ordering
so it is correct that there is no
doesn't have to be a global ordering but
like
all the functions that you know
manipulate the same shared sort of
log set they need to agree on in global
order
thank you
okay so one you know another sort of
uh challenge uh with box uh we've seen
now two challenges one is deadlock one
is modularity
uh the second uh challenge or third
challenge is just walks
versus performance
and you know really hinted at this a
couple times but it needs to uh
is important enough to sort of actually
put some emphasis on
uh and so basically if you want to get
performance you need to split up data
structures
right so if you have one big kernel lock
uh that will limit your performance to
basically performance in a single cpu
if you want you know performance remove
uh you want that to perform scales
with the numerous cpus you got to split
up
you need to split up data structures
um and the best split you know
[Music]
is not obvious or can be a challenge
uh you know for example you know if you
do associate the lock with every
directory should you associate the lock
with every inode
you know should you associate a lock
with every process or not uh
or is it better you know to sort of
split the data structures in a different
way
um and uh and if you make a change you
know you
re redesigned sort of the locking
discipline
uh and then they've got to make sure
that you know you're still maintained in
variance that actually
the kernel is trying to maintain uh and
if you split locks you know you also
have to rewrite the goat
or you may have to need that may write
may need to
rewrite code too
and so it turns out that basically
you refactor you know the
parts of your kernel or part of your
apparel program to get better forms
by splitting data structure ops
introducing more locks
uh you know that it's just it's a lot of
work you have to carefully think through
that you maintain the values that you
intended to maintain
you have to rewrite code and so
generally this is just a lot of work
and not easy
and so this is a little bit of a
negative you know news point right
because
you know we want to get better
performance and that suggests you know
more locks
uh and uh but that
you know it's actually a you know a lot
of work
and so the general recipe you know to
how to go about this
is to you know start of course during
walks
and then measure
so i'm going to run a bunch of
applications on top of your kernel
and see whether you get actually any
speed up if they actually explode
multiple cars
and if they do you know your base will
be done right
your walking design is good enough if if
you don't get speed up
basically that means that some lock is
contended
multiple processes are trying to get the
same lock and therefore they are
serialized
and therefore you don't get speed up
then you know you have to rethink about
then you need to redesign
but the point is that you want to be
guided you know by these
measurements uh because it may be the
case that you know some module that
uses of course green block is just not
called uh in parallel often
and therefore it's not necessary to
actually redesign
and since redesign is a lot of work you
know and you know it also
can complicate the reasoning about that
code uh you know then
you know it's a good idea not actually
to do that redesign is it's not
necessary
um and so in general a good
rule of thumb is you know start with
course grade locks
measure whether a contention appears in
one of these locks and then
redesign that part of the system so that
you get better better parallelism
does it all make sense any questions so
far
okay let's look at uh uh
let's do a little uh let's look at the
in xc6 uh you know some code you know
so you can understand a little bit uh
how this locking sort of works out in
practice in xv6 uh
and so i'm going to go back to our uh
to the this screen
uh i really need this and i want to look
at
view art because you know we're start
talking about locking there
uh on
[Music]
a monday and i want to look a little bit
more in detail
uh now that we know a little bit more
about locks and then also
illustrate a couple of interesting
points
so first uh you know it turns out you
know i want to go to
you know looking at lock
you know turns out that the uart
actually has only one lock
so you can think about this as a
reasonable coarse grained uh
design at this particular point at least
for the uart
and that particular lock you know
protects uh basically the uart
transmission buffer and the right
pointer
and the read pointer and so when we
transmit you know the
right pointer points to the next free
slot in the transmission buffer
and the read pointer is the next law
that actually needs to be transmitted
okay this is our uh standard design
for uh parallelism uh over consumer
producer consumer parallelism so let me
go back and
brought it out so case study
uart and there's basically a buffer
and there's a read point there's a right
pointer or
right read index and read index
this has to go to the uart displayed
and this is the writer
printf maybe that actually sticks
characters into this buffer
okay and so you know what we can see is
that the lock
uh you know the lock has multiple rolls
one is to basically protect this data
structure
and this data structure has some
invariance
namely the read to proceed you know the
right
anything between r and w our characters
that need to be sent
anything between w and r are things that
actually are empty slots and the locks
basically help us
maintain that invariant
so here's our
code again and you know let's look at
the choirs so
here's the uart put c and you know the
first thing
you know you work with c does is
actually you know grab the lock
uh and then stick the character
if there's a place in the buffer sticks
the barrier character in the buffer
and starts you know the printing and
then releases
the lock so if two
processes at the same time call uart
quick c
then this lock will ensure that you know
one character from the first process
goes in the first slot
and then the uh second character
of the second process you know goes in
the next slot and they're known as
happen to
end up in the same slot right so this is
like a clear example where
luck you know helps us to uh
uh you know avoid the race condition
uh because otherwise you know the the
second process might over
write you know the first processes
character
so that's one part so then we go look at
uh
we did that a little bit before if you
look at start you know we see a couple
more things going on
um the uh
we see actually that the uh if the
buffer is not you know the uh
if the buffer is not empty then you know
we know that
basically there's a bunch of uh
characters that are being progressed
or being sent and you know the lock you
know make sure that we don't really
uh overwrite any of those and so
anything that's sort of at the
tail end of the queue uh is actually uh
being processed
by the uart uh
itself so tail end
is in flight
and we make sure that we basically don't
modify or interfere with that particular
aspect by you know
grabbing a lock and then finally
the sort of more and more thing is that
the rights
you know to the registers of the uart
like the thr register
which one there's only one you know
basically the lock ensures
uh you remember that you are start is
called with the lock held
uh ensures that there's only one writer
you know to the ta
register and so another sort of
invariant
or another aspect that the locking
enforces is that
hardware registers
have one writer
okay now there's one other instant thing
that i want to
uh talk a little bit about and that is
uh you know if the uart is done correct
the hard work is done then
there was an interrupt and uh
and as you know we noticed before york
start correct you know we have to
the color it's it's on the collar to
require the lock
to ensure uh that uh with
multiple uh entities writing to the
right register
um and so uh the uart interrupt itself
could run in parallel you know with
another process that called printf so if
some practical printf
that runs a cpu zero and on cpu one
actually takes the uart interrupt you
know because maybe it's doing nothing
and so it's ready to take an interrupt
at any particular point in time
and it will uh call your start
and it has to be the case correct you
know we want to ensure that there's a
single raider you know to these hardware
registers
uh or to protect you know the variance
actually of the
transmission buffer uh you know we have
to acquire the lock
and so it is the case that uh in xv6
actually that
interrupts you know can run you know so
the bottom half of the driver can run
truly concurrent on uh uh on different
processors
with the top half of the driver and so
therefore your interrupt
functions uh also acquire walks and in
fact in this particular case
uh you know it requires the one lock
that is actually in the uart and
then calls you right start and then
releases the lock
and i'll come back to that in a second
because there's a little bit trickiness
uh in implementing a lock in such a way
that this actually works out correctly
and the the thing that actually you
should be worried about
is that i'll actually talk about it in a
second let me postpone that until i get
there
okay so any uh questions about this is a
simple example of uh lock use
in the uart
okay let me uh that brings let me
talk about implementing a lock uh
and so the spec is that only one uh
process
can acquire a lock uh there's no more
than
one lock holder at any given point of
time and and we now want to look
and understand actually how you
implement the walk in such a way that
that actually is guaranteed
let me first write a broken lock so that
we understand
you know what the challenges for
broken acquire
so now we know what the challenge is
actually in implementing choir
uh so here's my broken one uh so
construct takes in environment front
lock
star l and
you know what it does is as follows it
has an infinite loop
while one uh you know if
uh l is
locked to zero meaning nobody's holding
it
then presumably the caller should grab
the log so
then we set l lock to one
and you know at that point we got the
lock so we can return
nothing to do anymore and close
loop if we didn't get the lock because
when the lock was one that means
somebody else is holding lock so we just
keep spinning
and waiting to go around the loop over
and over and over
until at some point you know the whole
lock holder called
release which will set lock to will set
lock to zero
and you know so what's wrong with this
particular implementation
i think two processes might read that
it's uh
not locked at the same time yeah right
yeah so there's a race condition here
right and uh
just to make sure that the race is right
here
we can have basically two cpus coming in
so if we talk a time diagram
you know cpu one uh cpu zero
cpu one you know this is statement a
maybe this is statement b uh both cpu
one
you know reaches statement a uh
and cpu zero and cpu uh
zero one both are each statement a so
they both see
uh locked being zero and then they above
execute b
all right so here they see lock to zero
this guy c lock to zero
and so they both execute statement b and
now both uh
have uh acquired the lock and uh which
violated you know the spec of this
particular function
this makes sense
so it turns out you know to solve this
problem
and sort of get a correct implementation
there are multiple ways of going about
it
but the most common way is to rely
basically on a special hardware
instruction
uh an art of instruction that basically
what it does
it does this test and this set
atomically
and so the solution to this
problem is hardware
test and set support
and the way you can think about it you
know on the risk five you know this
instruction actually is the
atomic memory operation swap
that we're going to be using uh and
it basically boils down to test and then
a set and you know basically what the
hardware guarantees
if you will so you take this uh it takes
two arguments or three arguments an
address
uh a register one r1
and a register two and essentially what
the hardware does the
just conceptually is basically it locks
the address
if you will i'll talk about that in a
second a little bit more with logs
address
it
it puts in a temporary variable you know
the
value that actually is at that
particular address
and then
writes the value of r1 into that address
and then basically puts the value that
was at the
originally at the address into the temp
uh the temporary value that was the
original value that was actually
addressed actually into an r2
and then basically unlocks and returns
um and you know
in the this lock if you will guarantee
is that basically this test
you know where the result of the test is
returned into r2
and the set actually happen atomically
and so this is a hardware instruction uh
most processors have an artwork
instruction like this
because it's a convenient way to
actually implement locks
and so basically what we've done is like
we've reduced you know sort of the
automaticity of this
or the software lock implementation to
basically
a hardware lock implementation uh
and uh so the processor might implement
this in
very different ways so basically uh the
instruction set itself where this is
like a specification it doesn't actually
say how it's implemented
and this is very dependent in the actual
implementation
of this is dependent
on how the memory system exactly works
so for example uh if you know the module
processor
uh share a single memory controller that
retail writes to memory
then the memory controller can actually
support this operation you can basically
allow uh basically you know set a lock
and a particular address you know and
then
let you know one processor do two
operations or three uh
instructions and then basically unlock
and so since all the
processors the reason writes go for this
memory controller the memory controller
can do the ordering or the blocking
uh if the memories are in this processor
sit on the shared bus
it's often the bus arbiter that can
actually do that where the bus arbiter
has support for
basically executing two uh memory
operations in an atomic way
uh if it's a if the processors have
caches
uh then it's sort of typically part of
the cash rehearse protocol where
uh the cash continues protocol will
ensure that
if there's a writer you know that that
particular uh
the cash line that holds you know the
the value that we want to update ends up
in one single cache
and then you know basically the
processor is going to sort of lock that
single cache line across
two uh operations and so the the
implementation of this
you know can be done in many different
ways uh but conceptually
the what's going on is like you lock the
address uh you read the original value
you store in the new value and you
return the old value
does that make sense
to make that to see how we can use that
instruction
let's actually look at the
implementation of acquire and release in
xv6 and then we'll expose a couple of
other interesting details
so let me first uh bring up spinlock.h
uh it's been locked at h as you can see
it's pretty straightforward uh it has
this
flight lock exactly as in our pseudocode
and then it has two other things for
debugging namely the name of the lock
and the cpu the last the current cpu
that actually is holding the lock
and this is mostly to print out
debugging messages for example if you do
two acquires on the same cpu
okay so then let's look at
the implementation
uh and so let's start out with the choir
um and let's first look at this loop
so this is actually uh the sort of test
and set loop that i just talked about
it turns out that in um
uh the c standard actually defines
uh one of these atomic operations and so
um and so the c standard actually has a
function that
uh says you know sync lock test and set
and basically it specifies behavior that
i
just described and then every processor
basically is required you know to
implement
uh that behavior and since most
processors have a
matching sort of test and set hardware
instruction this turns out to be a
reasonable straightforward or
approximate to implement
and so in fact if you look at kernel.asm
you know we can look at the assembly
instructions and see exactly you know
what the risk 5 processor does
so back here is
our assembly instructions for require
and
let's here's our atomic swap instruction
uh so as you can see uh if
you know an atomic swap basically uh is
called with the register a5
and uh as the input and the output also
ends up in a5
and s1 is to hold to the address and
uh and if it's not equal
uh we return and otherwise
basically we go back you know to uh
jump back to uh uh
double check i'm saying the right thing
here uh move a
four in six if not equal to go to ox
20 plus oaks 22.
uh that's a little bit hard to calculate
but that basically in one case we branch
out
and in the other case we branch back and
so this may be easier to
look at the c code
[Music]
so let's go in here so what happens so
if the
if the lock is not held uh what will be
the value of l locked well
l log will be zero all right and so
we call this test and set what will
happen is we'll write a one
yeah in walked but return the previous
value
so if the previous value is zero uh
then we're good right because that means
that nobody was holding the lock and we
fall through
and we're done with this while loop
now let's say the log value was one so
the pro the
the lock was actually locked well what
will this instruction do
it will uh read you know the old value
and put that at the site correct that is
one actually in this case and then write
a new one into that location
um and but that will change nothing
right because the
lock was already locked and and the
function will return one
indicating that actually somebody the
previous hold that it was already locked
and so in that case
it's unequal to zero and so we'll spin
and we'll keep spinning
until locked actually is set back to
uh zero and zoom level happened in the
release
any questions about this
no questions okay um
so now basically you know let's look at
the corresponding uh
the release operation and
uh
and uh here's uh the release operation
and if you look at the kernel asm again
that instruction uh so let's release
probably right after it here's release
so the release actually also uses this
atomic swap instruction
and putting basically zero into s1
and so this guarantee is basically that
this atomic update you know to
lock or lk locked uh
writing a zero into lk locked is an
atomic operation
many of you ask why not just you know
you store
a store instruction to actually write to
zero and anybody
may want to guess why why that might not
work or
what the problem could be because then
some other process might be writing a
one to the log or
no or writing another zero but that
can't be the case right
yeah well there could be okay so there
could be two processes or two cpus
writing to l locked at the same time
right
uh but i think what the the question
really is that you know for many people
and i often assume this too
is that you when you do a single store
instruction that's sort of like an
atomic operation
and that is not always the case you know
for example if you
uh and it really depends on the
architectural implementation
like for example if the cascadiers
protocol works or the cache system works
using cache lines where a cache line may
be
bigger than an integer typically bigger
than the integer
uh then really what's happening is the
first operation is loading the cache
line and then updating the cache line
so in fact you know a store instruction
basically has sort of two micro
operations in it
and and you can get the wrong result
and so uh you know the to the devoid you
know
having to understand anything of the
hardware implementation of exactly and
whether integers operations are atomic
or not
or writing to 64-bit 64
bit memory values and atomic operation
you know we use the
uh uh there is five
operation that is guaranteed to be
executed atomically
does that make sense
yes okay okay so just to uh
just for your amusement uh the
atomic swap is not the only instruction
uh that exists uh so here's the risk
five manual
uh and it lists a whole bunch of the
atomic operations so there's an atomic
end
an atomic ore and there's a max min
that all can read and write a value
in an atomic operation
okay so there's a couple other things
that i want to point out
uh in this particular implementation um
and let me start again and go back to
acquire uh so
one of the first things that the uh
acquire function does
uh is it uh turns off
interrupts and it'd be good to
understand why that is the case and so
for that i'm to go back to our uart exam
code and you think a little bit about
this
and so we want to think about the case
where
uh a query is actually maybe incorrectly
implemented and does not turn off
erupts so and the way to think about
this is if we go to europe
put c and here you know let's say your
qt runs
and uh acquires the lock
and but does not turn off interrupts
what can happen
i'll give everybody a couple seconds to
think about it but
if you have an idea or why it might be
wrong you know like
jump in
perhaps it could be interrupted because
of um because of the clock
and then something happens and it needs
to print something
else and it tries to do your put c again
but the lock is already taken yeah that
might be a possible scenario
uh there's a much more direct example
for this
so let's just say you are could see you
know drives lock
and the universe basically transmitting
some character
so one the urge is done uh transmitting
character what does it do
it causes an interrupt correct and you
are interrupted runs
and what does your interrupt do it grabs
the same lock
you know that the pc is holding right so
what will happen here
if there's only one cpu and so there's
no other cpu where this
interrupt could be running well we have
a deadlock
right because the current cpu is holding
the lock as part of you put see then
later
the interrupt came in and the first
thing it tries to do is actually
acquired a lot that's already held
in fact you know in the case of xv6 you
know we'll get a panic you know because
you know the same cpu
is actually trying to acquire the same
lock again
so basically you know what acquire or
spinlock deals with is sort of two
different types of concurrency
you know one there's sort of concurrency
between two different cpus
we got to make sure that for example if
the interrupter function runs on a
different cpu
that basically we don't get a raise on
the transmission buffer
but if they run in the same cpu we got
to make sure that it's still atomic
uh and that is not being interrupted and
therefore we actually turn the yarn
wraps off
in the choir and they're only turned on
again
at the end of release when the lock
actually has been released and at that
point it's safe again you know to take
these interrupts
because the lock actually is not
released anymore it's not acquired
holding it not health anymore
does that make sense
okay there's one more subtle thing in
this
implementation that i want to talk about
and that we need to deal with
and that is uh memory ordering
so uh for example if you think about you
know locked
is let's say acquires it's locked you
know
to one uh maybe we have a critical
section in which you know x is except x
plus one
and uh and then require
release you know says lock to zero so
you sort of think about the instruction
stream that's being executed on a
particular cpu
you know so these are sort of the
instructions that are being executed
right
now if the code were just purely uh
sequential
[Music]
the compiler or the
processor could actually or reorder
instructions you know just to get better
performance
so for example uh if it were a
sequential stream
would it be okay to move this
instruction to afterwards
would that change the correctness of the
single stream of execution
no not really right because lock and x
are totally independent of each other
there's no relation to it so it'd be
perfectly fine if it were a sequential
execution
that the x you know has moved after the
locked uh
log zero so that you know on the single
single serial execution
that's okay
and in fact so in effect processors you
know do this all the time you know they
do respectively execute stuff
uh or especially execute instructions
and so that can result in basically
these instructions reorderings
uh the compiler does it too you know to
maybe optimize you know some code path
and it also will reorder instructions as
long as it like you know
results in the same serial execution but
clearly during concurrent execution this
would be disaster correct because if
locked which a require and this was our
release
then basically what we've done we moved
to the critical section outside of the
the the acquiring release and then be
totally incorrect
so that's wrong wrong
in a concurrent execution
and so you know to forbid or tell the
compiler in the hardware not
you know to do this uh there's something
what's called
a memory fence or something kind of
synchronized
uh there's an instruction that basically
says like any loads of storage before
this point
you're not allowed to move beyond this
point
and so release has this and uh acquiring
has this
and so for example this x plus x plus
one if that was
uh uh updated after the choir and before
the release
that x plus x plus one has to stay
before you know this particular memory
synchronization point
and so it will not be there will be no
trouble uh
with uh memory ordering so this is the
reason
why sync synchronizes there uh both in
the
release and also there's one in the
acquire
does that make sense
i have a question um
is it is it by convention that the start
of
the port so i guess i guess
the compiler could figure out that there
is an
instruction before the lock is even
acquired
and that it can be just as well moved
after the lock is released
um can that happen or will it
encounter the barrier and see that we'll
see you know in this case
a choir has a barrier and releases a
barrier so anything that happened before
locked in sector one will happen before
that it will never pass that instruction
so this is a barrier so if you will
this is barrier one and this is barrier
two
and so that means that any instructions
before here stay here
any structure in between will happen
between the two between between required
release and then instruction after
it will stay after the release
okay
okay okay so i'm running uh you know
close to the end
so let me just actually uh
wrap up here
so uh so locks you know
blocks are good for correctness
uh but can be bad for performance
uh which is sort of a bummer correct
because one reason we actually
you know got into locks is basically to
get correctness during aerial execution
uh but the locks actually limit parallel
uh execution so that's one
and two locks complicate
uh programming and you will experience
that in some of the labs that we're
going to be doing in fact from now on
we'll see
locks showing up all the time and that
will give us uh
you know at least you know uh some
thought you know it's going to be
necessary to understand like why the
locks are there and you know what they
protect
um and but they're sort of inherent uh
if you didn't do parallel programming
uh the you know you need to use locks
and so you know if you want to avoid the
complications due to locks is you know
the couple things you could do you know
don't share if you don't have to
if you don't have shared data structures
these race conditions cannot happen uh
and so there
and so you you don't need locks and so
you don't need this complicated
programming
uh but you know typically you will have
some shared data structures you will do
uh you will need locks and i think the
thing to do is start with coarse grained
and then move to firing grain
if necessary based on you know
measurements you want to determine
make sure that the lock is actually
contended you know before you actually
start redesigning
and finally you know use a race detector
to
you know one of these race detector
tools to actually find
uh problems uh or race conditions
because you know you put the locks in
the wrong or you put the acquiring the
releases in the wrong place and in fact
you know you still have
uh races okay so this is a quick
introduction to logs uh we're going to
talk
a lot more about locks in the basically
for the rest of the semester that will
show up and we'll talk a little bit more
about lock free program and the end
and see how that is done in in kernels
okay so let me stop here so that anybody
who has to go to somewhere else can go
but if you have any more questions
please feel free to ask them
we have a question in the chat isn't the
fence instruction unnecessary because
the
amo swap instruction can have the
acquire release ordering
uh yeah uh okay so uh okay
so the two things uh there's the the the
the sync instructions there both for the
compiler and for the hardware
yeah i'm jumping off uh to start office
hours but i think there's still more
questions
how do you do it for the compiler only
uh
the the the compiler knows for which
architecture is compiling
and so it will know whether it actually
has to insert the appropriate fences you
know for
whatever architecture it's running on
and whatever memory consistency model it
has
so this gets in a little bit more
complicated discussion is that every
piece of hardware has
a memory model and the compiler has to
decide
uh you know given the memory model for
that particular architecture what
actually it can do what it cannot do
and i guess my question was that like
defense instruction only becomes
unnecessary if you call ammo swap
like w dot release
and uh
like putting in the the sync
and there that will sync with the you
know the compiler
ordering and then the um
the memory ordering and the out of
ordering
yeah machinery using the fence
instruction as well the fence
instruction is only unnecessary in the
case that you do
dot rl so it seems like it wouldn't
detect that so how would you do it
so the compiler enforces the ordering on
its end
but you already cover it using the
amazon yeah
so like uh if you uh it's a very good
question uh
and you know some more sophisticated
acquiring these implementation would be
uh we more like specialized uh
uh acquire a release implementation or
lease implementation for a risk fight we
will probably do more sophisticated
things than we do where we pretty of
course grain by just issuing defense
instruction
um the uh the
but it's slightly complicated um and so
if you uh if you're interested in this
uh
the memory model for the risk drive is a
reasonably complicated so if you look at
the instruction
manual for the unprevious instructions
there's a whole chapter
dedicated you know to memory ordering
and tells you what they have to what the
compiler should do
in this particular case
so you're saying the compiler would pick
up on the fact that we just put that
assembly instruction inside of there and
it wouldn't reorder
any of the memory accesses on its own
sorry the the
the synchronize this this synchronized
library function is a library function
right and can be implemented in
different ways
uh and this is one particular
implementation
and the library function is provided by
the compiler
so uh but is there like the option for
the compiler to do
optimization where it itself moves the
loads and stores around
uh yes compilers do so how do you
prevent
that without emitting defense
instruction that's what i was curious
about
i guess what i'm saying is that uh uh
maybe uh what i'm saying is that
basically the
this indication the sync synchronized
basically both tells the compiler and
hardware
but the compiler could actually
implement sync increment synchronized
differently it knows that they can't
move things around
but it doesn't have to issue a fence
instruction on the risk 5 it knew
that it was running in a particular way
on risk 5.
uh but isn't the risk five memory model
like loose enough to where the out of
order
machinery could reorganize stuff so you
do need like the acquire
like the whole point of having okay okay
so they're more
uh they're more complicated interfaces
than
seeing synchronized uh and which gives
the compiler writer
more it gives the programming more
freedom and will give the compiler
and sort decouple the compiler part and
the processor part
so for example i think there's a flag
that you can pass in you know to say
that this is a release consistent
uh synchronize uh
you know i i don't know the details
right of my head
but if you look into this this is sort
of the coarse grained interface and
there are more fine-grained interfaces
that give the programmer more control
okay thank you
i have a question one is um
how do you like for having multiple
threads on one
processor do you argue in roughly the
same way
as we did for multiple processors
uh so can you repeat that question just
to make sure i uh
um so we didn't i think i don't think we
really talked about multiple threads we
mostly talked about multiple cpus so
for multiple threads is the um i guess
the solution
the same as for when you have multiple
cpus like do you
have the same arguments there more or
less
uh at least conceptually is the right
way to think about it uh
so if you have multiple threads but only
one cpu
uh it's still the case that you want to
ensure that certain uh
kernel code sequences are executed
atomically
and so you still have to have a notion
of critical sections
uh you might not need locks or releases
explicitly but you do need a way of
turning on interrupts off and on in a
particular piece of code
so if you look at older operating system
kernels they typically don't have really
lock and acquire
uh in the kernel because they assume
they're running on a single processor
but they do have something like locks
you know to basically turn off
interrupts and interrupts on and off
okay i see um and my other question
was um actually on the slide with
um the yard picture
the buffer um
yeah is it yeah that one is it always
the case that
the read is going to be um like lagging
behind
i didn't understand that yeah okay so
the the
so this goes to the display yeah
whatever is in this you know basically
this is the sequence of characters that
needs to go to the display
and and the writer basically is
appending more and more more characters
right and so uh so the writer is going
that way
and basically the readers you know
following the writer right because you
know can't print the character that
hasn't been
you know put in the buffer yet um and so
what
you know the the the uart who
puts things on the display
you know we'll you know start basically
putting the first character as in this
slot you know onto the display
meanwhile printf could come in and
multiple printers come in that
they put more characters in here so that
the right point are staying standing
here
and then when this one character is
displayed then you know the uart will
move up this pointer
to display the next character right so
the uart is always lagging
a little bit behind the writer until the
point that it catches up right and
where r and w are the same and at that
point basically that means that there's
no character anymore in the buffer
oh okay i see that makes that makes a
lot more sense okay thank you so much
you're welcome any more questions
just us left here guys
see you later