sound check can everybody hear me
oh yep yup all right
okay so welcome to uh the next lecture
in s081
uh wherever you are a particular
i hope that the folks on the west coast
or in florida and alabama do okay
given all the terrible circumstances
there
um so uh the topic for today
is virtual memory particularly we're
going to talk about page tables
uh we'll return to this topic uh a few
times there will be multiple filicular
lectures
and maybe just to start off and you know
get our question and answer going again
i would like to ask you a little bit
what do you remember from
uh about virtual memory from double o4
maybe and or
uh nor six or two three if you're taking
that uh
i'll tell you my own sort of view on
virtual memory which is you know why i
took it when i first heard about it or
learned about it as a student
i thought you know it's pretty
straightforward you know hard can it be
it's a table that
you know maps virtual addresses to
physical addresses now uh
you know maybe a little more complicated
but you know not that complicated
and only when you start programming them
with it i should really have learned
that uh future memory is tricky and uh
fascinating um and very powerful
and so hopefully in the next you know
couple
lectures in the next couple laps you
know you'll you'll uh
you'll appreciate uh virtual memory from
that perspective
uh but we'll ask you a couple people
here that are online you know what do
you remember from
uh about virtual memory uh from either
double o four or
six or five if you're taking it and
again i'm just going to call out some
names and
you know share your your
your memories about the adela yang
oh sorry what was the question uh what
do you remember
uh about virtual memory from maybe 04
or 623 if you have taken that um
it uses like offset to save on like uh
remembering virtual address to physical
address mappings
okay uh how about abraham skandera
abram are you online
yeah uh my memory is that it uses uh
like it's a way of one protecting the
physical hardware
by kind of using your representation of
it
um and then yeah you just have like some
virtual address like
at least and double it for just like 12
bits that match
some physical address uh that's usually
i think
16 bits like that
uh how about the bibic pendant
um what i remember was um
you can have each process
has a separate address space and
the memory management unit or i mean
some other technique can be used to map
uh the virtual addresses of the address
space of each of the processes to the
physical
um physical address and
um the the virtual address the
the lower bits are kind of the same so
that uh the
the mapping is in blocks which
helps with performance
uh
i yeah um yeah i guess what i remember
most is that
virtual addressing allows us to um
yeah protect physical addresses from
from each process
and we can use some like clever
manipulations so that the
bits that correspond to the physical
address can be used somehow in the
virtual addresses as well
wilson spearman or spearman
yeah i remember it's really fundamental
to isolation because every process can
basically
uh pretend that it has its own uh
set of memory to use yeah good good
well so clearly uh that's awesome the
the here so clear two themes a year
correct
one is you know there's some form of
mapping uh and that mapping is helpful
in sort of achieving isolation and this
is exactly the
reason we're talking about uh virtual
memory you know isolation
so what we'll see is that uh in the next
you know the
the next couple lectures and
particularly when we start programming
with virtual memory
i really get an in-depth understanding
uh
what its power is uh and so to get a
sense of that you know
this is the first lecture and i'm mostly
focusing on the mechanisms
uh for uh virtual memory and then later
we can see how we can use these
mechanisms to achieve
you know cool tricks so the topic for
today
or the agenda for today uh the plan is
sort of free fault
uh first i'm going to talk about the
dress spaces as some of you mentioned in
your
uh just in the just mentioned
just briefly mentioned in a response to
this question
uh now i'm going to talk about the
paging hardware or paging hardener
and i'm going to focus of course on the
paging hardware of the risk 5
but basically every processor uh
modem processor has some form of aging
hardware
sort of d uh if you will the default
mechanism for actually uh
supporting virtual memory and then uh
the last part of the lecture is going to
walk through
some xp6 virtual memory code
and layout
of you know the kernel address space and
user address spaces
so that's the the main plan
okay so uh so i guess you know number of
you mentioned
in the response to this question you
know
one driving uh reason to have virtual
memory is because you can
use it to achieve isolation if you set
up the page tables correctly
and program them correctly then you can
in principle achieve
a strong isolation and so this is to
remind us again you know what we want
with
from isolation let's just say you know
our standard picture we have some user
applications like the shell
you know cat you know all the util
things that you built
uh in lab one and you know we have
the kernel or you know the kernel
sitting below through the operating
system or sitting in kernel space
and you know what we like to do is sort
of have
you know boxes around these
uh applications so that they can really
effective each other
and similarly you know we want them uh
to be
completely sort of independent of the
kernel in the operating system so that
like if an application does something
either
accidentally bad or maliciously bad that
doesn't really affect the operating
system and so that's our goal
and the particular aspect of the problem
that we
want to focus on today is the memory
side of things
so we really want to focus on memory
isolation and
by default you know if we don't do
anything you know we don't really have
memory isolation right because
if you think about it you know there's
going to be one you know there is five
boards that i showed you last week you
know it has like a memory
a bunch of dram chips uh and
in the drm chips you know the code for
these applications
uh is stored and so for example
somewhere in the memory is the kernel
you know text and data stack everything
somewhere in memory is the shell if the
shell is running
uh somewhere in memory is the cat
program
um and so there's one sort of physical
memory you know starting from someone
through zero to
you know so you know a big big address
you know depending how much memory we
actually have in our machine
and in that physical memory all these
programs must be present
and otherwise you know the processor
can't even execute their instructions
and so what the risk you know clearly
here is that let's say you know
let's make it a little bit you know
simplistic but let's say you know the
shell
you know sits from being addressed zero
to address 200
or 2000 from 1000 to 2000.
and let's say you know the you know
whatever cat has a
programming error uh it loads you know
in a register a0
let's say it loads a thousand the
address basically corresponding to the
start of the shell
and then you know by accident uh you
know it executes the instruction
you know dollar seven uh
a zero correct which has the effect of
the
basically it writes value seven to the
address you know one thousand and so and
then it would be scribbling over
you know the basically the memory image
uh that belongs to the shell
and so that would you know certainly not
uh that certainly would break isolation
uh and be quite undesirable
and so you know we want something that
basically really separates these
memories from the different programs
from each other so that things like that
just cannot happen so one way
you know to do that uh is an idea that's
you know typically called the dress
basis
and the basic idea is straightforward
what we want to do is basically give
every
application including the kernel its own
address space
and so we can think about this like
example use cat running
you know it has an address space
starting at zero you know
to whatever so maximum value you know
there's a shelra
has an address space its own address
space also starting at address zero
uh going to some value you know the
kernel has its own address space
os has its own address space
and and so one example when cat you know
refers to really we go back to our you
know the example of the previous slide
where
you know we did uh whatever store
seven to you know a0
and let's say in a0 there's the value of
1000.
you know if cat you know executes an
instruction uh it will write to the
address 1000 but it is its own address
1000.
it's not you know the address of the
1000 of the shell
so basically every program runs with its
own address space
has its own value and those address
spaces are completely independent
uh you know in this notion of different
different address spaces
cat doesn't really have an ability to
even refer to
an address that actually belongs to the
shell
and so that's sort of the the game that
we're the end goal that we'd like to
achieve
because this is going to provide us with
strong isolation because you know
it is just not possible for cat to refer
to any other memory that is not
you know its own and so our goal now is
to basically sort of
figure out how to multiplex if you will
all these different address spaces on a
single
physical memory because in the end we
only have a bunch of dram chips
uh where you know or ram chips where the
memory is located
and so uh
uh that's another plan okay yeah uh i'm
here you have a question go ahead
yeah so i'm wondering uh in the
configuration of the
physical hardware there's only so much
space
and in the virtual memory layout there's
also a max virtual address
uh by design is the virtual address
made to be small enough i know that it
no not necessarily you know the virtual
dress space could be bigger than the
physical memory the physical memory
could be bigger than the virtual address
phase
uh and we'll see in a second how that
all can happen and it's actually one of
the
you know cool parts about as we will see
with page tables
that's extremely flexible so is it
is it possible that like the physical
memory
gets exhausted uh because so many
processes use up
all their virtual space yeah that's
certainly possible
uh and we'll see in a second how for
example you know if you have a
bunch of big applications that each have
big page tables and they allocate a lot
of memory you know at some point you're
gonna run out of memory
i see thanks and so where does it show
up in xv6
anybody
you you sort of touched on it a little
bit in the
cisco lab that you're currently doing
where are pages allocated
or if you did the cisco lab and you
finished it you know one part of the
physical life correctly is printing how
much free memory there is
k alec yeah chaok right for chao it has
some list of three pages
if that list of three places is empty or
runs out at some point
then you know chaotic is going to return
a null pointer
and hopefully the operating system does
something sensible and that basically
propagates back to the user application
saying like well you know
no more memory for you or no more memory
in total for nobody
okay and just a job for the os to handle
those cases gracefully
where it basically generally means you
know propagating an error message to the
user application
okay good um so how do we implement
these
address spaces you know how basically
multiplex all these address spaces
across a single physical memory
and the most common approach and a very
flexible approach is to use
page tables
um and the idea is uh and this is a
hardware support
so this is implemented in hardware by
the processor
or uh by a unit called the memory
management unit
and so the picture that you sort of
should have in your head is you know you
have the cpu
that executes instructions you know
whatever our
you know uh uh our store instruction
that was you know putting dollar seven
into
uh a zero indirect
so it executes those kind of
instructions and you know one that
executes one is their story instruction
load instruction or whatever
anything that actually has an address
you know that address
uh we're going to think about as a
virtual address so it's not a physical
address it's a virtual address
and so for example the value in a0 that
we're using here
uh yeah say that's 1000
oh x you know 1000 data is a virtual
address
and that virtual address is basically
routed through something what's called
the
memory management unit
and the memory manager unit translates
it into
a physical address and
that physical address then you know is
actually used to you know index into
memory
and load whatever value or store
whatever value needs to be written there
and so the cpu from the cpu point of
view it always issues
every instruction that it issues uh once
the mmu is enabled
are virtual addresses and to translate
these virtual addresses to physical
addresses
basically the mmu has a table and
you know the virtual address on one side
physical drafts on one side
on the other side an example here is you
know our entry for
1000 and maybe that maps to whatever uh
you know ox whatever i'm just making
something up with like some big value
you know somewhere in physical memory
and so this mapping between virtual and
physical ma
uh it is quite flexible so on one side
we have the virtual address of the other
side of the physical addresses
um typically you know this this mapping
itself is also stored in memory and so
the cpu has some register
that basically points to uh
that contains the physical address of
where the page table is stored
so somewhere in the basically the page
table or this map is somewhere stored in
physical memory
uh let's say you know whatever you know
address
and basically this register which is
called on the risk 5
satp you know stores the
address 10 and so uh that the
cpu can tell the memory manage unit
where to find
you know basically the map to actually
translate uh
virtual to physical addresses and then
the basic idea is to give every
application its own map
so you know cad is going to have its map
go ahead um
so the mmu you said it doesn't
necessarily
store the mapping so does it
does it just just do the translation
like it will
read the memory and do the translation
but not necessarily
store the mappings that's that's exactly
the right picture that you should have
in your head
but every map okay so the the the map
itself is stored in memory the mmu just
basically walks or looks ups into the
map and we'll see in a second that you
know this map is slightly more
complicated than
what you're drawing here so every app
has its own its own map
correct and that map basically defines
its address space
and so when with the cpu or when the
operating system switches the cpu from
one process
or from one application to another
application it also switches to you know
the content of this
satp register to store
the root of the map of the appropriate
process
and so in that way basically you know
multiple applications can run
on the cpu every time we switch between
from one application to the next
application
we also switch the satp register to
point to the appropriate map for that
application
and in that way basically the virtual
addresses
for cad are translated differently than
the virtual addresses
for the shell because you know each one
of them has their own map
that makes sense
okay so the way
this is sort of the basic plan and the
way i've drawn
or you know explained it so far is
pretty naive
and unreasonable uh yeah did that go
ahead
i'm sorry um so um
the you said the satp register gets
modified uh
for the process i am guessing the value
of
uh for the satp register for each
process
is stored by the kernel yes yes the
kernel is writing the sntp your editor
in fact
writing or reading the or particularly
writing the uh
satp register is a privilege instruction
so
a user application cannot just you know
update the page map register and say
like i want to run with this page map
now
because that would violate isolation
right so it's only the kernel only a
code in kernel mode can actually update
it
i see okay so
as i said this picture is pretty naive
uh you know one thing i haven't really
said anything about how this actually
map works
uh and you know the way actually drawn
out seems to indicate that you know
basically for every
virtual address you have an entry in the
map
and if you do that how big would the map
be
on risk five
anybody
how many addresses are there on the risk
five in principle or how big
how many addresses could a register
store
registers are 64 bit wide so how many
addresses
anybody i know i'm so insulting your
intelligence by asking these questions
but
we have some answers in the chat like
two to the 64. uh so yeah i didn't see
the chat sorry
uh yeah two to the 64. let's see if i
can actually pop up the chip
so i can see it
yeah 2264. thank you
all right so this table would be
gigantic
uh in fact you know all memory would be
consumed by just having that table so
that's
unreasonable and so in fact you know
that's not how things work
in fact i'm going to go in two steps to
actually how it actually works in the
race five
so step one is you know don't play the
game
per address but do it per page
so you translate the page at a time and
the page uh
on the risk five is four kilobyte
and which is four and four thousand
ninety six bytes
and this is pretty common uh almost all
processors you know use roughly a page
size or four kilobytes or support
a page size or four kilobytes and so now
again translation works slightly
differently so if here
we have our virtual address and
basically we split it in two pieces
an index and an offset
and so the offset is basically the byte
within the page
and so when we do when the mmu does the
translation
it takes the index uh indexes into
the map that gives you you know some
physical page number
you know the in memory and that physical
page number that points to some you know
physical page of 4096 bytes
and then the offset part basically
indexes into that
physical page so for example the offset
is you know 12
then you know the
the 12th entry of that page is actually
used a lot of you people a lot of you
answered this and
mentioned this in the uh in response to
the question that
there's always some scheme of like
taking an offset and uh
adding that to the base of the page uh
to uh
obtain the actual uh memory fiscal
memory location where
a value is stored or where value will be
uh loaded to
and one of the interesting things about
the risk five is and there's a
in response to some other question to
them or somebody asked earlier the
physical uh or the virtual dresses are
64 bits
which makes totally sense correct
because the risk 5 is 64-bit register
but in fact on the risc-v processor that
we're using
uh not all of the 64 bits actually used
namely the top 25 are actually not used
at all
and so that limits the size of a virtual
address right that limits the size of a
virtual address space to
2 to the power 39
which is roughly 512
gigabytes
um and so of course you know later uh
versions of the processor might support
bigger address spaces if that isn't
necessary
and that could then be done and so that
for example some of those 25 bits that
are basically unused you know could be
used to
uh build bigger virtual address spaces
and so uh and so in the index in that
you know we're 39 bits left
you know as the virtual address 20 27
bits
are indexed and we'll see in a second
why they're 27
uh our index and then the 12 are
offset and you know they have to be 12
correct because 2 to the power 12
is you know 4 5 and 96
all right so that's virtual addresses on
the risk 5
physical addresses as you can see here
are actually 56 bits wide
so the physical memory you know can be
bigger than the
single virtual address space but it's
limited to two power up to 56
you know most boards probably you know
that don't support two to the power 56
uh physical memory because of gigantic
amount of physical memory
but in principle the board could you
know if you could manufacture it
support 2 to the power 56 of physical
memory
and so in this scheme then if you have
bits for the physical address 44 are
basically the physical page number
the ppn and 12 again are the offset that
are inherited directly from the
virtual address
does that all make sense
so i'm going to stop for a second here
usually you're collecting foss
the other thing point i wanted to make
here is that uh
this material uh is important so just
ask questions
uh the details matter uh and it will be
a large part
of you know you really need to
understand all this stuff uh to be able
to basically do lab
the next lap the page table lab yeah i'm
here go ahead
please if you can go back one slide
uh the screen is unclear
which one the page table slide
this one uh no the most recent one all
right it also doesn't really matter
uh yeah that this is perfect thank you
so i'm wondering
this 4096 byte range
which we've called a page is that
assigned as a
continuous chunk in memory yes there's a
continuous physical
you know continuous range of 4096
bytes in memory i see
and then the snap at a granularity
of 496 bytes okay
and then 12 the offset like 2 to the 12
is 4096 so that's sufficient to
uh to cover each of the chunks yeah each
byte and webpage
and where does the 56 come from in the
diagram
i could follow up until then but i
didn't get where that came from
uh the designers cook it up so the
hardware designers decide how big you
know a physical dress is
uh basically for the whatever board they
want to design
and so the risk 5 designers decided that
bit physical addresses were a good idea
and presumably the way they come up with
these numbers is they look at technology
trends
and say like well we want to be able for
the next sort of five years you know we
don't want to predict
that physical memory will be ever bigger
than 2 to the power 56
and probably they're thinking it won't
be bigger than you know something much
smaller but then you know give them some
v-way you know in case you know their
prediction is wrong
uh they pick a slightly bigger number
does that make sense see yeah thanks
yeah a lot of people ask about this
anybody else who raised a hand i think
there's a bunch of people asking
questions and
unfortunately my zoom doesn't show it's
more than two people ranked hands it's
just
multiple people are raising their hands
so please jump in if you have a question
okay if not i have a question
yeah go ahead um so if the virtual
memory is
up to 2 to the power of 27 and the
physical memory is up 2 to the power
2 to the 56 right so
we could have like we could
we could have multiple processes that
could exhaust all their virtual memories
without
using up all the physical memory right
that's correct
that's absolutely correct okay i have a
question too
yeah go ahead um so this 56
for the physical address is that the
the number of possible memory locations
i i don't think it's the number of bits
right because this is a 64-bit
machine that 56 could go up to
64 but they just chose it to have just
56.
that's right that's correct and one way
to think about it then they only have to
run 56 wire
wires on the board as opposed to 64.
i see i see
okay i also have a question um
so kind of um could you go back one
slide maybe
yep um so
from the cpu um we go through the mmu
and then to the memory
uh but where where here is the
distinction
for different processes because like
each process
like process like the shell process has
something at
address like 0x uh one zero zero zero
and then the ls process also has
something at address zero x one zero
zero zero
so we need to translate those to
different physical
so the satp register
contains the register it contains the
address of which map to use
so ls runs with its own map you know cat
runs with zone map
okay so so each process will have com
it's completely
own map yep makes sense thank you
and in fact there's a great uh leeway to
the next
point so if every process has its own
map
you know how big is this map like that
i've drawn here
well that map is 2 to the power of 47
entries correct
uh and that's pretty big uh and i would
feel
physical memory reasonable quickly uh if
every process exactly had a complete you
know
populated map right then it was gigantic
you know means that every process is
very big
and so in fact this is not the way uh
the hardware actually stores page tables
uh you know you can think about it
conceptually as an array
you know going from zero to two to power
27 but actually is not what happens in
practice
in practice it's a multi-level uh
structure
and here's actually the real risk five
page table structure
and what the hardware implements and so
what happens with the 27 bits that we
saw earlier
the index it's actually split in
three nine bit numbers
and the first the top nine bits are used
to index
into the top level page table directory
as they're called
and so in one directory you know one of
these guys you know is 496 bytes
496 bytes just like a page size
uh a pte entry one of these entries in
that thing is
64 bytes
64 bits i mean sorry like the register
with so eight bytes and so this is going
to mean that if you do 496
divided by 8 means there are 512 entries
in one of those directory pages
so basically what happens is the satp
points to the top
uh root directory we take the top level
nine bits index
into the page directory and that gives
us a new physical page number
and that physical page number is the
page directory for the next level
so whenever we use the next level index
to index into that page directory and
then you know and so forth you know we
like the final one you know we get the
bottom level page directory and that
basically gives us the entry
uh that maps the virtual address to a
fiscal address
so in some sense again it's very similar
to uh what i showed you in the previous
slide except you know basically the
index happens in three steps instead of
one step
and this is advantage the main advantage
of this scheme is that then
if large paid parts of the address phase
are not being used
you don't have to have any page table
entries for them
as for example let's say you have an
address space
that has only one page like the bottom
page
you know it's a 4096
and no other pages are in the address
page so only the addresses zero to four
thousand ninety five
six are actually mapped how many page
table entry or page table directors do
you need
to map that particular page
well you need one at the top correct and
you need
basically value in that entry for zero
the top level nine bits you know of the
zero earned zero so you need an entry
for zero
so that means you need one middle level
entry you know that basically uh
corresponds to the next
you know nine zero bits and then one
entry for the
next nine zero bits so basically we get
away
with three uh page directories
and in our previous scheme on the
previous slide correct we had 2 to the
power of 27
entries and now we basically have to
have 3 times whatever 512 entries and
we're done
and that's the main reason why
the actual hardware has this
hierarchical
or multi-level 3 scheme
any questions about this because it's
pretty important
samir go ahead um
so my question is
since the ppn number from each page
table is 44 bits
and the second say the middle table
resides on the virtual memory where do
we get the
missing 12 bits from well the final 12
bits
okay so good good so you're saying these
44 correct
yes what is going on with that well all
pages all page directories are
page lines and so basically their uh
physical page number is 44 plus the 12
uh
[Music]
12 zero bits
and so what actually happens if we look
at these pte entries you know they all
have the same sort of form
right if you look at one of these guys
they're 44
bits they're 12 bits zeros so that gives
us a
44 plus 12 is 56 so that gives us a
physical address
correct um and so that means
in this 64 bits there's actually some
bits left they're not being used in fact
the bottom 12 bits will basically or the
bottom 10 would definitely
you know the bottom bits are not not
used at all and in fact the paging
hardware
stores or stores that are a bunch of
flags
that control the translation and we'll
talk about those flags in a second
and but they're there to control the
translation and they're stored basically
in the bottom 10 bits
and it also means correct that you know
if you add these two up that's 54 bits
basically there's 10 bits left that are
unused and those 10 bits are
again you know for future growth so
at some point we might have a new type
of risk five processor that will have
slightly different structure page tables
and it might actually have bigger
than 44 bits for the physical page
number
okay and in fact you know you can see it
here like if you look at the single
entry correct
that's drawn here uh you know they're
basically
10 10 bits left that are not being used
um okay so let's look at the flags for a
second
because that's sort of important uh so
every translation
in the bottom 10 bits there are a bunch
of flags stored and the first
flag uh is valid and if
the valid bit is set that means this is
a valid pte
and you can use it for translation
and so for uh so for my little example
that i used here with
three page directories where only entry
zero is used
then only enter zero will have the valve
bit set and none the other five and
eleven entries will not have the valve
bit set
and that basically tells the uh mmu well
you know you don't have to change down
this
uh pt this pte just contains no valid
information
then r means you know you're allowed to
read from the page
right means you're allowed to write to
the page execute means
you're allowed to execute instructions
from it uh
and user means you know uh this page is
also accessible by a process user
running
in user space and then the other bits
you know not that important they'll all
show up at some point
but those are sort of the five important
bits
does it all make sense
yeah nithya
i'm
that's that's the right presentation
thank you um i had
a quick question about uh the three page
tables
no so um how are the addresses or like
the ppn values
combined to form the final physical
address and i might have missed that
i know well i may have not said i said
it very explicitly
uh so the first ppn correct in top step
page
the first vpn in the top level page
directory
contains the physical address of the
next
level down right and that one contains
the one next level down and then in the
final one
we still have our few 44 bits that
contains then the actual
physical address of the page that we're
actually trying to translate to
ah okay that makes sense thank you okay
and one
interesting question just like a side
note before let me answer this
my own question before answering the two
raised hands here uh
if you look back at this picture why why
are there physical page numbers stored
in these page directories
why not a virtual address
because we need to look it up in memory
like look up the next directory in
memory
yeah right we could not have you know
our translation scheme depend on yet
another translation scheme you know we
could sort of in a recursive intent
would look so it just doesn't make sense
so that's exactly the right answer it
has to be a physical number
how about the satp what do you use the
satp what does it store does it store a
physical address or a virtual address
also physical assuming that the first
page directory is also memory right
yep yeah exactly so it has to be a
physical number because
we're actually trying to use it for
translation and
uh so you know the sap needs to know
what the physical page number is
of the root of the page directory
okay there were two other questions or
two people raised their hands
could you
[Music]
repeat your question if if it hasn't
been answered yet
so there's a hierarchy of three tables
and each of them is indexed by a part of
the virtual address
each nine bits long uh
so i i'm not sure i understand how
chaining between them happens and what
it's meant to accomplish like shouldn't
it be sufficient
to just use those three nine bit
addresses to index into each of them
that's correct so the first the top
level nine bits are usually index in the
first top
uh page level directory the second and
the next one and the third in the third
one
and so maybe i'm just not understanding
this correctly
so when uh a process requests a certain
like virtual address to be looked up it
loads into the satp register or the cpu
does
and that gets the corresponding correct
highest level page table yeah
and then that page table
will and we'll use then the top level
nine bits from the 27
to index into that page directory
and then what is what is the result of
that like if the result is
there's nothing there does the mmu
create
a page table no no the mmu basically
tells the operating system
or tells the processor sorry i couldn't
translate that address and
uh and basically turns into a page fault
which we'll talk about a little bit
later
but just you just can't not translate
the address so it doesn't translate it
it's like you know you can't divide by
zero
you know you try to do that the process
just refuses to do it
i see okay
brandman what about you brandon yep um
so i just wanted to make sure i
understand
how i think maybe we covered
kind of intermediate page table how we
calculate the physical address of those
um so is it correct that say if we were
trying to find a second level page
table's physical address we would take
the ppn from the first level page table
that's 44 bits
and then we add the 12-bit offset from
the original virtual address to get the
full 56-bit
fiscal address we don't add the offset
from the virtual address we just take 12
zero bits
so we take the ppn there's 44 bits oh
okay
we do 12 zero bits in the bottom and
that gives us a 56 bit physical address
and that's where the next page directory
is and this requires that basically
every page directory is page aligned
i see okay that makes sense
so these are all great questions and
these are all things you're going to be
struggling with in the page table lab so
it's very good to ask them right now um
okay uh let me see uh
[Music]
yes uh okay let me
hold on for a second and collect my
thoughts
and see where i am
good good good okay one uh sort of uh
you know one other thing that i want to
mention because you will see that
is that if we think about this you know
the scheme that i just showed
correct uh what really seems to be going
on is that when you load
or store a value to memory or the
processor motor storage value to memory
we basically have to do three memory
lookups right one in the
top level page directory one in the
intermediate page therefore library and
then one in the bottom level page
directory
so it looks like that you know any
memory reference to a virtual address
basically requires free memory reads
and so that seems expensive uh and so
uh what happens in practice where almost
all every prussian does this
it has a cache sitting on the side that
contains recently used translations
and this is called the translation
leukocyte
buffer and you'll see that term
quite often and it's called the tlb
basically it's nothing else than the
cache of
entry page table entries pt entries
so when the processor has you know the
first time the processor looks enough a
virtual address you know walks this uh
the hardware walks this uh page the
three level page tables
it will come out with you know the final
physical uh page or the finder called
ppn for that particular virtual address
and then basically the the tob
store.vnpapn
or pa mapping uh on the site
and so then when the next time you refer
to that particular virtual address
i can just look at the straight up in
the tlb and the tlb will respond
instead of having to do the page table
walk
yep i'm here
so the tlb maps
virtual addresses to the physical
address of the page
that the virtual address uh along with
the offset
yeah right wouldn't it be more
efficient to like cache at the page
table level
uh okay so i let me uh take a step back
here
um there's many ways of implementing the
tob
uh the most important thing that you
need to know is that there is a top
uh and the exact details of actually how
the pov is implemented to sort of
you know now the topic that we're going
to talk about in a great amount of
detail
in fact not at all and so this is really
something that sort of sits
inside of the processor and is mostly
hidden from the operating system the
operating system doesn't really know how
the top
operates the only thing the reason you
need to know that the qob exists
is that if you switch page tables
then typically the operating system
needs to tell
the processor that it's switching page
tables
and the be needs to be flushed
because basically you can't use tail
entries like if you switch to a new cage
table
the entries in the tob may not be valid
anymore and so they need to be removed
because otherwise you know the
translation would be incorrect
and so the operating system is typically
where
it's aware that there's a t that there
is a tlb
only basically to tell the hardware once
in a while saying like okay well don't
use them anymore
because i'm going to switch page tables
and in fact on you know the uh
on the risk files the instruction to
flush the tov is called
s fence underscore vma
and that will actually flush the top
be back um
so i have a question uh like not
regarding tlb but
that brought kind of uh this question
the three level support that the three
level um
paging that we have is it implemented by
the operating system or the hardware
itself
it's implemented by the hardware so you
know this all happens in hardware
the mmu is a block of hardware not in
the operating system
we'll see in a second when we look at
xv6
that xv6 has a function that models the
page table walk because once in a while
you know sv6 basically has to do what
the hardware does
uh and so it also doesn't have a
function called walk
that basically does exactly the same
thing but in software
so can i ask a question yeah go ahead
so um where in this scheme does the
processor cache fit
does it happen before the address
translation or after
because yeah yeah okay let me just
switch back a little bit
a couple uh let me see
uh okay here's your mmu
the whale really the way to think if i
think about it is that all this
know this whole block is inside of the
processor silicon
so there's a risc-v chip and inside of
it is the cpu
in fact they're multiple cpu correct
they're four cores and there's an mmu
and you know you can think about that
either on this on the cpu site you know
there's a you know tlb
okay
that makes sense um but i guess my
question was about the like
um cash in terms of not the tlb but just
the
normal cash like uh because sometimes we
don't actually go all the way to access
the memory
yeah yeah good good point so like i
showed you like the schema last week
correctly the
monday of the risk five processor it has
now one cache it has an l2 cache
uh some caches are indexed by physical
address and some caches are indexed by
virtual address
so the caches that are indexed by
virtual address sit before
the mmu and cache their index by
physical addressing after the mmu
does that make sense can i also ask a
question
my question is you said that the um
tlb it walks so like to put stuff into
tlb
the hardware walks through the page
tables
um why do we write walk function if
hardware can do that
very good question um one reason
there's a couple of reasons why we do it
or why xv6 needs it
one is when it actually sets up the
initial page tables
uh you know it needs to program the the
three levels
and so it needs to basically emulate the
uh another uh example that you actually
sort of ran into or are running into in
the cisco lab
is that when you cop you know the in xv6
the kernel has its own page table
and every user address space has its own
page table
and but once in a while you know for
example it says info
you know like this is the pointer to the
system construct you know that lives in
user space
the kernel needs to be translated to an
address that it can use to read and
write it
and so for example if you look in copy
in or
copy out basically the kernel
translates the user virtual address
using the user uh virtual using the user
page table to get out a physical address
that that kernel then
uh to get an address out that actually
then the kernel can use to read and
write that memory
so there's a bunch of places like the
show job and i'll talk about it
hopefully in
you know whatever 10 minutes or 15
minutes um i have a question
why doesn't the hardware like expose
that walk function so we don't have to
write our own and like potentially have
bugs in it
uh why isn't there like a you know maybe
a privileged instruction that you can
pass a virtual address and it'll give
back the physical address
well this is just like just store to the
virtual address and you get back
and we'll do it right for you uh so and
we'll see
later on uh in the next lap the page
table app
in fact is exactly what you'll be doing
you will actually set up the page table
slightly differently so that you can
avoid
the walk and copy in and copy and string
i think this will become clear in a
second that we when we talk about look
at the xv6 okay
okay good um one more issue
and basically before jumping into the
x86 uh i wanted to make one
point um one way to think about
uh you know uh page tables
uh a popular way to phrase this
is the page tables uh provide
a level of indirection
and
and that uh and so basically this
indirection grid what i'm talking about
you know this mapping from virtual
address the physical address
and this mapping is completely under the
control
of the operating system
as we've seen you know in the last in a
couple of slides that we talked
and that means that the operating system
because it has so much control over it
has control over the complete control of
that translation
um it can do all kinds of interesting
tricks
uh and so for example like one trick uh
you know we talked a little bit about
this like if a pitch
pedal entry is invalid and will really
return a page you know the hardware will
raise a page fault in response that page
fault
the operating system could update the
page tables and then maybe
restart the instruction and so there's
all kinds of things that they can do
at runtime by manipulating the page
tables
and we're not going to talk about that
to today but in
two weeks we'll have a lecture exactly
sort of about this topic about
what cool things can you do once you
have page tables and page faults
but it's important to keep in mind that
this is a
incredibly powerful mechanism
that will provide the operating system
with a tremendous amount of flexibility
and there's one reason why page tables
are so popular
okay so what i want to do next is
actually talk about
xv6 and sort of see
how this all plays out in xv6
so the first thing i'm going to do is
i'm going to look at the
kernel page layout if you will um
and the the mapping is on this slide
so here's the virtual address space
of the kernel and here is actually the
physical memory so this is what
basically whatever you can think about
this is drm
and in fact it is not uh let me take the
back immediately
one part is drm and one part
is actually i o devices
and so to sort of maybe i'm going to
talk about the physical the right side
of the slide a little bit first and then
we'll talk about the left side in a
second
so the left side of the slide is
completely determined by the hardware
and so the hardware designers basically
determine the layout of that fit
and you know as you saw before last week
when the kernel starts it starts at this
address ox880
and that's just determined by the
hardware designers uh
and so to be more explicit
so if you look at the board this is the
same picture of the board that i showed
on monday but it's hopefully a little
bit better
picture it's easier to see here's our
risk five processor
and we now know correct that in the risk
five processor there are four cores
but there's also an mmu and there's also
a tob
or multiple tv every cord has his own
mmu and every core has his own tlb
and here are the d-ring chips and so
basically the designers of the board
have decided that uh
when you know the after you know the
translation for virtual to fiscal
address
basically physical addresses that's
starting you know at 08 you know a lot
of zeros
actually go to the dram chips and
dresses above below
oa8 may go to different io devices
and so the the platform decides
basically
the designers of this board have decided
exactly what the physical layout
in fact you can look that up the
physical layout if you want to
just let me show you that so here's the
the same manual that i showed you on uh
on on monday
and if you go to actually escape
you go to page 31 i believe
here is the page um and if you go down
this
is what's the memory it will spell out
what the memory map is
of the uh the board and it will say like
at address zero zero
is reserved nothing is there uh if you
go scroll down in this memory map you
know you'll see
some information about all the different
things that are mapped for example
ethernet board is mapped at ox 1
you know x something
if you go further down oops that was too
much down
here you see the entry for ox 8
0 0 0 correct and that actually is ddr
memory the off chip volatile memory and
so those are the dram chips that i just
showed you on the previous slide
and so it's just good to keep in your
head correct even though we're not
talking to keemu and your old osc
software
in the end everything is determined uh
by you know the actual board
okay so go back to uh my slides
uh so let's look at the layout
yeah uh noah go ahead
yeah when you say that this this layout
is determined by the hardware uh
do you specifically mean uh like the cpu
itself or the
the board on which the cpu resides the
board in which the cpu resides correct
because you know the board you know the
the cpu is that that
gray thing in the middle that square
thing saying uh whatever risk five
the dram chips are sitting off the uh
of the processor correct and it's the
board designers who put the
chip the the the many i o devices all
together
the large part of an operating system is
actually you know the cpu is one part
but the i o devices are at least as
important right and so when you're
writing an operating system
you both have to deal with the cpu as
well as you know with the i o devices
you know you and you want to send a
packet over the internet
well somebody has to tickle
you know the network drive or the nic
card to actually do that and that's the
operating system
so going back to the right side of this
picture correct this is the physical
dress
layout you know we see basically that
you know the bottom was unused as i
showed you on that uh
document it turns out that ox100 that
physical address does where the boot rom
is so when you turn on
you know that board the first thing that
happens is actually code in the boot rom
runs and when the boot run is done it
actually will jump to this ox000
and it's a job of the operating system
make sure that there's some
you know some data there and then
there's a bunch of other devices
that we'll talk about here's the uh an
interrupt controller
uh we'll talk about it next week uh
there's a clint
another a part of the interrupt story
that we'll talk about next week
so basically multiple devices can
generate interrupts there needs to be a
plan to route those interrupts to
the to the appropriate request level and
that's all implemented by
those interrupt controllers and let me
finish for a second you know this this
slide before
answering the question um then there's a
uart that was the device
uh that was actually the thing that
actually the device is actually in a new
device that actually interacts with the
console and the display
and then there's the virtual there's the
disk uh
and that's the device there's where the
device sits that actually interacts with
the disk
and so when you write to location to
address let's say
ox200 then that physical address
corresponds to the clint
and so do you when you do store
instruction or load instruction you're
reading and writing to the chip that
implements the
uh clint and we'll see later what that
exactly means
but basically you can think about this
as interacting directly with the device
and not reading and writing physical
memory
yeah there was a question um
so just trying to make sure the
addresses below
ox800 they don't really exist in dram
if when we mention those addresses we
directly go to the other hardwares
yeah yeah so like if you go back to this
picture
anything above ox one zero correct
that's these dram chips and
you know i can't draw you i can't point
you to the clint uh but like for example
here's the
uh and so that's it's a particular
physical address and we can write
you know with load and store
instructions this is called memory
mapped io
we can do load and store instructions we
can program the ethernet controller
um i also have a question uh why why is
this big chunk
at the top says and used why is it not
used
oh uh okay so remember uh
not every machine not every so there's
two to the power 56
uh bytes of physical address space uh
but you don't have to
you know plug in that much memory into
the board if you don't want to
and so some parts of it may be unused
depending on how much you know dram
chips are sitting on the board
in fact like in xv6 we i think
limit ourselves to 128 megabytes
and no more
so when um um when a
load restore instruction goes out of the
cpu
um does that go like
where does it get routed to the correct
i o like already from the cpu
so kind of like if the cpu before it
sends it out
it says okay if it's lower than 0x8 and
all the zeros
then i'm gonna send it to like the
correct i o device and then otherwise
i'm going to send it to
the um to the memory like the dram chip
you can think about as a demultiplexer
sitting on the inside of the
risc-5 you know blob oh so it's inside
of that block
okay that's your memory controller
and that doesn't do routing
very important to have that sort of all
clear in your head
are we okay so now i want to switch to
the right side of this picture
and this is basically what xv6 sets up
to uh the virtual dress space that xv6
sets up so when the machine boots
there's no
aging enabler yet uh xv6 sets up the
first
you know page page tables the first
virtual address space and that's
actually the virtual address space that
the kernel uses and we'll look at it in
a second at the code
but uh and this is the layout and it
turns out
uh you know because we want to keep xv6
as simple as possible it's
easy for you to understand the mapping
from virtual
to physical is mostly in identity
mapping
so basically what that means is that the
virtual address ox200
maps to physical address ox2000
the kernel will set up the page tables
exactly in that way
and so that means basically that you
know for all virtual addresses
below this top which is the top of
physical memory
are identical to the physical addresses
that are actually being used
uh on the right side and so this is like
why all the arrows are straight
because it's you know identity mapping
okay there's a small changes to this
uh uh the two important things to
mention
uh let me hold one second uh while i try
to
first mention the two important things
to mention um
first of all there's some pages some map
is very high up in memory
some pages very high up in memory uh for
example
the stack uh the kernel stack actually
sits up
it's also mapped high up in memory and
the reason it's high up in memory is
because we have a guard page below it
that is not mapped
so the pte entry below the kernel stack
of one of the kernel stacks
does have not have uh it's valid bit set
and uh so if you know the kernel runs
off its stack
it will result in a page fault which is
better than basically
you know scribbling over some other
memory that the kernel has you get an
immediate panic and you know that
something's bad
to stack um of course we don't want to
waste physical memory
and so when we do that by basically uh
putting the stack high
uh in a guard page an empty guard
pte entry below it and the guard
page doesn't really consume any physical
memory like it's sitting high up in the
virtual address space so
nothing is being consumed but that means
that they're showing this k stack page
for example is mapped twice
it's mapped at a high address and it's
mapped directly
you know by one of the addresses that
below this top
and so you can do this is one example of
all the sort of
cool things you can do with page tables
you can map a physical address twice
you cannot map a physical address uh you
know it can be one-to-one mapping
one-to-many mapping many-to-one mapping
all that kind of stuff is possible xv6
doesn't really
use many of them but there's a couple
places we use those tricks and
the stack and the guard page is one
example of one of the cool trick that
you know xv6 uses mostly to track down
bugs
the second thing i wanted to mention is
that the permissions
so for example the kernel text the pages
for the kernel text are mapped
read nx meaning you can read it and
execute it
but you cannot write the kernel text and
again this is basically the void
box so that we catch them early kernel
data of course needs to be able to be
written to
and so it has is mapped read write but
you cannot execute
out of kernel data pages instructions
so the xbit is not set
it all make sense uh i skipped one or
two questions so if
these questions are still not answered
you know please ask them
we have a question in the chat um do we
have multiple
kernel stacks for different processes
like will we have n
k stacks for n processes answers yes
so every process every user process has
a corresponding kernel stack
and we'll see that in a little bit later
okay okay so let me uh
uh samir go ahead um
so what the virtual memory of another
application mapped to somewhere in the
physical memory in the unused space
or yes uh very good point so there's
a bunch of physical memory correct
here's free memory
uh and that's free memory year two right
uh and uh we use that or xpc it uses
that free memory to basically store
pages of page tables of user processes
as well as you know the text and data of
user level processes and if we run many
many many usual level processes at some
point we'll run out of free memory
and then basically fork or exact will
return an error
but that means that the virtual space
for processes are much smaller than the
virtual space for
the kernel right well the virtual stages
is the same
as the same you know size in principle
but it will be less populated
let me uh let's let's look at some code
and i think that all the stuff becomes a
little bit more clear
uh just one small thing um is so given
that
um a lot of the like each process has a
big part of the memory mapped the same
location
is that optimized by like consolidating
in
that into one place that mapping or no
because
you could uh xp6 does not do that uh
but like one of the challenge exercises
in the page table app is to actually
implement
that let's see and the real operating
system would do that
yeah that makes sense very good question
and i think you get a sense of like what
all kinds of things are possible once
you have page tables
okay so let's do the usual thing
boot our xv6 again and again you know
qmu is just basically implementing the
board
and you know let's oops
[Music]
so last time we looked at uh how the
booting happens correct and then we got
to main and then basically one of the
things that
uh uh the kernel uh when
one of the functions is called called
kva minute and that actually sets up the
address space
for the kernel and so we saw in the
picture or in the previous slide what
that
you know looks like and here we can see
seeing code how it actually is being set
up
uh
and why hold on something is not going
as i wanted to am i in the right
directories
hold on a second here while i'm trying
to sort out my problems
that is good
and in the right directories yeah
okay gdp
and let's have a break from the main
just to make sure
good and then i set a breakpoint at kvm
in it actually i can just stack to it
now
next console in it greendev in it you
know we shot it before
uh physical memory allocator
and
now something happens that i'm not
expecting
[Music]
what is going on
we're gonna run this right before
lecture ah here that's what's going on
that actually is printing
uh okay um
huh interesting okay one more time see
if i can get
lucky more looks
continue and hopefully it will get there
it's going to wait a little bit okay
great we're at the kvm unit
so basically we're now at this function
here on the right side in the emacs
buffer
you can see it and
i think i modified the function slightly
i hope i did
i think i did well we'll see um and what
we're going to do is
again we're going to walk step into that
function
uh it'll give me the layout split it's
easier to see
and that's the first thing that you can
see is actually the kernel actually
allocates a physical page for the top
level page directory
and then it zeros it out so that all the
pte entries are zero
and then basically it starts mapping in
every
device i o device one by one and so for
example the uart0
it basically starts mapping and maps
that into the kernel
address space and so we can look at a
file called mem layout
this basically translates a page 31 that
i showed you from the document into a
bunch of constants that we're using
and so for example here it says what the
address of you ox1000 is
uh over the year it is and so
uh you know we can basically uh map it
into the address space by calling this
function kvmf which i will look in in a
second
and then in the first exercise of
the page table app you are asked to
implement a function called vm print
and i implemented it too and we're going
to step over it and we'll see
basically uh the page tables
uh the kernel page table as it is set up
after that one call to tpm map so i'm
going to do that
and boom and it prints out something and
so we're going to look at a little bit
of the output here so here's the page
table that is the
physical address of the top level
uh page directory so the thing that
actually sits in satp
or will sit in satp and then
you know we have entry 0 of the top
level page directly has
one pte entry in it
and that is the contains the physical
address for the middle level page table
directory
the middle page table directory has one
entry namely 128
and that points to the bottom page table
directory and the bottom plane table
directory has the entry then for the
physical page and you can see indeed
that the
physical address you know for that the
bottom level is ox
1 0 0 0 corresponding to uh 0.
so basically virtual address 1 0 0 0
translates to physical address one one
one zero zero
and we can sort of double check that
this is uh indeed all legit
right by uh let's take that address
on that ox one zero zero l and we're
going to shift to 12.
um and that should be uh
you know that gives us the top level 27
27 bits
we've shifted nine so i'm going to take
ox one zero zero
uh one zero zero zero one zero one more
and we're gonna shift at nine and print
that
and that is ox zero and actually if we
print ox0 as a decimal decimal number
it's going to be 128. okay
so we see you actually sort of you know
it all sort of makes sense
we also see i printed out the flags here
uh
and you know the bottom level has read
write
and uh invalid because valid is one
any questions about this
okay so um the kernel basically proceeds
uh you know doing setting up the whole
address space in this way
uh and so we've calls kvn map you know
for virgil
for the clint for the click uh maps the
kernel text maps the kernel memory or
kernel data
and then the trampoline page that we'll
talk about next week
uh and so in fact you know we can sort
of single step through this and then
see what the final page directory looks
like
uh next next
next next basically you know we set the
trampoline and so now we're going to
print the complete page table directory
and you know we see you know basically
a lot of pte is actually being uh
set up um and we're not gonna really
talk about in any detail
uh but you know basically it fills out
the page directory
uh to actually create that virtual
mapping mapping that we basically saw on
the previous slide
when i in fact what i'm going to do next
is actually much more interesting
i'm going to yeah i want to go here
actually i guess maybe i already did
this
uh we're 21 no i'm 21 okay so single
step
not okay that's too bad i got past that
but
basically uh let me
let me restart this
and i want to break point at
kvm in at heart
and continue
boom i'm now here at kvm at heart and we
see here basically
that we're writing the satp register so
basically the kernel is going to enable
uh the page table or the mmu to
basically start using the page table
that we just set up
and one uh interesting question
okay so i do have layout split again
so somewhere here correct is going to be
here's the instruction uh and
so once so something really dramatic
happens
after executing this instruction
once i say you know i can't see the
assembly instruction exactly but there
are there is this
this extent once this instruction is
executed what will happen with the next
address that's being translated
well at the point that we execute this
instruction before
executing this instruction there's no
page tables enabled yet so no
translation happens
but the next and then the program
counter is updated by four
and then the next instruction are
executed and the program counter will be
translated using the virtual page
page table memory and so this is a
you know the way to think about this
this is a dramatic moment
because basically the whole address
translation is starting to enable and
every address
needs to know maybe potentially
something different
right because before we're running
there's like the physical addresses then
the page table henderson
and whatever is in the mapping that is
now the new meaning of a virtual dress
and this is how this works out you know
the fact that this actually works out is
sort of remarkable because like the next
instruction the next value is a virtual
address and not a physical address
next instruction is going to be this
whatever ox1110
and why does this work out
well the reason works out is because the
kernel is set up with an identity page
mapping
so after we enable the virtual paging
hardware
we actually you know this translation
will translate again to the same
physical address
and so indeed you know we'll actually
end up you know
executing the right instruction because
that's actually exactly the instructions
the memory location that the
virtual hardware is programmed for so
does this make sense
again one reason why programming with
virtual memory is difficult
is because once you execute one of these
satp instructions
you know you load a page table in the
satp register your world completely
changes
and every address is now translated with
the pay stable that you set up
and so what happens if the page table
set up incorrectly
what would you what might happen
anybody who wants to say that answer it
or answer it in the chat either way
you could override kernel data yeah you
could overwrite kernel data what else
could happen yeah page fault you know
basically the
the mapping may be uh incorrect and
basically the dress can't be translated
at all and so the kernel can
you know the heart rate won't do it and
use the kernel just stops it panics
does that make sense so if you get a bug
in your page tables
you know you're going to see bizarre
errors
or crashes and so one reason that for
example the next lab
uh the page table app that we'll hand
out or release tonight
is going to be hard is because those
kind of bugs will show up
and you're going to be not careful
enough or you haven't fully internalized
some aspect yet
and you're basically going to get a
kernel crash and you're going to have a
hard time or you know it will take a
little bit of time and energy and
detective work to basically track down
why that happened
and that's just the that's just part of
like programming virtual memory
because it's such a powerful primitive
you know if you get it wrong you're also
going to have
powerful consequences
yet the other hand is a great amount of
fun so i don't want to end on a negative
note
but all that will give you sort of a
real understanding of actually what
really virtual memory is
and what it can do okay i think i'm
running out of time so i'm going to stop
here
so people have time to go to the next
class or next activity
uh but if you have any questions left uh
you know please hang on
and ask them and
we'll see you on monday and good luck
with
finishing the cisco lab
um hi i have a question about walk
um so it says and in the code it returns
the
like the first tables on pte
yeah right um but
but how does it work then like the other
functions when they expect
the actual pte that like the physical
address
like yeah so basically this
returns the pt entry in the page table
correct
and the kernel can read and write page
table entries
and so now you can stick values into the
pte
and so maybe i can draw a picture if
that is helpful
um let's see
so basically we have a page directory
and you know this walk code so the page
directory has 512
ptes in it
here's zero here's five and eleven and
basically what the function does
it returns a pointer to one of these
pkes and so that's just a virtual
address
and it just points to that particular
pte and now the kernel can
you know manipulate that pte by like
whatever writing values to it
like some physical address maybe
with some permissions ordered into it
for the top bottom 10 bits
and then that basically updates the page
sample directory and then later on
when you load that into satp now that
effect
that that change will go into effect
does that make sense yeah that makes
sense i guess i was just confused like
why does it do the work of going all the
way to the
third page table and then only return
the first pte no the return is actually
the
the bottom one all right actually but
let me
be careful uh if you notice it goes
through the end levels so it starts at
level two and then it goes to level one
then it goes to level zero
if uh the alkbit is set
and and level doesn't exist it will
create the intermediate page default
directory
and zero it out and then keep going in
the loop
so in what you always end up on the
bottom pte
if alex is not set you stop at the first
pte that doesn't have a value
okay that makes sense so this is the
last one the actual
one that gonna have okay okay thank you
any other questions
um so i have a question uh basically
everything made sense
until we mapped the virtual addresses to
of the kernel to the physical addresses
um
so my understanding is that each process
will have its own page table which is
also a three level tree
which maps its virtual addresses to
physical addresses
but then when we map the kernel address
the kernel virtual addresses to physical
addresses
i don't think we accounted for the
actual tree of the
virtual addresses of the kernel or where
other processes
will have their virtual addresses and
i'm sorry virtual addresses um like the
page table trees
and whatever the page table tree points
at
in the physical memory yeah so so
so you know you're back so this is the
slide with the kernel
uh uh address space the virtual kernel
address space
and so when the kernel allocates a proc
uh
and the page tables for that particular
process they're going to be allocated
out of memory here you know memory
that's not being used yet
and the kernel is going to program uh
we will probably allocate a couple pages
for the page table of the user level
process and we'll fill in the ptes
and then some point when the kernel runs
that process
it will load the root
physical address for those pages that it
allocated for that page table or
basically for the page table then built
into the satp register
and at that point the processor will run
with the virtual address space that the
kernel constructed for that particular
process
uh so the kernel give up some of its
memory
for processes and then but then the
virtual space
in theory is as big for the process as
the current but in reality it's really
not
yeah for example yes here's a picture
with the layout of a virtual address
space over user level process
and again it goes from zero to max va
in the same way as the kernel address
space does
and it just basically has his own set of
page tables to map those
do do do translation that the kernel set
up
but we can't actually use all of the max
va virtually no we cannot
we run out of memory
so many of the processes are much much
smaller correct than
all of the virtual address space
i see thinking
i've got a quick question yep um
could you go back to the walk code yeah
yeah yeah absolutely
and it's like one of my favorite
functions
uh so i guess um i think one thing i'm
confused about is
after you write to the set p register
can the colonel even
access physical addresses directly so it
looks like in the code that it's
converting you know like page tables
being set to a physical address but if
sap is set
um won't that be interpreted as a
virtual address
yeah uh so uh
okay so let's look at uh whatever the
heart in it
so there's kvm so built in the kernel
address space
uh the kernel page table uh
initially is a ver physical you know
there's an address it's translated to
uh a physical address and that's
actually written into the satp register
and at that point you know we're running
with the address space that we
constructed
like right before here in this kvm
minute
and kvn map is basically nothing else
than
calling uh uh walk
for every address or every page in that
range
and so what was your question uh
um i guess it's does walk still work the
same way if you call it after
set p is set yeah why
yeah why why would it work out the
reason it will work out is because the
kernel set up in identity mapping
uh okay right right
very important very good question
like a lot of things just happen to work
out because actually the identity
mapping is set up
i see okay i think that makes sense yeah
thanks i have a good question
no um where are the satp registers
stored for
all of the processes there's only one
satp per core
uh but in every proc structure
okay in every if you look in proctored h
uh there is a
uh uh pointed to the page table here
here okay that makes sense yep um and
also
um with regards to the three uh page
tables are like the three tables that
can
complete the full address and help you
get a full address for
um given something um how does how is
that better i guess than
than having one giant page table i
didn't really fully understand that okay
good good
there's a good great question the reason
is is because in the free level page
table you can leave a lot of entries
empty
so for example if you leave the an entry
in the top level page table
directly empty you don't have to create
middle level page tables
or bottom level page tables at all for
those entries
okay and so like this means like a big
swath
of the whole virtual address page
doesn't have to have any mappings at all
okay okay you don't have the table there
it just doesn't exist
see basically allocating these chunks on
demand
as opposed to auditing and typing okay
that makes sense yeah you start out
basically with three
page three pages namely one from the top
level one for the and one intermediate
and one for a and one bottom level
and then as you go you create more page
stable directories
okay okay cool cool thank you so much
are you welcome any more questions
oh sorry i have another one it's really
really small but
um in the vm dot c
online 43 yep or sorry 40
1 40 yeah um it says that it
no never nevermind 43. my bad um it says
physical stop
minus um un-64 e-text
but wouldn't that would not go over
the um i guess the memory that
we shouldn't touch i don't know if that
makes sense but
um wouldn't that go
i guess i don't i don't understand
wouldn't i go over free memory
uh no i don't think so uh
so current base is ox8800 correct so
that's the beginning
of memory uh and the kernel sits there
and uh basically
this thing is a size right so e-text is
the last address of the kernel
subtract current base that basically
gives you the size of the kernel
uh in uh in bytes
and you know i don't know how much it is
but the uh
uh it's like you know 60 or 90 pages or
something like that
uh and so this map is basically the text
part of the kernel
and uh and there's enough space
uh there's enough dram you know to map
that
the kernel text i'm not sure i'm
answering your question but
oh oh i think i think i understand i
thought that
attacks starts somewhere else okay i
think i understand now thank you
so much is basically the last
instruction the address of the last
instruction of the kernel
okay okay