am i loud and clear yep sounds good
okay great uh so good afternoon or good
evening or good morning or a good night
wherever you are
let's get started on the like i said
this third lecture in
so 81 which is going to be about ois
organization
and the topics for today
are
four things that i want to touch on one
is isolation
which you'll see is the driving design
goal
for os organization i'll talk a little
bit about
kernel and user mode
as a way of isolating the kernel from or
the operating system from
user applications uh then i'll talk
about system calls
which is a way for you know user
applications to basically transition
into the kernel
uh so they can ask for services and
we'll look at a little bit how this all
is
instantiated in a simple form uh inside
of
x36 so that is the the point for today
um and just to sort of
remind you uh where we were
after the first lecture uh the picture
sort of in your head
that you should have in your head is you
know there are processes
like the shell like echo
or whatever
find you know whatever some of the
utilities that you implemented
they're running on top of an operating
system
and you know the operating system
abstracts you know some of the hardware
resources
you know like a disk or cpu and you know
basically the interface between the
operating systems and the
is not typically referred to as a system
called interface and the interface that
we've been looking at
is the unix interface
and here what we see
is so that was roughly you know actually
with that unix interface you've been
playing around in lab one
uh were in the util app where you used
you know the system called interstates
or the unix api
to actually implement different sets of
applications and so
lab one uh user lab was mostly focused
on
you know sort of using you know this
part uh
of the design picture here and what
we're gonna be doing now
in this first lecture or this lecture
and many subsequent lectures
we're gonna really look actually how
that interface is actually implemented
in fact almost all the semester we're
going to be spending time on
figuring out actually how to implement
the interface and so this is going to be
the first lecture
of that kind of style and uh
unfortunately
uh you know a lot of you asked really
great questions uh
over email um or submitted a great
question to the website
uh and we won't be able uh you know to
go into great amount of detail
immediately in the sort of first lecture
that takes an inside loop of the
operating system
so we're going to touch on a lot of
different things but many things will
become more clear
in subsequent lectures where we're going
to explore them in more depth
but nevertheless if there's something
unclear
uh feel free to interrupt and ask a
question
and maybe just to start off uh before
actually going any further
uh let me ask you a question and sort of
get yes
questions and answering hopefully going
and ask you like
what is the sort of most interesting
thing that you learned from the
beautiful app and i'll start by
answering that question myself
uh one of the things that actually
surprised me after writing or doing the
usual app is that
i use xrx a lot more frequently than i
used to do i had another
way of doing basically the same thing as
xrx
instead of commands and after actually
doing the
xrg lab i was just like oh that's much
more convenient actually to use it in
that way
and so since then i've been a much more
aggressive user
of x-arcs and i'm just wondering you
know what the
you know what the experience has been
for some of you
and so maybe i'll call out a few names
and
maybe you can mute your microphone then
and sort of test it
and say a little bit about like your
experience with the youtube lab
uh so let me you know pick some people
uh
andrew you
andrew are you online we're listening uh
the most interesting thing for me was
just the pipes
on how to write concurrent programs
had you done any sort of pipe
programming before no i haven't i've
seen the old concurrent stuff but i
haven't seen like os level pipes before
okay how about uh elizabeth weeks
uh yeah i'd agree with that i also
thought that the like
os pipes were super interesting and like
the primes um
example specifically was cool to kind of
figure out and realize that like i
needed to close certain pipes and just
like
are they kind of related to each other
yeah yeah presumably you did find the
pipes of
crime is a little bit harder than uh you
might have thought
uh because it surprises me every time a
little bit tricky to get it right
uh jessica she
um i also thought the primes exercise
was most interesting
did it take you a lot of time or was it
not too bad
um it took me
more time after i realized my initial
implementation wasn't actually
concurrent so it was interesting to
think about like
what the differences are there okay
how about the uh robert murphy
yeah i think that the the my experience
was really just
um i found it really challenging to
program
in in the uh original way that was set
up so i actually created like a bunch of
helper functions that wrapped around
things
um so that's i guess what i did
okay any uh i might
also have sort of any piece of wisdom
amanda go ahead i i kind of liked it and
found it surprising slash cool that
um s2d and and std out are just filed
scripters themselves
zero and one yeah yeah yeah good yeah
yeah and xv6 doesn't hide that from you
at all at least in a normal ce
library that's a little bit wrapped up
in a uh in a
in an interface but uh xv6 doesn't hide
it for you but in the end it boils down
in d2
you know just file descriptor zero one
and two i guess for standard error
good good alexander
um i guess um one thing i was surprised
about
uh was also from the primes problem um
i had this bug that i spent hours on
and the thing was that i didn't realize
that actually there were
whenever you were um
opening a pipe and then for like calling
fork
then basically there would be four uh
ends to the pipe because that pipe it's
kind of
uh goes both to the child process and
the price
the parent process and but i was only
closing two of those
so yeah that was a common common problem
it made sense but for some reason
because
especially the textbook says that when
you fork
uh all of the open file descriptors get
copied
but i didn't think about it then yeah no
it's hard to i mean there's a lot of
details in that interface and you know
the only way to get actually really
familiar with it actually is to program
with it and then
experience it okay good well
i hope you enjoyed the lab uh and you
know of course i hope you'll enjoy the
subsequent labs too
so the lecture for today in some sense
is really you know partially to help you
to get going on the
uh the cisco lab if you haven't already
started and so again
uh you know feel free to interrupt and
ask questions
okay so the first thing i want to do uh
is uh talk a little bit about
isolation uh and you know why it's
important and
why we might care and you know the basic
stories you know reasonably simple
you know we have multiple applications
here we got the shell we got echo
we find and it would be great correct
that if you had a bug in the shell or
for example in your primes program that
actually didn't affect any of the other
applications you know particularly it
would be bad for example if it affected
the shell because probably the seller
you're using to actually you know kill
the program if something goes bad
so you want sort of strong isolation
between these uh
different applications and similarly you
know the os
is sort of the servant you know for all
the applications uh
and you would like it to be the case
that you know if again you know you make
a bug in one of your util programs that
actually the operating system doesn't
crash you know exactly you pass some
strange argument to the
operating system uh you know should be
the case that the operating system
handles that well
and so again you would like to be
there's a strong isolation between
uh the the applications and
the operating system itself um and one
way to think about this a little bit is
to say
is ask ourselves the question you know
what what would happen if there's
actually
no operating system so like you know
consider some straw man design
design
where there is no operating system
or you can think about it as the
operating system basically basically
just being a library you know sort of
thinking of
you know in terms of python uh maybe
just import os
and import os basically loads the whole
operating system inside of your
application
and that's you know the programming
interface you use
so if you think about that sort of way
of thinking so let's say we have to
shell here
you know maybe it includes the you know
the library for
the os and maybe we have some other
application echo
uh and then basically you know these
these applications
if there's no operating system really it
would directly interact with the
hardware
so for example you know they would
actually see you know there's a cpu core
you know there's another cpu core and
you know maybe there's a disk
and they interact directly with the disc
blocks and maybe there's memory and they
will directly interact with the memory
of the machine
and so there's really no layer between
no abstraction layer between basically
the applications
and the hardware and it turns out that
it's just not such a great design
uh for uh isolation
and you can see how isolation might be
broken let's assume for example that you
know
one of the goals graph the operating
system is run multiple applications
and so that has to be the case that in
once in a while it will switch
from one application to another
application let's say the hardware has
only one
cpu and so we're running the shell
saying that one cpu
but you know periodically and other
applications should be able to run too
well we have no operating system you
know to do it for us
then the shell basically has to sort of
give up you know the cpu once in a while
and so to be a nice person and say like
well you know i've run for a little
while now you get a chance to run
and this is sometimes called cooperative
scheduling um
but that's not so great for isolation
you know for example what what if you
know some function in the shell has an
infinite loop
and therefore it will never actually
give up the cpu and then no other
you know applications could run
including maybe the application that
would like stop or kill
you know the shell and so uh we
basically don't get any sort of form of
enforced
multiplexing and that's something that
we'd like to have
where you know no matter what the
application does it will be forced to
give up the cpu once in a while
so that other applications go wrong
similarly you know if you think about
this drama and design uh
you know we have there's like physical
memory right and all
i drew the picture here as for the
application sitting on the top of the
hardware
but you know there's physical memory and
basically the text
in the code and the data for these
applications actually sits in physical
memory right so here's memory
and here's me saying the you know the
part of physical memory that's used by
the shell
and here's maybe the part of the
physical memory that's used by
echo application and so you're gonna you
know and
again what we see here if we use like
simply simplistically like this
uh there's sort of no uh boundary
between these two guys if for example if
you know echo you know stores through
location that for example belongs you
know to
the shell like location 1000 and writes
a value there
you know whatever x uh then it would
just overwrite the physical memory of
the
shell memory and so that you know be
pretty undesirable okay because then a
bug you know an echo
could actually percolate into the shell
and you know it's going to be very
tricky to debug and that kind of stuff
and so this basically again
gives us like no strong isolation
what we'd like is uh to have
memory isolation so that one application
cannot overwrite
the uh memory of another application
um and it's a
you know one reason you know i mean
probably the main reason to actually
have an operating system
is basically to enforce you know both
the multiplexing
uh and to enforce you know strong memory
isolation
and if you didn't have an operating
system and the applicants were directly
interacting with the hardware
it would be very hard to achieve that
and so
this design of basically you know
operating system as a library
is not a very common design you may see
it in some real-time systems
where basically applications trust each
other but in most other
operating systems you know there's an
operating system that really enforces
you know that kind of
isolation so if we
look a little bit now at the unix
interface from this perspective
then we see that the interface actually
is carefully designed
so that it actually is feasible to
implement
that enforced uh isolation
in terms of multiplexing in terms of
physical memory and the way that is sort
of
done is that the interface basically
abstracts
the hardware
the hardware resources
in a way that then it makes it easy to
actually do
or not easier and it makes it possible
you know to provide you know the strong
isolation um and you know maybe
it gives you some examples uh so
processes now we've seen them like the
things that are created by fork
you know they're not you know literally
a cpu right i mean
but they correspond to like what a cpu
is and it allows you to run computation
but you know because you know they're
the applications cannot directly
interact with the cpu but only for this
process abstraction
the kernel sort of behind the scenes you
know can switch between processes
so instead of having you know direct
cpus to manipulate
or given to the application the
operating system provides processes
that extract the weight or the cpu
itself so that actually the operating
system can multiplex
and one cpu or multiple cpus among
multiple applications
similarly if you think about exec exec
provides a memory image um and
uh armando yeah go ahead ask your
question
one question about like processes sort
of like obstructing
the cpu is it that
one process uses part of the cpu
and another process uses a like more a
different part of that cpu or a
different cpu
if it's like a multi-core or like what
do you mean by processes instead of a
cpu
yeah okay so i really mean one cpu
abstracted away into a process so okay
so the way to think about it is the
uh the risc 5 core or risk 5 processor
that we're using
in the lab that's actually four cores
uh and so you can run four processes
concurrently or in parallel you know one
process on each core
and what the operating system does is
let's say you have eight applications or
seven applications
it will take some core and multiplexes
time multiplexes
between different processes so for
example it will run you know one app
process for 100 milliseconds
then stop unload you know that process
out of the
cpu or out of the core loading the next
uh
application or the next process and runs
that for 100 milliseconds
and it just enforces that no application
can run or no process can run longer
than 100 milliseconds
and we'll see exactly how this is done
in a couple lectures but that's sort of
the basic idea
okay but multiple processes cannot use
the same cpu at the same time
no it's time multiplied you run for one
for a while then you run the next one
for a while
all right thank you okay so
one way to think about exec is that it
actually
abstracts memory
so for example if you think about the
actual system call you know takes a file
name you know
and in that file is basically the memory
image of
a program store you know it's text you
know sometimes it's uh
global data uh and and that forms
the the memory uh of the application
now the application can grow its memory
for example by calling s-break
uh and uh extend there by extending its
data segment
but it doesn't really have a direct
aspect to physical memory you know
you can't just ask or no i want you know
addresses you know physical memory uh 1k
to 2k
uh you know there's no way of getting at
that and again the reason that there's
no way that you can get at that
is because the operating system usually
wants to provide memory isolation
and therefore wants to be in control or
sort of intermediate and intermediate
between the applications and the
physical hardware and exec is you know
sort of a system call that
you know capture or shows that there's
like no direct
access to the memory another example of
this is like files
files basically abstract away disk
blocks
so instead of reading and writing uh the
disc blocks of the the
the disc that sits attached to your
computer uh that's actually just not
allowed in unix you know the only way to
interact or with the storage system
is through files and you can read and
write files you provide a convenient
abstraction you can name files
et cetera et cetera but then the
operating system in itself can actually
decide how to map those files to
this box and make sure that for example
this block only shows up in one file and
that you know user a
cannot actually you know manipulate or
read or write
you know the files of uh user b uh and
again
you know this you know that sort of
interface that
the file abstraction allows that sort of
strong isolation between
even different users and you know to
different processes of the same user
and so you see that you know in some
ways you know the system called
interface or the unix interface that
you've been programming with you know in
the util lab
seems to be sort of carefully designed
to abstract the resources in a way
so that you know the operating system
the implementation of the interface
can actually multiplex you know the
resources on multiple applications
and provides strong strong isolation
any questions about that we have a
question in the chat that says uh do
more complex kernels try to reschedule
processes on the same core to reduce
cash misses
oh yeah uh there's something called
cache affinity
uh uh you know the scan version in you
know modern operating systems are
very sophisticated and indeed you know
trying to avoid cache misses and things
like that and to optimize in the
performance
and you know we'll see some of that much
later in the semester you know when
we're
going to be talking about high
performance networking uh that will show
up there
another question from chat where in xv6
can we see how the os multiplexes
processes
uh we're gonna there's a couple pile of
files that are relevant but proc.c
is probably the most relevant one uh
this will be a topic of
lecture in like two or three weeks and
we're going to go in great amount of
detail and show exactly how the
multiplexing happens
so one way to think about this lecture
is a little bit of an introduction to a
lot of different pieces
and you know because we've got to start
somewhere
okay so um so we go back into this
picture here that i showed a little bit
a while ago
we have this uh the shell running the
echo running or not that picture i want
this picture
here on this side we've got the
operating system we have the
applications running
and one thing we should be worried about
this square words that the operating
system so it should be
uh oh i should be defensive
and this is sort of an important mindset
you know that you
have to get used to uh when you're doing
kernel development
the operating system you know has to
ensure uh
that everything you know everything
works out and so uh
yeah it has to set up things up so that
you know an app cannot crash the
operating system
it would be too bad they have an
application uh that either by accident
or maliciously passes you know a tricky
argument bad argument to
the operating system and the oxford
system would crash that basically means
sort of denial service for
every other application so the operating
system has to be written in a way that
you know it can deal and handle
malicious applications
and particularly another concern is that
an application should not be able
cannot break out of its isolation
i mean the application might be
definitely malicious maybe
written by an attacker and attacker
probably
you know would like to break out of the
application for example and take control
over the kernel
and once you have control over the
kernel then you can do anything because
you know the kernel is
in control of all the hardware resources
and so the operating system has to be or
the kernel has to be written defensively
uh you know to avoid uh those kinds of
things
uh it turns out to be very tricky uh to
actually get right
in fact using linux you know they're
still periodic
bugs you know kernel bugs or blocks that
actually allow
an application to exploit uh or to break
out of this isolation domain
and to take control uh but this is
continuous concern and we like to do as
a good job as possible
and this is the mindset you have to have
you know when you're developing a kernel
that
actually applications are uh
perhaps malicious now this means that
the means
there has to be strong isolation
between the apps
and the os and if the os you know
needs to be defensive and uh needs to be
in a position that can defenses there
has to be sort of a strong wall between
the applications so that the operating
system can actually enforce
you know whatever policies it wants to
enforce
and this is typically done the typical
approach to achieving this strong
isolation
is using hardware support
and we'll give a little bit of flavor of
that in this lecture but we'll come back
to it in much more detail in subsequent
lectures and those are two
two parts of this hardware support one
is something that's called user kernel
mode
slash kernel mode in risk five it's
called supervisor mode but it's the same
thing
and then page tables or virtual memory
so all processors uh sort of all sort of
series processors
uh that are intended to run an operating
system in multiple applications
uh have support you know for either for
user kernel mode and virtual memory you
know it might mean men of stated or
implemented in all
slightly different ways but basically
all processors have it
um and our risk 5 processor that we're
using in this
class has that support too so
let me talk a little bit i'm going to
talk a little bit about user mode in
kernel mode first and then i'll talk a
little bit about virtual memory
mostly at the highest level possible
because there's a lot of important
details that i won't be able to cover
those in this lecture
so let's first talk about user kernel
mode
and basically what it means is that the
processor has two
modes of operation you know one is user
mode and the other one is kernel mode
and when running in kernel mode
the cpu can execute privilege
instructions
i'll come back to the in a second it out
when running in user mode
the cpu can only execute in unprivileged
instructions
and um structures are the instructions
you're well familiar with you know
think about like add sub you know adding
the
two registers together you know
subtracting through register so it's
really basic
you know you know procedure calls you
know jr
all that kind of stuff branches you know
those are all
uh privilege instructions that any user
application is allowed to execute
privileged instructions are structured
basically
are involved in manipulating the
hardware directly
setting up protections and things like
that so for example setting up a page
table register
which we'll talk about later or
you know disabling clock interrupts
and so there's all kinds of sort of
state on the processor that the
operating system you know is tended to
use
and manipulating that state is you know
completely uh
is done for privileged instructions and
so for example when a user application
tries to actually execute a privileged
instruction uh then the
processor voltage won't execute it
because if a critical instruction in
user mode is disallowed
and basically that will result in the
transfer control
from user space from user mode to kernel
mode so that then the operating system
can actually take control and maybe if i
kill the application because it's
misbehaving to get a little bit of a
sense
uh the difference between the two and
the privilege and imprivillage
instructions
let me switch display for a second and
here on the right side you have the
display
is a document you know the risk 5
privilege architecture document and that
document contains all the previous
instructions
you know it's linked from the website uh
under
the references page and in the
next couple of weeks uh you know or
almost months
you know you will be playing around you
know all these prisoners instructions
that you know are
shown here and in fact many of them will
you know show up and
some of them will actually show up in
the next lecture in a great amount of
detail
but users think about this as there are
previous instructions that user
applications should not be able to
execute
and those can only be executed in kernel
mode
so that's one aspect of you know this
sort of hardware support for strong
isolation
just a quick question like the
what i'm imagining in my head is
something like if kernel mode
allow else don't like what who is
running that code and checking if it's
current mode and how do they know if
it's in kernel mode
is it like a flag or something yeah it's
basically a flag in the processor
you know literally there's a bit in the
processor that says you know your
user mode you know one is saying uh
typically one is user mode and zero is
kernel mode
and so when the processor decodes an
instruction uh looks at the op code
if the op code is a privilege
instruction and the
bit is set to one and will deny
executing that instruction
it's like divided by zero you're not
allowed to do that
okay but if that bit has changed like if
some way you
you were just able to overwrite that bit
then that's the only thing controlling
yeah so what do you think what the
instruction that overrides a bit is that
a prefix instructor or an unprivileged
instruction
is it a question
clearly you know the the instruction
that you know sets the bit
must be a previous instruction because
the user application should not be able
to set the bit to kernel mode correct
and then you know be able to actually
uh run all kinds of preflight
instructions and so that bit is
protected
does that make sense okay yeah
um okay good so uh so let's use the
kernel mode or at least you know
the top view of the kernel mode it turns
out the risk five has a
as a number of you asked about has a
third mode called machine mode
uh we're mostly going to ignore that and
so i'm not going to much say about it
basically there's one more left because
basically three levels of privileges
instead of two level three figures
i'm here go ahead right so i'm wondering
with respect to security if
all user code does go through the kernel
the intent is that things are secure
but is there a way for uh a user of the
computer
to completely uh go around the operating
system
no not really at least you know if done
carefully
not
and if possible like you know that might
be the case that some programs have
additional privileges
uh that the operating system will uh
respect
uh but those privileges are not given to
every user you know example only the
root user has certain privileges that
allow you to do
uh security sensitive operations what
about bios
does bias happen before os or
after yeah so the bios this is the
the piece of software that basically
comes with the computer
and that's booted first and now the buys
basically boots the operating system
uh so the bios is a trusted pieces code
that better be correct and better be not
malicious
noah go ahead uh yeah so you mentioned
that the uh
you know the um instruction to set the
uh the kernel mode bit
is a privileged instruction how would a
user program
ever then be able to you know get like
like you know essentially have the
kernel execute any kernel instructions
if
like the very instruction to access
kernel mode
is itself a privileged instruction i
guess it seems like there's immediately
a barrier for a user program
ever changing that bit yeah yeah uh
that's correct and
that's exactly the way we want it
correct uh so one way to think about it
and this is not exactly how it works in
on the risk five but like if you
execute a previous instruction in user
space would try to execute
a privileged instruction
i'm back sorry about that it looked like
my
zoom client uh crashed uh on me
uh i apologize for that i don't really
know why
but it did um
can everybody hear me again yep you're
good
all good all right well
they're somewhere a bug
okay so back to
uh back to
uh the second piece of hardware support
which almost all cpus provide
uh which cpus provide
virtual memory
and i'm going to talk about this on
wednesday much much more
detail but basically the process has
something you know what it's called the
page table
and you've seen this a little bit i
think in double o4 and the page bagel
basically
maps virtual addresses
to physical addresses
and the basic idea is to give every
process
its own page table
and in this way you know the
the process can actually only use or is
only allowed to access that piece of
physical memory that actually shows up
in this page table
and so if you set up if the operating
system sets the page tables up in a way
that uh every uh process has disjoined
you know physical memory
then a process can't even access you
know somebody else's physical memory
because it's not even in its page tables
so there's nothing like no way even to
create an address or
write down an address that will allow a
process to access somebody else's
physical memory and so this gives us
strong memory isolation
basically page stable defines a view on
memory
and every where the user process has
its own view of memory independent of
each other
and this gives us very strong memory
isolation
and so now what we can do if we can
think a little bit in this way
then we can redraw the picture a little
bit earlier
and because we think about this as
follows you know we have a box
yeah and ls sits in that box and we have
another box
and you know echo sits in that box
and that box basically has an address a
virtual address range starting from zero
to like whatever some number two to the
power whatever the
number is uh in risk five which we'll
talk about on
on wednesday and similarly you know the
dress range for echo is you know
something
whatever it's saying to to the
powershell max and so
uh ls has a member location zero echo
has a location like a zero and you just
completely separate it
and if the operating system maps those
virtual addresses zero to different
pieces of physical addresses
then basically ls cannot access echo's
memory and echo cannot access ls memory
and similarly you know the kernel
actually you know sits below it
you know also has his own at least an
xv6 has his own
address range independent of the
applications
and we can think about the user kernel
mode as sort of sitting
in between you know the boundary uh you
know things that actually run
in user space running user mode
and things that sit in the kernel run in
kernel mode
and that's sort of the picture you know
that you should answer like the os you
know sits there you know sitting in
kernel mode
and so this is the picture that you
should have in your head
now as described so far this picture is
a little bit too strict
you know we have basically put
everything in the box but there's no way
for one box to transfer control to
another box
and clearly when that needs to happen
right because for example als you know
probably wants to call
you know reit the read system call or
write system call
or maybe you know whatever the shell
wants to call fork or an exit
and so there has to be a way for an
application
or user application to transfer control
in a coordinated manner
to the kernel so that the kernel can
actually provide services
and so there's a plan basically in
addition to this
two pieces of hardware support that i
talked so far talked about so far
is a way of controlled way of entering
the kernel
it turns out actually on risk five uh
there is a an instruction
uh for this it's called the e-call
instruction
and the e-call instruction takes one
argument a number
and so in a user application that wants
to transfer control into the kernel
basically can call the e-call
instruction with a number it's like two
or three or four or five
and that number basically is the system
call number
that the application wants to invoke
and that uh basically what that does it
actually enters the kernel at a
particular
uh point uh or a particular location in
the cont
in the kernel that's controlled by the
kernel and as we'll see in xv6
uh in some later lectures uh you know
there's basically a single
system called entry point and um
and every time an application calls
e-call you know the application
enters the kernel of that particular
point so one
um so one way to think about this is
that if you have fork
you know fork you know call in user
space for example the shell or your
prangs
program called fork well whatever it
calls fork it doesn't really call the
operating system directly you know the
corresponding function in the kernel
instead you know what it does it
actually calls an e-call
with you know the number for a fork
which you know and then that actually
jumps into the kernel
so this is a kernel transition and
there's the user side here's the kernel
side
and then on the kernel side you know
there's a function called syscall
in cisco.c and that basically every
system call will end up
at that particular system call function
and the system call will look at the
number
and then decide and the number is
actually passed in the register i think
it's a0
and it's just called can look at that
register look at a0
see what the number is and then for
example call the forex system call
and so just to make a little clear so
this is this hard boundary
between the user and kernel so the user
cannot
call you know the disks for directly
you know the only way you know user
application can actually invoke you know
the system call for fork
is actually through this e-coll
instruction
and so i have another
if i have another
another system called let's say right
it does something similar you know the
right uh system called cannot call
you know the right you know code
directly into the kernel
instead uh what it does it calls what's
these these
these little rappers are called uh
system call stops and we'll call ecall
a function called write that actually
execute the equal instruction you know
with the argument you know says right
to indicate you know the write system
call and add again you know transcript
control to syscall
and then syscall uh can actually
uh view multiplexing to the right system
call for two
questions please go ahead
um so i think my hand was off
okay i can go ahead um um
the question i had was um how does
or where does the kernel check um
for for example fork or write if it is
allowed or not
um right now you're just passing in like
you know you're just calling ecall and
the system call number
but where does the kernel basically
decide whether this application
should be able to invoke this particular
uh kernel syscall
yeah so a great question so in principle
the on the kernel side correct when we
actually spark
call runs i can implement any secure
check it wants you know i can look at
the arguments you know of the system
call
and decide whether actually the
application should be allowed to execute
the system call fork
now in user in unix any application can
actually call farc
but let's say you take write you know
right you know needs to check
whether uh the implementation of write
needs to check whether the address that
is actually passed
into right actually is a part of the
user applications
and so that you know the kernel is not
tricked to
writing data for somewhere else it
actually doesn't belong to the
application
they're more hints you know please ask
uh yeah i had a quick question um so how
does
the kernel seize back control from a
user application
in the case where the user application
is acting maliciously
or it's in an infinite loop yeah so the
way the plan for that and again we're
going to talk about in much more detail
in a couple weeks
uh is that the kernel actually programs
the hardware to
set a timer and uh after the timer goes
off
uh that will cause a transfer from usage
space to kernel mode so at that point
the kernel isn't backing control
and then the kernel can reschedule uh
the cpu to another
uh process okay make sense thank you
yeah and we'll see that the exact
details you know we'll
see in a little while you have one more
questions
yeah so this is more of a high level
question but what drives
the designers of an operating system's
implementation to use a language like c
ah okay so great question
um she gives you a lot of control
over hardware and so uh
so example you know you need to program
the timer chip uh
the in c that is actually easy to do uh
because you get a lot of low level
control over
any hardware resource and partly because
you can cast anything to anything
and so c is basically very convenient
program language if you have to do very
low level programming
particularly interacting with hardware
it doesn't mean you can't do it in other
languages uh but this is historically
the reason why ce has been successful
i see thanks why is c so much more
popular than uh
c plus only for historic reasons in like
these kinds of applications
or uh is there uh any other reason that
like
no like most os don't haven't adopted c
plus plus
yeah so most operating system you know
there are i think operating systems
written in c plus plus
uh totally possible probably the most
ones that you know you know
are not written in c plus plus uh and
the various reasons for it
uh you know linux is mostly c or no c
plus plus nothing partially because
linus just doesn't like c
plus
any other questions
okay so so in this view of the world
right where
uh you know we have a way of
transferring control
into uh the operating system using uh
system calls or this e-call instruction
uh and so the kernel is now responsible
for
uh implementing actually the the actual
functions and
ensuring uh you know checking arguments
and things like that to make sure that
you know the
uh it's not being tricked in something
uh doing something badly
and so in this view of the world the
kernel is sometimes called
you know it's the trusted computing base
sometimes called in security terms the
tcp
um and you know basically you know what
does it mean for it to be the trusted
computing mix well
it must be correct you know kernels must
have no bugs
because if there's a bug in the kernel
you know the way to think about it is
that maybe an attacker is able sort of
to
tickle the bug and turn the bug into an
exploit
and you know that exploit may maybe
allow that particular attacker to
break out of isolation or maybe take
some control over the kernel
and so it's really important that you
know the kernel really you know has to
have as few bugs as possible
and basically the kernel you know must
treat
let's treat user apps or applications or
processes
that's malicious
and basically as i said before you know
basically the german designer seems to
have sort of a security mindset
uh you know when writing and
implementing uh kernel code
and uh and you know it's hard to achieve
this goal right we're
having no bugs if you're playing system
gigantically big
uh is not that straightforward and you
know almost every operating system you
know that this
you use or is widely used uh once in a
while actually has a security bug
and you know they get fixed over time
but basically
no matter what there's always a new
exploit at some point
down the line and you know we'll see
later why it's so tricky to get it all
right but you know the sort of
understandable like
you know the kernel has to do tricky
stuff uh it has to manipulate hardware
uh it has to be very careful and it's
checking and it's very easy to make a
small slip up
and you know half a buck
and so
an interesting question correct is then
what should run
in kernel mode because it's really the
kernel code that actually is in kernel
mode
that is the uh sensitive code right that
is the trusted computing days
um and one answer you know to that
question is like well you know we have
our
user kernel boundary so here's user
here's kernel and
uh here's our applications running
and here is you know the program running
in kernel mode
one option is to stick the whole
operating system in kernel
mode so example uh in most unix
operating systems the whole
unix implementation runs inside of
kernel mode so for example in xv6
all the operating system services are
basically
in kernel mode and this is called
monolithic
kernel design
and you know there there's a couple
things in the way to think about it
um one you know it's probably not so
good for bugs right
um because any bug
you know that you might have in a
monolithical design you know might
actually turn into an
exploit and that would be bad uh so we
have a large operating system running
inside of the kernel it's likely that
they're going to be more books like any
statistics that you look up it says like
every 3000 lines of code will have you
know some small number of bucks
and so if you have many many more lines
of code you're running in the kernel box
you know the probability of the chance
that you have
uh and then the series buck you know it
goes up a little bit
and so the downside from the molecular
kernel design from the security
perspective is that there's a lot of
code in
the kernel uh the plus though
is you know typically if you're thinking
about an operating system it contains of
all kinds of different pieces you know
you might have to file system piece
you might have the virtual memory piece
uh you might have you know processes you
know
and so there are all kinds of sub
modules inside of the operating system
that implement particular functionality
and the plus side of that is there's
going to be tight integration possible
between these different sub modules if
they're all sitting in the same program
and that can actually lead you know to
great performance
uh an example if you look at an
operating system on linux it actually
achieves uh very impressive performance
and so this is one uh sort of one design
uh another design which basically
focuses on reducing the amount of code
in the kernel
is what's called microkernel design
and in this design the goal is actually
to run as few
lights as possible in kernel mode and so
for example there is
something often kernel but the kernel
has very few
uh components to it so for example it
typically has some form
of ipc or message passing a little bit
of
vm support very minimal basically only
the thing
necessarily for page tables and
something to multiplex
uh different cpus so some multiplexing
code
but generally the goal is to run the
bulk of the operating system outside of
the kernel
and so for example again as we have our
you know boundary here
uh what we'll do is actually we'll run
other parts of the kernel as usual
normal user applications so example we
might have an
oops
you might have a user process still okay
it's not going to intended but it
doesn't really matter
you know that's the file server and
so and the file server is just a regular
user space
so user space kernel so even though i
drew uh by accident
in red i intended to draw out in black
uh the faucets are mine run like a user
application like you know
echo you know the shell they're all
running user space and we might have
other you know user applications like
the
parts of the vm system might actually
run a regular user application
in um in user mode and so this is sort
of a nice design correct because
you know the amount of code that
presumably that's in the kernel is small
it's small and small means hopefully
fewer bucks
the one issue and of course it's like
you know we have to arrange that the
shell can talk to the file system for
example you know the shell calls exec
and there has to be a way you've got to
get into the file system and so
typically that way that works is that
the shell will send a message you know
through the ipc system
to the kernel the kernel will look at it
and say like oh you know this is
intended for the file system so the file
system sends it to the file system
the file system doesn't work you know
sends a message back
saying like you know here's the results
of your exact system call
and then you know sends it back to the
shell
and so uh these are typically
implemented using messages
uh and so for any interaction with the
file server
now you have to jump once into the
kernel once out of the kernel
once into the kernel once out of the
kernel if you compare that with the
previous design
like if this guy wants to talk to the
file system it's one system to call in
and one basically called back out and so
you double
the numer of system call entries
and so uh one typical problem or
challenge with offer with the micro
kernel approach is
uh is actually how to achieve good
performance and it has sort of two
components to it
one uh you know just jumping back and
forth
you know between user mode and kernel
mode to actually get something done
and the second part is because you know
the different pieces are really well
isolated from each other a tight
integration is less you know
more complicated to range than for
example in the monolithic kernel where
basically
everybody can you know for example the
file system in the virtual memory system
can easily
share a page cache which is a little bit
harder to achieve in the microkernel
design and therefore it's sometimes more
difficult
to get high performance now these
distinctions
you know between microcurrent and
monocle are very high level
so in practice both types of kernel
designs
show up most desktop operating systems
are typically
monolithical systems mostly for
historical reasons
uh a lot of the if you run very intense
you know os intense applications for
example in the data center
they typically run on a mole
monolithical kernel
mostly because for example linux
provides great performance
but many uh embedding settings uh
like minix or cell 4
those all tend to be micro kernel
designs
and so both designs are popular uh if
you probably start a new operating
system from scratch
you probably start with uh you may you
know uh
you may start with a microkernel design
and once you have a monolithical design
like for example linux you know it's
going to be
it would be a ton of work to rewrite it
into a micro kernel design and that's
maybe you know just not conducive to the
incentives you know people probably want
to spend rather time
implementing new features than actually
uh
uh you know restructuring their kernel
and so these are sort of the two main
designs
uh as you know xv6 is a it falls into
monolithical design as most classic unix
systems do but later in the semester
we'll talk a lot more in detail about
some of the microkernel designs
any questions about this because this
was a hot topic in the
in the email questions
okay uh okay so let me switch
a little bit i'm going to fill it to
some code and so to see how all this
plays out
in xv6
uh so here's a two windows
uh and you know your emacs we know with
like the proc structure
and the first thing i want to do is uh
you know
look a little bit at the code base uh
you've probably already done this
but you see that the code is sort of
organized along three uh
in three parts one the kernel and
we can kernel that basically includes
all the
kernel files and so xv6 being a
monolithical kernel
basically all these programs are
compiled things there's a single binary
called the kernel and that's actually
what we run in kernel mode
um and then you know there's user and
those are the
basically the programs that run in user
mode and this is why you know one is
called kernel the other called
user and then there's one more program
called makefs
which actually builds an empty file
system image
that we have stored on disk so that we
can get
off the ground with an empty file system
okay so before so let me switch back
again
to i want to say a little bit about how
the kernel is compiled
uh because you probably have seen this
and might not really have realized it
uh and sort of important to understand
uh
so when the kernel the construction of
the kernel
the make file basically you know takes
you know one of these cs files like
proc.c
you know invokes you know the gcc the
cc compiler that generates a file called
proc.s
that goes to the assembler
and this is basically a risk 5 assembly
and that actually produces a file called
proc.o
and basically that's you know the binary
version of the assembler so
um and you know the makefile does this
for all
you know part files of the kernel so for
example uh you know
pipe there's another one you know same
story
gcc compiles it to pipe.s
and we're going to go through 3d
assembler and we've got a pipe.o
and basically then the loader you know
takes all these dot o files
from all the different files and links
them together
and produces the current and produces
the kernel
and that is actually and then what we've
run and the
you know for your convenience you know
the makefile also produces a file called
kernel.asm
that has the complete kernel
disassembled and you can just look at it
and you know that helps later on
when you have kernel bugs and it's easy
to see which instruction
was executed at the point you got the
debug so
example if i uh
here kernel.asm
we see here's the kernel file
uh disassembly instructions and uh
and one thing you note for example is
that the first uh instruction is located
at this address eight zero zero zero
zero zero
um and that is in whatever aupc
instruction the risk life instruction
[Music]
and anybody knows what this is
zero zero eight one one seven or eight
three one or three six five oh five
anyone who wants to answer that question
that's the
hex version of the assembly instructions
on the right
yeah exactly so what here on the zero
zero a117 is exactly the same thing as
the symbolic you know the textual
version of that a upc
and so basically this is the binary
encoding of the actual instruction
and so and every instruction has a
binary encoding
and you know the kernel of the exam file
actually shows those binary encodings
and this is sometimes convenient when
you look at gdb and you want to know
what actually is going on you know you
can see actually what the binary
encoding is
okay okay so then when we
run xv6 i'm going to run on the inside
of actually let me first run it
without gdb uh you know we'll compile a
bunch of stuff and then it
invokes uh qmu right then this is a
basically c program
that simulates or emulates a risk five
processor
and you can see here in the dash kernel
flag it actually passes the kernel
uh and uh the program to be run
inside of qmu and qmu and
the kernel agreed uh basically the the
starting place for any program
is this address eight zero zero zero
zero
and we see that we pass a couple other
flags to team u it says here m that's
the amount of memory that the machine
this virtual machine has
this virtual risk fight machine it
passes in how many of course there are
it passes in the machine the disk drive
which contains the file fsnf image and
so basically a bunch of things are sort
of set up to make you know qmu behave
like a real computer
and so one way when you think about qmu
you really
should not think about it as a cd
program really the way you should think
about it
is as follows uh
you should think about it as um
as this uh namely a real
board uh so for example this on the left
you know this is a
risk five board uh actually there's a
risk five board that sits in my office
and you know it can boot uh more or less
xv6
and so when you're running you know qmu
uh with your kernel you should think
about it that actually you're running it
on this board
and you know the board has an on off
button
uh here's actually the risk 5 processor
uh you know there's room for peripherals
as for example one of these
connectors is a connector for ethernet
uh
one is the pcie slots uh there are some
ram chips on the
you know the board i don't exactly know
where they are but there are
um and so this is sort of a that's the
physical hardware the computer actually
that actually you're programming so xv6
manages this board uh and that's the the
picture you should have in your head
and in fact if you zoom in you know you
can find all the documentation
of like what actually sits inside of
this uh
and inside of this you know this is the
inside of this risc five
you know processor the the schema for
the risk five processor is
shown in this picture here uh and you
know we see here for example there are
multiple cores in fact the four cores
uh you know there is a l2 cache
uh there's a connector to dram uh
you know there's a bunch of ways to
connect to the outside world so for
example here's your
zero and uh zero is actually connected
on one end
you know to the keyboard and to the
other end to the display
um and you know there's some ways to
actually uh
get clocks uh going i'm i'll talk about
it in much more detail later
but these are all the components that
basically you know the xv6 or
and things that you'll be modifying to
interact with actually the real hardware
in fact the computer system or the
computer board that actually is
emulated by qmu is pretty close
you know minor some small details to
this particular you know computer board
which is made by sci-fi
and unfortunately i can't show you the
real thing as i said sits in my office
you know and i haven't been in my office
since march probably collecting a lot of
dust
uh but it's important to keep in your
head and when you're running qmu
you're running basically on real
hardware and just happens to be
implementing the software
does that make sense password second
tier
so let me say a little bit more about
this so what does it mean for qmu to
emulate
a risk 5 processor
well literally you know if you think
about it like you know as i said you
know people use a csv
program it's an open source c program
it's a big program you can actually just
you know download it or git clone it but
internally into c uh it is basically a
for loop an infinite for loop
that basically does nothing else then
read instruction
the risk five instruction you know
basically reach you know
four bytes or eight bytes and
basically looks at the bits in that
instruction and decodes them
you know figures out what the op code is
and we saw that for some of the
instructions the binary version of those
instructions in the
dot asm file and so it decodes the
instructions so for example maybe it
will decide this is an ad instruction
or there's a sub instruction you know
risk five sub-construction and then
basically
it executes the instruction in software
and you know that basically is all what
it does you know for every core
you know it runs this particular loop
and in addition sort of doing this loop
it has to maintain some state so
maintain state for all the registers
so it has a c declaration for like x0
register 0 x1 etc
and so basically when it executes
instruction for example the instruction
is like whatever
and you know a0
you know you know one through seven and
store it in a zero
then basically takes a constant seven
and one adds them up and sticks it in a
zero
right so examples towards the seven
meter and then it executes the next
instruction and it keeps going keeps
going
in addition to basically emulating or
correctly all the improv
privilege instructions it also emulates
all the privilege instructions
so that is in essence uh what key mu
does
uh and but the best picture for you to
have in your head is that basically
you're running on a real physical risk
five processor
like the ones you have probably you know
many of you implemented one i think in
double o4
any questions about this um hi
yeah i was wondering if it does any
hardware tricks
so like overlapping instructions or
anything
uh no uh it runs on a real processor
below it correct so when you run qmu
and runs probably on an x86 processor
that x86 processor
does all kinds of tricks you know to
pipeline instructions and things like
that
right so the way you think about qmu
it's just a c program
makes sense thank you
what about multi-threading so if the the
cmu
supports you said four cores or does it
only support one
and it is if that case does it have
actually multiple threads running it
yeah so uh actually the qmu that we use
on uh
athena and probably the ones that you
actually download uh
they will use multiple threads
internally so kim you internally use it
to get parallelism
so in fact these four cores that are
being emulated are sort of being
emulated in parallel
and we'll see that in one of the labs
later how that plays out
and so definitely there's a real
parallelism going on between the
different cores
okay so i'm gonna do a little bit of uh
uh you know walking through uh
uh xv6 to get a little bit of sense what
the layout of the land is
uh and you know in the later lecture
again we're gonna go in much more detail
so i'm gonna fire up uh qmu under uh
uh with gdp support so basically qmu has
inside of it a gdp server
um and so it starts it up and then it
just waits you know for
uh gdp to connect to that
so i'm going to start here on my
computer and this is a risc 64 linux new
gdb
on some of your machines it might be
multi-arch or
something else but basically the gdp
compiled for risk 64.
risk 564. and
i'm going to set the breakpoint at entry
because that's the first
we know that's roughly the first
instruction that actually where team
is going to jump to so i set the
breakpoint i run
and basically it doesn't actually break
exactly at eight zero zero zero but at
zero a
and if we look here on the right you
know we see that zero a is
uh right reading the control system
register
mr id and loading that value into a1
and so basically qmu simulates that
instruction then we can execute that
instruction then we go to the next
instruction
and basically this address address800 is
just basically something that was
agreed on you know uh
by qmu or commutal you know basically
says like you want to use qmu
the first instruction we're going to
jump to is at that particular location
and we basically arranged for the kernel
loader
to load the kernel of that program so
there's a file kernel ld
that basically specifies how the kernel
should be loaded
and you see here that basically the
first address that the kernel is going
to use is actually that particular
address that basic pmu specified
this is how we get off the ground
let's make that does that make sense
okay um and we see also that here
actually gdp
shows the binary encoding of the
instructions
and so we see that basically i guess the
csrr is a
four by destruction and an eye is a two
byte instruction
okay um so i'm going to see you know
basically so actually
six basically starts at entry.s uh and
we have no paging with no isolation and
in fact it starts in m mode
uh the exclusive jumps as quickly as
possible to
uh kernel mode or supervisor mode that's
called in risk five
i'm just going to set a breakpoint and
main uh which actually runs in
supervisor mode so i'm going to run
there
and then i get to the first instruction
of main so
let me show this here's main
and i'd like to run
gdb in this layout split mode
and so you can see in gdb actually and
what the next instruction is being
executed so you see there's a great
point
at that particular instruction since
this is a
wren uh qmu with one cpu
uh just makes it the gdp a little bit
easier so there's not only one core
active so commute emulates only one
single core
and i can step through that and so i can
go to the next instruction
and that is calls a function called
console init which does exactly what you
imagine it does it actually sets up the
console
and so once we set up the console we can
actually uh print to it
and so you'll see in a second we'll get
a new line
and we'll get xv6 booting okay so
there's a whole bunch of additional uh
code to set things up you know there's a
setting up the page allocator you know
setting up uh
virtual memory which i'll talk about on
wednesday loading actually starting
turning paging on which i also talked
about on wednesday
uh setting up the initial processes or
sending the process table
uh setting up code you know to do the
usual kernel transition
uh setting up the interrupt control the
click
uh we'll talk about when we talk about
interrupts but this is one like thing
that
uh we're going to be using to basically
talk to the disk or talk to the
console using interrupts uh sets up the
file system
allocates a buffer cache internet
emulation
initializes the inode cache initialize
the file system initializes the disk
and then basically once all sort of
things are set up you know when the
operating system is running
it's going to start running the first
process and this is the user in it
so this is a little bit of interesting
so i'm going to go to user init
for a second and i've got a single step
there
before continuing you know any questions
about this
is there a specific order in which the
setup functions need to be called
yes some function must be run after
other functions
and they're in particular in their some
of them doesn't matter but for you of
them yeah it's important that they run
after other ones
good point okay uh let me go to
uh so here's user in it and basically
user in it there's a little bit of
glue code or immunization code to sort
of take advantage of all the
general infrastructure that xv6 had to
basically get the first process of the
ground
you know x26 needs some image right we
can't run the file system really yet
or do exec and so the x36 needs sort of
a small little program to sort of get
off the ground
and that small little program is in its
code
and the binary version of that program
is actually linked or
declared statically into the kernel in
fact that code corresponds
to this particular user program
uh it's a but it's a little program
written in assembly
and basically it does it loads the
address within it into
a zero it draws the address of rv into
a1
and then it loads the number for this
exact system call into a7
and then look at here it calls e call
so basically what ina does is like
running three instructions
and then running the fourth instruction
to basically transfer back control to
the uh back control to the
operating system so for example if i set
a breakpoint in
syscall uh and i keep running then
basically you know
user init you know will create the
initial process
return to user space run these three
instructions
or four instructions and basically come
back into kernel space
so basically this is the first system
call that any user
application in xv6 runs so let's see
what happens if i'm right
so we're going to continue and we
actually got to syscall
so
so against this call we can look at it
it's a function at the bottom
and so we're back into kernel space now
and we can sort of walk through and see
actually what happens exactly
in syscall so i'm going to single step a
little bit
uh it looks about the current the
process is if it's in it you know
that pulls out the system call number
that's used so we can now print num
and we'll see it at seven and if we look
at
oops
user or kernel syscall.h
that declares all the system call
numbers and we see seven
that is indeed system called exec and so
basically this tells the kernel that you
know
some user application uh called an ecall
instruction
and with the intention of calling the
system call
for uh uh
with the intention of running the exact
system hall and so again we can single
step a little bit further
uh we go to the next thing this is the
line that executes the system call so
let's go there
and you see that basically the number is
used into index into an array
and the array has a bunch of function
pointers and
presumably the sys entry you know points
to the
sysex function so we're going to single
step into this
and we see that we're actually at the
system
so this is in sys file now we can move
it a little bit more
in a bigger window and we basically see
here the system call
and the first thing that you see is
actually it actually gets arguments from
user space so it gets the path name
so we can like jump a little bit further
uh mindsets
basically allocates space for arguments
you know copies all the arguments from
user space to kernel space
we'll look at that in great amount of
detail in a couple weeks so don't worry
about it too much yet
but basically there's some code to move
arguments from user space to kernel
space you know from the kernel
from the user address space to the
kernel address space and if we now look
at
path we can print the path hopefully and
we'll see actually that you know that is
a string
and we'll see that basically what that
little inner code
program does is trying to exec you know
the init
program which is yet another you know
program so let's look at that for a
second just to see
what that is
so here we have in it and in it
basically sets up a couple things
just for user space you know it opens to
console the file descriptor for the
console it dubs it
you know a couple times calls fork and
basically the first thing it does is
actually it tries to create a new
process
and it will exit the jail shell and so
this will
in the end result uh as the shell being
run
so for example if i would continue i
probably break again it says exec and if
i look at the arguments i will see that
actually
the exact system call is being called to
execs
the shell and once you accept the shell
you know let's do that
then we'll do a couple more system calls
and at some point we'll see the
continue then basically the shell starts
running
so it gives you a little bit of a sense
you know actually how xv6 gets off the
ground
how the first shell actually has to run
and we saw the sort of
a little bit of an overview about how
the first you know when the first system
call actually happened
we haven't really looked at the detail
machinery for these system calls now how
to get in and out of the kernel
we're going to talk about that in a
couple weeks or two weeks in the in
lecture in great amount of detail
but this is sort of enough for you to
understand actually how to do the uh
cisco lab you know that we assigned for
this week
and so these are the pieces that you
will be interacting with
any questions before i wrap up because
we're almost out of time
you're free to fire away
are we going to do anything with uh
networks or like networking and labs yes
the last lap is
uh you will implement a network driver
and so you will write the code that
interacts with the hardware and you have
to manipulate the
the registers of the network driver
uh over the network cart that basically
connects
you know to this risk 5 board you know
you saw that it was a block
basically to plug in an ethernet control
cable and so there's an ethernet
card and so you're going to be
programming that card and you're going
to
actually send some packets across the
internet
great thanks yeah it's the last lap
any other questions
okay let me wrap up here i think the
system called lab itself
um because we're not really going great
amount of detail
hopefully shouldn't be too bad uh might
be easier than the util app
uh the last next lap however might be
more difficult
and so it's always hard to get all these
labs right but this is collab hopefully
it shouldn't be uh
too difficult but please don't start
don't wait until the night before you
know get going early
so that if you're running some obscure
bug that we can actually help you out
and make sure that
your program works in the end
with that i'll sign off and i'll see you
in wednesday