all right
um i'd like to get started first can uh
can anyone hear me
yes good thank you very much
all right today i want to talk about
the transition between running and user
code
running programs in user code and
executing in the kernel
and this is the transition that has to
happen whenever a program makes a system
call
or if it experiences a fault like a page
fault or divide by zero
or if a device decides to interrupt and
needs to be served by a kernel device
driver
there's a lot of careful design and sort
of important details that go into the
how these traps from user to kernel
happen
and the details are pretty important for
enforcing isolation security
and also perform per performance there's
many programs that
transition to the kernel a lot either
due to system calls or page
page faults and it can be super
important
that the uh trap mechanism is as
streamlined as possible
all right so um starting situation is
pretty familiar
we have our user program i'll use the
shell as an example
it's running up in user space and
we have the kernel and what the shell
would like to do is make a system call
into the kernel and i'm going to use
write and use this shell writing its
prompt the very first
write that happens after you boot xv6
and use the shell trying to write
make the right system call as an example
and so we need to figure out how to
actually get execution to transfer from
running in the show
in user space with user privileges to
running in the kernel with supervisor
privileges
the state of the hardware is it's going
to be very important because a lot of
what we're doing is kind of
changing the hardware state from state
appropriate for running user code to um
state appropriate for running kernel
code
the state that we care about um you know
the biggest state is maybe the uh
32 user registers as you remember this
from
monday's discussion we have all the user
registers things like a0
and a1 risk 5 has a whole lot of these
32 in total
and we can expect user code to use all
of them right it's going to get the
highest performance if it uses all of
them
many of them have special purposes a few
which we'll see
a particularly interesting one is the
stack pointer is actually one of these
general purpose registers
okay we have these registers including a
stack pointer
there's a separate program counter
register in the hardware
there's the current mode either
supervisor or user and of course it's
user mode when we're executing up in the
in the shell
and then there's a bunch of registers
special registers that control
how the cpu works like there's the sat p
register that
contains a pointer to the page table and
it'll turn out there's a couple of
others that are super important for this
discussion
there's this st which is
addressing the instruction that should
handle traps in the kernel
um there's a register called scpc for
saving the program counter during a trap
and
we'll see there's another one called s
scratch
which is also very important so this is
the state of the running machine
at the time of the system call and we
actually need to change a bunch of this
state or do things
to the state as part of getting into the
kernel
and setting ourselves up to run just
ordinary c functions in the kernel
certainly at the instant of the trap all
the state of the cpu is set up to run
user code
not um not kernel code so the things
that are
going to need to happen is kind of a
preview of what i'll talk about
one is that we need to save all 32
registers because
we want to resume the user code
transparently
particularly if there's a device
interrupt which the user code isn't
expecting
and we want to be able to have the
kernel serve the interrupt and then
resume the user code without ever
noticing any difference and that means
that these 32 registers can't be
disturbed by the kernel
which and since the kernel needs to use
the registers it has to save them all
somewhere
first these need to be saved um the
program counter also needs to be saved
somewhere
because we need to you know it's a user
it's almost like a user register so
we need to continue executing the user
program where it left off
we need to switch the mode to supervisor
mode
because we need to use various
privileges in the kernel
this page table pointer is currently
pointing towards the user page table
which only contains just the mappings
that user programs need
plus one or two more as we'll see but
the user page table does not contain the
mappings for the bulk of the kernel data
so we need to switch page tables before
we can run most kernel code
we need to switch the stack pointer to
point to a stack that's in the kernel
somewhere because
we need a stack to call c functions on
and finally we need to jump into once
we've set all this up and switched all
this all these resources to be
appropriate for use in the kernel we
need to jump to
kernel c code and once we're in c code
life is much more sort of business as
usual we're just running
a c program in this kernel um and so for
today at least we'll
we'll talk about what the kernel does in
the c code later
but today the discussion is really how
to get from user space into the kernel
into a position where we can run
c code in the kernel there's a couple of
high level goals that can strain
our design options for this one is that
for security and isolation we really
don't want to let user code
interfere with this user kernel
transition
in a way that could be damaging to
security and so that means that
the sort of hardware and kernel
mechanisms that are involved in traps
really can't count on anything from user
space
you know we can't assume anything about
these registers they could be just
filled with terribly malicious values
um so basically the xp6 scrap handler
doesn't really even look at these
registers it just saves them away um
so okay so we're going to want to be
careful
to preserve isolation during this trap
mechanism against
intentionally malicious user code and
the other thing that's important
is that we want to be transparent to
user code we'd like to be able to
take the trap and do our business in the
kernel and resume the user code without
it ever having to notice that anything
funny happened
and that's just to make it easier to
write user code
and something to note we care about
isolation security here today we're just
going to talk about the
sort of aspect of security that involves
getting into the kernel but of course
the system called implementations you
know the actual right implementation in
the kernel
also everything in the kernel has to be
careful has to be written carefully and
securely also
so even if this transition into the
kernel is
perfectly secure the whole rest of the
kernel has to be
written securely and sort of mindful
that user code may be trying to trick it
a particularly important thing i want to
talk about is what it is that the mode
flag controls
this mode is either user or supervisor
of course it's user
when we're up in user space and the mode
flag is set to supervisor when we're
executing in the kernel
but it's important to know exactly what
privileges we gain by changing the mode
from user to supervisor
and it turns out these extra privileges
are
fairly restrictive that is what you can
do in supervisor mode that you couldn't
do in user mode
is not maybe as
privileged as you might think so this is
supervisor mode like exactly what it
controls
one thing it does is you can now read
and write
the control registers and
that is if if you're in supervisor mode
you can read and write sat p
uh the page table pointer this st vac
pointer which controls
where traps go in the kernel um
this register that holds the save
program counter during a trap in this
s scratch register plus a few others
so supervisor couldn't read and write
these registers and user code could not
the only other thing supervisor code can
do is
it can use pte's
that have the pteu flag set
i don't know if you remember but there's
this ptu flag to be set or not said in
each
page table entry a flag
that has this sorry sorry
you can use ptes that
don't have the ptu flag set if the pteu
flag is set it means that user code can
use that page table entry
if this flag isn't set in a page table
entry it means only
supervisor mode can use it um and you
know
we'll see that's important in a little
bit but
um these are really the only things that
supervisor mode can do it can't do
anything else in particular for example
supervisor mode code can't just
read and write arbitrary addresses say
physical addresses
no supervisor mode is forced to go
through the page table
just like any other code if a virtual
address isn't in the page
isn't it in the current page table
pointed to by sat p
um or if it has the pteu bit flag
set which means it's the user ppe then
supervisor mode code
cannot use that address so we're even
in supervisor mode were restricted to
whatever
virtual address virtual addresses were
set up in the current page table
um and that's it so we're just allowed
to do these things so you know we'll see
as a significant constraint on what the
trap code can do when we're entering the
kernel
can't do just anything i'm going to
preview a bit
i'm going to spend most of this lecture
in gdb
actually tracing through the execution
of
a trap entry into the kernel in return
this can be a lot of details in order to
uh maybe sort of help you
see ahead to what's coming we're going
to be
tracing the shells call to
right which from the shell's point of
view is just a c function call as part
of the shell
in fact wright makes this uh might
that's use the system call
by issuing the e-call instruction
which switches into the kernel which is
a supervisor mode where that goes
immediately that is the very first
instruction that's executed in the
kernel in supervisor mode
is in a function written in assembler
called
userback and this is in the
part of the trampoline um
uh in trampoline.s in the kernel source
so the very first code that's executed
is this uservec
assembler function um then next
the that assembler function jumps into c
code in particular a function called
usertrap
in trap.c um and now we're
getting it to c code so things are much
easier to understand
user trap sees oh we're executing a
system call
and it calls a function called syscall
which looks up the system call number in
a table and calls the particular
function inside the kernel that
implements that system calling for us
it's going to be right and right does
this business it happens to you know
uh arrange for the whatever bytes were
written to appear on the console
and when it's finished it returns back
up to this system call function
and then the system call function on in
order to return back to user space
because we want to resume
after the z call there's a bunch of
stuff
we'll see that has to happen in order to
return to user space so there's a
separate function called user
trap rat it's written in c
it's in trap.c that does the part of
this return to user space that's
convenient to do in c code
there's some final things that really
can only be done in assembly code
and the code for that is written in
assembler and it's again in this
trampoline page
in a function called user ret
to the last some last assembly stuff
that has to happen and finally
um this assembly function issues the
machine instruction that returns back in
the user space and
resume execution after the e-column
all right does anybody want to answer
ask a question i'm about to switch into
looking at stuff with gdb um any
questions about the sort of high level
picture
all right i am going to
sorry um let me see
what mode our vm.c functions run in uh
vm.c functions everything in there is a
part of the kernel and it's running
supervisor mode
um yeah
okay somebody asks why these functions
are named this way
um uh the naming is a bit of a disaster
and for next year i'm resolved to
make them more rational
i think the naming question might have
referred to the name of the registers
in the previous board they all started
like yes
for supervisor
[Music]
other than that it's there's five people
pick these names somebody's asking don't
the vm.c functions
access physical memory directly that's
absolutely true
the reason why they're allowed to do
that though is that the kernel carefully
sets up direct mappings in the page
table
there's many many pte's in the page
table which cause
whenever the colonel tries to read or
write a physical address it actually is
a virtual address that's translated
by the kernel page table into the
physical address that's equal
to the virtual address it was issued so
it's like super convenient in the kernel
once you're using the kernel page table
because the kernel has all these direct
mappings
but until we've set up the current
until the trap machinery has switched to
the kernel page table
none of those mappings are available so
until the
kernel trap code is switched to the
kernel page table we're still using the
user page table which has none of these
convenient mappings
for physical addresses
okay
can i ask a question please um
so um um
i don't know this is maybe not exactly
relevant to what was just said but
um the read and write system calls right
like those
are pretty expensive compared to just a
memory
store because you have to actually
switch modes and go back and forth
would it be possible to just like
instead of when when you open a file
instead of getting back a file
descriptor that you call with the system
call
to get a page table mapping
and then you would just write to a
certain address
that's just mapped to the device and you
can set up the restrictions so that
the the program can only write to a
device to like a
file descriptor that it's allowed to
which is allowed to through the virtual
page
table mapping instead of jumping to the
kernel and back
yeah that's a good observation and
indeed uh
many operating systems provide this
what's called memory mapped file access
where
indeed you map pages that correspond to
the file contents
into the into your virtual into the user
virtual address space so you can read or
write them
directly through memory in fact you'll
be implementing a version of this
in the map lab in a couple of weeks
and indeed as you apply it's a good deal
faster
for many programs than calling a medium
right
okay
i'm gonna switch to the gdb world
all right at this point everybody should
uh
see my screen share
we're going to watch an xv system call
the write
the shells right of its initial prompt
make its way through the system you can
see
the user code that initiates this in
sh.c
and i'm showing that here it's just
making the right system call
with this dollar sign prompt um let me
fire up
gdb
excellent so what actually happens when
user
code when the shell calls right right is
just a
it's a library function that's part of
the
that's linked into the shell and you can
see the source for it in
[Music]
usys.s
so it's this couple of instructions here
is the implementation of the write
function
that the shell is actually calling and
this is a very short function all it's
doing is loading into a7
a number cis write which is just
symbolically defined to be 16 that tells
the kernel
i want to run the 16th system call which
happens to be right
and then this little function uses the
e-call instruction
which is what actually gets the code
into the kernel the kernel
does its thing um and then when the
kernel is finally done it returns
back into user space to execute the
instruction after the e-call
which is that rhett that returns back to
the shell
returns from that right library function
back into the shell
so what i'd like to do in order to show
the system call part of this
i'm going to start by putting a break
point on that
e-call instruction and
we need to know its address of course
but we can find that out by looking in
sh.asm which the
xp6 compilation process produces um and
an
xbsh.asm there's a assembly code with
addresses
of the um the instructions
for the shell so i'm going to put a
breakpoint on the e
call instruction which is it d address
de6
excellent now i'm going to actually
start xc6 running
and i'm hoping to have the system break
in the shell just before executing ecall
all right excellent um we're now you can
see from gdb we're about to
uh we're about to execute that e call
let's just check that we are where we
think we are
let's print we can print the program
counter this is 0x to e6 just what we
asked for
we can also print the all 32 registers
and some of these values whatever we
don't know we don't care what they
are but a0 a1 and a2 are the three
arguments that the shell passed
right so those arguments are file
descriptor two
in a zero um the pointer to the buffer
of characters that the shell wants to
write in a1
and the number of characters it wants to
write in a2
and we can convince ourselves that we're
looking at the code we think we're
looking at
by actually printing out
the bytes in that buffer that the
shuttle wants to write and indeed it's a
dollar sign
and a space so um
we're at the system call that we we hope
to be at
one thing to notice is that the program
counter and the stack point are both at
low addresses
address is quite close to zero and that
um
just reinforces our belief that we're
still executing
in user and the user address space where
all the addresses are quite small once
we get into the kernel you see the
addresses are
the kernels actually loaded much much
higher in memory
okay we the point of the system call is
to
switch around a lot of state one of the
most important pieces of state
that has to get switched and that we
have to live with before it's switched
is the current page table of course we
can look at
uh sat p
um but all we get there is the address
in physical memory the page table
doesn't actually tell us much about what
the mappings are
what the page table looks like luckily
there's a way in qmu to ask it to print
the current page table
and if i print ctrl a c i get into the
qmu
monitor or console and if i then type
info mam
it'll print the complete page table
now this is a very small page table that
contains only six mappings
of course it's the page table for the
shell shell's a pretty small
program and these six mappings are in
order
the shell's instructions the shell's
data
an invalid page which access the
stack a guard page in case the shuttle
tries to use too much stack space
and we can see it's invalid because it
doesn't have the u flag set
over here in this attribute or flag
column
these are all the pte underscore flags
rw and x are
just control whether a page can be read
or written or executed
the next column is you and that's
whether or not the pteu flag is set and
user code can only get at
pde entries for which the u flag is set
um
i don't know what the next column is i
have to admit and the next column is a
for whether the page table entries have
ever been used and
d for whether or write has ever been
issued for this address
okay so we have this tiny page and the
last two page table entries by the way
are way up
at um enormous virtual addresses
close to the very close to the top of
the virtual address space
and this is these two um as you read
about in the book and we'll hear much
more about are the trap frame page
and now the trampoline page and as you
can see neither of them
has the u-bits set so user code can't
get at either of these
can't use either of these addresses but
once we enter supervisor mode we can get
at these two pages
all right um one thing you notice about
this page table
is there's no mappings for anything in
the kernel you know there's no physical
address mappings there's no mappings for
the kernel's data or the kernel's
instructions or anything else
this is uh except for the last two just
the very last two pages
now this is a page table almost entirely
dedicated to user execution and is not
directly particularly useful for
executing the kernel
all right what's the what's the a
attribute on the
on the page table listing on the top i
believe this means the page table has
ever been
this page table entry has ever been
accessed
uh by code that is
whether it's ever issued an address that
refers to this page table entry
um and the d is whether the program has
ever written
uh ever done a store through this
page table entry and these are bits that
the hardware maintains for the
convenience of the operating system and
operating systems more sophisticated
than
xv6 may need to evict pages
if they're running short on physical
memory they may need to write
some pages of memory to disk and
invalidate the page table entries to
free up the physical memory
and many policies you could imagine a
operating system using to
pick which pages to exist um we'll
consult the a bits to see whether this
page table entry has ever even been used
um and if it hasn't been used or haven't
been used recently then
that's a good candidate for evicting to
disk
and the d tells the kernel that
oh this page has actually been written
since it was read from disk
xp6 doesn't actually use either of these
all right other questions
all right let's execute the um
[Music]
let me just remind us where we are i'm
going to print out the
contents of the right we're in the right
library function
in uh
in the shell and the program counter is
pointing to the e-call instruction we're
about to execute the e-call instruction
we're still in user space but we won't
be for long um
boom i executed the e-call instruction
okay so first question is where are we
after the e-call we can look at the
program counter
we see this now used to be a very low
number de6 now it's a very high number
in fact we look at the the program
counter as a virtual address
like all addresses that instructions use
and we can look in the page table
actually let's just check what the page
table is
just be sure i'm going to ask qmu for
info mam again
it's the very same page table so
nothing's changed there
we'll look up our new current program
counter there
the program counter is at the
right at the beginning of this
trampoline page that's mapped
way up high and in the user memory
that's where we're executing we can see
the instructions that are there
i'm going to use
these are the instructions
the very first instructions that the
kernel executes in supervisor mode at
the beginning
very beginning of the trap and through
some weirdness in gdb we've actually
already executed the first instruction
at the very beginning of this page
and we're about to execute the second
instruction
we can look at the registers
i don't know if you remember these
register values but nothing has changed
here these are exactly the same register
contents that the user program has
had so these are all full of user values
for many of them
or all of them for all we know they're
the only locations these value exists so
we have to be very careful that we can't
actually use
any registers at this point without
first saving those registers somewhere
so we can restore them
because if the kernel was to use any of
these registers at this point it would
overwrite whatever that user value is
and then if we try to resume the user
program we wouldn't be able to set up
its registers with the correct values
and the
user program would just do something
totally wrong
um a question yes could you return to
the
instructions panel that you had before
i'm wondering what the crrw
instruction is doing
the csr rw okay we'll talk about this uh
in in a few minutes
um but the answer to your question is
that instruction swaps
a0 with the contents of the special
scratch register um and so in
yeah okay and this is like super
important
and basically answers the question how
can the
this kernel trap code do anything if it
can't use any registers
the answer to that question is it exit
really has to execute this
csrw a0 scratch instruction
that simultaneously saves a0 in scratch
and happens to load scratch into a0
so now the kernel can use a0 for
whatever it wants to
after this instruction
okay thanks yeah okay so
we're currently this address this three
ffff000
um this last page is the trampoline page
and we're currently executing
in the trampoline page which contains
the very first instructions
of the kernel's trap handling code
ecall doesn't switch page tables that's
a very important thing about ecall and
what that means is that
these very first instructions have to be
present in every user page table
because since z-call doesn't switch page
tables we need to be executing the first
bit of the kernel
somewhere in the user page table and
it's this trampoline page
which the kernel carefully maps into
every user page table
that gives the kernel a place to execute
at the very beginning of a trap when
we're still using the user page table
and the way this is controlled
is through the st vec register this is
another privileged
register only readable by the writable
by the supervisor
and the kernel before it entered user
space set up the st vec
to point to the place where the colonel
wanted traps to go
and so as you can see the kernel has
previously set up this st deck
to this three ffff000 address which is
the beginning of the trampoline page
and it's this st vec register that its
contents is the reason why after the
e-call
we ended up executing at this particular
place um
and finally i just want to remind you
that even though the trampoline and trap
frame pages are mapped into the user
page table user address space
the user code cannot write them
because the pdes for them don't have the
pteu flag so they're protected
against user code and that's why this
trick is
part of the reason why this trick is
safe
um i've been sort of telling you and
assuming that we're in supervisor mode
i don't know any way of finding out what
mode the machine is in
directly but i do observe that the
program counter is currently executing
in a page the trampoline page
that doesn't have a pdeu flag set
and that can only happen without a crash
if we are in supervisor mode so i
deduce from the lack of a crash um and
the
value of the program calendar that we
must be in supervisor mode
how we got here of course uh is through
ecall ecall really just changes three
things
um first e call changes mode from user
to supervisor
second ecall saves the program counter
register in the sepc register so we can
see the effect of that
print the program register program
counter it's certainly no longer the
user program counter
even though all the other registers were
it's this value copied from sdvac
and we can also print uh the saved
um it's the supervisor exception program
counter is what that stands for
but this is where ecall saves the user
pro prime counter
and that has the familiar value de6
which is
the address in user space of the e-call
instruction
so we got that one register at least
saved away by e-call
and the final thing that e-call does the
third thing it does is jump
to the instruction that s t vic points
to
[Music]
all right um so what needs to happen now
ecal has done a little bit of work for
us but
it turns out we're nowhere near ready to
actually execute ordinary c code in the
kernel
what has to happen now is we need to
save the 32 user register contents
so we can later restore them and when we
want to resume the user code
now we need to switch to the kernel page
table because currently we're using the
user page table
we need to create a stack or find a
stack and set the stack point of
register to point to the
kernel stack so we can run c code which
requires the stack
and then we need to actually jump to
some sensible place
in the c code in the kernel now as an
aside
you know e-call didn't do any of these
things for us um
you know but you could have we the
hardware could have defined e-call to do
much more
many more of these steps for us instead
of leaving them to software and as
we'll see the doing the software is not
particularly straightforward
um so you should ask yourself why the
ecall doesn't do more of the work
of getting from user space into the
kernel and why doesn't it
save their user registers or switch
page table pointers to point to the
kernel page table or
automatically set the stack pointer to
point to the kernel stack
or jump right to kernel c code geez
rather than having to go through all
this
complicated assembly code
and there's actually been machines that
have done all of these things
in hardware during system calls
the risk five doesn't do any of them
numbers five really the attitude they've
taken is that ecall
does the absolute minimum that's
required that it could possibly do and
leave everything else up to software
and the reason for this is because the
risk 5 designers want to allow maximum
flexibility
to the software the operating system
programmers to design the
program operating system however they
like
and so you can imagine ways xv6 really
doesn't use this freedom
but other operating systems do so some
examples of
things that are kind of enabled for the
software to do
because e-call is so simple
maybe some operating systems can execute
some
traps some system calls without
switching page tables
the switching page page table is
expensive if vcall forces you to do it
that rules out the possibility of very
streamlined
implementations for some system calls
that don't switch page tables
some operating systems map both user and
kernel
virtual addresses into a single page
table and use the same page table for
both user and kernel and therefore don't
even have to switch page
tables ever when transitioning between
user and kernel
and for them also if you call switch
page tables that would just be a waste
and slow things down maybe in some
circumstances
system calls for example some registers
don't have to be saved
and which ones have to be saved or not
sort of depends on the software the
language and the compiler but
you might be able to save a lot of time
by saving fewer than 32 registers so you
don't want equal to kind of force you
you don't necessarily want equal to
force you to save all the registers
and finally maybe no stack at all is
required for some simple system calls so
again for operating systems that care a
lot about performance it's good that
ecall doesn't force
any particular stack policy on you
and again there's many clever uh
hardware software schemes for very
streamlined high performance
system calls and traps just because the
performance of this stuff is
like super important and people worry
about it a lot
okay so back to xv6 and risk five
um the first thing we need to do is save
some registers we
can do hardly anything on the risk 5
without a few
registers without being able to use
register so what are our options for
saving user registers
in on some other machine we might be
able to just write the contents of the
32 registers somewhere convenient in
physical memory
we can't actually really do that on the
risk 5 because
supervisor code isn't allowed to
directly access physical memory we can
only use what's in the page table
there's not much in the page table
another possibility that xv6 doesn't do
is simply setting the sat p to uh to the
kernel page table right and then we
could
use all the kernel mappings and use them
maybe to help us save the user registers
and that'd be legal the supervisor can
certainly change that b
however at this point in the trap
handler namely the beginning
we don't even know the address of the
kernel page table and furthermore the
instruction that you execute
to change sat p require that the address
that you're loading into sap come from a
register
so to even execute the instruction to
change
page tables we need some spare registers
in order to put the new page table
address in those registers so we can
execute
the sat p modifying instruction
all right so we really need to save the
user registers
there's two parts to the solution for
how xv6 does this on the on the risk 5
one is
part of the solution is that xv6
into every user address every user page
table maps this trap
frame page and every process has its own
trap frame page
um and the crafting free page
actually contains some interesting a
bunch of different kinds of data but
at this point the most important data it
contains is 32 slots
empty slots in memory in which to save
the 32 registers
so the good news right now in the trap
handling code is we have a mapping we're
guaranteed to have a mapping
set up by the kernel previously in the
user page table
that points to a place where that's
prepared for us to save this processes
user registers
and it's here it's three it's always
three f f
e zero zero zero virtual address
and if you want to see what's there
actually in that trap frame it's
what xv6 puts there is defined in
proc.h and struck frat frame which is
right here so you can see
um what's supposed to go in each slot
and there's a 32 slots you know named ra
sb gp whatever which are places to save
registers there's also these five things
at the beginning
which we'll see will come in handy very
soon which are values
that the colonel previously placed in
these slots in the trap frame
like for example this very first slot in
the trap frame contains a pointer to the
kernel page table
and this will be the value that we're
about we're very soon gonna
uh the trap handling code is gonna load
into sat p
okay so half the answer to how to say
the registers is that
the kernel has conveniently mapped this
trap frame
into every user page table the other is
this uh instruction this scratch
register which we
uh mentioned before um so there's the
special scratch register
provided by risk 5 for exactly the
purpose we're about to use it for
the kernel when it before goes into user
space puts a pointer there to the trap
frame basically just point
puts into sat p this
this address um just for the convenience
of the trap handling code
more importantly though there's an
instruction on the risk 5 that it's
going to allow us to swap
any register and that's scratch which
will save that register as well as
load the value of s scratch into
whatever register we specified
as you can see if i look at the
trampoline code
we're right at the beginning of the
trampoline code here
the very first thing it does is this
csrw
instruction this is the source in this
window over in this window we can
actually see what gdb sees in the kernel
and we've actually just executed this
swap instruction
and i swapped a0 with scratch in order
to see what it did let's print out
a0 a0 is now this
three fffe00 value which is a pointer
which is the virtual address of the trap
frame which used to be in s scratch but
we just swapped it
and then we can print out what's in s
scratch
and it's 2 which is the old value of the
a0 register of course a0 held the first
argument to the right function which is
file descriptor 2 which
you know is what the shell pass so we
saved away a0
and we have a pointer to the trap frame
and it turns out now that we're well on
our way to be able to save the registers
in fact that's what the very next um
30 odd instructions do in this
trampoline code
it just systematically executes these sd
instructions you just save
64-bit store instructions to store every
single register
to a different offset in the trap frame
a0
if you recall now contains after the
swap contains a pointer to the
trap frame that is contains the
virtual address of this page and we're
just storing
each register at a different offset in
the track frame
all these stores are a bit boring so i
think i'm going to skip over them
um
[Music]
and let me set a breakpoint a little
farther on
professor question yes how did the
address of the trap frame end up in s
scratch when we swapped it with a0
okay before the kernel
before it previously transitioned to
user space
set s scratch to be equal to
three f f e zero zero zero the virtual
address of the trap frame
so all the time when we were executing
in user space in the shell s scratch had
this pointer to the trap frame
and then the shell executes uh
ecall which jumps to the beginning of
the trampoline and the very first
instruction in the trampoline
is this csr rw instruction which swaps
a0 into scratch
and so now the old value of the scratch
namely the point of the trap frame is
now in a0
does that answer your question
as i guess i'm wondering where in the i
look does this happen
during the allocation of the process
like where does the scratch register
live
where does this as well the scratch
order itself lives
on the cpu it's a special register in
the cpu
where and the colonel sets it um
well uh
it's a little bit involved the actual
place where it's set or what i'm now
showing you on the right here
is um the code that the kernel x
the last two instructions that the
kernel executes
while returning a user space and what's
happening is that
the very last thing it does after the
kernel restores
all the user registers and is you know
just about ready to return to user space
it actually does another one of these
swaps the kernel has set up a0 to be
equal to the trap frame
and s scratch still holds the saved user
a0 so the kernel does this swap which
ends up with scratch having a pointer to
the trap frame and a0 having the saved
user a0 and then this s rep returns
to user space so you may wonder how a0
ever got to have the value of the uh
the address of the trap frame answer
that question
is that um
we're now looking in trap.c
at this last c function to run
on the way out to user space
and the last thing the c function does
is calls this function here
whatever this fn is and the arguments it
passes
are the trap frame and the user
page table and so in c code when you
call a function the first argument goes
into
a zero that's basically y why a0
held a pointer to the trap frame and
this function its value is set up here
to be
in that trampoline page towards the end
that code i showed you
this code is that uh
is that a good answer yes thanks
i'm sorry i also was confused about that
i was
not sure so when you start when you
start your process
and it's it's good and running and then
at some point it doesn't
equal i guess in some or something and
then
when did you call this return function
because
it should have been called before the
call
but it didn't return from you didn't
return before
i i don't know i don't understand what
you call the either trafford
okay well maybe one answer to this
question is that
the kernel always or the the machine
boots up in the kernel
so so when the machine starts it's in
the kernel anytime
the only way to get into user space
you know the very first time or when
returning from a system call
is in fact to execute this s-red
instruction
that that this escrow instruction is the
way that the risk find
five defines to transition from
supervisor mode
into user mode and so
before any user code ever executes the
kernel
executes the code i'm showing you here
in these these two editor buffers
that set up all kinds of things like
scratch and
st back
okay i see thank you you're welcome
oh i have a question i'm not sure if we
touched on this or if i'm like you know
i missed it but
uh when we called the e-call instruction
in the assembly code
uh what triggers the trampoline code to
start like
is it the switch of the um cpu mode from
supervisor
i'm sorry from user supervisor is it
something else
okay um so the code we're executing is
this e-call
the shell executes it in user space and
e-call does a couple things
the e-call instruction sets the mode to
supervisor
and the e-call instruction
saves the program counter and epc and
the e-call instruction sets the program
counter equal to
the control register called st vac so
and that seebeck is one of the many
things which the kernel sets up before
entering user space
and so here's sdvac scpec is just the
kernel set it
to the beginning of the trampoline page
that is
this address here so that when e-call
happens e-call just
copies s-t-vec into the program counter
and continues but now
and the program counter is executing
this address in the trampoline page
that clarifies it thank you okay
i also have a question um
why so some of the registers that are
saved
in the trap frame should not um
are also registers that um
the user program had access to
why why why did we
need to um
use a new
region in memory and not use the program
stack
okay um well there's maybe two questions
here one is
maybe why do we have to save the
registers at all
the the reason why the kernel has to
save the registers is that the kernel
is about to run c code that overwrites
those registers
um and if we ever want to resume the
user code correctly we need to resume it
with its registers
having their original values that you
know as of when the e call
was executed so we have to save all the
registers
in the trap frame so that later on we
can restore
all of their values just before resuming
the user code
maybe the other half of your question is
how come they're saved in the crap frame
and not on the user stack
um the answer to that is that we're not
sure the user program even has a stack
there are certainly programming
languages that don't have a stack
and the stack pointer doesn't point to
anything in particular or might be have
value zero
there's also programming languages that
yeah they have a stack but it's in like
a format that's
you know some weird format that the
kernel doesn't understand
uh maybe because the programming
language allocates its stack in small
blocks
uh from the heap and the programming
language runtime understands how to
you know use these small blocks of
memory as a stack but
you know the kernel has no idea
so we if we want to be able to run sort
of arbitrary user programs written in
lots of different languages
the kernel can't make any assumptions
about
what parts of user memory it's allowed
exists or valid or it's allowed to read
or write
and so the kernel has to be sort of
self-contained in saving and destroying
the registers
that's why the kernel saves this stuff
in its own
memory in the trap frame rather than in
user memory
okay
okay anything else
okay we're still right at the beginning
of um
the code in trampoline
um this code is unfortunately we refer
to it both
as uservac um and as the trampoline code
we barely started executing it i think i
just set a breakpoint
um in this code um
after all the registers have been saved
i think i set a
uh breakpoint of this instruction um so
we'll continue executing
skip over all these saves of all the
user registers the crap frame
okay and now we're executing this load
instruction this load instruction
is loading into the stack pointer
register
and what it's loading is the value is
the eighth slot
in the block of memory pointed to by a0
we remember a0 points this the trap
frame
to this uh virtual address you know the
second to last page
and the format of the trap page of the
trap frame here's the form of the trap
name
we've conveniently labeled each field
with its
offset in bytes so that means that load
in the
eighth starting at the eighth byte of
the trap frame means we're loading
the kernel stack pointer and the one of
the things the kernel sets up
before entering user space is it sets
this slot in the trap frame
to be equal to this processes
uh kernel stack so what this instruction
here is doing is
initializing the stack pointer to point
to the top
of this processes kernel stack which is
part of what you need to do in order to
to run user code
all right so what's left or within a few
instructions of getting to the end of
this trampoline code
um we loaded the stack pointer
so maybe i can print the stack pointer
for you let's see
yeah this is um
uh all right well this is the kernels
this process is kernel stack it's up in
high memory because xv6
um treats kernel sex especially so that
you can put a guard page
under each kernel stack okay so this
load into tp
it turns out that because there's no
direct way in risk five to figure out
what core
which of the multiple cores you're
running on
xv6 actually keeps the core number
called the heart id in the tp register
and this is used in a bunch of places in
the kernel for example
it's part of the machinery for kernel
code to figure out what process
is currently running on that core
okay and if we execute this hopefully uh
tp we're running on core zero and that
makes sense because i've configured
qmu to only give one core to xv6 so we
are indeed running on core zero
this next thing uh is loading the
address
of um well actually the
the load into t0
um i think loaded a
pointer to the first c
function that we're going to execute
which is user trap so we use that in a
few instructions to just
jump um to the user trap c function
this load into t1 here is loading the
address of the
kernel page table so we can print
so we're about to switch page tables
turns out the uh
this thing in t1 is not actually
literally the address of the kernel page
table it's the thing you need to put
into sat p
um which is a has the address of the
kernel page table but shifted around
with some extra flag bit set but as soon
as the csrw
instruction executes we'll switch page
tables from the user page table to the
kernel page table
and let me just reinforce that by
looking at the current page table
right now we're still executing with
this very small
user page table and run step by to
execute
the load into sat p
and we'll look again at the kernel page
and now we're in a completely different
page table right this is the kernel page
table
and you can see all these different
regions of memory and device control
registers and whatnot that the uh
kernel sets up in its own uh big kernel
page date
so we've successfully switched page
tables and now the kernel page tables
and
so we're like in pretty good shape at
this point because we have a stack
um we have the kernel page table we can
read my kernel data we're really
pretty much ready to execute c code in
the kernel
one puzzle though is how come
we didn't just crash after all we were
executing somewhere in memory
and the program counter holds a virtual
address if we
switch page tables why doesn't that
um just cause some random garbage or
nothing at all
uh to be mapped in the new page table
under foot where we were executing
and we're not crashing here actually
executing these instructions
um any guesses what's going on
i think it's because oh sorry
um because we're still in the trampoline
code and the trampoline
is mapped at the same virtual address
both in
user and kernel that's absolutely
correct
and so you i don't know if you remember
what was mapped here in the user page
table
but this mapping here at the end of the
kernel page table is exactly the same
mapping in the same place
as the trampoline mapping at the end of
the user page table
all the other mappings are different but
this mapping is the same this is the
mapping that holds the instructions we
were executing and because it didn't
change when we switch page tables
we actually continue executing and we're
still executing the same sequence of
instructions
and not crashing
and so that's the sort of special thing
about the trampoline page it's
it's mapped both into user
page tables and into the kernel page
table
and the reason it's called a trampoline
page is because you sort of
bounce on it on the way from user space
to kernel space
and with the next instruction this jr
we're about to bounce
right out of the trampoline um into
kernel c
code and to see where we're going jr is
just like
jump to a subroutine this operating is
pointed to by register t0 print t0 to
see where we're going
uh maybe we'll print some instructions
there
okay so these are the instructions we're
about to jump to they're in the
the beginning of the function called
user trap
user trap is just a c function
defined in trap dot c
here's user trap now we're about we're
about to jump from assembly code to user
trap with a stack
with a kernel page table uh let me
actually do the
execute the instruction and now i'm
going to turn on
[Music]
um turn on displaying of c
code and gdb now that we're executing c
code
okay so now we're in a much more sane
world we're just executing c code
should be a little bit easier to
understand and there's
you know we'll still spend some time
reading and writing various interesting
control registers but um
the environment is hopefully a good deal
less mysterious than
it was in the track frame all right
any function any any questions at this
point
um i have a question why didn't we see
with the gdb
um what equal does
i i maybe i missed it but um i
think we jumped directly into the
trampoline
he called ecall did jump
what ecall does is
just switch just changes the mode bit to
be supervisor
and equals sets the
program counter register to be equal to
the whatever happens
whatever the kernel happened to store in
st back
kernel stored this value i just printed
3dff00 which is
the beginning of the trampoline page the
kernel stores
this number in st vac before entering
user space
so where ecall goes that is where it
says the program
counter to is st vac which is the
beginning of the trampoline page
does that answer your question
yes i think so okay
okay so now we're in uh when user trap
user tribe is entered actually just like
the trampoline page and
just like the trampoline page for a
number of different kinds of traps
there's system calls
there's exceptions like dividing by zero
or using a unmapped virtual address
and there's a device interrupts and they
all come here and so
user trap sort of saves and restores
hardware state but it also needs to
look at the state at the cause of the of
the trap
to figure out what to do with it um
and so we're gonna see both things as we
execute along in user trap
let me just um
run stuff in user trap let's see
the first thing it does here is that it
changes that s
t back register um it turns out that the
the way xv6 handles traps is different
depending on whether they come from user
space or from the kernel
we've only been talking about what
happens if a trap occurs from user space
there's a quite different sequence of
events
for traps that come from the kernel that
occur while in the kernel because after
all for example
the kernel is already using the kernel
page table
um you know if a trap occurs while
you're in the kernel you already have
the kernel page tables there's a whole
bunch of stuff that doesn't have to
happen
if the trap occurred while in the kernel
so before getting much further in the
kernel code we change
sd vac to point to this kernel vect
which is the kernel
trap handler rather than the user trap
handler
we need to for various reasons we need
to figure out what process we're running
we do that by calling this myproc
function and my proc actually looks at
an array
indexed by the current core number the
heart id
which you remember we put in tp
that's how myproduct figures out what
process is currently running
we need to save that saved user program
counter it's still sitting there
in an sepc
but because one of the things that could
happen while we're in the kernel is that
we
might switch to another process and that
other process might
go into that process user space and that
other process might make a system call
which causes
scpc to be overwritten we have to save
our
sepc in um some memory associated with
this process
so it doesn't get overwritten and it
gets you know we use this trap frame
to save epc as well as lots of other
stuff
and anyway that's what this current line
of code is doing
the next thing that happens we need to
figure out
why we came here the s cause the risk
five s cause register
has a different number depending on why
this trap occurred
you know uh some kind of exception or
versus system call versus device
interrupt
value eight means we're here we took a
trap because of a system call
and hopefully indeed this calls us eight
it does have eight because
we're here because of a system call um
so we're gonna execute this
this if statement um
first thing is if some other process has
killed this process we don't want to
continue but
that's not the case for our shell um
it turns out that the risk 5 the program
counter that gets stored in sepc
is the address of the instruction that
caused the trap
but when we resume we want to resume at
the next instruction
after the e-call and so therefore we
this
code for system calls which need to
return
we add four to the saved user program
counter so that we
resume on the next instruction and don't
just re-execute
the e-call
all right next it turns out that xv6
enables interrupts while it's handling
system calls just so that interrupts
can be served faster some system calls
take a lot of time
[Music]
uh interrupts are always turned off by
the risc-v
trap hardware um and so we have to
explicitly
turn them back on at this point um and
the next thing that happens
is we call this syscall function the job
of syscall i'll just enter it
um it's defined in
just called.c here we are
what it does is it looks up the system
call number in this um
[Music]
big table of system calls at the top of
the page
um if you remember the shells write
function
set register a7 to be the system call
number namely
16 for write so what cisco does is it
retrieves the saved a7
that was saved away in the trap fame by
the trampoline code
and it uses that to index into this
table of
pointers to functions that implement
each system call
so we're going to fish this number
i'm going to print num now that's the
save d7 indeed it's 16
the same 16 that the shell originally
put there
um the system call
code indexes into that syscalls table we
can find out what function
come it's got out of the system call
table
uh by stepping into it right now we're
in write or insist write
so isn't this
file.c this write is the
kernel implementation of the write
system call
i'm not going to go into this it's like
fairly complicated what happens from
here on
in and the implementation of the system
call for this lecture i'm only really
interested in getting into and out of
the kernel
um so i'm going to
um step over
the actual implementation system call
one thing an interesting thing to note
is that
the system calls need to find their
arguments so you know remember the
arguments to write or
two and a buffer pointer and another two
and the way that the
system called code gets at them is just
looking at this um
well looking in the trap frame
so just like we could look in the trap
frame for a7 we can look for a0
and that's the first argument we look at
a1 that's that buffer pointer we can
look at a2 that's the second argument
the number of
bytes to write okay so the system call
does its job and then
cis write finally returns
and we're going to watch what happens
the reason for this assignment here the
reason why we're assigning
to a0 in the trap frame is that
this system calls all have a return
value
like write returns the number of bytes
written and the convention and for c
code on the risk five is that
return values are placed in register a0
by whatever function you're calling and
so to simulate a return value we just
stick the return value
in a0 in the trap frame and we'll see by
and by that when we return to user space
this a0 slot in the trap frame is
restored back into the actual a0
register
and the shell sees that a0 value as um
as the return value from right and if we
just execute through this and print pro
trap
frame starter we'll see it as value 2
what that means is that right
return value is 2 saying that it
actually wrote two bytes just as
instructed
okay at this point we're back in
trap.c in usertrap um
just after the called assist call so
we're now with this
pierrot which is checking if the func if
the process has been killed because
we don't want to resume executing it's
already been killed but of course
our shell has not been killed skip over
this
and then um user trap calls a separate
function
user trap red in order to set up all the
stuff that i talked about previously
whenever i said
well before entering user space the
kernel does blah blah blah
it's user trap red that's responsible
for
setting all that stuff up
and so we can look at all the different
things it does um
it um it turns interrupts off
they were turned on for the duration of
a system call they're turned off now
because we're about to change the st vec
to point to the user
trap handler whereas while we're in the
kernel it was pointing to the kernel
trap handler
so we turn off interrupts because once
we changed st vector point to the user
trap handler we're still executing in
the kernel
and if an interrupt should occur then it
would go to the user trap handler even
though we're executing in the kernel
and for various detailed reasons um
that would cause the kernel to
malfunction so we turn off interrupts
and they're left off from between the
time or from the very next line where we
set up the s t vec to point to the
trampoline
all the way through the final s red
instruction that returns to user space
it turns out that s red instruction at
the end of the trampoline
um turns interrupts back on so the
interrupts are on when we're executing
in uh
user code even though we just turned
them off the next couple of lines
fill in those trap frame slots that we
saw before that hold various
values that are convenient for the
trampoline code
so the code here stashes away a pointer
to the kernel
page table in the trap frame it stashes
away
a pointer to this processes kernel stack
uh it stashes away in the trap frame
a pointer to the user track function
which is what the trampoline code jumped
to at the very end
and it stashes the way the current core
number
read from the tp register so that the
trampoline code can just restore that
same value because user code may have
disturbed it
all right yes um why didn't we save the
sepc in the trampoline
it could have
uh yeah yeah i mean that that the scpc
could have been
the trampoline code happens not to save
it along with the other registers
we perfectly well could modify the xv6
to save it i mean where it is actually
saved as you
probably remember is just happen to save
it in user trap and c code instead of an
assembly code
in the trampoline code
um i don't think this i can't think of a
good reason to do it one way or the
other
the user registers really have to be
saved in the assembly code
because any c code is entitled for all
we know the compiler generates code
which modifies any
user register so those user registers
are pretty important to save them in
assembly code before entering c
but the epc we could have been saved
earlier or later
okay so we're in user trap red sort of
preparing the trap we prepared the trap
frame with all these values that are
going to be needed
um next time there's a transition from
user space to kernel
next trap
there's a couple things we have to set
up in the s status
control register it turns out this
spp bit in s status
controls weather controls the mode
that s red returns to and by clearing it
we're just saying
oh look next time we execute sret
we want to go to user mode instead of
supervisor mode
and this spie bit controls whether
interrupts will be enabled after we
execute s-red
and you know after we get into user
space and we do want them to be enabled
so i'm going to set that spie bit and
then we're going to write this new
modified status into the actual hardware
status register
it turns out what sret does
you know the sro we're going to execute
right at the end of the trampoline code
what that s red does
is um sets the program counter equal to
the sepc register
so we're now going to set up the sepc
register to have
the saved user program counter
which if you recall we recently saved in
the trap frame that's what's happening
here
if you remember also the trap frame
contain a pointer to
the kernel page table because the
trampoline needs to switch to it
we need to cook up the special bit
pattern that you need to write to satp
that's done here and
i'm sorry we're now preparing a pointer
to the user page table
which we need to switch to on the way
into user space
we're actually going to do that switch
in assembly code because it has to
happen
in the trampoline because only code in
the trampoline is mapped in both user
and kernel space
so we can only really switch page tables
when we're executing on the trampoline
but we're not executing on the
trampoline yet
we're still just in an ordinary c
function so we prepare this pointer
and we're going to pass it to the
assembly code as the second argument in
a1
what this line here doing is just
calculating the address
of where we want to jump to at the end
of the trampoline code and it turns out
that there's a that we where we want to
go is user read user writes the address
of the instructions that'll take us back
to user space
and this little formula works out um
the address and the virtual address and
the trampoline
that corresponds to that user rat
function
um
oops okay so we calculate the address of
that
user at function and then this mess this
next line
call uses this fn
variable as a function pointer and jumps
to that function with these two
arguments in a0 and a1
we can now just go to
trampoline code
in the trampoline code there's um
[Music]
well first we switch to the user page
table so it means actually execute this
and we can see the page tables change
just for chuckles we're still using the
giant kernel page table
um i'm going to run through user trapret
quickly
until we get to the point where it jumps
to the trampoline
all right we're in the trampoline um
these are the instructions so we're
about to start executing the trampoline
code
right here we can now again
let's print the page table it's still
the kernel page table
um the first thing that's going to
happen here though is that the
trampoline code is going to load the
that pointer to the user page table
into the sat p register so we switch
page tables if i type info map now
we now have a much smaller user page
table but luckily
still with the trampoline page map so we
don't crash on the next instruction
the next thing that happens is this um
um i showed you a while ago that the
second to last thing that this sequence
of code does on the way to user space
is swaps s scratch with a zero
so we need to set up s scratch with the
saved user a0 so that when we do that
swap
a0 will end up having the saved user a0
it turns out
a0 is a pointer to the trap frame
because
the c code passed that as the first
argument 112
of a0 is the address of the saved a0
in the track frame so we're going to
load that and then into t0 and then load
that into
scratch at this point we're still
running with the
kernel stuff and all the registers
the next 32 instructions though load out
of the trap frame which
a0 points to load all of the
saved user registers out of the trap
frame
into the actual register so we're like
really close to being able to
the point where we can run user code i'm
going to skip over all these loads
any questions before we uh approach
closer to user space
i have one quick question is the value
in the trap frame a0 now the return
value of that system call that we made
um
yeah yeah the relay zero holds just this
under the trap frame but the after we
execute
the well s
okay the current location of the user
saved
uh yes i was calling it the user saved
a0 but in fact
the system call returns stuff overwrote
it with the return value that we want
the shell to see in a0 so the current
location of that a0 which we overwrote
with 2
as the return value is s scrap so i'm
going to point s scratch and hope that
it's equal to two
it is equal to two um
does that answer your question yes i
think so
okay i'm gonna uh skip over all these
loads
the restore the saved user values out of
the trap frame into the registers
why don't i print out the registers at
this point
um actually gonna
print out the registers i don't know if
these look familiar but they happen to
be
the same set of user registers we saw
way back at the beginning of this
exercise
for example a1 or the stack pointer
holds this small value appropriate for a
user stack low in memory
a1 is that buffer pointer that we passed
to write
2 is that number of bytes a0 however is
the exception is
not a saved user value because it still
has the pointer to our trap frame in it
um but let's look we're about to execute
um we're about to execute is this
csr rwa0 scratch
right at the end of trampoline just
before returning to user space this is
going to swap a0 and scratch
scratch indeed has
ah that's scratch
has two which is going to be the return
value a0
has this kernel pointer and it points to
points to the trap frame but after
executing the csrw
instruction to swap them hopefully we'll
see that
um a0 holds this return value of two
and s
scratch holds a pointer to the trap
frame which is
the second to last page in memory um
and that value is going to stay in
scratch until the user
program does another trap and at that
point the trap handling code that we
talked about before we'll
be able to use that scratch to get at
the trap frame all right we're still
in the kernel but this is our last
instruction in the kernel
and when i execute this s-ret it will uh
switch to user mode um before i do that
let's look at
it'll switch to user mode it'll copy
sepc to the pc because we're still
um
we're still executing with the pc that's
in the trampoline
so esret's gonna switch to user mode
copy scpc
to pc
[Music]
and then resume executing so i'm gonna
run the
sret boom um
now we're back at um
back at address zero x dea which is a
low address
likely to be user memory and it's the
look back at sh.asm and address
xerox dea
is indeed the address of the return
function at the end of write
and
a0 is this return value that was
supposed to be turning
so we're back in user space and we can
about to do the return
back to the shell from the right system
from the right library function that
made the system call
okay any questions
uh sorry can you repeat again what
happens with the
interrupt during s red
what happened with interrupts you said
you are turning them
off but then something else turns them
back on
s-rat um s-red enables interrupts
so this s-ret the very last instruction
that we're executing in supervisor mode
in the kernel
um i forgot to say that just now but as
well as setting the program counter
equal to the
scpc and switching to user mode s
red is going to re-enable interrupts
does that mean you know that's you know
user programs that may run for a long
time it'd be nice to be able to take
disk interrupts or whatever
user programs are running i see thank
you
other questions
okay to uh to wrap up the system calls
sort of look like function calls that
are kind of meant to be thought of a lot
like function calls
but um the user kernel transitions are
much more complex than
than function calls are a lot of the
complexities due to the requirement
for isolation the kernel just can't
trust anything in user space
and also the desire to have simple and
very fast hardware mechanisms so really
xp6 doesn't care that much about
performance but in general operating
system designers and the
cpu designers are very interested in the
sort of speed at which you can do the
efficiency of traps
xp6 does it you know does all these
things in a particular way there's
certainly other ways to do them a few
questions
a few design questions alternatives you
could think about
one is is can you think of ways to make
the
hardware or software aspects redesign
xv6 redesigned the risk five
to make this whole sequence simpler um
or could you think of ways to make the
whole sequence
faster and another sort of set of
questions to keep in the back your head
is whether or not malicious programs
could abuse any of these mechanisms
to break isolation
all right that is all i have to say for
this lecture i'm
happy to take questions
uh sorry i have another question please
um i saw that there is
a um u i e regis
or yeah i think register in status
but we don't use it we just use
s i e and we set it to false in user
space why couldn't we use
the ui gosh
the answer is going to be i don't know
um
[Music]
uh we're sp what we set is s what we
said is
spi we may actually end up setting
um i know nothing about uie i'm going to
guess
let me see i'm going to guess that what
actually happens here
i'm in this code where we're
okay so here we are in user trap red
we're returning or setting
s-p-i-e in the s-status
and i believe the s-red instruction will
copy this s-p-i-e and this is this
previous the name of this is the
supervisor previous interrupt enable
i suspect s copies that bit
into the uh
into whatever controls interrupts in
user mode which is possibly this ui
and s status how's that for a guess
i see thank you