声音检查，大家能听到我说话吗？
Sound check, can everybody hear me?
是的。好的，
Yep, yep. Okay okay,
欢迎收听 6.S081
so welcome to the next lecture
的下一节课，
in the 6.S081, wherever you
无论你在哪里，
are, particular,
我希望西海岸，
I hope that the folks on
佛罗里达和
the west coast or in Florida
阿拉巴马州的人们都还好，
and Alabama do OK, you know, all
那里糟糕的情况会好起来。
the terrible circumstances there.
嗯，那么，
Um, so,
今天的话题是
um, the topic for today,
虚拟内存，
is virtual memory, particularly we're
特别是我们要讲的页表，
going to talk about page tables
我们多次讲到
we'll return to this topic
这个话题，
few times,
有多次关于
there will be multiple
这个的讲座。
[] lectures.
一开始，
Maybe just start off and,
我们会再次开始
you know, get our question and answer
我们的问答环节，
going again,
我想问
I would like to ask you
一些问题，
a little bit,
你对 6.004 或
what do you remember from，
6.033 的讲的
about virtual memory from 6.004
虚拟内存
maybe from 6.033,
有什么印象。
if you're taking that.
我要告诉你们，
I'll tell you, my own sort
我自己对虚拟内存的看法，
of view on virtual memory,
这就是当我
which is when I took it,
第一次了解它的时候，
to first learned about it,
还是个学生的时候，
learned about it as
我认为
a student, I thought it
它很简单，很直接，
was pretty straightforward,
你知道的，
you know how hard could
它能有多难，
it be,
就是一个将虚拟地址
it's a table that maps virtual
映射到物理地址的表。
addresses to physical addresses.
你知道，
You know, maybe a
可能有一点复杂，
little more complicated,
但没有那么复杂。
but you know not that
只有当你实际
complicated, only when you start
用它来编程的时候，
programming with it.
我真的知道了，
I should really learn, virtual
虚拟内存是巧妙的，迷人的，
memory is tricky and fascinating,
而且非常强大。
and very powerful.
所以，
So, hopefully in the
希望在接下来的几节课，
next couple of lectures, in
接下来的几个实验中，
the next couple of labs,
你们能从这个角度
you'll know appreciate
理解虚拟内存。
virtual memory from that perspective.
我们将提问
We will ask a couple
在线的的几个人，
people here are online, you know
关于你对
what do you remember about virtual
6.004 或 6.033
memory from either 6.004 or
虚拟内存的印象是什么。
6.033 taking it.
我要叫几个名字，
Again, I'm just gonna call some
你知道，
names and you know,
分享你的印象。
share your memories. About the
Adela Yang.
抱歉，问题是什么？
Sorry, what's the question? What
你对
do you remember about
6.004 或
virtual memory from maybe 6.004
6.033
or 6.033
的虚拟内存有什么印象？
if you have taken that.
它使用
It uses like, offset to save
偏移量来记录
on like, remembering virtual address
虚拟地址到物理地址的映射。
to physical address mappings.
好的，下一个， Abrams Caldera 。
OK, how about Abrams Caldera.
Abrams ，你在线吗？
Abrams, are you online?
是的，我的印象是
Yeah, my memory is that
它使用，
it uses like,
就像通过
it's a way of one protecting
一种[]表示
the physical hardware by
来保护物理硬件，
kind of [] representation of
然后，
it and then you just
你使用一些
have some virtual address things like,
至少 44 位的虚拟地址，
at least 44 bit, that map
来映射一些物理地址，
some physical address,
这些物理地址
that's usually I think 16
通常是 64 位的。
bits were in fact.
好的，下一个， Bibic Pendant 。
Okay, good, how about Bibic Pendant.
我记得的是，
What I remember was,
你可以让
um, you can have
每个进程有一个
each process has a separate
单独的地址空间。
address space.
还有，
And,
可以使用内存管理单元
the memory management unit or I
或者一些其他技术
mean some other technique can be
来映射，
used to map,
将每个进程
the virtual addresses of the
地址空间的
address space of each of the
虚拟地址转换为
processes to the physical,
物理地址。
physical address.
还有，虚拟地址的
And the virtual address, the
最后几位
lower bits
是相同的，
are kind of the same,
因此，
so that,
映射是以块为单位的，
the the mapping is in blocks,
这有助于提高性能。
which helps with performance.
Wiseley Wu.
是的，
Yeah, I guess what I
我印象最深的是
remember most is that virtual address
虚拟地址允许我们
allows us to,
保护物理地址
yeah, protect physical addresses from
不受每个进程的影响。
each process.
我们可以使用
And we can use some clever
一些巧妙的操作，
manipulation, so that the bits that
这样对应于物理地址的位
correspond to the physical address can
也可以
be used somehow in the virtual
在虚拟地址中使用。
addresses as well.
Wilson Spearmen.
是的，我记得
Yeah, I remember it's really fundamental
这是隔离的基础，
to isolation,
因为每个进程都
because every process can basically pretend
可以假装
that it has its own
它有自己的内存可以使用。
sort of memory to use.
很好，很清楚，
Good good well so clearly,
很棒，
that's awesome,
显然，这里有两个主题，
the clear, two themes here
一个是
correct, one is you know
有某种形式的映射，
there's some form of mapping and
这种映射有助于
the mapping is helpful in sort
实现某种程度的隔离，
of achieving isolation,
这正是我们讨论
this is exactly the reason, we're
虚拟内存隔离的原因。
talking about virtual memory isolation.
因此，
So, what
我们在接下来的
we'll see is that in
几节课中会看到，
the next, in the next couple of lectures,
特别是，当我们开始
in particular, when we start programming
使用虚拟内存编程时，
with virtual memory,
我们会真正深入了解
really get an in-depth understanding
它的力量。
of what its power is.
为了让你理解，
And, so to get a
你知道，
sense, that you know, this is
这是第一节课，
the first lecture and mostly focusing
内容主要集中在虚拟内存的机制上，
on the mechanisms for virtual memory,
稍后我们可以看到，
and then later we can see
如何使用这些机制来实现
how we can use these mechanisms
那些很棒的技巧。
to achieve, you know, cool tricks.
所以
So the topic for today, or
今天的话题或议程是，
agenda for today, the plan
计划分为三部分。
is sort of three part.
首先，
First, I'm going to talk about the
我要谈谈地址空间，
address spaces, as some of you
你们中有些人也提到这个。
mentioning in your.
这正是我们需要的。
Just what we need.
刚才回答问题的时候
Just mentioned just briefly mentioned,
简单提了一下，
in response to the question,
我还要讲一下
I'm going to talk about the
分页硬件。
paging hardware paging hardware.
当然，
And I'm going to focus of
我将重点介绍
course on the paging hardware of
RISC-V 的分页硬件。
the RISC-V.
但是基本上每个处理器，
But basically every processor, modern processor
现代处理器都有
has some form of paging hardware
某种形式的分页硬件。
sort of,
实际上它是
if you will, the
支持虚拟内存的
default mechanism for actually
默认机制。
supporting virtual memory.
然后，
And then,
课程的最后一部分
the last part of
将介绍一些
the lecture is going to
xv6 的
walk through some xv6
虚拟内存代码。
virtual memory code.
还有，内核地址空间和
And, layout of kernel address space and
用户地址空间的布局。
user address spaces.
所以这是主要的计划。
So that's the main plan.
好的，那么
Okay, so,
如果我们回答，
if we answers, you know, []
你所提到的[]，
you mentioned,
回答这个问题，
in response to this question,
你知道，
you know,
有虚拟内存的一个驱动力
one driving reason to have
是因为
virtual memory is because you can
你可以用它来实现隔离，
use it to achieve isolation,
如果页表设置正确，
if you set up the page
并且编程正确，
tables correctly and program them correctly,
那么原则上
then you can in principle
就可以实现强隔离。
achieve strong isolation.
这再次提醒我们，
And so this is to remind us again,
我们想从隔离中
you know what we want with
得到什么，
from isolation,
比如，
let's say, you know a
你知道一张标准图片，
standard picture,
我们有一些用户应用程序，
we have some user applications
比如 shell ，
like shell,
cat ，还有
you know cat, you know, all the util
你在实验一中构建的
things, that you've built in
所有实用工具，
lab one, and we have
我们还有内核，内核在下面，
the kernel, the kernel sitting below,
操作系统在
the operating system sitting in
内核空间里。
kernel space.
你知道，
And you know what we like
我们要做的是
to do is sort of have
把这些应用程序框起来，
you know boxes around these
这样它们
applications, so that they can't
就不会真正相互影响，
really affect each other and similar
类似的，我们希望它们
we want them to be completely
完全独立于内核和操作系统，
independent of the kernel,
这样即使
the operating system, so that if
一个应用程序做了
an application does something either accidentally
一些意外或恶意的事情，
bad or maliciously bad,
也不会
that doesn't really affect the
真正影响操作系统。
operating system.
这就是我们的目标，
So that's our goal and the
今天我们关注的
particular aspect of the problem that
具体方面是
we want to focus on today
内存方面的问题，
is the memory side of things,
所以我们关注的是
so we really want to
内存隔离。
focus on memory isolation.
默认情况下，
And by default,
如果我们什么都不做，
if we don't do anything,
我们就没有内存隔离，
we don't really have memory isolation,
因为如果你想一下，
because if you think about
这有一个 RISC-V 板，
it, there's going to be one
就是我上周给你们
RISC-V board that I showed
展示的那个，
you last week,
它有一个内存，
it has a memory,
一堆 DRAM 芯片，
a bunch of DRAM chips,
在 DRAM 芯片中
and the in the DRAM
存储着
chips, the code for
这些应用程序的代码，
these applications
内存中的
is stored, somewhere in memory
某个地方是内核，文本数据堆栈或其他，
is the kernel, text data stack
如果 shell 正在运行，
everything, somewhere in memory used to
内存中的某个地方是 shell ，
shell if the shell is running,
还有某个地方是 cat 程序。
somewhere in memory the cat program.
所以有一种物理内存，你知道，从零开始，到你知道的大地址，并不取决于我们的机器真正有多少内存，在那个物理内存中，所有这些程序都必须存在。
And so there's one sort of
physical memory,
you know starting from someone
from zero to you know
big big address, no
depending how much memory we
have really have in our
machine and in that physical
memory all these programs must
be present.
是啊，否则你就会知道处理器甚至不能执行他们的指令。
Yeah, otherwise you know the processor
can't even execute their instructions.
这就是风险所在，你清楚地知道这里是什么，让我们说你知道，让我们做一点，你知道，简单化，但让我们说外壳，你知道，对于最小地址0到200,2000到2000，你知道的，你知道的，坐在一个最小的地址0到200,2000到2000之间。
This is what the risk, you
know clearly here is, that let's
say you know let's make a
little bit,
you know simplistic but let's say
the shell,
you know sits for a min
address zero to address 200,
two thousand one thousand to 2000.
假设你知道，你知道，不管什么猫有编程错误，嗯，它加载到，你知道的寄存器a0中。
And let's say you know the
you know whatever cat has a
programming error,
um, it loads,
you know in register a0.
假设加载的千位地址基本上对应于外壳的开始，然后你知道，意外地执行了指令，你知道，$7，a0。
Let's say loads the thousand
address basically corresponding to the
start of the shell and then
you know by accident,
you know, executes the instruction,
you know, $7, a0.
它的作用是，基本上它将值7写到地址1000，所以它会在基本上属于shell的内存映像上乱涂乱画。
Which has the effect of that,
basically it writes the value 7
to the address 1000 and so
it would be scribbling over you
know the basically the memory image,
um that belongs to shell.
因此，我们肯定不会，肯定会打破孤立，是相当不受欢迎的。
And so,
we're certainly not, certain
would break isolation, and be
quite undesirable.
所以我们想要一些东西，从根本上把这些记忆从不同的程序中分离出来，这样就不会发生这样的事情了。
And so we want something that
basically really separates these memories from
the different programs from each other,
so that things like that just
cannot happen.
要做到这一点，一种方法是，嗯，你知道，这是一种通常被称为地址空间的想法。
So one way, to do that,
um is an idea that's you
know typically called address spaces.
基本思想很简单，我们想要做的基本上是给每个应用程序，包括内核，它自己的地址空间。
And the basic idea is straightforward,
what we wanna do is basically
give every application including the kernel,
its own address space.
所以我们可以像使用猫奔跑一样思考这个问题。
And so we can think about
this like we use cat running.
你知道它有一个从0开始的地址空间，你知道做任何最大的值，你知道shell run有一个地址空间，它自己的地址空间，也从地址0开始，嗯，到某个值你知道内核有它自己的地址空间。
You know it has an address
space starting at 0, you know
do whatever maximum value, you know
shell run has an address space, its
own address space,
also starting at address 0,
um, going to some value
you know the kernel has
its own address space.
操作系统有自己的地址空间。
OS has its own
address space.
所以，有一个例子，当我们提到猫的时候，我们回到上一张幻灯片的例子，我们确实是这样做的。
And so,
one example when cat you know
refers to, we go back to
our example of the previous slide
where we did.
嗯，不管7号店到哪家店，你都知道0。
Um, whatever store 7 to, you
know a0.
比方说在0中，1000就有价值。
And let's say in a0,
there's value in 1000.
你知道如果可以执行一条指令，它会写到地址1000，但它是它自己的地址1000，不是的，你知道外壳的1000的地址。
You know if can execute
an instruction,
it will write to the address 1000,
but it is its own
address 1000,
it's not,
you know the address of the
1000 of the shell.
所以基本上，每个程序都有自己的地址空间，有自己的值，这些地址是完全独立的。
So basically, every program runs with
its own address space, has its
own value and those addresses are
completely independent.
嗯，你知道这个不同地址空间的概念，CAT甚至没有能力引用一个地址，那实际上是属于shell的。
Um, you know this notion of
different address spaces,
cat doesn't really have an ability to
even refer to an address, that
actually belongs to the shell.
所以这就是我们想要达到的最终目标，因为它将给我们提供强大的隔离，因为你知道，猫不可能引用任何不属于它自己的其他记忆。这就是我们想要达到的最终目标，因为它将给我们提供强大的隔离，因为你知道，猫不可能引用任何不属于它自己的记忆。
And so that's sort of the
game that were the end goal
that we'd like to achieve, because
it's going to provide us with
strong isolation, because you know it's
just not possible for cat to
refer to any other memory that
is not, you know, its own.
因此，我们现在的目标基本上是解决如何在单个物理内存上多路复用所有这些不同的地址，因为最终，我们只有一堆DRAM芯片。
And so,
our goal now basically
sort of figure out how to
multiplex if you will all these
different address bases on a single
physical memory,
because in the end,
we only have a bunch of
dram chips.
嗯，你知道吗，公羊芯片是用来看记忆的。
Um, were you know, ram
chips were the memories look at.
所以，嗯，所以我计划好了，是的，我在这里。如果你有问题，请便。
And so,
Um, and so I sort of
plan okay,
yeah I'm here. You have
a question,
go ahead.
嗯，所以我想知道，在物理硬件的配置中，只有这么大的空间，而在虚拟内存布局中，还有一个最大的虚拟地址被设计成足够小的虚拟地址。
Um, so I'm wondering,
in the configuration of the
physical hardware,
there's only so much space and
in the virtual memory layout,
there's also a max virtual address
by design is the virtual address
made to be small enough.
不，不一定，您知道虚拟地址空间可能比物理内存大，物理内存可能比虚拟地址空间大，我们很快就会看到这一切是如何发生的，它实际上会拉动各个部分，就像我们将在页表中看到的那样，嗯，这是非常灵活的。
No, not necessarily,
you know the virtual address
space could be bigger than
the physical memory,
the physical memory could be bigger
than the virtual address space
and we'll see in a second
how it all can happen and
it's actually going to pull parts
about, as we'll see with
page tables,
um that's extremely flexible.
那么，有没有可能，就像物理内存耗尽一样。
So, is it, is it
possible that like the physical
memory gets exhausted.
嗯，因为这么多进程使用了所有的虚拟空间，是的，这当然是可能的，我们将在第二部分看到，例如，你知道你有一堆大型应用程序，每个应用程序都有很大的页表，它们分配了很多内存，你知道有些时候内存会用完。
Um, because so many processes use
all their virtual space,
yeah that's certainly possible and we'll
see in the second, how,
for example you know you have
a bunch of big applications that
each have big page tables,
they allocate a lot of memory,
you know some point you run
out of memory.
我明白了，谢谢。那么，有没有人知道这在xv6中有什么用武之地呢？
I see,
thanks. And so where does this
show up xv6, anybody.
你，你确定吗。
You, you sure.
我在SysCall实验室谈到了一点，就是您目前正在做的事情。
Touched on a little bit
in the syscall lab, that
you're currently doing.
分配页面的位置。
Where page is allocated.
或者，您做的是syscall实验室，但是您在syscall实验室的一个部分完成了它，打印了多少空闲内存地址。
or, you do the syscall lab
but you finished it in one
part of the syscall lab,
printing how much free memory address.
卡洛克？是的，卡洛克，对，卡洛克，我有一个长达三页的单子。
Kalloc? Yeah, kalloc, right,
for kalloc, I have some list of
three pages.
如果三页列表在某一时刻为空或用完。
If that list of three pages
it empty or runs out at
some point.
然后，你知道，kalloc将返回一个空指针，希望这个操作能做一些明智的事情，基本上传播回用户应用程序，说，好吧，你知道没有更多的内存给你，或者没有人有更多的内存。
Then, you know, kalloc is going
to return a null pointer and
hopefully the operation does something sensible
that basically propagated back to the
user application saying like well, you
know no more memory for you
or no more memory in total
for nobody.
好的?然后，操作系统只需要做一项工作就可以很好地处理这些情况，这通常意味着将错误消息传播到用户应用程序。
Ok? Then just a job for OS
to handle those cases gracefully where
basically generally means propagating an error
message to user application.
好的，很好。
Okay, good.
那么如何实现这些地址空间，您知道基本上如何在单个物理内存中多路复用所有这些地址空间，最常用的方法和非常灵活的方法是使用页表。
So how do you implement these
address spaces,
you know how basically multiplex
all these address spaces across a
single physical memory and the most
common approach and a very flexible
approach is to use page tables.
嗯，这个想法是，嗯，这是一项艰苦的工作支持，所以这是由处理器或由一个称为内存管理单元的单元在硬件中实现的，所以你应该想到的画面是，你知道，执行指令的CPU，无论是什么，你知道，嗯，我们的存储指令，你知道，你知道，把7美元放到一个间接的0中。
Um the idea is,
um, this is a hard
work support,
so this is implemented in hardware
by the processor or by a
unit called the memory management unit,
so the picture that you should
have your head is, you know
the CPU,
that executes instructions, whatever are,
you know,
um, our store instruction that
was you know putting $7
into a0 indirect.
也执行这些类型的指令，您知道它何时执行它们的STOR指令之一，LOAD指令，任何实际有地址的指令。
Also executes those kind of
instructions and you know when
it executes one of their
stor instruction, load instruction,
whatever anything that actually has
an address.
你现在，那个地址，我们会把它看作一个虚拟地址，所以它不是一个物理地址，而是一个虚拟地址。
You now, that address we're going
to think about it as
a virtual address,
so it's not a physical address,
it's a virtual address.
例如，我们在这里使用的a0中的值，嗯，是的，假设是1000，0x1000数据是一个虚拟地址，虚拟地址基本上是通过所谓的内存管理单元路由的。
And so,
for example the value in a0
that we're using here,
um, yeah, say that's 1000,
0x1000 data is a
virtual address and virtual addresses basically
routed through something what's called
the memory management unit.
嗯，并且存储器管理器单元转换成物理地址。
Um, and the memory manager unit
translates into a physical address.
然后该物理地址实际上被用来索引到存储器中。
And that physical address then was
actually used to index into memory.
并加载或存储需要写入的任何值。
And load whatever value or
store whatever value needs to be
written there.
嗯，所以CPU从CPU的角度来看，它总是发出，一旦MMU使用，它发出的每条指令都启用了我们的虚拟地址。
Um, and so the CPU from
the CPU point of view,
it always issues,
every instruction that issues,
once the MMU use, enabled
our virtual addresses.
为了将这些虚拟地址转换成物理地址，基本上，MMU有一个表。
And to translate these virtual addresses
to physical addresses, basically,
MMU has a table.
你知道，虚拟地址在一边，物理地址在一边，另一边，例如，这里是我们的1000的条目，可能映射到任何，你知道，0x任何你正在虚构的东西，比如某个大的值，在物理内存中的某个地方。
And you know virtual address
on one side, physical address
on one side,
the other side, for example here is
our entry for 1000 and maybe
that maps to whatever,
you know, 0x whatever you're
making something up with like
some big value,
somewhere in physical memory.
所以虚拟地图和物理地图之间的这种映射。
So this mapping between virtual and
physical map.
嗯，相当灵活。
Um, it's quite flexible.
因此，在一侧，我们有物理地址的另一侧的虚拟地址。
And so on one side,
we have the virtual address
of the other side of
the physical addresses.
通常，您知道此映射本身也存储在内存中。
Typically, you know this mapping itself
is also stored in memory.
所以CPU有一些基本上指向的寄存器，它包含存储页表的物理地址。
And so the CPU has some
register that basically points to,
that contains the physical
address of where the page
table is stored.
所以基本上是在页表中的某个地方，或者只是映射存储在物理内存中的某个地方。
So somewhere in basically the page
table or just map somewhere stored
in physical memory.
比方说，你知道，不管怎么说，地址10，基本上就是在RISC-V SATP上调用的这个寄存器。
Let's say, you know,
whatever, address 10,
basically this register which is
called on the RISC-V satp.
您知道存储地址10，因此，CPU可以告诉内存管理单元在哪里查找，您知道，基本上是将虚拟地址转换为物理地址的映射。
You know stores the address 10
and so, that the CPU
can tell the memory managed units
where to find, you know, basically the map
to actually translate virtual to
physical addresses.
然后，基本的想法是给每个应用程序提供它自己的地图。
And then the basic idea
is to give every application
it's own map.
所以猫会有，它是地图。哎呀。
So cat is going
to have,
it's map. Oops.
所以每一张地图都是自己的..。
So every map, it's own...
是的，[大本钟]，去吧。
Yeah, [Big Ben], go ahead.
嗯，那么MMU，您说它不一定存储地图。
Um, so the MMU,
you said it doesn't necessarily store
the mapping.
所以它只是，只是做翻译，就像它会读取内存并进行翻译一样，但不一定存储映射。
So does it just,
just do the translation like
it will read the memory
and do the translation,
but not necessarily
store the mappings.
这正是你应该有头脑的照片。
That's exactly the right picture that
you should have your head.
但是每张地图，好的，所以地图本身存储了记忆，MMU基本上只是走进或者看着地图，我们很快就会看到，你知道，这张地图比我在这里画的稍微复杂一些。
But every map, okay, so the
map itself stored memory,
the MMU just basically walks or
looks into the map and we'll
see in a second, you know,
this map is slightly more complicated
than I used draw here.
嗯，所以每个应用都有自己的，自己的地图。
Um, so every app has
its own, its own map.
对，这个映射基本上定义了它的地址空间。
Right, and that map basically defines
its address space.
因此，当使用CPU时或当操作系统将CPU从一个应用程序切换到另一个应用程序时，它还切换该SATP寄存器的内容以存储适当进程的映射的根。
And so when with the CPU or
when the operating system switches the
CPU from one process from one
application to another application,
it also switches the content
of this
satp register to store
the root of the map of
the appropriate process.
因此，通过这种方式，基本上您知道在CPU上运行多个应用程序，每次我们从一个应用程序切换到下一个应用程序时，我们还会切换SATP寄存器以指向该应用程序的适当映射。
And so in that way,
basically you know multiple applications to
run on the
CPU, every time we switch
between from one application to the
next application,
we also switch the satp
register to point to the appropriate
map for that application.
通过这种方式，基本上，您所知道的cat虚拟地址的转换方式与shell的虚拟地址的转换方式不同，因为您知道每个虚拟地址都有自己的映射。
And in that way,
basically, virtual addresses you know
for cat are translated differently,
than the virtual addresses for the
shell, because you know each one
of them has their own map.
这事儿可以理解。
That makes sense.
好的，我们也是，这是基本的计划，到目前为止，我画的或者将要解释的方式，是相当幼稚的，也是不合理的。
Okay, so do we, this is the
basic plan and the way I've
drawn or gonna explain it so
far it's pretty naive,
and unreasonable.
嗯，是的，大卫，说吧。
Um, yeah, David, go ahead.
很抱歉，您说的SATP寄存器为进程修改了a，我猜每个进程的FOR SATP寄存器的值都是由内核存储的。
I'm sorry,
So, the you said the
satp register gets modified a
for the process, I am guessing
the value of for
satp register for each process
is stored by the kernel.
是的，内核正在写入SATP寄存器，实际上写入或读取特定写入SATP寄存器是特权指令。
Yes yes,
the kernel is writing satp register,
in fact writing or reading a
particular writing the satp register is
a privilege instruction.
因此，用户应用程序不能只更新页面映射寄存器，然后说我现在要使用此页面映射运行。
So user application cannot just
update the page map register, and
say like I want to run
with this page map now.
因为，那会违反孤立。
Because,
that would violate isolation.
所以它只是内核，只有内核模式下的代码才能真正更新它。
So it's only the kernel, only
code in kernel mode can actually
update it.
我明白了。
I see.
好的，正如我所说的，这张图片相当幼稚，你知道有一件事我没有真正说过这张地图是如何工作的。
Okay, so as I said this
picture is pretty naive,
you know one thing I
haven't really said anything about how
this actually map works.
嗯，而且，你知道，我画出来的方式似乎表明，基本上每个虚拟地址，你在地图上都有一个条目。
Um, and,
you know the way I've
drawn out seems to indicate a
basically for every virtual address,
you have an entry in
the map.
嗯，如果你这么做了，那在RISC-V上会有多大的影响呢？
Um, and if you do that,
how big would that be
on RISC-V.
RISC-V上原则上有多少地址，或者有多大，有多少地址进入寄存器存储。
How many addresses are there on
the RISC-V in principle, or
how big, how many addresses go
to registers store.
寄存器是64位宽，那么有多少个地址呢？
Registers are 64 bit wide,
so how many addresses.
我知道，问这些问题是对你智力的侮辱。
I know, so insulting your
intelligence by asking these questions about.
我们在聊天中有一些答案，比如两个对64个。
We have some answers in the
chat, like two to the 64.
我没看到聊天内容，抱歉，嗯，是的，2比64。让我们看看我是否真的能把芯片弹出来，这样我就能看到它了。
I didn't see the chat,
sorry, um,
yeah, two to 64. Lets see
if I can actually pop off
the chip,
so I could see it.
是的，2比64，谢谢。
Yeah, two to 64,
thank you.
好的，那么这张桌子会很大。
Alright, so this table would
be gigantic.
嗯，事实上，我们知道光有桌子就会消耗所有的内存，所以这似乎是合理的。
Um, in fact we know
all memory would be consumed
by just having the table
so that seems reasonable.
嗯，所以事实上你知道事情不是这样的。
Um, and so in fact you
know that's not how things work.
嗯，实际上我要分两个步骤，来了解它在RISC-V中的实际工作原理。
Um, in fact I'm going to
go in two steps, to actually, how
it actually works in RISC-V.
第一步不是按地址玩游戏，而是按页面玩。
Step one is don't play
the game per address,
but do per page.
所以你一次翻译一页，RISC-V上的一页a是4千字节。
So you translate a page at
a time and a page a
on RISC-V is 4 kilobytes.
它是一个4,4096字节。
Which is a four, and
4096 bytes.
这很常见，您知道，几乎所有处理器都使用大约4千字节的页面大小，或者支持4千字节的页面大小。
This is pretty common,
almost all processors, you know, use
roughly page size 4 kilobytes, or support
page size 4 kilobytes.
现在再说一遍，转换的工作原理略有不同，因此，如果在这里，我们就有了虚拟地址。
And so now again, translation works
slightly differently,
so if here, we have our
virtual address.
令人惊讶的是，我们将其一分为二，一个索引和一个偏移量。
Amazingly, we split it in two pieces,
an index and
an offset.
所以偏移量基本上就是页面中的字节。
And so the offset is basically
the byte within the page.
因此，当我们这样做时，当MMU进行转换时，它会获取索引，索引到映射中，给出一些物理页码，或者您知道的在内存中。
And so when we do,
when the MMU does
the translation it takes the index,
indexes into the map that
gives you some physical page number,
or you know in memory.
在指向4096字节的某个物理页的物理页号中。
In the physical page number that
points to some physical page of
4096 bytes.
然后是偏移量部分，基本上索引到该物理页面中，例如，偏移量是，您知道的，12。
And then the offset part,
basically indexes into that physical page,
so, for example,
the offset is, you know, 12.
那么你就知道那一页的第12个条目是实际使用的。
Then you know there are
the 12th entry of that
page is actually used.
很多人，很多人，你们中的很多人，在回答这个问题时，总是有一些方案，取一个偏移量，然后把它加到页面的底部，以获得实际的内存，物理内存位置，值存储的位置，值也将被加载到那里。
A lot of people a lot
of you entered in the message
in the,
in response to the question,
there's always some scheme of taking
an offset and adding that to
the base of the page
to obtain the actual
memory, physical memory location, where
a value store, where value will
be loaded too.
关于RISC-V的一个有趣的事情是，这是对一些问题的再次回答，有人问到看起来物理地址或虚拟地址是64位。
And one of the interesting things
about the RISC-V is and
this is a response to some
questions again,
somebody asked look a
the physical,
or virtual addresses are
64 bits.
这使得意义完全正确，因为RISC-V是64位寄存器。
Which makes totally sense correct,
because the RISC-V is
64-bit register.
嗯，但实际上在我们使用的RISC-V处理器上，并不是所有实际使用的64位。
Um, but in fact on the
RISC-V processor, that we're using,
not all of the 64 bits
actually used.
也就是说，前25名实际上根本没有使用。
Namely, the top 25 are
actually not used at all.
嗯，这限制了虚拟地址的大小，这将虚拟地址空间的大小限制为49的幂。
Um, and so that limits the
size of a virtual address, that
limits the size of a virtual
address space two to the power
of 49.
嗯，大约是512G字节。
Um, which is roughly
512 gigabytes.
嗯，当然您知道更高版本的处理器可能支持更大的地址空间，这是必要的，然后可以完成，例如，这25位中的一些基本上没有使用，可以用来构建更大的虚拟地址空间。
Um, and so of course you
know later version of the
processor, might support bigger address spaces
and that is necessary and could then
be done, for example, some of those 25 bits
that are basically unused, could be used to
build bigger virtual address spaces.
所以，嗯，等等，在索引中，然后，你知道，剩下的39位，你知道，你知道虚拟地址27，27位是索引，我们一会儿就会看到，为什么他们是27位是索引，然后12位是偏移量。
So, um,
and so in the index
and then, you know, where
39 bits left,
you know as the virtual address
27, 27 bits are
index and we'll see you in
a second, why they are 27
are index and then
the 12 are offset.
你知道必须是12，因为2的12次方是4096。
And you know there has to
be 12, because two to the
power 12 is 4096.
这是RISC-V物理地址上的虚拟地址，正如您在这里看到的，实际上是56位宽。
So that's virtual addresses on the
RISC-V physical addresses as you
can see here are actually 56
bits wide.
所以物理内存，可以大于单个虚拟地址空间。
So the physical memory,
you can be bigger than the
single virtual address space.
但它被限制在两次电源最多56次，您知道，大多数主板可能不支持两次56次物理内存的能力，因为大量的物理内存。
But it's limited to two power up
to 56,
you know most boards probably, you know,
don't support two to the power
of 56 physical memory, because
a gigantic amount of physical memory.
嗯，但原则上这块板可以，你知道，如果你能制造它支持2到56物理内存的幂。
Um, but in principle the
board could,
you know,
if you could manufacture it
support two to the power
of 56 physical memory.
因此，在该方案中，如果物理地址44的56位基本上是物理页号，则PPM和12是直接从虚拟地址继承的偏移量。
And so in this scheme,
then if 56 bit for
the physical address 44 are basically
the physical page number,
the PPM, and twelve are the
offset that are inherited directly from
the virtual address.
这有意义吗。
Does that make sense.
所以，嗯，你知道在这里停一下。所以你要集中你的思想，我想在这里指出的唯一的一点是，这个材料很重要，所以只要问问题，细节很重要，它将是你的一大部分，你真的需要理解所有这些东西，才能基本上做实验，下一个实验，页表实验。
So, um,
you know stop for a second
here. So you collect your thoughts,
the only point I wanted to
make here is that this material
is important,
so just ask questions,
the details matter,
and it will be a large
part of you,
you really need to understand all
this stuff,
to be able to basically
do lab, the next lab, the page
table lab.
是的，我在这里，请说吧。
Yeah I'm here,
go ahead, please.
嗯，如果你能倒退一张幻灯片，我的屏幕不清楚。
Um, if you can go back
one slide, I have the screen
is unclear.
哪一个，页表幻灯片？嗯。
Which one,
the page table slide? Yeah.
这一个?嗯，没有。
This one?
Um, no.
最新的一个，但也不要紧，嗯，是的，这很完美，谢谢你，所以我想知道这个4096字节的范围，我们称之为页面，是作为内存中的连续区块分配的，是的，这是包括内存在内的4096字节的连续物理范围。
The most recent one, but it
also doesn't really matter,
um, yeah,
this is perfect,
thank you so I'm wondering this
4096 byte range which we've called
a page, is that assigned as
a continuous chunk in memory,
yes that's a continuous physical,
continuous range of 4096 bytes
including memory.
我明白了，然后。你知道，地图，4096字节的粒度。
I see, and then. You know, the map,
a granularity of 4096 bytes.
好的，然后是12，比如2到12的偏移量是4096，那么这足以覆盖每一块了吗？是的，页面中的每个字节。
Okay, and then 12, the
offset like two to the
twelve is 4096,
so that's sufficient to cover each
of the chunks? Yeah, each byte in the page.
在图表中，56是从哪里来的，我可以一直跟踪到那时，但我不知道它是从哪里来的。嗯，这是设计师们炮制出来的。
And where does the 56 come
from, in the diagram I could
follow up until then,
but I didn't get where
that came from. Um, the
designers cook it up.
所以硬件设计师决定你知道的物理地址有多大，基本上是他们想要设计的任何电路板的物理地址，所以RISC-V设计师在56岁时决定物理地址是一个好主意。
So the hardware designers decide
how big you know physical
addresses basically for whatever board
they want to design,
and so the RISC-V
designers who decided at 56,
that physical addresses were a
good idea.
嗯，通常他们得出这些数字的方式是看技术趋势。
Um, and usually the way they
come up with these numbers is
they look at technology trends.
然后说，我们希望在接下来的5年里，你知道预测物理内存将会大于2的56次方。
And say like well we want
to be able for the next
sort of 5 years,
you know to predict the physical
memory will be ever bigger than
two to the power 56.
也许他们认为它不会比小得多的东西更大，但你知道，给他们一些[v方式]，你知道，如果你知道他们的预测是错误的，他们会选择一个稍微大一点的数字。
Probably they think it won't be
bigger than something much smaller,
but then you know give them
some [v way], you know,
in case you know their
predictions wrong,
they pick a slightly
bigger number.
这是有道理的。
Is that makes sense.
好的，谢谢。很多人问起这件事。
Yeah, thanks. A lot of people
ask about this.
其他举手的人，我想有一群人在提问，不幸的是，我的变焦没有显示超过两个人举手，只有多个人举手。
Anybody else, who raised a hand
I think there's a bunch of
people asking questions and unfortunately my
zoom doesn't show its more than
two people raised hands just multiple
people are raising their hands.
所以如果你有问题，请进来吧。
So you please jump in, if
you have a question.
好吧。我有一个问题，是的，如果虚拟内存是2的27次方，而物理内存是56的2次方，那么，我们可以有多个进程，这些进程可以耗尽所有的虚拟内存，而不会用完所有的物理内存，对吗？没错。
Okay. I have a question,
yeah, so if the virtual
memory is up to two
to the power of 27
and the physical memory is
up two to the power
due to the 56, right,
so, we could have,
like we could have multiple processes
that could exhaust all their virtual
memories without
using up all the physical memory,
right? That's correct.
这是完全正确的。
That's absolutely correct.
好的，我也有个问题。
Okay I have a question, too.
好的，去吧。
Yeah, go ahead.
所以这56个物理地址就是可能的存储器位置的数目。
So this 56 for the physical
address is that the,
the number of possible memory locations.
我认为这不是位的数量，因为64位的机器。
I don't think it's the
number of bits because the 64
bit machine.
嗯，五十六个可以涨到六十四个，但是他们就是选择只有五十六个。
Um that 56 could go up
to 64,
but they just choose it
to have just 56.
没错，从一种角度来看，他们只需要在棋盘上跑56码，而不是64码。
That's correct,
one way to think about it,
then they only have to run
56 wide on the board as
opposed to 64.
我明白了，我明白了。
I see, I see.
好吧。我还有一个问题，嗯，你能不能倒退一张幻灯片，从CPU开始，我们先检查内存，然后再到内存，但是哪里有不同进程的区别，因为像每个进程，像进程，像shell进程的地址是0x1000，然后ls进程也有地址0x0000的东西，所以我们需要将它们转换成不同的物理进程，所以。是的，SATP寄存器包含寄存器，该寄存器包含要使用的映射的地址。
Okay. I also have a question,
um, so kind of, could you
go back one slide maybe,
so from the CPU,
we go through the MMU and
then to the memory, but
where, where here is the distinction
for different processes, because like each
process, like process, like the shell
process has something at address like
0x1000,
and then the ls process
also has something at address
0x0000, so
we need to translate those to
different physical, so. Yeah, the satp register
contains the register who contains the
address of which map to use.
所以ls有自己的地图，你知道猫有自己的地图。
So ls runs with its own map,
you know cat with its own map.
好的，所以每个进程都有自己的地图。嗯。
OK, so each process will have
its completely own map. Yeah.
有道理，谢谢。
Makes sense,
thank you.
事实上，有一个很好的方法可以到达下一个点，所以如果每个进程都有自己的地图。
In fact, there's a great a
way to the next,
point, so if every process has
its own map.
你知道这张地图有多大，就像我在这里画的那样。
You know how big is this
map, like that I've drawn here.
嗯，这张图是27的2次方，正确。
Well, that map is two to
the power 27 entries, correct.
嗯，那可是相当大的一笔钱。
Um, and that's pretty big.
嗯，如果每个进程都准确地完成你知道的填充地图，我会相当快地填满物理内存。
Um, and I would fill physical
memory reasonable quickly,
if every process exactly how
to complete you know populated map.
然后是巨大的，意味着每个进程都非常大，所以实际上不是这样的，硬件实际上存储页表，你可以把它概念上想成一个数组，你知道从0到2的27次方，但实际上并不是这样发生的。
And then there's gigantic, means that
every process is very big,
and so in fact this is
not the way, hardware actually
stores page tables,
you can think about it
conceptually as an array,
you know going from zero to
two power 27,
but actually is not what happens
in practice.
实际上，这是一个多级结构，这里实际上是真正的RISC-V页表。
In practice,
it's a multi-level structure that
here's actually the real RISC-V
page table.
结构以及硬件实现的内容。
Structure and what the hardware implements.
那么我们之前开始的27位会发生什么，索引。
And so what happens with the
27 bits that we started earlier,
the index.
它实际上被分成三个9位数字。
It's actually split in three
nine bit numbers.
前九位用于索引顶层页表，也就是它们所称的目录。
And the first the top nine
bits, are used to index into
the top level page table,
directory as they are called.
所以，然后是一个目录，你知道这些人中的一个，你知道是4096字节，4096字节。
And so,
then one directory,
you know one of these guys,
you know is 4096 bytes,
4096 bytes.
就像页面大小一样。
Just like the page size.
PTE条目，其中一个条目是64字节。
A PTE entry, one of
the entries in the thing
is 64 bytes.
64位，我是说，对不起，就像寄存器有8个字节一样。
64 bit,
I mean, sorry, like the register
with so eight bytes.
所以这就意味着你要做4096次。
And so there's going to mean
that you do 4096.
除以8表示其中一个目录页中有512个条目。
Divided by eight, means there are
512 entries in one of those
directory pages.
因此，基本上发生的情况是，SATP指向顶层根目录，我们将顶层9位索引放入页目录。
So basically what happens is
like the satp points
to the top,
root directory,
we take the top level 9
bits index into the page directory.
现在给我们一个新的物理页码。
And now gives us a new
physical page number.
物理页码是下一级别的页面目录，所以当我们使用下一级别索引来索引到该页面目录时，您知道，等等，我们想要找到一个，我们会得到最低级别的页面目录。
And that physical page number
is the page directory for
the next level,
so when we use the
next level, index,
To index into that page
directory and then you know
and so forth,
you know, we'd like to find
one we get the bottom level
page directory.
这基本上为我们提供了将虚拟地址映射到物理地址的条目。
And that basically gives us
the entry,
that maps the virtual address
to physical address.
所以在某种意义上，它与我在上一张幻灯片中展示的非常相似，除了它们基本上是索引发生在三个步骤而不是一个步骤中。
So in some sense,
it's very similar to where I
showed in the previous slide except
they're basically the index happens in
three steps instead of one step.
这就是优点，这种方案的主要优点是大部分地址空间没有被使用，您不需要有任何页表条目来实现这一点。
And this is advantage,
the main advantage of this scheme
is that large parts of the
address space are not being used,
you don't have to have any
page table entries for that.
例如，假设您有一个新的地址库。
For example,
let's say you have a new
address base.
它只有一页，就像最下面的一页。
That has only one page like
the bottom page.
是的，4096号。
Yeah, 4096.
并且没有其他页面或在地址空间中，因此实际只映射地址0到4095和6。
And no other pages or in
the address space,
so only addresses zero to 4095
and 6 are actually mapped.
您需要映射多少个页表条目或页表目录。
How many page table entry or
page table directories do you need
to map that.
特定的页面。
Particular page.
嗯，你需要一个顶层的，对吧。
Well, you need one of the
top, correct.
你基本上需要该条目中的值为零。
And you need basically value in
that entry for zero.
最高级别的9位，你知道0，所以你需要一个0的条目。
The top level nine bits,
you know zero zero so you
need an entry for zero.
这意味着你需要一个中级条目，你知道基本上a对应于下一个，你知道九个零比特，然后一个条目对应接下来的九个零比特。
So that means you need one
middle level entry,
you know that basically a corresponds
to the next,
you know nine zero bits and
then one entry for the next
nine zero bits.
所以基本上我们只需要三页目录就可以了。
So basically we get away with
three page directories.
在我们上一张幻灯片上的前一个方案中，我们有2的27次幂的参赛作品，现在我们基本上必须有3倍于512个参赛作品的参赛作品。
In our previous scheme on the
previous slide correct,
we have two to the power
27 entries and now we basically
have to have three times whatever
512 entries that we're done.
这就是为什么你知道实际硬件的主要原因，我有这个分层的，嗯，多层树方案。
That's the main reason why
you know the actual hardware I
has this hierarchical,
um multi-level tree scheme.
任何关于这个的问题，因为这很重要。
Any questions about this, because it's
pretty important.
萨米尔，说吧。
Samir, go ahead.
所以我的问题是，因为每个页表的PPM号是44位。
So my question is as since
the PPM number from each page
table is 44 bits.
第二个表示中间表驻留在虚拟内存上。
And the second say the middle
table resides on the virtual memory.
我们从哪里得到丢失的十二个比特。
Where do we get the missing
twelve bits from.
最后十二位好的，所以你说的是这44个，正确的。
On the final twelve bits okay
so good good good,
so you're saying these 44, correct.
是的，这是怎么回事，而所有的页面，所有的页面目录或页面行。
Yes, what is going on
with that,
while all page, all page directories
or page line.
所以它们基本上是一个物理页码是44加上12，12个零位。
And so they basically they're a
physical page number is 44 plus
twelve, twelve zero bits.
如果我们看这些PTE条目，它们都有相同的形式，如果你看这些人中的一个，会发生什么呢？
And so what actually happens if
we look at these PTE entries,
they all have the same sort
of form,
if you look at one of
these guys.
有44位，有12位是0，所以我们得到了44加12是56的物理地址，Um，这意味着有64位，实际上还有一些位没有使用，事实上，最下面的12位基本上是最低的，或者说最下面的10位肯定是最低的，因为根本没有使用，事实上，寻呼硬件存储或存储了一系列控制转换的标志，我们将在第二节中讨论这些标志的情况。(=
There are 44 bits,
there are 12 bits
zero, so that gives us a
44 plus 12 is 56, so
that gives us a physical address,
Um, and so that means there's
64 bits,
there's actually some bits left
there not being used and
in fact the bottom twelve
bits were basically or the
bottom ten definitely bottom based
on not used at all and
in fact the paging hardware
stores or stores a bunch
of flags that control the
translation and we'll talk about
those flags in the second.
嗯，用它们来控制翻译，它们基本上存储在最下面的10位。
Um, and with their
to control the translation and
they're stored basically in the bottom
10 bits.
嗯，这也意味着，你知道，如果你把这两个加起来就是54位，基本上还剩下10位。
Um, it also means that, you
know, if you add these two
up that's 54 bits,
basically there's 10 bits left.
还有未使用的，这10位也是为了将来的增长，所以在某个时候，我们可能会有一种新型的RISC-V处理器，它的页表结构会略有不同，它实际上可能会有比44位更大的物理页码，好吗？谢谢。
There are unused, those 10 bits
are again,
you know for future growth,
so at some point we might
have a new type of
RISC-V processor, that will have a
slightly different structure page tables,
and it might actually have bigger
than 44 bits for the physical
page number, OK?
Thank you.
事实上，你可以在这里看到，如果你看一下这里画的单个条目，嗯，你知道它们基本上是。
In fact you can see
it here like if you
look at a single entry
direct that's drawn here,
um, you know they're basically.
10，10位未使用的剩余位。
10, 10 bits left, that
are not being used.
嗯，好的，我们来看一下旗帜，因为这很重要。
Um, okay,
so let's look at the flags
for a second, because it's sort
of important.
嗯，那么，在最下面的10位中的每一个翻译，都有一串标志存储，第一个标志是有效的。
Um, so,
every translation in the bottom 10
bits, there's a bunch of flag
stored and the first flag
is valid.
如果设置了有效位，则意味着这是有效PTE，您可以将其用于转换。
If a valid bit set,
that means this is a
valid PTE,
and you can use it
for translation.
因此，我们将运行我在这里使用的小示例，三个页面目录，当只使用条目零时，只有条目零将设置有效位，其他五个[和十一个]条目都不会设置有效位。
And so, we're going to
run my little example, that I
used here, three page directories,
when only entry zero is used
then only entey zero will have
valid bit set and none of
the other five [and eleven] entries
will not have valid bit set.
这基本上告诉我们，MMU，你不需要追查这个PTE，PTE只是不包含有效信息。
And that basically tells, MMU
well you don't have to chase
down this PTE, PTE just contains no
valid information.
那么“r”表示允许您从该页读取，“Write”表示允许您向该页写入。
Then "r" means you're allowed
to read from that page, write
means you're allowed to write to
the page.
Execute意味着允许您执行其中的指令。
Execute means you're allowed to execute
instruction from it.
嗯，在User中，意味着您知道在用户空间中运行的进程也可以访问此页面。
Um, in user, means you
know this page is
also accessible by a process
running in user space.
然后是其他你不那么重要的部分，它会在某个时候出现，那是定义重要部分的5个部分。
And then the other bits you
not that important,
it will show up at
some point, those are sort of five
define important bits.
这有意义吗。
Does that make sense.
是的，妮思娅，我可能会念错你的名字，我向你道歉。
Yeah, Nithya, I'd probably mispronouncing your
name I apologize to you.
这就是表示法，谢谢，我有一个关于三个页面表的快速问题，那么地址或PPM值是如何组合在一起形成我可能会错过的最终物理地址的。
That's, that's the representation,
thank you,
I had a quick question
about,
the three page tables,
so how are the addresses or
the PPM values combined to form
the final physical address I might
miss that.
嗯，是的，我们可能不会说得很清楚。因此，第一个PPM校正位于页表的顶部，即顶级页面目录中的第一个PPM。
Um, yeah,
well may not say that said it
very explicitly. So the first
PPM correcting tops the page table,
the first PPM in the top
level page directory.
并且包含下一层的物理地址。
And contains the physical address of
the next level down.
其中一个包含下一层，最后一个包含[几个]44位，它包含了我们实际上试图转换到的页面上的实际物理地址。
And one contains the one next
level down and then in the
final one we still have are
[few] 44 bits that contains then
the actual physical address off the
page that we're actually trying to
translate to.
嗯，好的，有道理，谢谢。
Um, OK,
that makes sense, thank you.
好的，还有一个有趣的问题，让我们边说一下，在我回答我自己的问题之前，在回答这里的两个举手之前，回顾这张图片，为什么，为什么物理页码存储在这些页面目录中。
Okay, and one interesting question,
just let us side note,
before let me answer my
own question before answering the
two raised hands here,
look back at this picture,
why, why are the physical page
numbers stored in these page directories.
为什么不是虚拟地址呢？
Why not a virtual address.
因为我们需要在内存中查找它，就像在内存中查找下一个目录一样。
Because we need to look it
up in memory, like look up
the next directory in memory.
是的，我们不能有依赖于另一种翻译方案的翻译方案，你知道我们可以，递归地看意图，所以这就没有意义了。
Yeah right,
we could not have a
translation scheme depends on yet
another translation scheme,
you know we could sort of,
recursive intent look, so that
just doesn't make sense.
这就是正确的答案，它必须是一个物理数，那么SATP呢？你怎么使用SATP，它存储什么，它存储物理地址还是虚拟地址。
That's exactly the right answer,
it has to be a
physical number,
how about the satp,
what do you use the satp,
what does it store it store
a physical address or a virtual address.
嗯，也是物理的，假设第一页目录也是内存。完全正确，所以它必须是一个物理数，因为我们实际上是在试着用它来翻译。
Um, also physical, assuming that
the first page directory is
also memory. Right exactly so
it has to be a
physical number because we're actually
trying to use it for
translation.
而且，嗯，你知道SATP，你需要知道物理页码是什么。
And, um,
so you know the satp, you
need to know what the physical
page number is.
嗯，在页面目录的路径上。
Um, on the route of the
page directory.
好的，还有另外两个问题，或者两个举手的人可以做，重复你的问题，如果。
OK, there were two other questions
or two people who raise their
hands could do,
Repeat your question if.
因此，有一个由三个表组成的层次结构，每个表都由虚拟地址的一部分进行索引，每个虚拟地址有9位长。
So there's a hierarchy of three
tables and each of them is
indexed by a part of the
virtual address,
each nine bits long.
因此，我不确定我是否理解它们之间的链接是如何发生的，以及它意味着什么，比如，仅仅使用这三个9位地址来索引它们中的每一个难道不够吗？
So I'm not sure
I understand how chaining between
them happens and what it's
meant to accomplish like shouldn't
it be sufficient to just
use those three 9 bit
addresses to index into each
of them.
没错，所以第一个顶层9位用来表示在第一个顶层页级目录中，第二个、下一个和第三个位在第三个目录中。
That's correct,
so the first top level
nine bits are used to
mean that in the first
top page level directory,
the second and the next
one and the third in
the third one.
因此，可能我只是没有正确理解这一点，所以当一个进程请求查找某个虚拟地址时，它会加载到SATP寄存器或CPU中，这样就会得到相应的正确的最高级别页表。
So maybe I'm just not understanding
this correctly,
so when a process requests
a certain virtual address to be
looked up,
it loads into the
satp register or the CPU
does and that,
get to the corresponding correct highest
level page table.
然后是那个页表。
And then that page table.
将要。我们在顶层使用了27位中的9位来索引该页目录。
will. We used in the top
level nine bits from the 27
to index into that page directory.
然后是什么结果呢，比如如果结果是什么都没有，MMU会创建一个页面表，不，不，MMU基本上会告诉操作系统或处理器，很抱歉我无法转换该地址，基本上会变成页面错误，我们稍后会讨论这个问题。
And then what is what is
the result of that,
like if the result is there's
nothing there does MMU
create a page table,
No, no,
MMU basically tells the operating
system or tells the processor,
sorry I couldn't translate that address,
and basically turns into a
page fault which we'll talk about
a little bit later.
但就是不能翻译地址，它不能翻译，就像你知道你不能被零除，你知道如果你试图这样做，检察官会拒绝这样做。
But just cannot translate the address,
it doesn't translate it's like you
know you can't divide by zero,
you know if you try to
do that the prosecutor refuses to
do it.
我明白了，好的。
I see, OK.
布兰登，你呢，布兰登。
Brandon, what about you, Brandon.
嗯，所以我只是想确保我理解我是怎么想的，也许我们想知道中间页是怎么排好表的，我们是怎么计算它们的物理地址的。
Um, so I just wanted to
make sure I understand how I
think maybe we want to understand
how the intermediate page tables well
how we calculate the physical address
of those.
嗯，那么，如果我们试图找到第二级页表物理地址，我们将从第一级页表中提取PPM，即44位，然后我们将原始虚拟地址的12位偏移量相加，以获得完整的56位，这是正确的吗，这个问题是。我们不将虚拟地址的偏移量相加，我们只取12个零位。
Um, so,
is it correct that say if
we're trying to find a second
level page tables physical address,
we would take the PPM from
the first level page table,
that's 44 bits and then we
add the 12 bit offset from
the original virtual address to get
the full 56 bit, this question
is. We don't add the offset
from the virtual address,
we just take twelve zero bits.
所以我们取PPM，有44位。好的，底部有12个零位，这给了我们一个56位的物理地址，这就是下一页目录的位置，这要求基本上每个页目录的页都要对齐。
So we take the PPM
there's 44 bits. Okay, 12
zero bits on the bottom
and that gives us a
56 bit physical address and
that's where the next page
directories,
and this requires that basically every
page directories page aligned.
我明白了，好的，这是有道理的。
I see,
OK, that makes sense.
这些都是很棒的问题，这些都是东西，你们会在页表实验室里苦苦挣扎。
So these are all great questions
and these are all things,
you're gonna be struggling within the
page table lab so.
是啊，现在就去问他们是非常好的。
Yeah it's very good to ask
them right now.
好的，嗯，让我想想，好的，好的，让我稍等一下。
Okay, um,
let me see,
Yes, yeah okay,
let me hold on for
a second.
我引用我的想法。
And I quote my thoughts.
嗯，我知道我在哪里了
Um I see where I am.
好的，一种，你知道，还有一件事我想提一下，因为你会看到，如果我们想一想，你知道我刚才展示的方案，嗯，看起来真正发生的事情是我们将价值加载或存储到内存中。
Good good,
good, okay,
one a sort of a you
know one other thing that I
want to mention because you will
see that, is that if
we think about this,
you know the scheme that I
just showed right,
um what really seems to be
going on is that we load
or store value to memory.
在处理器加载或存储价值内存的地方，我们基本上必须进行空闲内存查找，对吧，一个在页面目录的顶部，一个在中间页面目录，然后一个在最底层的页面目录。
Where the processor loads or stores
value memory,
we basically have to do free
memory lookups, right,
one in the top of the
page directory,
one intermediate page
directory and then one in the
bottom level page directory.
看起来，您知道任何对虚拟地址的内存引用基本上都需要空闲内存才能到达。
It looks like, that you know
any memory reference to virtual address
basically requires free memory to reach.
所以这似乎很贵。
And so that seems expensive.
嗯，那么，嗯，在几乎所有处理器都这样做的实践中会发生什么，它的一侧有一个缓存，其中包含最近使用的翻译。
Um, and so,
um, what happens in practice where
almost all every processor does this,
it has a cache sitting
on the side, that contains
recently used translations.
这被称为翻译后备缓冲器。
And this is called translation look-aside buffer.
那么你会经常看到这个术语，TLB。
Then you'll see that term
quite often, of TLB.
基本上，它只是条目、页表条目、PTE条目的缓存。
Basically it's nothing else than
the cache of
entry, page table entries,
PTE entries.
因此，当进程让您知道进程路由第一次查找虚拟地址时，您知道这个，硬件遍历此页，即三级页面表，您知道该特定虚拟地址的最终物理页(通常称为PPN)，然后基本上TLB存储VA、PA、PN或PA映射。
So when the process has you
know the first time the process
routes look through virtual address,
you know walks this, hardware
walks this page, the the three
level page tables, that will come
out with you know the final
physical page, often called PPN,
for that particular virtual address,
and then basically the
TLB stores,
VA, PA, PN,
or PA mapping
on the side.
因此，下一次您提到那个特定的虚拟地址时。
And so,
then the next time you refer
to that particular virtual address.
我只需直视TLB中的上方，TLB就会做出响应，而不必执行页表遍历。
I can just look at straight
up in the TLB and the
TLB will respond instead of having
to do the page table walk.
嗯，是的，艾米亚。
Um, yep, Amiar.
因此，TLB将虚拟地址映射到页面的物理地址，虚拟地址和偏移量是绝对正确的，在页表级别进行缓存不是更有效吗？
So, the TLB map
virtual addresses to the physical address
of the page that the virtual
address along with the offset you're
absolutely right,
wouldn't it be more efficient
to like cache at the
page table level.
嗯，好的，我再退一步，嗯，实施TLB有很多种方式，嗯，最重要的是要知道，有一个TLB。
Um, okay so I let me
take a step back here,
um, there are many ways of
implementing the TLB,
um, the most important thing that
you need to know is that
there is a TLB.
嗯，TLB具体是怎么实施的，这种你知道的，我们不会讲太多细节的话题。
Um, and the exact details
of actually how the TLB
has implemented, this sort of
you know not a topic
that we're going to talk
about in great amount of
detail.
嗯，那根本不是，嗯，所以这实际上是位于处理器内部的东西，大部分对操作系统是隐藏的，操作系统并不真的知道TLB BE是如何操作的，你需要知道TLB存在的唯一原因是，如果你切换页表。
Um, that's not at all,
um, and so this is really
something that sits inside of the
processor and is mostly hidden from
the operating system,
the operating system doesn't really know
how to TLB be operates, the
only thing the reason you need
to know that the TLB
exist is that if you switch
page tables.
然后，通常操作系统需要告诉处理器正在切换页表。
Then, typically the operating system needs
to tell the processor that's switching
page tables.
并且需要刷新TLB。
And the
TLB needs to be flushed.
因为基本上您发送的是陈旧的条目，但是如果您切换到新的页表，TLB中的条目可能不再有效，因此需要删除它们，否则您知道转换将是不正确的。
Because basically you send you
stale entries,
but if you switch to a
new page table,
the entries in the TLB may
not be valid anymore and so
they need to be removed because
otherwise you know the translation would
be incorrect.
所以操作系统通常会意识到有一个，有一个TLB，基本上只是偶尔告诉硬件，好的，我们不再使用它们了，因为我要交换页表。
And so the operating system is
typically where
it's aware that there's a,
that there is a TLB
only basically to tell the
hardware once in a while saying,
okay well don't use them anymore,
because I'm gonna switch page tables.
事实上，在RISC-V上，刷新TLB的指令称为sfence_vma。
And in fact on you know
the, the RISC-V, the instruction
to flush the TLB is called
sfence_vma.
实际上我不是。
I'm not actually.
刷新TLB。[双背]。
Flush the TLB. [Biback].
所以我有一个问题，不是关于TLB，而是带来了这个问题。
So I have a question,
like not regarding TLB
but that brought kind
of this question.
三级支持，即我们拥有的三级分页，是由操作系统还是硬件本身实现的。它是在硬件中实现的。
The three level support, that the
three level paging that we have,
is it implemented by the operating
system or the hardware itself. It
implemented in hardware.
所以你知道所有的事情都发生在硬件上，内存管理单元是硬件的挡路。
So you know there's all happens
in hardware,
the MMU is a block
of hardware.
在操作系统中，我们很快就会看到xv6，xv6有一个模拟页表遍历的函数，因为有时您知道xv6基本上必须做硬件所做的事情。
In the operating system we'll
see in a second when we
look at xv6, xv6
has a function that models the
page table walk, because once in
a while you know xv6
basically has to do what the
hardware does.
嗯，所以它知道它没有一个叫WALK的功能，基本上做的是完全一样的事情，但是是在软件中。
Um, and so it knows
it doesn't have a function
called walk, that basically does
exactly the same thing,
but in software.
那么，我能问个问题吗？那么，嗯，在此方案中，处理器缓存适合的位置是在地址转换之前还是之后，因为。好的，好的，让我来，让我们往后调几个，让我想想。
So, can I ask a question?
So um,
where in this scheme does the
processor cache fit,
does it happen before the address
translation or after,
because. Yeah, okay let me so
let's switch back a little bit
a couple, let me see.
好的，通常MMU真正思考的方式就是所有这些东西。
Okay, usually MMU will
really the way to think about
is that all this stuff.
你知道整个挡路都在处理器硅里。
You know the whole block is
inside the processor silicon.
所以这里有一个RISC-V芯片，它的内部是CPU，实际上有多个正确的CPU，有4个核心。
So there's a RISC-V
chip and inside of it
is the CPU,
in fact there are multiple CPU
correct, there 4 cores.
这是一个MMU，你可以想一想，在CPU这一边，你知道有一个TLB。
And there's a MMU
and you know you can think
about that,
either on this on the
CPU side,
you know there's a TLB.
这是有道理的，嗯，但我想我的问题是关于类似的，缓存不是TLB，而是一个普通的缓存，比如，有时我们实际上不会一直访问内存。
That makes sense,
um, but I guess my question
was about the like,
cache in terms of not
the TLB,
but just a normal cache like,
sometimes we don't actually go all
the way to access the memory.
好的，我想我应该在上周的周一正确地计划RISC-V处理器，现在有一个缓存，有两个缓存。
Yeah, good points I think I
should like to scheme last week
correctly on monday of the RISC-V
processor and has now one cache
it has two cache.
有些高速缓存按物理地址索引，有些高速缓存按虚拟地址索引。
Some caches are indexed by physical
address, some caches are indexed by
virtual address.
因此，按虚拟地址索引的高速缓存位于MMU之前。
So the caches that are indexed
by virtual address sit before the
MMU.
并通过MMU之后的物理地址在它们的索引中进行高速缓存。
And cache in their index by
physical addresses after the MMU.
这说得通吗？我也可以问一个问题吗？我的问题是，你说TLB，它是行走的，所以我喜欢把东西放进TLB，硬件遍历页表。
Does that make sense?
Can I also ask a question
my question is,
you said that the TLB,
it walks so I like to
put stuff into TLB,
the hardware walks through the
page tables.
如果硬件可以做到这一点，我们为什么要达到步行功能。
Why do we arrive walk function,
if hardware can do that.
很好的问题，嗯，我们有几个原因，或者为什么xv6需要它，一个是它实际设置初始页表的时候。
Very good question,
um, one reason we have, a
couple of reasons why we do
it or why xv6 needs it,
one is when it actually sets
up the initial page tables.
嗯，你知道它需要对三级进行编程。
Um, you know it needs to
program the the three levels.
所以它需要基本上模仿这三个层次。
And so it needs to basically
emulate the three levels.
嗯，还有另一个例子，您实际上在syscall实验室中遇到或正在遇到的是，当您复制xv6时，内核有自己的页表，每个用户地址空间都有自己的页表。
Um, and um,
another example,
that you actually sort of run
into or are running into in
the syscall lab is that when
you copy the xv6, the
kernel has its own page table
and every user address space has
its own page table.
偶尔，例如，它会说信息就像系统一样，指向系统基础设施，你知道它生活在用户空间。
And with once in a while,
for example it says info go like
system, pointed to system infrastructure,
you know that lives in
user space.
需要将内核转换为它可以用来写入它的地址。
The kernel needs to be translated
to an address that it can
use to write it.
所以，举个例子，如果你看的是拷贝入或拷贝出。
And so,
for example if you're looking copy
in or copy out.
嗯，基本上内核使用用户虚拟来转换用户虚拟地址，使用用户页表来获取该内核的物理地址，然后获得一个地址，实际上内核可以使用该地址来读写该内存。
Um, basically the kernel translates the
user virtual address using the user
virtual, using a user page
table to get out of physical
address that that kernel,
then get an address out,
actually the kernel can use to
read and write that memory.
所以有一大堆地方会出现，我希望在10分钟或15分钟内谈到。
So there's a bunch of places
going to show up and I'll
talk about hopefully in whatever ten
minutes or fifteen minutes.
我有一个问题，为什么像这样的硬件不公开那个遍历函数，这样我们就不必编写自己的函数，而且里面可能有bug，为什么不像这样，也许有一个特权指令，你可以传递一个虚拟地址，然后返回物理地址。
I have a question,
why doesn't the hardware like expose
that walk function,
so we don't have to write
our own and potentially have bugs
in it,
why isn't there like, maybe
a privileged instruction that you can
pass a virtual address and will
give back the physical address.
嗯，这就像是存储到虚拟地址，你回来，我们会为你做好的，嗯，所以我稍后会看到，在下一个实验中，页表实验室，实际上就是你要做的事情，你实际上会以稍微不同的方式设置页表，这样你就可以避免走进或复制和复制。
Well, this is just like just
store to the virtual address,
you get back and we'll do
it right for you,
um, so I will see
later on,
in the next lab,
the page table lab,
in fact is exactly what you'll
be doing you'll actually set up
the page table slightly differently,
so that you can avoid the
walk in or copyin and copyinstr.
我想这一点在我们谈到xv6的时候就会变得清晰起来，好的。
I think this will become clear
in the second we when we
talk about we look at the
xv6, OK.
好的，很好。
Okay, good.
在跳到xv6之前，还有一个基本上可以肯定的是，我想说明一点。
One more sure basically before jumping
into xv6, I wanted to make
one point.
一种方式来考虑，嗯，你知道，页表。
One way to think about,
um, you know,
page tables.
一种流行的说法，这个嗯。
A popular way
to phrase,
this um.
页表提供了一定程度的间接性。
It's the page tables provide
a level of indirection.
基本上这是间接的，你知道从虚拟地址到物理地址的映射。
And, that and, so basically
this indirection,
what I'm talking about you know
this mapping from virtual address to
physical address.
并且该映射完全在操作系统的控制之下。
And this mapping is completely
under control
of the operating system.
正如我们已经看到的，你知道在最后几张幻灯片中，我们谈到，嗯，这意味着操作系统因为它有这么多的控制权，它有完全的控制权，翻译，它可以做各种有趣的把戏。
As we've seen, you know in the last
a couple slides that
we talk,
um, and that means that the
operating system because it has so
much control,
it has control complete control that
translation, it can do all
kinds of interesting tricks.
嗯，举个例子，就像一个小把戏，稍微谈谈这个，比如如果一个页面，页面条目是无效的，并且真的会返回一个页面，你知道硬件会引发页面错误。
Um, and so for example, like
one trick, talk a little
bit about this,
like if a page, page entry is
invalid and will really return a
page you know the hardware will
raise page fault.
作为响应，页错误，操作系统可以更新页表，然后可能重新启动指令。
In response,
the page fault,
the operating system could update
the page tables and then
maybe restart the instruction.
因此，在运行时，通过操作页表，它们可以做各种各样的事情。
And so there are all kinds
of things they can do, at
runtime, and by manipulating
the page tables.
我们今天不会讨论这个话题，但是两周后，我们会讲授这个话题，一旦你有了页表和页面错误，你可以做什么很酷的事情。
And we're not going to talk
about it to today,
but in two weeks,
we'll have a lecture exactly about
this topic about what cool things
can you do once you have
page tables and page faults.
嗯，但重要的是要记住，这是一种令人难以置信的强大机制。
Um, but it's important to keep
in mind that this is
incredibly powerful mechanism.
嗯，那会给操作系统带来极大的灵活性。
Um that,
will provide the operating system
with a tremendous amount of flexibility.
页表如此受欢迎的原因有一个。
And there's one reason why page
tables are so popular.
好的，我接下来要做的实际上是讨论xv6。
Okay, so what I wanna do
next is actually talk about xv6.
嗯，稍微看看在xv6中会有什么效果。
Um, sort of see how
it all plays out in xv6.
所以我要做的第一件事，是看看内核页面布局，如果你愿意的话，映射在这张幻灯片上，这是内核的虚拟地址空间。
So the first thing I'm gonna
do, is going to look
at the kernel page layout,
if you will, and
the mapping is on this slide,
so here's the
virtual address space
of the kernel.
这是，实际上是物理内存，所以这基本上就是你能想到的任何东西，这就是DRAM。
Here is,
actually the physical memory,
so this is basically whatever you
can think about this is DRAM.
事实上并非如此，让我马上收回这一点，其中一个部分是DRAM。
And in fact it is not,
let me take that back immediately
one part is DRAM.
其中一部分实际上是IO设备。
And one part is actually
IO devices.
嗯，也许我会先谈一下幻灯片的右边，然后我们再谈第二张幻灯片的左边。
Um, and so,
to sort of maybe, I'm
going to talk about the physical,
the right side of the slide a
little bit first and then we'll
talk about the left side in
the second.
因此，幻灯片的左侧完全由硬件决定。
So the left side of
the slide is completely determined
by the hardware.
嗯，所以硬件设计师基本上决定了合身的布局，你知道的，就像你上周看到的那样。
Um, and so the hardware designers
basically determined the layout of that
fit and you know as you saw
before last week.
当内核启动时，它从此地址0x8000开始。
When the kernel starts,
it starts at this address 0x8000.
嗯，这是由硬件设计师决定的。
Um, and that's determined by the
hardware designers.
嗯，所以你应该更清楚地说，嗯，如果你看电路板，这是我周一展示的同一张电路板的图片，但希望是更好的图片，很容易看到，这是我们的RISC-V处理器。
Um, and so you should be
more explicit,
um, if you look at
the board,
this is the same picture of
the board, that I showed on
monday but is hopefully a little
better picture,
it's easy to see,
here's our RISC-V processor.
我们现在知道RISC-V处理器是正确的，有四个内核，但也有MMU。
And we now know correct in
the RISC-V processor,
there four cores, but there's also,
MMU.
还有一个TLB或多个TLB，每个内核都有自己的MMU，每个内核都有自己的TLB。
And there's also a TLB or
multiple TLB, every core has its
own MMU and every
core has its own TLB.
这是DRAM芯片。
And here are DRAM chips.
所以基本上电路板的设计者已经决定，当你知道，在你知道，在从虚拟地址到物理地址的转换之后，你知道，从08开始的基本物理地址，你知道，很多零实际上进入了DRAM芯片，你知道，当你知道，你知道，在从虚拟地址到物理地址的转换之后，你知道，很多零实际上进入了DRAM芯片。
And so basically the designers of
the board have decided that,
when, you know, after, you
know, the translation from virtual to
physical address basic physical addresses that's
starting you know at 08,
you know, a lot of zeros actually go to
the dram chips.
0a8以下的地址可能去往不同的IO设备。
Addresses above below 0a8, may go
to different IO devices.
所以平台基本上决定了设计者，这块板确切地决定了物理布局。
And so the platform decides
basically the designers this board have
decided exactly what the physical layout.
我想你可以查一下物理布局，如果你想调整，让我给你看看，这是我在，嗯，在，嗯，星期一给你看的同一本手册，如果你真的转到第31页，我相信。
I think you can look that
up the physical layout,
if you want to adjust,
let me show you so here's
the same manual that I showed
you on, um,
on um,
on um, Monday and if you
go to actually,
go to page,
31 I believe.
是的，这是一页，如果你往下看，这就是内存，它会写出内存图，在电路板上，我们会看到在地址0，0是预留的，那里什么都没有。
Yeah it's a page and
if you go down,
this is whats the memory,
it will spell out the memory
map is, of the  board
and we'll see at address zero
zero is reserved nothing is there.
嗯，如果你往下滚动这张内存映射图，你会看到关于映射的所有不同事物的一些信息，例如，以太网板映射到OX1，你知道，0x什么的。
Um, if you go scroll down
in this memory map,
you'll see some information about all
the different things that are mapped,
for example, ethernet board is mapped
at Ox1, you know,
0x something.
嗯，如果你可以再往下一点的话，哎呀，太往下了。
Um, if you might go further
down, oops, too much down.
嗯，在这里，您可以看到0x8000的条目有效，这实际上是DDR内存，片外易失性存储器，所以这些是DRAM芯片，或者我可以在上一张幻灯片上展示给您看。
Um, here,
you see the entry for
0x8000 worked
and that actually is DDR memory,
the Off-Chip Volatile Memory, so
those are the DRAM chips or
I can show you on the
previous slide.
所以，保持头脑清醒是很好的，即使我们在和QEMU交谈，你是在监督软件，最终一切都是由你知道的实际董事会决定的。
And so it's just good
to keep your head correct
even though we're talking to
QEMU, you're overseeing software in
the end everything is determined,
by you know the actual
board.
好的，回到我的幻灯片。
Okay, so go back to a
my slides.
嗯，那我们来看一下布局。好的，诺亚，去吧。
Um, so let's look at the
layout. Yeah, Noah,
go ahead.
嗯，您说这个布局是由硬件决定的，具体是指CPU本身还是CPU所在的板。
Yeah, when you say that this
this layout is determined by the
hardware, do you specifically mean
like the CPU itself or the
board on which the CPU resides.
应该驻留的板，对吗？因为你要驱逐出去，你知道，CPU是中间那个正方形的灰色东西，说无论RISC-V DRAM芯片处于什么位置，关闭处理器是正确的，是电路板设计师把芯片放在DRAM上，你知道，总共做很多IO设备。
The board which should be resides,
correct. Because you're going to deport,
you know, the CPU is the
grey thing in the middle that
square thing, saying whatever RISC-V
the dram chips are sitting off,
the off the processor correct, it's
the board designers who put the
chip the dram, you know, do many
IO devices altogether.
操作系统的很大一部分实际上是CPU的一部分，但IO设备至少同样重要，对吧，所以当你编写操作系统时，你既要处理CPU，也要处理IO设备，你知道，你想要通过互联网发送数据包，你知道的，你知道的，你想要通过互联网发送数据包，是这样的，你知道，但IO设备至少是同样重要的，所以当你编写操作系统时，你必须同时处理CPU和IO设备，你知道，你想要通过互联网发送数据包。
And make a large part of
an operating system is actually,
you know the cpu is one part, but the
IO devices are at least as
important, right and so when you're
writing an operating system you both
have to deal with the CPU
as well as you know with
the IO devices,
you know and you want to
send a packet over the Internet.
嗯，总得有人来接手。
Well, somebody has to
take over.
你知道网络驱动程序，真正做到这一点的网卡，那就是操作系统。
You know the network driver,
the NIC card to actually
do that,
and that's the operating system.
回到这张图片的右侧，这是物理地址布局，您知道，正如我在文档中显示的，底部基本上是未使用的。
So going back to the right
side of this picture correct,
which is the physical address layout,
you know we see basically the
bottom was unused as I showed
you on that document.
结果是0x100，也就是物理地址，这就是引导ROM所在的位置，所以当你打开那块板时，首先要做的就是对引导ROM运行进行编码。
It turns out that
0x100, that physical address,
that's where the boot rom
is, so when you turn
on that board,
the first thing that happens is
actually coding the boot rom runs.
当启动ROM完成时，它实际上会跳到这个0x000，这是操作系统的工作，确保那里有一些，你知道，一些数据。
And when the boot rom is
done it actually will jump to
this 0x000 and it's
a job of the operating system make
sure that there's some,
you know, some data there.
然后还有一堆其他的设备将会讨论到中断控制器，我们将在下周讨论这个问题。
And then there's a bunch of
other devices that will talk about
goes to
interrupt controller,
we'll talk about it
next week.
嗯，有一个客户端，我们将在下周讨论中断故事的另一个部分，所以有多个设备可以生成中断，需要计划将这些中断路由到适当的请求级别，这都是由那些中断控制器实现的。
Um, there's a client, another part
of the interrupt story that we'll
talk about next week,
so there's multiple devices can generate
interrupts there needs to be planned
to route those interrupts to the
to the appropriate request level and
it's all implemented by those
interrupt controllers.
嗯，让我说完，你知道这个，这张幻灯片之前。
Um, and let me finish for
a second you know this,
this slide before.
回答问题，然后有一个UART是设备，这实际上是设备实际上UART设备实际上与控制台和显示器交互，然后是虚拟的，这是磁盘。
Answering question,
then there's a uart
that was the device,
that was actually the thing
that actually,
the device actually UART device actually
interacts with the console and the
display and then there's the virtual
there's the disk.
这就是设备，有一个设备属于它，它实际上是与磁盘交互的。
And that's the device,
there's a device belong,
it's that actually interacts with
the disk.
所以当你把位置写到地址时，比方说。
And so when you write through
location to address, let's say.
0x200，则该物理地址对应于CLINT，因此您想要执行存储指令、加载指令以及对实现CLINT的芯片的读取和写入。
0x200 then
that physical address corresponds to the
CLINT and so do you want
to do store instruction,
load instruction,
your reading and writing to the
chip that implements the CLINT.
我们稍后会看到这到底意味着什么，但基本上您可以认为这是直接与设备交互，而不是读或写物理内存。
We'll see later what that exactly
means but basically you can think
about this as interacting directly with
the device and not reading or
writing physical memory.
是的，我有个问题。
Yeah there's a question.
嗯，所以我只是想确认0x800以下的地址并不存在于DRAM中。
Um, so just trying to make
sure the addresses below
0x800, they don't really exist
in dram.
如果当我们提到这些地址时，我们会直接转到其他硬件。
If when we mention those addresses
we directly go to the other
hardwares.
是的，是的，所以如果你回到这张照片。
Yeah yeah,
so if you go back to
this picture.
任何大于0x10的，都是正确的。
Anything of above
0x10, correct.
这就是这些DRAM薯片。
That's these dram chips.
你知道我不会画画，我不能指给你看克林特，但我一般都听人说，嗯，以太网。
And you know I can't
draw, I can't point you
to the CLINT,
but like generally hears that,
um, ethernet.
这是一个特定的物理地址，我们可以写入加载存储指令，称为内存映射IO，我们可以加载和存储指令，我们可以编程以太网控制器。
And so that's a particular physical
address and we can write you
know load store instructions is called
memory mapped IO,
we can load and store instructions,
we can program ethernet controller.
我还有一个问题，为什么上面的这一大块写着没有使用。
I also have a question,
why was this big chunk at
the top says unused.
为什么不用呢？好的，记住，嗯，不是每台机器都有，所以有2的56次方，字节的物理地址空间，但是你没有，你知道，如果你不想的话，把那么多内存插到电路板上。
Why is it not used. OK,
so remember,
um, not every machine not
every so there's two to
the power 56,
bytes physical address space,
but you don't have those,
you know, plug in that much memory
into the board,
if you don't want to.
因此，它的一些部分可能是未使用的，这取决于你在电路板上有多少DRAM芯片。
And so some parts of it
may be unused, depending on how
much you're dram chips are sitting
on the board.
事实上，他们喜欢xv6，我想我们把自己限制在128兆字节。
In fact,
they like in xv6,
we I think limit ourselves to
128 megabyte.
仅此而已。
And no more.
那么，当加载存储指令从CPU发出时，会不会发生这样的情况：它从哪里路由到正确的IO，比如已经从CPU路由到正确的IO，就像CPU在发出指令之前说OK一样，如果它小于0x8且全是零，那么我会将其发送到正确的IO设备，否则我会像DRAM芯片一样将其发送到内存。
So when a, when a
load store instruction goes out of
the CPU,
does that go,
like where does it get
routed to the correct IO, like
already from the CPU,
so kind of like if the
CPU before it sends it out
it says OK,
if it's lower than 0x8
and all the zeros then
I'm going to send it to
the correct IO devices,
and then otherwise I'm going to
send it to the to the
memory like dram chip.
是的，你可以把它想象成一个安装在RISC-V内部的多路分解器，你知道挡路。
Yeah, you can think about as
a demultiplexer sitting on the
inside of the RISC-V, you
know block.
哦，那么它就在那个挡路里面了。好的。
Oh, so it's inside of
that block. OK.
作为存储控制器并进行路由。
As a memory controller and does
routing.
因为非常重要的是要把这一切都弄清楚。
Because very important to have
that sort of all clear
in your head.
你还好吗，所以现在我想换到这张照片的右边。
Are you okay,
so now I want to
switch to the right side
of this picture.
这基本上就是xv6设置的虚拟地址空间，也就是xv6设置，所以当机器启动时，还没有启用页面，xv6设置了第一个页表，虚拟地址空间，这实际上是虚拟地址空间，内核使用，我们将在第二个中看到它。
And this is basically what
xv6 sets up, to
the virtual address space, that
xv6 setup,
so when the machine boot, there's
no page enable yet,
xv6 sets up
the first page tables, virtual
address space and that's actually
the virtual address space,
the kernel uses and we'll look
at it in the second.
在代码中，但是，这就是布局，你知道，因为我们想让xv6尽可能简单，所以你很容易理解。
At the code,
but,
and this is the layout
and it turns out,
you know,
because we want to keep
xv6 as simple as possible,
it's easy for you to understand.
从虚拟到物理的映射。
The mapping from virtual
to physical.
主要是身份映射。
Is mostly in identity mapping.
基本上，这意味着虚拟地址0x200映射到物理地址0x200，内核将完全按照这种方式设置页面表，这基本上意味着您知道此顶部下面的所有虚拟服装。
So basically what that means is
that the virtual address 0x200
maps to physical address
0x200, the kernel
will set up the page tables
exactly in that way,
and so that means basically that
you know all virtual dresses,
below this top.
这是物理内存的顶部，与右侧实际使用的物理地址相同。
Which is the top of
physical memory are identical to the
physical addresses that are actually being
used on the right side.
这就是为什么所有的箭头都是直的，因为这是身份映射。
And so this is why all
the arrows are straight, because it's
identity mapping.
对于这一点的小变化，有两件重要的事情要提。
The small changes to this,
there are two important things
to mention.
让我稍等片刻，试着先提一下要提到的两件重要的事情。
Let me hold on a second, while
try to first mention the two
important things to mention.
首先，有一些页面，一些地图在你的记忆中非常高。
First of all,
there's some pages,
some maps very high up in
your memory.
其中一些页面在内存中的位置非常高，例如内核堆栈实际所在的堆栈也映射到内存位置较高的位置。
Which some pages very high
up in memory,
for example the stack a
kernel stack actually sits up is
also map high up in memory.
嗯，内存较高的原因是因为我们在它下面有一个未映射的保护页。
Um, and the reason is high
up in memory is because we
have a guard page below it
that is not mapped.
因此，内核堆栈[]之一的内核堆栈下面的PTE条目没有设置有效位。
So the PTE entry below
the kernel stack, of one of
the kernel stack [], does
have, not have it's valid
bit set.
而且，嗯，如果你知道，内核在堆栈之外运行，会导致页面错误，这比基本上在内核拥有的其他内存上乱涂乱画要好得多。
And, um,
so if you know, the kernel
runs off its stack and will
result in a page fault,
which is better than basically scribbling
over some other memory that the
kernel has.
你马上就会惊慌失措，你知道有些东西堆积如山是不好的。
You get immediate panic,
you know that something's bad to stack.
当然，我们不想浪费物理内存，所以当我们这样做的时候，基本上是把堆栈放得很高，在它下面放一个保护页，一个空的保护PTE条目。
Of course, we don't want
to waste physical memory and so
when we do that by basically
putting the stack high,
in,
a guard page, an empty guard
PTE entry below it.
嗯，而且守卫页面实际上并不会消耗位于虚拟地址空间高处的任何物理内存记录，所以没有消耗任何内容。
Um, and the guard page
doesn't really consume any physical memory
records sitting high up in the
virtual address space,
so nothing is being consumed.
但这意味着他们展示了这种情况，例如，堆栈页面被映射了两次。
But that means that they're showing
this case, stack page,
for example is mapped twice.
它被映射到一个很高的地址，它直接由[这个]上衣下面的一件连衣裙映射。
It's mapped at a high
address and it's mapped directly
by one of the dresses
that below [this] top.
所以你可以这样做，这是所有很酷的事情的一个例子，你可以用页表来做，你可以映射一个物理地址两次，你不能映射一个物理地址，你知道它可以是一对一映射，一对多映射，多对一映射，所有这些事情都是可能的。
And so you can do, this
is one example of all the
sort of cool things, you can
do with page tables,
you can map a physical
address twice,
you cannot map a physical address,
you know it can be
one to one mapping, one to
many mapping, many to one mapping,
all that kind of stuff
is possible.
嗯，实际上它用的不是很多，但是有几个地方我们用到了这些招数。
Um, actually it doesn't really use
many of them, but there's a
couple places we use those tricks.
保护页面中的堆栈就是一个例子，这是xv6主要用来跟踪bug的一个很酷的技巧。
And there's the stack in
the guard page is one
example, of one of the
cool trick then xv6 uses
mostly to track down bugs.
我想提的第二件事是权限。
The second thing I wanted to
mention is that,
the permissions.
因此，例如内核文本，内核文本的页面被映射为R-X，这意味着您可以读取并执行它。
So, for example the kernel text,
the pages for the kernel text
are mapped
R-X, meaning you can
read it and execute it.
但是您不能写入内核文本，同样，这基本上是空的。
But you cannot write to
kernel text and again this
is basically devoid.
框，所以，我们提前捕捉到它们，内核数据当然需要能够被写入，所以它映射了读写，但是你不能执行内核数据页之外的指令。
Box so that, we catch
them early, kernel data of course
needs to be able to be
written to, and so it has
mapped read write,
but you cannot execute
out of kernel data
pages instructions.
嗯，所以执行位没有设置。
Um, so the execute bit is
not set.
这有意义吗。
Does that make sense.
嗯，我跳过了一两个问题，如果这些问题还没有回答，请你问一下。
Um I skipped one or
two questions,
so if these questions are still
not answered,
please ask them.
我们在聊天中有一个问题。
We have a question in the
chat.
我们是否有多个内核堆栈用于不同的进程，就像我们有n个堆栈用于n个进程一样。
Do we have multiple kernel stacks
for different processes like we have
n stacks for n processes.
回答是肯定的。
And answers yes.
因此，每个进程、每个用户进程都有一个对应的内核堆栈。
So every process every user process
has a corresponding kernel stack.
稍后我会看到这一点。
I will see that in a
little bit later.
好的，那么让我，嗯，萨米尔，继续。
Okay, so let me,
um, Samir,
go ahead.
嗯，那么另一个应用程序的虚拟内存映射到物理内存中未使用的空间或。
Um, so what's the virtual memory
of another application
map to somewhere in the physical
memory in the unused space or.
是的，一个非常好的观点，所以有一堆物理内存，对，这是空闲内存。
Yes, a very good point,
so there's a bunch of
physical memory,
correct, here's free memory.
嗯，现在这里有空闲的内存，对，我们实际上使用这些空闲内存来存储页表的页面，用户进程，以及你知道的用户级进程的文本和数据。
Um, now that's free memory
here to, right, and
we use that actually use
that free memory to basically
store pages of page tables,
user processes as well as you
know the text and data of
user level processes.
如果我们在很多用户进程上，在某个时候我们会用完空闲内存，然后基本上fork或exec会返回一个错误。
And if we are on
many many,
many user processes at some point
we'll run out of free memory,
and then basically fork or exec
will return an error.
但这意味着进程的虚拟空间比内核的虚拟空间小得多。
But that means that the
virtual space for processes are
much smaller than the virtual
space for the kernel.
嗯，虚拟空间的大小原则上是一样的，但是人口会少一些。
Well, the virtual spaces as
the same as the same
size in principle,
but it will be less populated.
然后让我们来看一些代码，我认为所有这些东西都变得更清楚了。
Then let me let's look at
some code,
and I think that all this
stuff becomes a bit more clear.
我只想要一些小东西，嗯，考虑到很多类似的东西，每个进程都有很大一部分内存映射到相同的位置，这是通过将其合并到一个映射或不映射的位置进行优化的。
I just want small thing,
um, is so given that
a lot of the like,
each process has a big part
of the memory map to the
same location is that optimized by
like consolidating that into one place
that mapping or no.
嗯，这很好，xv6不能做到这一点，就像页表实验中的挑战练习之一就是实际实现它一样。
Um, it's good,
xv6 does not do that,
like one of the challenge
exercises in the page table lab
is to actually implement that.
我明白了。真正的操作系统会做到这一点。
I see. The real operating system
would do that.
嗯。合乎道理。
Yeah. Makes sense.
问得好。
Very good question.
我想一旦你有了页表，你就会明白什么事情都是可能的。
I think you get a sense
of what all kinds of things
are possible,
once you have page tables.
好的，嗯，让我们做些平常的事情，一遍又一遍地引导xv6，你知道QEMU基本上是用来实现电路板的。
Okay, um,
so let's do the usual thing,
boot xv6 again
and again,
you know QEMU uses basically implementing
the board.
嗯，你知道让我们。哎呀，-gdb，上一次我们看了路由是如何正确发生的，然后我们到了main，然后基本上是内核，当其中一个函数调用kvminit时，它实际上为内核设置了地址空间。
Um, and you know let's. Oops,
-gdb,
last time we looked at
how the routing happens correct
and then we got to
main and then basically one
of the things that,
um, the kernel,
when one of the functions called
kvminit and that actually
sets up the address space for
the kernel.
我们在图片中看到，在上一张幻灯片中，您知道它看起来是什么样子，现在我们开始，CC编码它是如何实际设置的。
And so we saw in the
picture where in the previous slide,
what that you know looks like
and here we go,
CC code how it actually is
being set up.
还有为什么，等等，有些事不对劲。
And why, hold on, something's
not going.
如我所愿。
As I wanted to.
我找对目录了吗？
Am I the right directories.
等一下，我正在想办法解决我的问题。
Hold on a second here
while I'm trying to sort
out my problems.
那很好。
That is good.
我的意思是正确的目录，是的，我们想从主要发送一个中断，只是为了确保。
I mean the right directory,
yeah,
We want to send a
break from the main just
to make sure.
很好，然后是kvminit的中断点。
Good, and then a break point
at kvminit.
实际上我现在可以直接跳到它，下一个consoleinit printfinit，你知道，我们之前已经看到了，物理内存分配器。
Actually I can just step to
it now, next consoleinit
printfinit,
you know, we saw it before,
physical memory allocator.
你知道吗，发生了一些我意想不到的事情。
You know, something happens that I
not expecting.
这是怎么回事。
What is going on.
我们要在讲课前播放这段视频。这里，这就是实际打印的情况，嗯，好的。
We're gonna run this right before
lecture. Here,
that's what's going on actually printing,
um, okay.
嗯，有意思，好吧，再来一次，看看我能不能多看几眼。
Um, interesting,
okay one more time,
see if I can get lucky
more looks.
非常好。
Very good.
继续，希望它能到达那里，稍等片刻。很好，我们在kvminit，所以基本上我们现在是这个函数，在emacs缓冲区的右边，你可以看到它。
Continue, hopefully it will get there,
wait a little bit. Okay great
we're at the kvminit,
so basically we're now this function
here, on the right side in
the emacs buffer,
you can see it.
而且，我想我稍微修改了一下函数，我希望我是这样做的。
And,
I think I've modified function
slightly I hope I did.
嗯，我想我做到了，我们拭目以待，我们所知道的将步入函数。
Um, I think I did, we'll
see, and what we knew
is going to walk step into
the function.
给我布局拆分，这样更容易看到。
Give me layout split it's
easier to see.
这是您可以看到的第一件事，当前的这一部分实际上为顶级页面目录分配了一个物理页面。
And this is the first thing
that you can see, this section
of the current actually allocates a
physical page, for the top level
page directory.
然后将其置零，使得所有PTE条目都为零。
And then zeroes it
out so that all the PTE
entries are zero.
然后基本上开始在每个设备、IO设备中逐个映射。
And then basically starts mapping in
every device, IO device one
by one.
例如，UART0，它基本上开始将映射映射到内核地址空间，所以我们可以看到一个名为memlayout.h的文件，它基本上是将我从文档中向您展示的第31页转换成我们正在使用的一系列常量。
And so,
for example, the UART0, it
basically starts mapping maps that into
the kernel address space and so
we can look at a file
called memlayout.h, is basically translate
page 31 that I showed
you from the document into a
bunch of constants that we're using.
举个例子，这里说的是0x1000的地址。
And so,
for example here it says what
the address of 0x1000 is.
嗯，你有什么想法。
Um, do you ideas.
所以，你知道，我们基本上可以通过调用这个函数kvmmap将其映射到地址空间，我稍后会看到这个函数。
And so,
you know, we can basically
map it into the address space
by calling this function
kvmmap which I will look in
a second.
然后，在页表实验的第一个练习中，要求您实现一个名为vm_print的函数。
And then,
in the first exercise of
the page table lab,
you are asked to implement a
function called vm_print.
嗯，我也实现了它，我将跳过它，我们将看到，页表，内核页表，它是在对kvmmap的一次调用之后设置的，所以我要这样做。
Um, and I implemented it too,
and I'm going to step over
it and we'll see basically,
page tables,
kernel page table as it
is set up after that one
call to the kvmmap,
so I'm going to do that.
我们要打印一些东西。
And we're going to print
out something.
所以我们要看一下这里的输出，这是页表，它是顶层的物理地址，页面目录，所以实际上位于SATP中，或将位于SATP中的东西。
And so we're going to
look a little bit of
the output here,
so here's the page table that
is the
physical address of the top level,
page directory,
so the thing that actually sits
in satp,
or will sit in satp.
然后我们有了顶级页面的条目0，其中实际上有一个PTE条目。
And then we have
entry zero of the top
level page really has one
PTE entry in it.
嗯，那就是包含中级页表目录的物理地址。
Um, and that is the contains
the physical address for the middle
level page table directory.
中间页面级目录具有一个条目，即128。
The middle page level directory has
one entry namely 128.
它指向页表目录的底部，并且底部的页表目录具有用于物理页面的条目。
And that points to the bottom
of page table directory and the
bottom page table directory has the
entry then for the physical page.
您可以看到，实际上，您知道该底层的物理地址是0x1000，对应于uart0。
And you can see,
indeed that the physical address,
you know for that bottom level
is 0x1000
corresponding to uart0.
对，基本上虚拟地址转换成物理地址11100。
Right, so basically virtual address
1000 translates
to physical address 11100.
软弱的不确定的复核，这确实是完全合法的。
A weak unsure double-check,
this is indeed all legit.
根据嗯的不同，我们取那个地址0x100L，我们将移位12。
Vary by um,
and let's take that address 0x100L
and we're going
to shift 12.
嗯，这应该是，你知道的，那就是最高级别的27位。
Um, and that should be,
you know, that gives the top
level 27 bits.
我们移了9，所以我取0x100，A 1000101，我们可以9移，打印出来。
We shifted 9,
so I'm gonna take 0x100,
A 1000101 and we can
shift at 9,
print that.
那就是0x000，实际上把0x0打印成一个十进制数字，它将是128，好的。
And that is 0x000,
and actually print 0x0
as a decimal decimal number, it's
going to be 128, OK.
所以我们看到，实际上，你知道，这一切都是有意义的。
So we see actually sort of
you know it all sort of
makes sense.
我们还看到我在这里打印出了标志，您知道最下面的级别是读取、写入和有效，因为Valid是1。
We also see I printed out
the flags here,
and you know the bottom
level has read,
write and valid, because valid
is one.
有任何关于这个的问题吗。
Any questions about this.
好的，那么嗯。
Okay, so um.
内核基本上在继续，你知道，用这种方式设置整个地址空间。
The kernel basically proceeds, you know
doing setting up the whole address
space in this way.
因此，我们为虚拟IO调用了kvmmap，为客户端调用了kvmmap，用于单击。
And, so we've called
kvmmap for virtual IO, for the
CLINT, for the click.
映射内核文本，映射内核内存或内核数据，然后映射我们将在下周讨论的蹦床页面。
Maps the kernel text, maps
the kernel memory or kernel data,
and then the trampoline page that
we'll talk about next week.
嗯，所以实际上我们可以单步走一步，然后看看最终的页面目录是什么样子。
Um, and so in fact we
can single step through this and
then see what the final page
directory looks like.
嗯，那么下一个。
Um, so next next next next.
基本上，您知道设置蹦床，所以现在我们要打印完整的页表目录。
Basically, you know set the trampoline,
so now we're going to print
the complete page table directory.
嗯，你知道我们基本上看到很多PTE实际上正在设置中。
Um, you know we see basically
lot of PTE is actually
being setup.
嗯，我不会详细讨论，嗯，但是您知道，基本上是填写目录来实际创建虚拟映射，就像我们在上一张幻灯片中看到的那样。
Um, and I'm not going to
talk about in any detail,
um, but you know basically fills
out the
directory to actually create
virtual mapping that we
basically saw on the previous slide.
当我预料到我下一步要做的事情实际上要有趣得多的时候。
When I expect what I
wanna do next is actually
much more interesting.
是的我会的。
Yeah I'm gonna.
是的，我想去这里，实际上，我猜我可能已经这样做了，当时21岁，不，我21岁还可以，所以单步走不了。
Yeah I wanna go here,
actually, I guess maybe I already
did this, were 21,
no, I'm 21 okay so single
step not.
嗯，好吧，那太糟糕了，我已经过去了，但基本上是这样。
Um, OK that's too bad, I
got past it but basically.
嗯，让我再说一遍。
Um, let me let me
restart this.
我想要在kvminithart的转折点。
I wanna break point at kvminithart.
继续，我们现在在kvminithart，您在这里看到，基本上我们正在写入SATP寄存器，所以基本上内核将启用页表或硬MMU，嗯，基本上开始使用我们刚刚设置的页表。
And continue,
are now here at kvminithart,
and you see here,
basically that we're writing the
satp register,
so basically the kernel is going
to enable page table or
the hard, MMU,
um, to basically start using
the page table that we
just set up.
还有一个有趣的问题。
And one interesting question.
好的，所以他们确实又把版面拆分了，嗯，所以。
Okay, so they do have layout
split again,
um so.
这里的某个地方是正确的，这是一条指令，在执行这条指令后，发生了一些非常戏剧性的事情。
Somewhere here correct is going to
be,
here's the instruction,
in,
once, something really dramatic happens
after executing this instruction.
嗯，比方说，是的，我完全可以看到相同的指令，但是在这个范围内，一旦执行了这条指令，下一个要翻译的地址会发生什么。
Um, let's say yeah I can
see the same instruction exactly but
there's this this extent,
once this instruction is executed what
will happen with the next address
that's being translated.
嗯，在我们执行这条指令之前执行这条指令的时候，还没有启用页表，所以没有发生转换。
Well, at the point that
we execute this instruction before
executing this instruction,
there's no page tables enabled yet
so no translation happens.
但是下一次然后程序计数器被更新4。
But the next and then the
program counter is updated by 4.
然后执行下一条指令，并且将使用虚拟页、页表存储器来转换程序计数器。
And then the next instruction is
executed and the program counter will
be translated using the virtual page,
page table memory.
所以这是，你知道，思考这个问题的方式，这是一个戏剧性的时刻。
And so this is, you
know, the ways to think about this,
this is a dramatic moment.
因为基本上整个地址转换都开始启用，每个地址都不需要，可能潜在会有所不同。
Because basically the whole address translation,
they started to enable and
every address needs no maybe
potentially something different.
对，因为在我们运行您的物理地址之前，然后是页表，还没有安装，无论映射中有什么，现在都有了虚拟地址的新含义。
Right, because before we're running your
physical addresses,
then the page table,
haven't install, and whatever is in
the mapping,
now there's now the new meaning
of a virtual address.
嗯，这就是它的工作原理，你知道，这个实际工作的事实是值得注意的，因为就像下一条指令一样，下一个值是一个虚拟地址，而不是一个物理地址。
Um, and here's how this works
out, you know, the fact that
this actually works out is remarkable
because like the next instruction,
the next value is a virtual
address and not a physical address.
下一条指令将是这个，不管是0x1110。
The next instruction is going to
be this,
whatever 0x1110.
为什么这会成功呢。
And why does this work out.
原因是因为内核已经设置好了，我们可以标识页面映射。因此，在我们启用虚拟分页硬件之后，我们实际上知道这个翻译器将再次转换为相同的物理地址，因此我们实际上将结束执行写入指令，因为这实际上正是虚拟硬件编程所针对的指令和内存位置。
And the reason works out is
because the kernel is setup,
we can identity page mapping. So,
after we enable the virtual
paging hardware,
we actually know this translator will
translate again to the same physical
address and so indeed we'll actually
end up, you know,
executing the writing instruction, because that's
actually exactly the instruction,
the memory location that the virtual
hardware is programmed for.
那么这有意义吗。
So does this make sense.
同样，虚拟内存编程困难的一个原因是，一旦执行了这些SATP指令之一，您就在SATP寄存器中加载了页表，您的世界就完全不同了。
Again, one reason why programming virtual
memory is difficult is because once
you execute one of these satp
instructions you load a page table
in the satp register, your world
completely changes.
现在，每个地址都会使用您设置的页表进行转换。
And every address is now translated
with the page table, that you
set up.
那么，如果页表设置不正确会发生什么呢？
And so what happens if the
page table setup incorrectly.
你会怎么做，可能会发生什么。
What would you, what might happen.
任何想在聊天中回答或回答的人，可以等待。
Anybody who wants to
say that answered or answered in
the chat,
you can wait.
您可以覆盖内核数据。
You could override kernel data.
是的，你可以覆盖内核数据，还有其他可能发生的事情，是的，页面错误，你基本上是这样做的，映射可能是不正确的，基本上地址完全可以转换，所以内核可以，你知道，头件不会这样做，而使用内核时会停顿和死机。
Yeah you could overwrite kernel data
what else could happen,
yeah page fault,
you basically do,
the mapping may be incorrect and
basically the address can be translated
at all,
and so the kernel can, you
know, the headware won't do it
and use the kernel there stops
and panics.
这有意义吗？所以如果您的页表中有错误。
Does that make sense,
so if you get a bug
in your page tables.
你知道你会看到这些都是错误或崩溃。
You know you're going to see
these are errors or crashes.
所以，下一个实验室考试的原因之一，就是今晚分发或发布的那个页桌实验室，会很难，因为那些细菌会出现。
And so,
one reason that exam the
next lab,
that page table lab, that
will hand out or release tonight,
is going to be hard,
because those kind of bugs will
show up.
如果你不够小心，因为你还没有完全内化某些方面。
If you're not careful enough for
you haven't fully internalized some aspect yet.
你基本上会遇到内核崩溃，当你需要花一点时间、精力和侦察工作来基本上追踪发生这种情况的原因时，你会遇到一段艰难的时期。
And you're basically going to
get kernel crash and
you're gonna have a hard
time when you will take
a little bit of time
and energy and detective work
to basically track down why
that happened.
这只是，这只是虚拟内存编程的一部分。
And that's just the, that's just
part of like programming virtual memory.
因为它是如此强大的原始体，你知道，如果你弄错了，你会产生强大的后果。
Because it's such a
powerful primitive, you know, you
get it wrong,
you're gonna have
powerful consequences.
然而，另一方面是非常有趣的，所以我不想以负面的笔记结束，嗯，但所有这些都会让你真正理解什么是真正的虚拟内存，以及它能做什么。
Yet the other hand is great
amount of fun,
so I don't want to end
on a negative note,
um, but all that will give
you a real understanding of actually
what really virtual memory is and
what it can do.
好的，我想我的时间不多了，所以我就到此为止了，这样人们就有时间去下一节课或下一次活动了，但是如果你们还有什么问题，请稍等，然后问他们。
Okay I think I'm running
out of time so I'm
gonna stop here,
so people have time to
go to the next class or
next activity,
but if you have any questions
left, please hang on and
ask them.
我们周一见。
And, um,
we'll see you on monday.
祝你顺利完成SysCall实验室。
And good luck with finishing the
syscall lab.
嗯，嗨，我有一个关于Walk的问题，它说，在代码中，它返回的就像PTE上的第一个表。
Um, hi I have a question
about walk,
so it says and in
the code,
it returns the
like the first tables on PTE.
是的，是的，嗯，但是它是如何工作的，那么就像其他函数一样，当它们期望实际的PTE时，但是像物理地址一样。
Yeah right,
um, but but how does
it work,
then like the other functions when
they expect
the actual PTE,
but like the physical address.
基本上这会返回页表中的PTE条目，内核可以读取或写入页表条目。
Yeah basically this returns the PTE
entry in the page table,
and the kernel can read or
write page table entries.
嗯，现在你可以把值放到PTE里了。
Um, and so now you can
stick values into the PTE.
所以也许我可以画一幅有帮助的画。
And so maybe I can draw
a picture that is helpful.
让我们看看。
Let's see.
所以也许我们有一个页面目录。
So maybe we have a
page directory.
而且，你知道，这个行进代码，所以页面目录中有512 PTE。
And, you know, this walk code,
so the page directory has
512 PTE in it.
在接近零的位置，这里是511，基本上函数的作用是返回一个指向其中一个PTE的指针。
Near zero,
here's 511 and basically what the
function does it returns a pointer
to one of these PTEs.
这只是一个虚拟地址，它指向那个特定的PTE。
And so that's just a
virtual address,
and it points to that
particular PTE.
现在内核可以，你知道的，通过向它写入值，来操纵那个PTE。
And now the kernel can, you
know manipulate that PTE, by whatever
writing values to it.
就像某个物理地址。
Like some physical address.
也许有一些权限，或者进入它的前十位。
Maybe with some permissions or
into it for the top
bottom ten bits.
然后基本上更新页表目录，然后在稍后将数据加载到SATP中时更新页表目录。
And then basically updates the page
table directory,
and then later on when you
load data into satp.
现在，这一影响将会生效。
Now that affect that change will
go into effect.
这有意义吗。
Does that make sense.
是的，这是有道理的，我想我只是搞不懂，为什么它要一直转到第三个页表，然后只返回第一个PTE。不，退货实际上是最底层的。
Yeah that makes sense, I guess
I just confused like why does
it do the work of going
all the way to the third
page table and then only return
the first
PTE. No, return is actually the
bottom one.
实际上，让我小心点，如果它通过了n级，从2级开始，然后到1级，再到0级。
Actually, let me be careful,
If, you know, it goes through
the n levels, started level 2
and then go to level 1,
again a level 0.
如果分配位设置和级别不存在，将创建中间页表目录。
If the alloc bit set
and level doesn't exist,
it will create the intermediate page
table directory.
把它清零，然后继续找。
And zero it out and then
keep going to look.
所以，你总是落在最底层。
So, you always end up
on the bottom PTE.
如果没有设置分配，你会在第一个PTE停止，这是没有价值的。
If alloc not set, you stop
at the first PTE, that doesn't
have value.
好的，这就说得通了，这是最后一张了，实际上会有好的，好的，谢谢。
Okay, that makes sense,
this is the last one,
the actual on gonna have
okay okay,
thank you.
还有其他问题吗。
Any other questions.
嗯，所以我有一个问题，在我们将内核的两个虚拟地址映射到物理地址之前，基本上一切都是有意义的。
Um, so I have a question,
basically everything made sense until
we mapped the virtual addresses
two of the kernel to
the physical addresses.
所以我的理解是，每个进程都会有自己的页表，这也是一个三级表，它将其虚拟地址包装到物理地址，但然后我们将内核虚拟地址映射到物理地址，我认为我们没有考虑到实际的三个地址。
So my understanding is that
each process will have its
own page table,
which is also a three level
three which wraps its virtual addresses
to physical addresses,
but then we map the kernel
virtual addresses to physical addresses, I
don't think we accounted for the
actual three of them.
内核的虚拟地址或其他进程将拥有其虚拟地址的位置。
Virtual addresses of the kernel
or where other processes will have
their virtual addresses.
我很抱歉虚拟地址就像可视的桌树和。
And I'm sorry virtual addresses like
the visual table trees and.
页表树在物理内存中指向的任何内容。
Whatever the page table tree points
at in the physical memory.
是的，所以你又回来了，这是关于内核的幻灯片，基于地址的虚拟内核地址空间，所以当内核分配proc时。
Yeah, so yeah so so you're
back, this is slide with kernel,
address based virtual kernel address
space and so when the kernel
allocates proc.
UM和该特定进程的页表，在这里它们将被分配到内存之外，内存还没有被使用。
Um and page tables for
that particular process they're going
to be allocated
out of memory here, memory is
not being used yet.
内核将进行编程，我们可能会为页表分配几个页面，脱离通常的问题过程，并填充PTE。
And the kernel is going to
program, we'll probably allocate a
couple pages for the page table,
off the usual problem process and
will fill in the PTEs.
在内核运行该进程的某个时刻。
And at some point when the
kernel runs that process.
它将加载为该页表或基本上页表分配的那些页的路由、物理地址，然后将其构建到SATP寄存器中。
It will load the route,
physical address for those pages that
is allocated for that page table
or basically page table then built
into the satp register.
在这一点上，处理器将使用内核为该特定进程构造的虚拟地址库运行。
And at that point the processor
will run with the virtual address
base that the kernel constructed for
that particular process.
嗯，所以内核为进程释放了一些内存，然后在理论上虚拟空间和内核一样大，但在现实中，虚拟空间对进程来说和内核一样大。这真的不是一个虚拟地址空间布局的图片，他们通常的水平过程，再一次，它从零到MAXVA。
Um, so the kernel gave up
some of its memory,
for processes,
and then but then the virtual
space in theory is as big
for the process as
the kernel,
but in reality. It's really not
have a picture with the layout
of a virtual address space with
their usual level process and again
it goes from zero to MAXVA.
就像内核地址空间一样，它基本上有自己的一组页表来映射这些趋势，因为转换，内核设置。
In the same way as the
kernel address space does and it's
basically has his own set of
page tables to map those trends
due to translation,
the kernel setup.
但是我们不能实际使用所有的MAXVA虚拟。
But we can't actually use all
of the MAXVA virtual.
不，我们不能。
No, we cannot.
如果我们的内存用完了。
If we run out of memory.
因此，许多进程比所有虚拟地址空间都要小得多，这是正确的。
So many of the processes are
much much smaller, correct, than
all of the virtual address space.
我看到了思考。
I see thinking.
我有一个简短的问题，嗯，你能不能回到行走规则上来，好的，好的，当然可以。
I've got a quick question,
Um, could you go back to
the walk code,
yeah yeah absolutely.
嗯，这是我最喜欢的功能之一。
Um, it's one of my
favorite functions.
嗯，所以我猜，有一件事我很困惑，那就是在你写到SATP寄存器之后，内核甚至可以直接访问物理地址吗，所以在它正在转换的代码中，你看起来就像是将Pay设置为物理地址，但是如果设置了SATP，那不会被解释为虚拟地址吗？
Um, so I guess, one
thing I'm confused about is after
you write to the satp
register can the kernel even access
physical addresses directly,
so it looks like in the
code that it's converting you know
like pay was being set to
a physical address,
but if satp is set,
won't that be interpreted as
a virtual address.
是的，嗯，所以，嗯，好的，让我们来看看哈提尼特。
Yeah, um,
so, um okay so let's look
at hartinit.
KVM，所以内置在内核地址空间中。
kvm, so built in kernel address space.
内核页表(最初是虚拟物理地址)被转换为物理地址，并且该地址实际上被写入到SATP寄存器中。
The kernel page table,
Initially, the virtual physical, address
is translated to a physical
address and that's actually written into
the satp register.
嗯，在这一点上，您知道我们使用的是我们在此之前构建的地址空间，这个kvminit。
Um, and at that point you
know we're running with the address
space that we've constructed right before
here, this kvminit.
给了我一张地图，基本上就是给每一个地址打电话，每一页都在这个范围内。
And gave me a map is
basically nothing else than calling
walk for every address where
every page and at the range.
那么你的问题是什么，嗯，我想，如果你在说了SATP之后，步行仍然是一样的工作方式。是啊，怎么了。
And so what was your question,
Um I guess,
it's does walks still work
the same way if you
call it after satp
is said. Yeah why.
为什么我们要找出它不能解决在身份映射中设置的内核的原因。
Why we work out the reason
it won't work out the kernel set up in identity mapping.
好的，对，对。
Ok, right, right.
非常重要，非常好的问题，很多事情碰巧都解决了，因为实际上身份映射已经设置好了。
Very important,
very good question,
a lot of things just happened
to work out because actually the
identity mapping is set up.
我明白了，我想这是有道理的，我有一个简短的问题。
I see I think that
makes sense,
I have a quick question.
其中为所有进程存储SATP寄存器。
Where the satp register stored
for all of the processes.
每个核心只有一个SATP。
There only one satp per core.
嗯，但是在每一个程序结构中。
Um, but in every proc structure.
如果你看一下pro.h。
If you look at proc.h.
嗯，有一个指向页表的指针，你是你是。好的，有道理。
Um, there is,
a pointer to the page table,
you're you're. okay, makes sense.
另外，关于三个页表就像三个表，可以完成完整的地址，甚至可以帮助您获得一些东西的完整地址，我想这比拥有一个巨大的页表有什么更好的地方，我并没有真正完全理解什么。这是一个很好的问题，原因是在自由级别的页面表中，您可以将许多条目留空。
And also with regards to the
three page tables are like the
three tables that can complete the
full address and help you get
a full address for even something,
how does how is that better
I guess than than having one
giant page table I didn't really
fully understand what. A great question,
the reason is because in the
free level page table,
you can leave a lot of
entries empty.
因此，例如，如果您将顶层页表中的条目直接留空，则根本不必为这些条目创建中层页表或底层页表。
So, for example if you leave
the entry in the top level
page table directly empty,
you don't have to create middle
level page tables or bottom level
page tables at all,
for those entries.
这意味着整个虚拟地址空间的一大块(条带)根本不需要任何映射。
Like this means like a big
[swath] of the whole virtual address
space doesn't have to have any
mapping at all.
好的，好的，你那里没有桌子，它根本不存在。
Okay, okay,
you don't have the table there,
it just doesn't exist.
我明白了，基本上这些块是按数量和类型分配的，好的，这是有道理的，是的，你基本上是从三页开始，三页，一幅。
I see,
basically allocating these chunks on demand
as volumes and types,
OK that makes sense,
yeah you're starting basically with three
page three pages namely,
one from the top level one
for, one intermediate one frame,
one bottom level.
然后，随着操作的进行，您将创建更多的页表目录。
And then,
as you go you create more
page table directories.
好的，好的，太好了，太感谢你了。
Okay, okay,
Cool, thank you so much.
不用谢。
You're welcome.
还有什么问题吗。
Any more questions.
我很抱歉我有另一个，它真的很小，但是我在vm.c的43，41行，嗯，它说，不，Mignt 43，我的错，嗯，它说物理停止减去(Uint64)etext，但不会，不会复习一下，我想我们不应该接触的记忆，我不知道这是否有意义，但是，会不会这样。
I'm sorry I have another one,
it's really really small but
I'm in the vm.c
on line 43, 41,
um, it says that,
no, mignt 43,
my bad,
um, it says physical stop minus (uint64)etext
but wouldn't that,
would not go over the,
I guess the memory that
we shouldn't touch, I don't
know if that makes sense,
but,
Would that go.
我想我不明白，他们会不会检查一下空闲内存。
I guess I don't understand, would
they go over free memory.
不，我不这么认为，所以KERNBASE是0x8000，对，所以这是内存的开始。
No, I don't think so,
so KERNBASE is 0x8000, right
so that's the beginning of memory.
内核在那里，基本上，这是一个大小，对，所以etext是内核的最后一个地址，减去KERNBASE，它基本上给出了内核的大小，im，以字节为单位。
Kernel sits there in,
basically,
this thing is a size,
right, so etext is the
last address of the kernel,
subtract KERNBASE, that basically gives
you the size of the kernel,
im, in byte.
而且，你知道，我不知道它有多少，但它就像你知道的60或90页或类似的东西。
And, you know, I don't know how
much it is, but it's
like you know 60 or 90
pages or something like that.
嗯，所以这个映射基本上是内核的文本部分。
Um, and so this map
is basically the text part
of the kernel.
嗯，还有嗯，还有足够的空间。
Um, and um,
and there's enough space.
嗯，那里有足够的DRAM来映射内核文本。
Um, there's enough DRAM there to
map that the kernel text.
我不确定，我在回答你的问题，但是。我想我明白了。
I'm not sure, I'm answering
your question,
but. I think I think
I understand.
我以为etext是从别的地方开始的，好的，我想我现在明白了，谢谢，所以etext基本上是最后一条指令，内核最后一条指令的地址。
I thought that etext starts
somewhere else, okay I think I
understand now,
thank you,
So etext basically the last instruction,
the address of the last instruction
of the kernel.
好的，好的。
Okay, okay.