Sound check, can everybody hear me?
Yep, yep. Okay okay,
so welcome to the next lecture
in the 6.S081, wherever you
are, particular,
I hope that the folks on
the west coast or in Florida
and Alabama do OK, you know, all
the terrible circumstances there.
Um, so,
um, the topic for today,
is virtual memory, particularly we're
going to talk about page tables
we'll return to this topic
few times,
there will be multiple
[] lectures.
Maybe just start off and,
you know, get our question and answer
going again,
I would like to ask you
a little bit,
what do you remember from，
about virtual memory from 6.004
maybe from 6.033,
if you're taking that.
I'll tell you, my own sort
of view on virtual memory,
which is when I took it,
to first learned about it,
learned about it as
a student, I thought it
was pretty straightforward,
you know how hard could
it be,
it's a table that maps virtual
addresses to physical addresses.
You know, maybe a
little more complicated,
but you know not that
complicated, only when you start
programming with it.
I should really learn, virtual
memory is tricky and fascinating,
and very powerful.
So, hopefully in the
next couple of lectures, in
the next couple of labs,
you'll know appreciate
virtual memory from that perspective.
We will ask a couple
people here are online, you know
what do you remember about virtual
memory from either 6.004 or
6.033 taking it.
Again, I'm just gonna call some
names and you know,
share your memories. About the
Adela Yang.
Sorry, what's the question? What
do you remember about
virtual memory from maybe 6.004
or 6.033
if you have taken that.
It uses like, offset to save
on like, remembering virtual address
to physical address mappings.
OK, how about Abrams Caldera.
Abrams, are you online?
Yeah, my memory is that
it uses like,
it's a way of one protecting
the physical hardware by
kind of [] representation of
it and then you just
have some virtual address things like,
at least 44 bit, that map
some physical address,
that's usually I think 16
bits were in fact.
Okay, good, how about Bibic Pendant.
What I remember was,
um, you can have
each process has a separate
address space.
And,
the memory management unit or I
mean some other technique can be
used to map,
the virtual addresses of the
address space of each of the
processes to the physical,
physical address.
And the virtual address, the
lower bits
are kind of the same,
so that,
the the mapping is in blocks,
which helps with performance.
Wiseley Wu.
Yeah, I guess what I
remember most is that virtual address
allows us to,
yeah, protect physical addresses from
each process.
And we can use some clever
manipulation, so that the bits that
correspond to the physical address can
be used somehow in the virtual
addresses as well.
Wilson Spearmen.
Yeah, I remember it's really fundamental
to isolation,
because every process can basically pretend
that it has its own
sort of memory to use.
Good good well so clearly,
that's awesome,
the clear, two themes here
correct, one is you know
there's some form of mapping and
the mapping is helpful in sort
of achieving isolation,
this is exactly the reason, we're
talking about virtual memory isolation.
So, what
we'll see is that in
the next, in the next couple of lectures,
in particular, when we start programming
with virtual memory,
really get an in-depth understanding
of what its power is.
And, so to get a
sense, that you know, this is
the first lecture and mostly focusing
on the mechanisms for virtual memory,
and then later we can see
how we can use these mechanisms
to achieve, you know, cool tricks.
So the topic for today, or
agenda for today, the plan
is sort of three part.
First, I'm going to talk about the
address spaces, as some of you
mentioning in your.
Just what we need.
Just mentioned just briefly mentioned,
in response to the question,
I'm going to talk about the
paging hardware paging hardware.
And I'm going to focus of
course on the paging hardware of
the RISC-V.
But basically every processor, modern processor
has some form of paging hardware
sort of,
if you will, the
default mechanism for actually
supporting virtual memory.
And then,
the last part of
the lecture is going to
walk through some xv6
virtual memory code.
And, layout of kernel address space and
user address spaces.
So that's the main plan.
Okay, so,
if we answers, you know, []
you mentioned,
in response to this question,
you know,
one driving reason to have
virtual memory is because you can
use it to achieve isolation,
if you set up the page
tables correctly and program them correctly,
then you can in principle
achieve strong isolation.
And so this is to remind us again,
you know what we want with
from isolation,
let's say, you know a
standard picture,
we have some user applications
like shell,
you know cat, you know, all the util
things, that you've built in
lab one, and we have
the kernel, the kernel sitting below,
the operating system sitting in
kernel space.
And you know what we like
to do is sort of have
you know boxes around these
applications, so that they can't
really affect each other and similar
we want them to be completely
independent of the kernel,
the operating system, so that if
an application does something either accidentally
bad or maliciously bad,
that doesn't really affect the
operating system.
So that's our goal and the
particular aspect of the problem that
we want to focus on today
is the memory side of things,
so we really want to
focus on memory isolation.
And by default,
if we don't do anything,
we don't really have memory isolation,
because if you think about
it, there's going to be one
RISC-V board that I showed
you last week,
it has a memory,
a bunch of DRAM chips,
and the in the DRAM
chips, the code for
these applications
is stored, somewhere in memory
is the kernel, text data stack
everything, somewhere in memory used to
shell if the shell is running,
somewhere in memory the cat program.
So, there's one physical memory,
you know starting from zero to
big, big address,
depending how much memory we
have, really have in our
machine and in that physical
memory all these programs must be present.
Otherwise, you know, the processor
can't even execute their instructions.
This is what the risk, you
know clearly here is, that let's
say, let's make a little bit
simplistic, let's say the shell,
you know sits for
address 0 to address 200,
two thousand, 1000 to 2000.
And let's say you know,
you know whatever cat has a
programming error,
it loads, you know, in register a0.
Let's say, loads the 1000
address basically corresponding to the
start of the shell and then
you know by accident,
executes the instruction 'sd $7, (a0)'.
Which has the effect of that,
basically it writes the value 7
to the address 1000 and so
it would be scribbling over, you
know the basically the memory image,
that belongs to shell.
And so,
we're certainly not, certain
would break isolation, and be
quite undesirable.
And so we want something that
basically really separates these memories from
the different programs from each other,
so that things like that just cannot happen.
So one way, to do that,
is an idea that's you
know typically called address spaces.
And the basic idea is straightforward,
what we wanna do, is basically
give every application including the kernel,
its own address space.
And so we can think about
this like, we use cat running,
you know, it has an address
space starting at 0, you know
to whatever maximum value, you know
shell run has an address space, its
own address space,
also starting at address 0,
going to some value,
you know the kernel has
its own address space.
OS has its own
address space.
And so,
one example when cat you know
refers to, we go back to
our example of the previous slide
where we did,
whatever 'st 7, (a0)',
and let's say in a0, there's value 1000.
You know if cat execute
the instruction,
it will write to the address 1000,
but it is its own address 1000,
it's not,
the address of the 1000 of the shell.
So basically, every program runs with
its own address space, has its
own value and those addresses are
completely independent.
You know this notion of
different address spaces,
cat doesn't really have an ability to
even refer to an address, that
actually belongs to the shell.
And so that sort of the
game that were the end goal
that we'd like to achieve, because
it's going to provide us with
strong isolation, because you know it's
just not possible for cat to
refer to any other memory that
is not, you know, its own.
And so, our goal now basically
sort of figure out how to
multiplex if you will all these
different address bases on a single
physical memory,
because in the end,
we only have a bunch of DRAM chips.
were you know, ram
chips were the memories locate.
And so, um, and so I sort of plan.
Okay, yeah, Amiar,
you have a question, go ahead.
So I'm wondering,
in the configuration of the
physical hardware,
there's only so much space and
the virtual memory layout,
there's also a max virtual address,
by design is the virtual address
made to be small enough.
No, not necessarily,
you know the virtual address
space could be bigger than
the physical memory,
the physical memory could be bigger
than the virtual address space
and we'll see in a second
how it all can happen and
it's actually going to []
about, as we'll see with page tables,
that's extremely flexible.
So, is it, is it
possible that like the physical
memory gets exhausted,
because so many processes use
all their virtual space.
Yeah, that's certainly possible and we'll
see in the second, how,
for example you know you have
a bunch of big applications that
each have big page tables,
they allocate a lot of memory,
you know some point you run
out of memory.
I see,
thanks. And so where does this
show up xv6, anybody.
You, you sure,
touched on a little bit
in the syscall lab, that
you're currently doing,
where page is allocated.
Or, you do the syscall lab,
you finished it in one
part of the syscall lab,
printing how much free memory address.
Kalloc? Yeah, kalloc, right,
for kalloc, have a list of free pages,
if that list of free pages
is empty or runs out at some point.
Then, you know, kalloc is going
to return a null pointer, and
hopefully the operation system does something sensible,
that basically propagated back to the
user application saying like well, you
know no more memory for you
or no more memory in total, nobody.
Ok? Then just a job for OS
to handle those cases gracefully where
basically generally means propagating an error
message to user application.
Okay, good.
So how do you implement these
address spaces,
you know how basically multiplex
all these address spaces across a
single physical memory and the most
common approach and a very flexible
approach is to use pagetables.
The idea is,
this is a hard work support,
so this is implemented in hardware
by the processor or by a
unit called the memory management unit,
so the picture that you should
have your head is, you know, the CPU
that executes instructions, whatever are,
you know, are store instruction that
was you know 'sd $7, (a0)',
also executes those kind of
instructions and you know when
it executes one of their
store instruction, load instruction,
whatever anything that actually has
an address.
You know, that address we're going
to think about it as
a virtual address,
so it's not a physical address,
it's a virtual address.
And so,
for example the value in a0
that we're using here,
yeah, say that's 1000,
0x1000 data is a
virtual address and virtual addresses basically
routed through something what's called
the memory management unit,
and the memory manager unit
translates into a physical address.
And that physical address then was
actually used to index into memory.
And load whatever value or
store whatever value needs to be written there.
And so the CPU from
the CPU point of view,
it always issues,
every instruction that issues,
once the MMU use, enabled
our virtual addresses.
And to translate these virtual addresses
to physical addresses, basically,
MMU has a table.
And you know virtual address
on one side, physical address
on one side,
the other side, for example here is
our entry for 1000 and maybe
that maps to whatever,
you know, 0x whatever you're
making something up with like
something value,
somewhere in physical memory.
So this mapping between virtual and
physical, it's quite flexible.
And so on one side,
we have the virtual address
of the other side of
the physical addresses.
Typically, you know this mapping itself
is also stored in memory.
And so the CPU has some
register that basically points to,
that contains the physical
address of where the page table is stored
somewhere, in basically the page
table or just map somewhere stored
in physical memory.
Let's say, you know,
whatever, address 10,
basically this register which is
called on the RISC-V satp.
You know stores the address 10
and so, that the CPU
can tell the memory manager units
where to find, you know, basically the map
to actually translate virtual to
physical addresses.
And then the basic idea
is to give every application
it's own map.
So cat is going to have it's map.
So every map, it's own...
Yeah, [Big Ben], go ahead.
So the MMU,
you said it doesn't necessarily store
the mapping.
So does it just,
just do the translation like
it will read the memory
and do the translation,
but not necessarily
store the mappings.
That's exactly the right picture that
you should have your head.
But every map, okay, so the
map itself stored memory,
the MMU just basically walks or
looks into the map and we'll
see in a second, you know,
the map is slightly more complicated
than I just draw here.
So every app has
its own, its own map.
Right, and that map basically defines
its address space.
And so when with the CPU or
when the operating system switches the
CPU from one process from one
application to another application,
it also switches the content
of this satp register to store
the root of the map of
the appropriate process.
And so in that way,
basically you know multiple applications to
run on the
CPU, every time we switch
between from one application to the
next application,
we also switch the satp
register to point to the appropriate
map for that application.
And in that way,
basically, virtual addresses you know
for cat are translated differently,
than the virtual addresses for the
shell, because you know each one
of them has their own map.
That makes sense?
Okay, so we, this is the
basic plan and the way I've
drawn or gonna explain it so
far it's pretty naive,
and unreasonable.
Yeah, David, go ahead.
I'm sorry,
so, the you said the
satp register gets modified
for the process, I am guessing
the value of for
satp register for each process
is stored by the kernel.
Yes yes,
the kernel is writing satp register,
in fact writing or reading,
particular writing the satp register is
a privilege instruction.
So user application cannot just
update the page map register, and
say like I want to run
with this page map now.
Because, that would violate isolation.
So it's only the kernel, only
code in kernel mode can actually
update it.
I see.
Okay, so as I said this
picture is pretty naive,
you know one thing I
haven't really said anything about how
this actually map works.
And, you know the way I've
drawn out seems to indicate a
basically for every virtual address,
you have an entry in the map.
And if you do that,
how big would that be on RISC-V.
Anybody, how many addresses are there on
the RISC-V in principle, or
how big, how many addresses go
to registers store.
Registers are 64 bit wide,
so how many addresses.
Anybody, I know, so insulting your
intelligence by asking these questions about.
We have some answers in the
chat, like two to the 64.
I didn't see the chat, sorry,
yeah, two to 64. Lets see
if I can actually pop off the chip,
so I could see it.
Yeah, two to 64, thank you.
Alright, so this table would be gigantic.
In fact, we know
all memory would be consumed
by just having the table
so that seems unreasonable.
And so in fact you
know that's not how things work.
In fact, going to
in two steps, to actually, how
it actually works in RISC-V.
Step one is don't play
the game per address,
but do per page.
So you translate a page at
a time and a page
on RISC-V is 4 kilobytes.
Which is a four, 4096 bytes.
This is pretty common,
almost all processors, you know, use
roughly page size 4 kilobytes, or support
page size 4 kilobytes.
And so now again, translation works
slightly differently,
so if here, we have our virtual address.
Amazingly, we split it in two pieces,
an index and an offset.
And so the offset is basically
the byte within the page.
And so when we do,
when the MMU does
the translation it takes the index,
indexes into the map that
gives you some physical page number,
you know in memory.
The physical page number that
points to some physical page of 4096 bytes.
And then the offset part,
basically indexes into that physical page,
so, for example, the offset is, you know, 12.
then you know there are
the 12th entry of that
page is actually used.
A lot of people a lot
of you entered in the message
in the, in response to the question,
there's always some scheme of taking
an offset and adding that to
the base of the page to obtain the actual
memory, physical memory location, where
a value store, where value will be loaded too.
And one of the interesting things
about the RISC-V is and
this is in response to some
questions again,
somebody asked look the physical
or virtual addresses are 64 bits.
Which makes totally sense correct,
because the RISC-V is
64-bit register.
But in fact on the
RISC-V processor, that we're using,
not all of the 64 bits
actually used,
namely, the top 25 are
actually not used at all.
So that limits the
size of a virtual address, that
limits the size of a virtual
address space 2 to the power of 39,
which is roughly 512 gigabytes.
So, of course you
know later version of the
processor, might support bigger address spaces
and that is necessary and could then
be done, for example, some of those 25 bits
that are basically unused, could be used to
build bigger virtual address spaces.
So, and so in the index
and, you know, where 39 bits left,
you know as the virtual address
27, 27 bits are
index and we'll see you in
a second, why they are 27
are index and then
the 12 are offset.
And you know there has to
be 12, because 2 to the
power 12 is 4096.
So that's virtual addresses on the
RISC-V. Physical addresses as you
can see here are actually 56
bits wide.
So the physical memory,
can be bigger than the
single virtual address space.
But it's limited to 2 power to 56,
you know most boards probably, you know,
don't support 2 to the power
of 56 physical memory, because
a gigantic amount of physical memory.
But in principle the
board could, you know,
if you could manufacture it
support two to the power
of 56 physical memory.
And so in this scheme,
then 56 bit for
the physical address, 44 are basically
the physical page number,
the PPM, and 12 are the
offset that are inherited directly from
the virtual address.
Does that make sense.
So, um, you know stop for a second
here. So you collect your thoughts,
the only point I wanted to
make here is that this material is important,
so just ask questions,
the details matter,
and it will be a large
part of you,
you really need to understand all
this stuff,
to be able to basically
do lab, the next lab, the page table lab.
Yeah, Amiar, go ahead, please.
If you can go back
one slide, I have the screen is unclear.
Which one,
the page table slide? Yeah.
This one? Um, no.
The most recent one, but it
also doesn't really matter,
yeah, this is perfect,
thank you, so I'm wondering this
4096 byte range which we've called
a page, is that assigned as
a continuous chunk in memory.
Yes, that's a continuous physical,
continuous range of 4096 bytes
including memory.
I see, and then. You know, the map,
granularity of 4096 bytes.
Okay, and then 12, the
offset, like 2 to the 12 is 4096,
so that's sufficient to cover each
of the chunks? Yeah, each byte in the page.
And where does the 56 come
from, in the diagram, I could
follow up until then,
but I didn't get where
that came from.
The designers cook it up.
So the hardware designers decide
how big you know physical
addresses, basically for whatever board
they want to design,
and so the RISC-V
designers who decided at 56,
that physical addresses were a
good idea.
And usually the way they
come up with these numbers is
they look at technology trends.
And say like, well, we want
to be able for the next
sort of 5 years,
you know, we don't predict the physical
memory will be ever bigger than
2 to the power 56.
Probably they think it won't be
bigger than something much smaller,
but then you know give them
sort of leeway, you know,
in case you know their predictions wrong,
they pick a slightly bigger number.
Is that makes sense.
Yeah, thanks. Yeah, a lot of people
ask about this.
Anybody else, who raised a hand,
I think there's a bunch of
people asking questions and unfortunately my
zoom doesn't show its more than
two people raised hands just multiple
people are raising their hands.
So you please jump in, if
you have a question.
Okay. I have a question,
yeah, go ahead. So if the virtual
memory is up to 2 to the power of 27
and the physical memory is
up 2 to the power of 56, right,
so, we could have,
like we could have multiple processes
that could exhaust all their virtual
memories without
using up all the physical memory,
right? That's correct.
That's absolutely correct.
Okay. I have a question, too.
Yeah, go ahead.
So this 56 for the physical
address is that the,
the number of possible memory locations.
I don't think it's the
number of bits because the 64 bit machine.
That 56 could go up to 64,
but they just choose it to have just 56.
That's correct,
one way to think about it,
then they only have to run
56 wide on the board as opposed to 64.
I see, I see.
Okay. I also have a question,
um, so kind of, could you
go back one slide maybe. Yeah.
so from the CPU,
we go through the MMU and
then to the memory, but
where, where here is the distinction
for different processes, because like each
process, like process, like the shell
process has something at address like 0x1000,
and then the ls process
also has something at address 0x1000, so
we need to translate those to
different physical, so. Yeah, the satp register,
contains, the register who contains the
address of which map to use.
So ls runs with its own map,
you know cat with its own map.
OK, so each process will have
its completely own map. Yeah.
Makes sense, thank you.
In fact, there's a great a
way to the next,
point, so if every process has its own map.
You know how big is this
map, like that I've drawn here.
Well, that map is 2 to
the power 27 entries, correct,
and that's pretty big.
And I would fill physical
memory reasonable quickly,
if every process exactly how
to complete you know populated map.
And then there's gigantic, means that
every process is very big,
and so in fact this is
not the way hardware actually
stores page tables,
you can think about it
conceptually as an array,
you know going from zero to 2 power 27,
but actually is not what happens in practice.
In practice,
it's a multi-level structure that
here's actually the real RISC-V page table.
Structure and what the hardware implements.
And so what happens with the
27 bits that we started earlier, the index.
It's actually split in three
9 bit numbers.
And the first, the top nine
bits, are used to index into
the top level page table,
directory as they are called.
And so, then one directory,
you know one of these guys,
you know is 4096 bytes, 4096 bytes,
just like the page size.
A PTE entry, one of
the entries in the thing is 64 bytes,
64 bit, I mean, sorry, like the register
with so eight bytes.
And so there's going to mean
that you do 4096
divided by eight, means there are
512 entries in one of those
directory pages.
So basically what happens is
like the satp points to the top
root directory,
we take the top level 9
bits index into the page directory.
And now gives us a new
physical page number.
And that physical page number
is the page directory for the next level,
so when we use the
next level index,
to index into that page
directory and then you know
and so forth,
you know, we'd like to find
one we get the bottom level
page directory.
And that basically gives us the entry,
that maps the virtual address
to physical address.
So in some sense,
it's very similar to where I
showed in the previous slide except
they're basically the index happens in
three steps instead of one step.
And this is advantage,
the main advantage of this scheme
is that large parts of the
address space are not being used,
you don't have to have any
page table entries for that.
For example,
let's say you have a new
address space.
That has only one page like
the bottom page.
Yeah, 4096.
And no other pages in
the address space,
so only addresses 0 to 4095(6)
are actually mapped.
How many page table entry or
page table directories you need
to map that particular page.
Well, you need one of the top, correct.
And you need basically value in
that entry for zero,
the top level 9 bits,
you know zero, zero so you
need an entry for 0.
So that means you need one
middle level entry,
you know that basically corresponds
to the next,
you know nine 0 bits and
then one entry for the next
nine zero bits.
So basically we get away with
three page directories.
In our previous scheme on the
previous slide correct,
we have 2 to the power
27 entries and now we basically
have to have 3 times whatever
512 entries that we're done.
That's the main reason why
you know the actual hardware
has this hierarchical,
multi-level tree scheme.
Any questions about this, because it's
pretty important.
Samir, go ahead.
So my question is as since
the PPM number from each page
table is 44 bits.
And the second say the middle
table resides on the virtual memory.
Where do we get the missing 12 bits from.
Well, the final twelve bits okay
so good good good,
so you're saying these 44, correct.
Yes. What is going on with that,
while all page, all page directories
or page line,
and so they basically they're a
physical page number is 44 plus
twelve, twelve zero bits.
And so what actually happens if
we look at these PTE entries,
they all have the same sort of form,
if you look at one of these guys.
There are 44 bits,
there are 12 bits 0,
so that gives us a
44 plus 12 is 56, so
that gives us a physical address,
and so that means there's 64 bits,
there's actually some bits left
there not being used and
in fact the bottom 12
bits were basically or the
bottom 10 definitely bottom based
on not used at all, and
in fact the paging hardware
stores or stores a bunch
of flags that control the
translation and we'll talk about
those flags in the second.
And with their
to control the translation and
they're stored basically in the bottom
10 bits.
It also means that, you
know, if you add these two
up that's 54 bits,
basically there's 10 bits left.
There are unused, those 10 bits
are again,
you know for future growth,
so at some point we might
have a new type of
RISC-V processor, that will have a
slightly different structure page tables,
and it might actually have bigger
than 44 bits for the physical
page number. OK? Thank you.
In fact you can see
it here like if you
look at a single entry
direct that's drawn here,
you know they're basically.
10, 10 bits left, that
are not being used.
Okay, so let's look at the flags
for a second, because it's sort
of important.
so, every translation in the bottom 10
bits, there's a bunch of flag
stored and the first flag is valid.
If a valid bit set,
that means this is a valid PTE,
and you can use it for translation.
And so, we're going to
run my little example, that I
used here, three page directories,
when only entry 0 is used
then only entey 0 will have
valid bit set and none of
the other 511 entries
will not have valid bit set.
And that basically tells MMU,
well, you don't have to chase
down this PTE, PTE just contains no
valid information.
Then "R" means you're allowed
to read from that page, write
means you're allowed to write to the page.
Execute means you're allowed to execute
instruction from it.
User, means you know this page is
also accessible by a process
running in user space.
And then the other bits you
not that important,
it will show up at
some point, those are sort of five
important bits.
Does that make sense.
Yeah, Nithya, I'd probably mispronouncing your
name I apologize to you.
That's, that's the representation,
thank you,
I had a quick question about,
the three page table,
so how are the addresses or
like the PPN values combined to form
the final physical address, I might
miss that.
Um, yeah,
I may not say that said it
very explicitly. So the first
PPN correcting tops the page table,
the first PPN in the top
level page directory.
And contains the physical address of
the next level down.
And one contains the one next
level down and then in the
final one we still have are
[] 44 bits that contains then
the actual physical address off the
page that we're actually trying to
translate to.
OK, that makes sense, thank you.
Okay, and one interesting question,
just let us side note,
before let me answer my
own question before answering the
two raised hands here,
look back at this picture,
why, why are the physical page
numbers stored in these page directories.
Why not a virtual address.
Because we need to look it
up in memory, like look up
the next directory in memory.
Yeah right,
we could not have a
translation scheme depends on yet
another translation scheme,
you know we could sort of,
recursive intent look, so that
just make sense.
That's exactly the right answer,
it has to be a physical number,
how about the satp,
what do you use the satp,
what does it store it store
a physical address or a virtual address.
Also physical, assuming that
the first page directory is
also memory, right. Exactly so
it has to be a
physical number because we're actually
trying to use it for translation.
And, so you know the satp, you
need to know what the physical
page number is,
on the route of the
page directory.
OK, there were two other questions
or two people who raise their
hands, you do,
repeat your question if.
So there's a hierarchy of three
tables and each of them is
indexed by a part of the
virtual address,
each 9 bits long.
So I'm not sure
I understand how chaining between
them happens and what it's
meant to accomplish, like shouldn't
it be sufficient to just
use those three 9 bit
addresses to index into each
of them.
That's correct,
so the first, top level
9 bits are used to
index the first
top, page top directory,
the second and the next
one and the third in the third one.
So maybe I'm just not understanding
this correctly,
so when a process requests
a certain virtual address to be
looked up,
it loads into the
satp register or the CPU
does and that,
get to the corresponding correct highest
level page table.
And then that page table will.
We used in the top
level 9 bits from the 27
to index into that page directory.
And then what is what is
the result of that,
like if the result is there's
nothing there does MMU
create a page table,
No, no,
MMU basically tells the operating
system or tells the processor,
sorry I couldn't translate that address,
and basically turns into a
page fault which we'll talk about
a little bit later.
But just cannot translate the address,
it doesn't translate it's like you
know you can't divide by zero,
you know if you try to
do that, the processor refuses to
do it.
I see, OK.
Brandon, what about you, Brandon.
So I just wanted to
make sure I understand, how I
think maybe we want to understand
how the intermediate page tables well,
how we calculate the physical address of those.
So, is it correct that say if
we're trying to find a second
level page tables physical address,
we would take the PPN from
the first level page table,
that's 44 bits and then we
add the 12 bit offset from
the original virtual address to get
the full 56 bit, this question is.
We don't add the offset
from the virtual address,
we just take twelve 0 bits.
So we take the PPN
there's 44 bits. Okay,
12 0 bits on the bottom
and that gives us a
56 bit physical address and
that's where the next page directories,
and this requires that basically every
page directories page aligned.
I see, OK, that makes sense.
So these are all great questions
and these are all things,
you're gonna be struggling within the
page table lab so.
Yeah it's very good to ask
them right now.
Okay, let me see,
Yes, yeah okay,
let me hold on for a second.
And I quote my thoughts
see where I am.
Good good,
good, okay,
one a sort of you
know one other thing that I
want to mention because you will
see that, is that if
we think about this,
you know the scheme that I
just showed right,
what really seems to be
going on is that we load
or store value to memory.
What the processor loads or stores
value to memory,
we basically have to do free
memory lookups, right,
one in the top of the
page directory,
one intermediate page
directory and then one in the
bottom level page directory.
It looks like, that you know
any memory reference to virtual address
basically requires free memory reach.
And so that seems expensive.
And so,
what happens in practice where
almost all every processor does this,
it has a cache sitting
on the side, that contains
recently used translations.
And this is called translation look-aside buffer.
Then you'll see that term
quite often, of TLB.
Basically it's nothing else than
the cache of
entry, page table entries, PTE entries.
So when the process has you
know the first time the process
routes look through virtual address,
you know walks this, hardware
walks this page, the three
level page tables, that will come
out with you know the final
physical page, often called final PPN,
for that particular virtual address,
and then basically the
TLB stores, VA, PA, PN,
or PA mapping on the side.
And so,
then the next time you refer
to that particular virtual address,
I can just look at straight
up in the TLB and the
TLB will respond instead of having
to do the page table walk.
Yep, Amiar.
So, the TLB map
virtual addresses to the physical address
of the page, that the virtual
address along with the offset
absolutely,
wouldn't it be more efficient
to like cache at the
page table level.
Okay, so I let me
take a step back here,
there are many ways of
implementing the TLB,
the most important thing that
you need to know is that
there is a TLB.
And the exact details
of actually how the TLB
has implemented, this sort of
you know not a topic
that we're going to talk
about in great amount of detail.
That's not at all,
and so this is really
something that sits inside of the
processor and is mostly hidden from
the operating system,
the operating system doesn't really know
how to TLB be operates, the
only thing the reason you need
to know that the TLB
exist is that if you switch page tables,
then, typically the operating system needs
to tell the processor that's switching
page tables.
And the TLB needs to be flushed.
Because basically you send
stale entries,
but if you switch to a
new page table,
the entries in the TLB may
not be valid anymore and so
they need to be removed because
otherwise you know the translation would
be incorrect.
And so the operating system is
typically aware
it's aware that there's a,
that there is a TLB
only basically to tell the
hardware once in a while saying,
okay we'll don't use them anymore,
because I'm gonna switch page tables.
And in fact on you know
the, the RISC-V, the instruction
to flush the TLB is called sfence_vma.
I'm not actually,
flush the TLB. [Biback].
So I have a question,
like not regarding TLB
but that brought kind
of this question.
The three level support, that the
three level paging that we have,
is it implemented by the operating
system or the hardware itself. It
implemented in hardware.
So you know there's all happens
in hardware,
the MMU is a block of hardware.
In the operating system we'll
see in a second when we
look at xv6, xv6
has a function that models the
page table walk, because once in
a while you know xv6
basically has to do what the
hardware does.
And so it knows
it does have a function
called walk, that basically does
exactly the same thing,
but in software.
So, can I ask a question?
So, where in this scheme does the
processor cache fit,
does it happen before the address
translation or after,
because. Yeah, okay let me so
let's switch back a little bit
a couple, let me see.
Okay, usually MMU will
really the way to think about
is that all this stuff,
you know the whole block is
inside the processor silicon.
So there's a RISC-V
chip and inside of it
is the CPU,
in fact there are multiple CPU
correct, there 4 cores.
And there's a MMU
and you know you can think about that,
either on this on the CPU side,
you know there's a TLB.
That makes sense,
but I guess my question
was about the like,
cache in terms of not the TLB,
but just a normal cache like,
sometimes we don't actually go all
the way to access the memory.
Yeah, good points I think I
should like to scheme last week
correctly, on monday of the RISC-V
processor and has one cache
it has two cache.
Some caches are indexed by physical
address, some caches are indexed by
virtual address.
So the caches that are indexed
by virtual address sit before the MMU.
And cache in their index by
physical addresses after the MMU.
Does that make sense?
Can I also ask a question
my question is,
you said that the TLB,
it walks so I like to
put stuff into TLB,
the hardware walks through the page tables.
Why do we arrive walk function,
if hardware can do that.
Very good question,
one reason we have, a
couple of reasons why we do
it or why xv6 needs it,
one is when it actually sets
up the initial page tables.
you know it needs to
program the the three levels.
And so it needs to basically
emulate the three levels.
Um, and um, another example,
that you actually sort of run
into or are running into in
the syscall lab is that when
you copy, the xv6, the
kernel has its own page table
and every user address space has
its own page table.
And once in a while,
for example it says [info], you know, like
system, pointed to system infrastructure,
you know that lives in user space.
The kernel needs to translate
to an address that it can
use to read and write.
And so,
for example if you're looking
copyin or copyout.
Basically, the kernel translates the
user virtual address using the user
virtual, using a user page
table to get out of physical
address, that kernel
then get an address out,
actually the kernel can use to
read and write that memory.
So there's a bunch of places
going to show up, and I'll
talk about hopefully in whatever ten
minutes or fifteen minutes.
I have a question,
why doesn't the hardware like expose
that walk function,
so we don't have to write
our own and potentially have bugs
in it,
why isn't there like, maybe
a privileged instruction that you can
pass a virtual address and will
give back the physical address.
Well, this is just like just
store to the virtual address
you get back and will do
it right for you,
so I will see later on,
in the next lab,
the page table lab,
in fact is exactly what you'll
be doing you'll actually set up
the page table slightly differently,
so that you can avoid the
walk in copyin and copyinstr.
I think this will become clear
in the second we when we
talk about we look at the xv6, OK.
Okay, good.
One more sure basically before jumping
into xv6, I wanted to make one point.
One way to think about, you know, page tables.
A popular way to phrase this.
It's the page tables provide
a level of indirection.
And, that and, so basically
this indirection,
what I'm talking about you know
this mapping from virtual address to
physical address.
And this mapping is completely
under control of the operating system.
As we've seen, you know in the last
a couple slides that we talk,
and that means that the
operating system because it has so
much control,
it has control complete control that
translation, it can do all
kinds of interesting tricks.
And so for example, like
one trick, talk a little
bit about this,
like if a page, page entry is
invalid and will really return a
page you know the hardware will
raise page fault.
In response the page fault,
the operating system could update
the page tables and then
maybe restart the instruction.
And so there are all kinds
of things they can do, at
runtime, and by manipulating
the page tables.
And we're not going to talk
about it today,
but in two weeks,
we'll have a lecture exactly about
this topic about what cool things
can you do, once you have
page tables and page faults.
But it's important to keep
in mind that this is
incredibly powerful mechanism.
That, will provide the operating system
with a tremendous amount of flexibility.
And there's one reason why page
tables are so popular.
Okay, so what I wanna do
next is actually talk about xv6.
Sort of see how
it all plays out in xv6.
So the first thing I'm gonna
do, is going to look
at the kernel page layout,
if you will, and
the mapping is on this slide,
so here's the
virtual address space of the kernel,
here is, actually the physical memory,
so this is basically whatever you
can think about this is DRAM.
And in fact it is not,
let me take that back immediately
one part is DRAM.
And one part is actually IO devices.
And so, to sort of maybe, I'm
going to talk about the physical,
the right side of the slide a
little bit first, and then we'll
talk about the left side in a second.
So the left side of
the slide is completely determined by the hardware.
And so the hardware designers
basically determined the layout of that
fit and you know as you saw before last week.
When the kernel starts, it starts at this address 0x8000.
And that's determined by the hardware designers.
And so you should be more explicit,
if you look at the board,
this is the same picture of the board, that I showed on
Monday but is hopefully a little better picture,
it's easy to see,
here's our RISC-V processor.
And we now know correct in the RISC-V processor,
there four cores, but there's also, MMU.
And there's also a TLB or
multiple TLB, every core has its own MMU and every
core has its own TLB.
And here are DRAM chips.
And so basically the designers of
the board have decided that,
when, you know, after, you
know, the translation from virtual to
physical address basic physical addresses that's
starting you know at 08,
you know, a lot of zeros actually go to the DRAM chips.
Addresses above below 0x8, may go
to different IO devices.
And so the platform decides
basically the designers this board have
decided exactly what the physical layout.
I think you can look that up the physical layout,
if you want to, just let me show you so here's
the same manual that I showed
you on, um,
on um, Monday and if you go to actually,
go to page 31, I believe.
Yeah it's a page and if you go down,
this is whats the memory,
it will spell out the memory map is, of the board
and we'll see at address zero
zero is reserved nothing is there.
If you go scroll down in this memory map,
you'll see some information about all
the different things that are mapped,
for example, ethernet board is mapped
at Ox1, you know, 0x something.
If you might go further down, oops, too much down.
Here, you see the entry for 0x8000 worked
and that actually is DDR memory,
the Off-Chip Volatile Memory, so
those are the DRAM chips or
I can show you on the previous slide.
And so it's just good to keep your head correct
even though we're talking to
QEMU, you're overseeing software in
the end everything is determined,
by you know the actual board.
Okay, so go back to a my slides.
So let's look at the layout.
Yeah, Noah, go ahead.
Yeah, when you say that this
this layout is determined by the
hardware, do you specifically mean
like the CPU itself or the
board on which the CPU resides.
The board which the CPU resides,
correct. Because you know the borad,
you know, the CPU is the
grey thing in the middle that
square thing, saying whatever RISC-V,
the DRAM chips are sitting off,
the off the processor correct, it's
the board designers who put the
chip the DRAM, you know, do many
IO devices altogether.
And large part of
an operating system is actually,
you know the CPU is one part, but the
IO devices are at least as
important, right, and so when you're
writing an operating system you both
have to deal with the CPU
as well as you know with the IO devices,
you know and you want to
send a packet over the Internet.
Well, somebody has to take over.
You know the network driver,
the NIC card to actually do that,
and that's the operating system.
So going back to the right
side of this picture,
which is the physical address layout,
you know we see basically the
bottom was unused as I showed
you on that document.
It turns out that
0x1000, that physical address,
that's where the boot ROM
is, so when you turn on that board,
the first thing that happens is
actually coding the boot ROM runs.
And when the boot rom is
done it actually will jump to
this 0x000 and it's
a job of the operating system make
sure that there's some,
you know, some data there.
And then there's a bunch of
other devices that will talk about
goes to interrupt controller,
we'll talk about it next week.
There's a CLENT, another part
of the interrupt story that we'll
talk about next week,
so there's multiple devices can generate
interrupts there needs to be planned
to route those interrupts to the
to the appropriate request level and
it's all implemented by those
interrupt controllers.
And let me finish for
a second you know this,
this slide before
answering question.
Then there's a uart
that was the device,
that was actually the thing that actually,
the device actually UART device actually
interacts with the console and the
display and then there's the VIRTIO
there's the disk.
And that's the device,
there's a device belong,
it's that actually interacts with the disk.
And so when you write to
location to address, let's say,
0x200 then
that physical address corresponds to the
CLINT and so do you want
to do store instruction,
load instruction,
your reading and writing to the
chip that implements the CLINT.
We'll see later what that exactly
means but basically you can think
about this as interacting directly with
the device and not reading or
writing physical memory.
Yeah there's a question.
So just trying to make
sure the addresses below
0x800, they don't really exist in DRAM.
If when we mention those addresses
we directly go to the other hardwares.
Yeah yeah,
so if you go back to this picture.
Anything of above
0x8000, correct，
That's these DRAM chips.
And you know I can't
draw, I can't point you
to the CLINT,
but like generally hears that,
ethernet.
And so that's a particular physical
address and we can write you
know load store instructions is called
memory mapped IO,
we can load and store instructions,
we can program ethernet controller.
I also have a question,
why was this big chunk at
the top says unused.
Why is it not used. OK,
so remember,
not every machine not
every so there's 2 to the power 56,
bytes physical address space,
but you don't have those,
you know, plug in that much memory
into the board,
if you don't want to.
And so some parts of it
may be unused, depending on how
much you're DRAM chips are sitting
on the board.
In fact, they like in xv6,
we I think limit ourselves to
128 megabyte.
And no more.
So when a, when a
load store instruction goes out of
the CPU, does that go,
like where does it get
routed to the correct IO, like
already from the CPU,
so kind of like if the
CPU before it sends it out
it says OK,
if it's lower than 0x8 and all the zeros then
I'm going to send it to
the correct IO devices,
and then otherwise I'm going to
send it to the to the
memory like DRAM chip.
Yeah, you can think about as
a demultiplexer sitting on the
inside of the RISC-V, you
know block.
Oh, so it's inside of
that block. OK.
As a memory controller and does routing.
Because very important to have
that sort of all clear in your head.
Are you okay,
so now I want to
switch to the right side of this picture.
And this is basically what
xv6 sets up, to
the virtual address space, that
xv6 setup,
so when the machine boot, there's
no page enable yet,
xv6 sets up
the first page tables, virtual
address space and that's actually
the virtual address space
the kernel uses and we'll look
at it in the second.
At the code, but,
and this is the layout
and it turns out, you know,
because we want to keep
xv6 as simple as possible,
it's easy for you to understand.
The mapping from virtual to physical
is mostly in identity mapping.
So basically what that means is
that the virtual address 0x200
maps to physical address
0x200, the kernel
will set up the page tables
exactly in that way,
and so that means basically that
you know all virtual addresses,
below this top.
Which is the top of
physical memory are identical to the
physical addresses that are actually being
used on the right side.
And so this is why all
the arrows are straight, because it's
identity mapping.
The small changes to this,
there are two important things to mention.
Amiar, hold on a second, while
try to first mention the two
important things to mention.
First of all,
there's some pages,
some maps very high up in
your memory.
Which some pages very high
up in memory,
for example the stack a
kernel stack actually sits up is
also map high up in memory.
And the reason is high
up in memory is because we
have a guard page below it
that is not mapped.
So the PTE entry below
the kernel stack, of one of
the kernel stack [], does
have, not have it's valid bit set.
And, so if you know, the kernel
runs off its stack and will
result in a page fault,
which is better than basically scribbling
over some other memory that the
kernel has.
You get immediate panic,
you know that something's bad to stack.
Of course, we don't want
to waste physical memory and so
when we do that by basically
putting the stack high, um,
a guard page, an empty guard
PTE entry below it.
And the guard page
doesn't really consume any physical memory
records sitting high up in the
virtual address space,
so nothing is being consumed.
But that means that they're showing
this case, stack page,
for example is mapped twice.
It's mapped at a high
address and it's mapped directly
by one of the dresses
that below PHYSTOP.
And so you can do, this
is one example of all the
sort of cool things, you can
do with page tables,
you can map a physical address twice,
you cannot map a physical address,
you know it can be
one to one mapping, one to
many mapping, many to one mapping,
all that kind of stuff is possible.
Actually it does really use
many of them, but there's a
couple places we use those tricks.
And there's the stack in
the guard page is one
example, of one of the
cool trick then xv6 uses
mostly to track down bugs.
The second thing I wanted to
mention is that, the permissions.
So, for example the kernel text,
the pages for the kernel text
are mapped R-X, meaning you can
read it and execute it.
But you cannot write to
kernel text and again this
is basically devoid,
[bugs] we catch
them early, kernel data of course
needs to be able to be
written to, and so it has
mapped read write,
but you cannot execute
out of kernel data pages instructions.
So the execute bit is not set.
Does that make sense.
I skipped one or two questions,
so if these questions are still
not answered, please ask them.
We have a question in the chat.
Do we have multiple kernel stacks
for different processes like we have
n kstacks for n processes.
And answers yes.
So every process every user process
has a corresponding kernel stack.
I will see that in a
little bit later.
Okay, so let me,
Samir, go ahead.
So what's the virtual memory
of another application
map to somewhere in the physical
memory in the unused space or.
Yes, a very good point,
so there's a bunch of
physical memory,
correct, here's free memory.
Um, that's free memory
here too, right, and
we use that actually use
that free memory to basically
store pages of page tables,
user processes as well as you
know the text and data of
user level processes.
And if we are on many many,
many user processes at some point
we'll run out of free memory,
and then basically fork or exec
will return an error.
But that means that the
virtual space for processes are
much smaller than the virtual
space for the kernel, right?
Well, the virtual spaces as
the same as the same size in principle,
but it will be less populated.
Then let me let's look at
some code,
and I think that all this
stuff becomes a bit more clear.
I just want small thing,
is so given that a lot of the like,
each process has a big part
of the memory map to the
same location, is that optimized by
like consolidating that into one place
that mapping or no.
Um, it's good,
xv6 does not do that,
like one of the challenge
exercises in the page table lab
is to actually implement that.
I see. The real operating system
would do that.
Yeah. Makes sense.
Very good question.
I think you get a sense
of what all kinds of things
are possible, once you have page tables.
Okay,
so let's do the usual thing,
boot xv6 again and again,
you know QEMU uses basically implementing
the board.
And you know let's. Oops, -gdb,
last time we looked at
how the routing happens correct
and then we got to
main and then basically one
of the things that, the kernel,
when one of the functions called
kvminit and that actually
sets up the address space for the kernel.
And so we saw in the
picture where in the previous slide,
what that you know looks like
and here we go,
C code how it actually is being set up.
And why, hold on, something's
not going as I wanted to.
Am I the right directories.
Hold on a second here
while I'm trying to sort
out my problems.
That is good.
I mean the right directory,
yeah, We want to set a
break from the main just
to make sure.
Good, and then a break point at kvminit.
Actually I can just step to
it now, next consoleinit
printfinit,
you know, we saw it before,
physical memory allocator.
You know, something happens that I
not expecting.
What is going on.
We're gonna run this right before
lecture. Here,
that's what's going on actually printing,
Okay.
Interesting.
Okay one more time,
see if I can get lucky more [].
Very good.
Continue, hopefully it will get there,
wait a little bit. Okay great
we're at the kvminit,
so basically we're now this function
here, on the right side in
the emacs buffer, you can see it.
And,
I think I've modified function
slightly I hope I did.
I think I did, we'll
see, and what we knew
is going to walk step into the function.
Give me layout split it's
easier to see.
And this is the first thing
that you can see, this section
of the current actually allocates a
physical page, for the top level
page directory.
And then zeroes it
out so that all the PTE entries are zero.
And then basically starts mapping in
every device, IO device one by one.
And so, for example, the UART0, it
basically starts mapping maps that into
the kernel address space and so
we can look at a file
called memlayout.h, is basically translate
page 31 that I showed
you from the document into a
bunch of constants that we're using.
And so, for example here it says what
the address of 0x1000 is.
Um, [do you ideas].
And so,
you know, we can basically
map it into the address space
by calling this function
kvmmap which I will look in
a second.
And then,
in the first exercise of
the page table lab,
you are asked to implement a
function called vmprint.
Um, and I implemented it too,
and I'm going to step over
it and we'll see basically,
page tables, kernel page table as it
is set up after that one
call to the kvmmap,
so I'm going to do that.
And we're going to print
out something.
And so we're going to
look a little bit of the output here,
so here's the page table that
is the
physical address of the top level,
page directory,
so the thing that actually sits
in satp, or will sit in satp.
And then we have
entry 0 of the top
level page really has one
PTE entry in it.
And that is the contains
the physical address for the middle
level page table directory.
The middle page level directory has
one entry namely 128.
And that points to the bottom
of page table directory and the
bottom page table directory has the
entry then for the physical page.
And you can see,
indeed that the physical address,
you know for that bottom level
is 0x1000
corresponding to uart0.
Right, so basically virtual address
1000 translates
to physical address [1000].
We can sure double check,
this is indeed all legit.
By,
and let's take that address 0x100L
and we're going to shift 12.
And that should be,
you know, that gives the top
level 27 bits.
We shifted 9,
so I'm gonna take 0x100,
0x10000, and we can
shift at 9, print that.
And that is 0x80,
and actually print 0x80
as a decimal number, it's
going to be 128, OK.
So we see actually sort of
you know it all sort of
makes sense.
We also see I printed out
the flags here,
and you know the bottom
level has read,
write and valid, because valid is one.
Any questions about this.
Okay, so.
The kernel basically proceeds, you know
doing setting up the whole address
space in this way.
And, so we've called
kvmmap for VIRTIO, for the
CLINT, for the PLIC.
Maps the kernel text, maps
the kernel memory or kernel data,
and then the TRAMPOLINE page that
we'll talk about next week.
And so in fact we
can single step through this and
then see what the final page
directory looks like.
Um, so next next next next.
Basically, you know set the TRAMPOLINE,
so now we're going to print
the complete page table directory.
You know we see basically
lot of PTE is actually being setup.
And I'm not going to
talk about in any detail,
but you know basically fills
out the page
directory to actually create
virtual mapping that we
basically saw on the previous slide.
When I expect what I
wanna do next is actually
much more interesting.
Yeah I'm gonna.
Yeah I wanna go here,
actually, I guess maybe I already
did this, were 21,
no, I'm 21, okay so single step that.
OK that's too bad, I
got past it. But basically,
let me, let me restart this.
I wanna break point at kvminithart.
And continue,
are now here at kvminithart,
and you see here,
basically that we're writing the
satp register,
so basically the kernel is going
to enable page table or
the hard, MMU,
to basically start using
the page table that we just set up.
And one interesting question.
Okay, so they do have layout
split again,
So,
somewhere here is going to be,
here's the instruction in,
so once, something really dramatic happens
after executing this instruction.
Um, let's say yeah I can
see the same instruction exactly but
there's this this extent,
once this instruction is executed what
will happen with the next address
that's being translated.
Well, at the point that
we execute this instruction, before
executing this instruction,
there's no page tables enabled yet
so no translation happens.
But the next and then the
program counter is updated by [4].
And then the next instruction is
executed and the program counter will
be translated using the virtual page,
page table memory.
And so this is, you
know, the ways to think about this,
this is a dramatic moment.
Because basically the whole address translation,
they started to enable and
every address needs no maybe
potentially something different.
Right, because before we're running your
physical addresses,
then the page table,
haven't install, and whatever is in
the mapping,
now there's now the new meaning
of a virtual address.
And here's how this works
out, you know, the fact that
this actually works out is remarkable
because like the next instruction,
the next value is a virtual
address and not a physical address.
The next instruction is going to
be this, whatever 0x1110.
And why does this work out.
And the reason works out is
because the kernel is setup,
we can identity page mapping. So,
after we enable the virtual paging hardware,
we actually know this translator will
translate again to the same physical
address and so indeed we'll actually end up, you know,
executing the writing instruction, because that's
actually exactly the instruction,
the memory location that the virtual
hardware is programmed for.
So does this make sense.
Again, one reason why programming virtual
memory is difficult is because once
you execute one of these satp
instructions you load a page table
in the satp register, your world
completely changes.
And every address is now translated
with the page table, that you set up.
And so what happens if the
page table setup incorrectly.
What would you, what might happen.
Anybody who wants to
say that answered or answered in
the chat, you can wait.
You could override kernel data.
Yeah you could overwrite kernel data
what else could happen,
yeah page fault, you basically do,
the mapping may be incorrect and
basically the address can be translated at all,
and so the kernel can, you
know, the hardware won't do it
and usally the kernel there stops and panics.
Does that make sense,
so if you get a bug
in your page tables,
you know you're going to see
these are errors or crashes.
And so,
one reason that example, the next lab,
that page table lab, that
will hand out or release tonight,
is going to be hard,
because those kind of bugs will show up.
If you're not careful enough or
you haven't fully internalized some aspect yet.
And you're basically going to
get kernel crash and
you're gonna have a hard
time when you will take a little bit of time
and energy and detective work
to basically track down why that happened.
And that's just the, that's just
part of like programming virtual memory.
Because it's such a
powerful primitive, you know, you
get it wrong,
you're gonna have powerful consequences.
Yet the other hand is great amount of fun,
so I don't want to end on a negative node,
But all that will give
you a real understanding of actually
what really virtual memory is and
what it can do.
Okay I think I'm running
out of time so I'm
gonna stop here,
so people have time to
go to the next class or next activity,
but if you have any questions
left, please hang on and ask them.
And, we'll see you on monday.
And good luck with finishing the syscall lab.
Um, hi, I have a question about walk,
so it says and in the code,
it returns the like the first tables of PTE.
Yeah right.
But how does it work,
then like the other functions when
they expect the actual PTE,
than the physical address.
Yeah basically this returns the PTE
entry in the page table,
and the kernel can read or
write page table entries.
Um, and so now you can
stick values into the PTE.
And so maybe I can draw
a picture that is helpful.
Let's see.
So maybe we have a page directory.
And, you know, this walk code,
so the page directory has 512 PTE in it.
Here's zero, here's 511 and basically what the
function does it returns a pointer to one of these PTEs.
And so that's just a virtual address,
and it points to that particular PTE.
And now the kernel can, you
know manipulate that PTE, by whatever
writing values to it.
Like some physical address,
maybe with some permissions
into it for the bottom ten bits.
And then basically updates the page table directory,
and then later on when you load data into satp,
now, that affect that change will go into effect.
Does that make sense.
Yeah that makes sense, I guess
I just confused like why does
it do the work of going all the way to the third,
page table and then only return the first PTE.
No, return is actually the bottom one.
Actually, let me be careful,
if, you know, it goes through
the n levels, started level 2 and then go to level 1,
again a level 0.
If the alloc bit set and level doesn't exist,
it will create the intermediate page table directory.
And zero it out and then keep going to look.
So, you always end up on the bottom PTE.
If alloc not set, you stop
at the first PTE, that doesn't have value.
Okay, that makes sense,
this is the last one, the actual on gonna have.
Okay okay, thank you.
Any other questions.
So I have a question,
basically everything made sense until
we mapped the virtual addresses
to, of the kernel to the physical addresses.
So my understanding is that
each process will have its own page table,
which is also a three level tree
which wraps its virtual addresses to physical addresses,
but then we map the kernel
virtual addresses to physical addresses, I
don't think we accounted for the
actual tree of them virtual addresses of the kernel
or where other processes will have their virtual addresses.
And I'm sorry, virtual addresses like
the virtual table trees and
whatever the page table tree points
at in the physical memory.
Yeah, so yeah so so you're
back this is slide with kernel,
address space, virtual kernel address
space and so when the kernel allocates proc,
and page tables for that particular process, they're going
to be allocated at memory here, memory is
not being used yet.
And the kernel is going to
program, we'll probably allocate a
couple pages for the page table,
off the usual process and
will fill in the PTEs.
And at some point when the
kernel runs that process,
it will load the route,
physical address for those pages that
is allocated for that page table
or basically page table then built
into the satp register.
And at that point the processor
will run with the virtual address
space that the kernel constructed for
that particular process.
So the kernel gave up
some of its memory for processes,
and then the virtual space in theory is as big
for the process as the kernel,
but in reality, it's really not.
Yeah, have a picture with the layout
of a virtual address space with
their usual level process and again
it goes from zero to MAXVA.
In the same way as the
kernel address space does and it's
basically has his own set of
page tables to map those translation
the kernel setup.
But we can't actually use all of the MAXVA virtual.
No, we cannot.
We run out of memory.
So many of the processes are much smaller than
all of the virtual address space.
I see, thank you.
I've got a quick question,
could you go back to the walk code,
yeah yeah absolutely.
It's one of my favorite functions.
So I guess, one
thing I'm confused about is after
you write to the satp register, can the kernel even access
physical addresses directly,
so it looks like in the
code that it's converting you know
like page was being set to a physical address,
but if satp is set,
won't that be interpreted as a virtual address.
Yeah,
so, okay so let's look at hartinit.
That's kvm, so built in kernel address space.
The kernel page table,
initially, the virtual physical, address
is translated to a physical
address and that's actually written into the satp register.
And at that point you
know we're running with the address
space that we've constructed right before
here, this kvminit.
And gave me a map is
basically nothing else than calling
walk for every address where
every page and at the range.
And so what was your question?
I guess,
it's does walks still work
the same way if you call it after satp
is set. Yeah why.
Why we work out the reason
it work out the kernel set up in identity mapping.
Ok, right, right.
Very important,
very good question,
a lot of things just happened
to work out because actually the identity mapping is set up.
I see, I think that makes sense,
I have a quick question.
Where the satp register stored for all of the processes.
There only one satp per core,
but in every proc structure.
If you look at proc.h, there is,
a pointer to the page table,
here, here. okay, makes sense.
And also with regards to the
three page tables are like the
three tables that can complete the
full address and help you get
a full address for even something,
how does how is that better
I guess than than having one
giant page table I didn't really
fully understand what. A great question,
the reason is because in the free level page table,
you can leave a lot of entries empty.
So, for example if you leave
the entry in the top level page table directly empty,
you don't have to create middle
level page tables or bottom level
page tables at all, for those entries.
Like this means like a big
[] of the whole virtual address
space doesn't have to have any mapping at all.
Okay, okay.
You don't have the table there,
it just doesn't exist.
I see,
basically allocating these chunks on demand
as volumes and types,
OK that makes sense,
Yeah you're starting basically with three
page three pages namely,
one from the top level one
for, one intermediate one from,
one bottom level.
And then,
as you go you create more
page table directories.
Okay, okay,
cool, thank you so much.
You're welcome.
Any more questions.
I'm sorry I have another one,
it's really really small but
in the vm.c on line 43, 41,
it says that, no, might 43, my bad,
it says 'PHYSTOP-(uint64)etext', but wouldn't that,
would not go over the, I guess the memory that
we shouldn't touch, I don't
know if that makes sense,
but, would that go.
I guess I don't understand, would
they go over free memory.
No, I don't think so,
so KERNBASE is 0x8000, right
so that's the beginning of memory.
Kernel sits there in,
basically, this thing is a size,
right, so etext is the last address of the kernel,
subtract KERNBASE, that basically gives
you the size of the kernel, in byte.
And, you know, I don't know how
much it is, but it's like you know 60 or 90
pages or something like that.
And so this map
is basically the text part of the kernel.
Um, and there's enough space.
There's enough DRAM there to map that the kernel text.
I'm not sure, I'm answering your question,
but. I think, I think I understand.
I thought that etext starts
somewhere else, okay, I think I understand now, thank you.
So etext basically the last instruction,
the address of the last instruction of the kernel.
Okay, okay.