The lab compares to a the locking lab.
It was a bit more straightforward.
Good, are you completely, have you finished the lab, where you are.
I just started yesterday and a halfway, so.
Okay, good I guess that's good news for people who are starting,
anybody finished it yet.
I have, I finished it.
And any any nasty surprises are worked out reasonably well.
I think it worked out Okay, yeah.
Much easier than the lock lab.
I think so, at least.
Well, hopefully will be the case for everybody else too.
Yeah yeah, let me get started
and the topic I want to talk about today is virtual memory for user applications,
you know on a, sort of guided by this paper from 1991, by Appel and Li.
So the starting point basically is that, as you well know,
that the OS kernel use virtual memory page tables in creative ways.
You've seen that we have a lazy allocation lab, copy-on-write to lab,
as well as many other sort of features that you know implementation to or aspects of the implementation in the xv6,
so and basically the argument that the paper makes, the paper argues,
you know the user application should actually benefit to or should have the same powers,
you know, [] user apps can use VM too.
A little bit, I mean when I mean again, of course, your application running with virtual memory,
but I really mean with VM is that they would like to have the same mechanisms that kernel has
to its access user application where user modes,
application will be able to take page faults, and then you respond to those page faults,
you know be able to change the protection bits, or the privilege level to levels in the page table.
And so, in the paper argues this case by looking at a bunch of different applications.
like six or seven different types of applications
and maybe I will ask you like what was your favorite application, you encountered in the paper.
Anybody wanna chime in and plot [there].
They can allow the user application to decide that a page is going to be,
I guess they change the access bits for some particular page.
Yeah, that's one of the mechanisms,
I'm just curious, which applications,
you know they make the case with a bunch of different applications,
like the garbage collector or concurrent garbage collector,
and a couple other ones,
you know, just wondering which ones you thought were most interesting.
What other applications do they use or the used to make their case.
I thought the data compression application was pretty cool.
And the other [] were, people were compelled by.
I thought the sort of shared virtual memory between multiple different systems that was pretty cool,
I didn't, I don't think I fully understood how it worked,
but the general idea of using the protection bits
to make sure that different machines are are using that shared memory in the right way
and protecting invariance makes sense.
So, that's it, you know, basically it turns out that whole area developed in a way that one paper originally described the SVM,
developing a whole research area,
where you know people all kinds of clever tricks to try to make that actually yeah that scheme to fly.
Any others.
Because they go off and do a couple other paper applications
and they basically argue that you know if you look at all these different quite different applications
like shared virtual memory data compression to garbage collector,
you know very different in nature,
but it turns out that all of them actually rely on a small number of virtual memory primitives to actually make it work.
And so the first question to the paper address is
like Okay what what what should the primitives look like,
the user application needs if they want to implement one of those applications.
And so let me talk a little bit about that,
first you know what primitives is.
And so they are, the ones they the obvious one, of course you need something of a primitive, let's go what I call Trap,
basically to allow a page fault that happens sort of inside the kernel to be propagated up to user space.
And then in user space, you know and handler can then deal with its page fault
and then of course return in the usual way back to the kernel,
and then resume the instruction.
So clearly the primitive like that is necessary,
because otherwise you couldn't do anything in response to a page fault.
The other primitive you know they talk about this Prot1,
which decreases the accessibility of page,
they talk a lot about accessibility, or and what do you mean with accessibility.
Anybody?
Whether is read, write.
Yeah, yeah, so there's different ways in which you can decrease their accessibility,
you go from a page that maybe has read write, go to just read only,
or maybe you go from here, or read only to actually have no access at all.
They also proposed that basically there should be one for each individual page, that's Prot1,
there should be one that actually you can do for the application call for a collection of pages.
And so basically ProtN boils down in principle to calling Prot1 N times,
but why, why do they argue that we should have actually a ProtN version of this primitive too.
Is it because actually it's more efficient,
because the overhead of protecting the N pages is not much more than protecting one,
because, they talked about something like amortizing the work of.
Yeah yeah, absolutely right,
so basically if you do a Prot1,
basically you have to change the page table bits, and do some work,
and then at the end of that problem,
you typically want to have to flush the TLB,
remember this from xv6 implementation,
and flushing TLB is expensive
and it would be nice if you could amortize basically flushing TLB overall you know the page table changes.
So basically ProtN boils down to N times N times changing page table bits plus one TLB flush.
And if you did N times Prot1,
you would have a one page table switch plus one page to table modification plus one TLB flush from each page,
so you can save the TLB flush.
Does that make sense?
Okay, then you know the primitive Unprot, this increases accessibility as they call it,
basically meaning you know if page for example and have [watched] and read only access now,
we're just going to promote it to actually have read and write access.
There are two other primitives are mentioning,
one is primitive to actually find out which page when a page is dirty,
and another primitive Map2 which allows,
to allows an application to map a particular range twice in the same address page, the same address space,
but with a different degrees of accessibility.
We'll see that showing up in a second.
So you look at these primitives, you know xv6 support any of these,
you know for user level applications.
Not out of the box, but maybe the alarm handler that we implemented feels close.
Good yeah they keep the alarm handler in their mind,
that certainly feels very close correctly that is related to the Trap one,
but other than that there are xv6 support none of this right,
actually it's a very minimal Unix interface,
doesn't support any of the more advanced virtual minimal primitives,
even though internally the kernel itself does have all the mechanism available,
but you're not exposed to user space into a form of system calls.
As a result, the papers arguing that
any sort of good operating systems should provide you know these primitives are system calls,
so the application can use them.
So that naturally relates to the question,
like what what's the scope you know we've Unix today are available,
it turns out, basically you know any, look at modern Unix like Linux,
you know these primitives are there,
maybe not exactly the same flavor as argued in the paper, but they are there.
You even saw it in the paper, correct
or some of the operating system did have some version of a subset of them,
but today they basically widely supported.
If you look at Unix today.
Let's see how it actually there instantiate it.
And so one of the, first ones is probably the most important one is something that's just called mmap,
and that can be used to take some object and map it into the address space of the caller,
sort of example if you want to map a file.
You know, then you know the system calls something of the following form,
you call mmap, mmap actually has quite a bit of a building number of arguments,
the first basically says like whether you, you can specify a particular address,
or you would like it to be mapped to
or you can let the kernel decides to choose the address,
and in that case, you specified just know and kernel pick an address where to map,
you know the object, specify the length, you specify the protection bits,
you know, for example read slash write,
and then you know some argument, we want to talk about,
but there's something called math private,
basically you have to say something about how, what happens if you actually write to that particular object.
Let's skip that mostly,
then you can forget we can actually pass in the file descriptor in offset.
And basically what this says is that you know you should map the content of the file object,
pointed to by the file descriptor and you take the file comes to the object you know at offset,
map that basically, that particular a particular address from with that length.
And so this basically allows you to serve what is called memory map file,
so you can bring the contents of the file into your address space,
we've actually having to call read or write system calls.
It's sort of convenient correct,
because then you can manipulate the file just ordinary pointers,
you can write at particular locations
and then at some point you can write to come back to, to the disk
and so it is a convenient interface to a manipulate data structures,
that might be stored into might be stored in the file.
And in fact, you will be implementing this specific version of an mmap
or some version of the file based mmap actually in the next lab.
So this basically integrates you know the file system part of xv6,
you know virtual memory part of xv6
and you can sort of hook them up and by supplying by actually implementing mmap,
mmap can also be used in other ways,
so you can use the map file, you can also use it to map anonymous memory.
And that's basically sort of an alternative to sbrk
where you can sort of ask the kernel, please, you know give me a bunch of memory,
and you know map at this particular address.
So obviously one of the core system calls and related back to the primitives in the second.
Okay, there's a couple more calls that are necessary to actually support the primitives at the paper argued for
and Unix has has them,
so there's more Unix today,
there's an imperative system call.
So once you have something mapped into the address space,
you can actually you know change the the permissions,
so whatever you can make it just know and protect the particular match something into the address space,
then you go and protect for example for a subset of that part or all of it
and map it to particular protection level,
so for example if you did this,
basically loads could be executed,
but stores would you know change into, change into a page fault
and similarly if you want to make sure that range in address space is completely inaccessible,
now, you can, and protected with none
and you know basically then both, everything basically, every access to that particular page or to that address range
starting from address to address plus length,
will result in a page fault.
There's a similar [invention], there's a corresponding call to mmap called unmap,
that allows you to basically remove a mapping or move an address range.
And actually, if you curious you know exactly how these calls work,
you know you should look up the man page of these system calls.
And then finally you know the one that we really need is system call sigaction.
And basically this is a signal handler.
And allows the application to say like you know if a particular signal happens,
then you know call this particular function.
So maybe you can install basically function f as a signal handler for a particular signal.
And in the case of you know page faults,
you know the signal that is generated yeah something was called segfault.
Typically, you might have seen segfault in user code before,
you know typically what happens in the segfault is basically application stops and crashes,
but if the application had installed a handler for you know segfault event or segfault signal,
then instead of the application being stopped, the handler would have been called by the kernel,
and then the application can maybe respond to that particular segfault
in the same way in some sense that the kernel responds to a page fault
and maybe fixes up the page table so that you know the execution can continue
and in this case, maybe the handler will actually call and protect or change the permissions,
so that actually the instruction can resumed and continue.
And, so in this in fact you know you are the most familiar version that we were,
the things that we've seen like a sigaction much like sigalarm,
as Amir mentioned a little bit earlier,
in this sigalarm lab where you could install the alarm program,
basically installed a handler that will have to be called at every clock tick or every you know period of time,
and you know physically sigaction is sort of the equivalent that the general version of it where basically can respond to different types of signals.
Any questions about this.
It seems like mprotect implies that you can add different permission levels on individual addresses
whereas in like xv6 that we've been working with,
you can only apply permissions on full pages,
is that is that a difference, that's a present.
No, it's not real difference, you know works at a page level granularity.
And it doesn't expose you know there's a separate call to find out what the page page sizes,
if you actually curious about it.
Thank you.
Um, so if you think about the primitives that were in the paper,
you know we can map them correctly like what currently Unix or Unix typically provide.
So, what equivalent correct for trap,
you know that we're in Unix would be provided something called the sigaction sigaction call.
And about you know ProtN and Prot1 what is the equivalent to that.
Okay, so basically all three of them correctly can be implemented using mprotect.
And mprotect you know is flexible enough that you could do it by a single page
or actually just ask or you can actually provide something consists of multiple pages
and then you could do, you get the same benefit of one TLB flush,
for changing permissions on a whole series of pages.
Okay?
These calls are almost directly map into some of the primitives,
turns out that you know dirty, actually a little bit harder to do,
you know there's not a direct primitive for or system call for,
although you can sort of more or less get it done with some tricks.
And I'll talk a little bit later about Map2,
there's also not a way to do it,
but it's not completely you know sort of a system called just directly maps onto Map2,
it turns out that if you with multiple mmaps,
you can actually achieve this particular functionality too.
Okay?
So one way to think about this paper is
the kernel developers, you know maybe not totally driven by this paper,
but kernel developers, you know have extended you know these, we have provided these primitives actually to, you know today's user applications.
Okay, I want to say a few words about the implementation,
just a much more sketch level,
and then talk a little bit about you know the applications themselves
and see how they use these particular primitives.
Okay, so, let's talk about there's two aspects that are sort of interesting.
One is actually what actually happens inside the virtual memory system to actually support this.
I'm just going to sketch this out like what the most important pieces are
and in fact you know this is sort of a little bit relevant to mmap lab that is coming up,
because you're going to do something similar.
So address space, typically in Unix today is represented by you know, of course the hardware page table,
which contains the translations,
but typically it's augmented with a set of OS data structure, not related to any specific hardware design,
these are called virtual, virtual memory areas, in short, VMAs.
Basically, what VMA, what VMA represents is you know record some information about the contiguous range of addresses.
So if you think about an address space,
it might have a number of sections in the address space,
you know each [formula] contiguous ranging,
basically for each section that would be VMA.
And the VMA you know may also has all the same permissions through all the pages
in that arrange at the same permissions.
And they're backed by the same object.
For example, if you have a mmap map map, mmap file,
then, the be VMA for that file that describes whatever permissions for the file
as well as you know the information about the file itself,
the file descriptor, for example, that goes along with that particular VMA
and you know the offset in the file were that VMA corresponds to.
In fact you know in the lab upcoming lab,
you know you will implement a very simple version of VMA
and use that to actually implement mmap system call for files
where basically you can record in the VMA,
you are literally the file descriptor in the offset that corresponds to that particular mmap call, the range have been mapped.
Any questions about this?
Okay, so then the second piece you know sort of important
and then we have a little bit of experience with it's probably worthwhile,
you know going through is actually how trap or sigaction,
actually, the handler, how an actual trap will work.
Actually, you'll be more careful.
So we have a user level traps are implemented.
And this follows very, it follows very much you know the same outline as actually the sigalarm system call
and then the up call that happened when a clock tick, actually passed the time limit.
And so the sort of setting here is not not you know clock ticks but page tables,
so let's assume there's some PTE that
has that marked you know you're invalid or maybe it's not read only and you're actually stored to it
and so what happens when the application accesses that PTE that actually is basically invalid or doesn't result in a valid translation.
Well as we know then the CPU, jumps into kernel mode,
jumps into the kernel at a fixed address,
you know you know look at the think the trampoline code,
the kernel save state, so, for example save to trapframe,
then basically asks, you know the VM system.
And what now, what to do.
And the VM system might do something so gently
and in case if this happened in the lazy lab and in the copy-on-write lab
where you know your trap handler code, you know sort of looks at the page table data structures,
in this case, resume will look at the VMAs,
and you see what the scope is just to address that were where the processor folded on
and see what needs to be done
and so for example if it is a segfault
and application has installed a handler to deal with it,
then basically that up call or a handler of the event would be propagated to user space.
And so basically let's say there was a handler installed,
then basically we're gonna get up call to into user space,
in the same way as in the sigalarm lab,
you know that will run you know the handler in user space,
the handler you might call you know mprotect you know to change the protections.
And, then the handler returns to user handler returns to kernel code,
there's a kernel,
and then the kernel basically resumes,
you know they interrupted process.
Okay, and you have to if the, when the kernel resumes that interrupt the process,
you know if example the handler fixed up sort of the address space of the user program,
then they might actually instruction might use execute correctly
or if something is wrong, maybe trap back into the kernel right away again,
if you know the.
If the the hardware still can't translate that particular virtual address.
Does this make sense?
Maybe there's, remember again, the sigalarm lab and then this would be quite familiar.
Yeah, I have a question.
What kind of, I think when we're allowing the user to effectively run a handler code on a page fault,
aren't there additional security vulnerabilities that could result as a part of this,
so I was wondering if it could speak to that.
Yeah, it's a great question,
by the way can you like maybe everybody turn on their cameras to [], if possible,
if you're comfortable doing that I really appreciate it.
I think many students in the class will appreciate it too.
Yeah, so yeah there's a security issue, the first, what do people think,
does this break user kernel, or you know the isolation between different processes.
Another way asking the question did sigalarm break, you know isolation.
Would it be okay,
because the, that that code that the handler would still have access to the same virtual memory,
I mean if there are different virtual memories for the process and for like for each of the processes,
then that handler should be able to look into other process's memory, that would be okay.
Yeah, sure when we do the upcall correct,
we're up, make the upcall that specific user space that actually installed the handler,
so the handler basically runs in the same context,
as runs with the same page table as the application that installed the handler
and so the only thing it really can do is you know affect that application,
but you know that's the application problem can really affect anybody any other application,
because it doesn't have any access to the other applications to page tables, can force switch into them.
So this turns out to be fine,
of course if the handler doesn't return or does something bad,
in the end, the kernel just kill, can always kill the process,
so nothing really, you know the only thing that can go bad is you know the process can hurt itself,
but it can't hurt any other processes.
Amir, does that make sense?
Yes, thank you.
Okay, so now I want to go through a couple examples.
And so to see how you could use it
and I'll start out with very simple example to get ourselves into it
and then we'll move to the garbage collector,
because lots of people ask questions about the garbage collector,
so that seems like a good one to dive into.
Okay, the first example I want to talk about trivial idea,
but you know, in fact there's not even mentioned in the paper,
but it is a sort of a cool way of illustrating you know the power that applications get
if they actually have these primitives available to them.
And the basic idea is to actually build a huge you know memorization table.
And the memorization table is basically what it does
it just remember you know the result of some computation.
And so, for example you can think about in the following way,
let's say we're here's our table,
and you know table start to get whatever zero to some n
and what the table stores is a the result of running some expensive function,
for that argument zero or for whatever f(n).
So if you wanted to, you know if this table were sort of pre computed,
it wants in the beginning of time
and then you wanted to look up like you wanted to know what value for f(i) was,
well what you do is you just look up in the table,
you know in the slot i
and basically you get the the value that if i would have computed.
And so this would return maybe an expensive computation,
maybe f is very expensive, into a basically table lookup,
sort of a cool trick you to basically store the results for pre computers
and store the results of an expensive computation,
and if that's the same computation is actually many many times,
then you know pre computer good ones you might be an advantage to a smart thing to do.
Does that setup makes sense?
Okay, so then the issue, yeah you, of course is that the table or the challenge,
the table might be big, might be actually, in fact very big,
it might be bigger than maybe your physical memory,
but it's still nice to have it.
So the solution, one solution you know that you could, used to solve this problem is
to basically use the virtual memory primitives as described in the paper.
Primitives.
And what you do is you know first of all you allocate a huge range,
but don't really map, you don't actually allocate any physical memory corresponding to that range
[to] use part of your address space,
then say I'm going to use that part of my address space, you've got to store the table.
And then, on a, page, the, there's no content in the table,
[there is] address ranges exist,
so if you do a table lookup, like table i,
you know that will result into a page fault.
And so this plan is on the page fault,
you know, you compute all the entries
or you know all the page basically covers a bunch of entries in the table,
if we reach one of them you're basically you compute function f(i),
store it in the slot table i,
and then basically resume you know the application right now, the,
of course the map the physical page you know so basically take the page fault,
you allocate page, and may restore in that page,
as a result of f(i) for all the slots in the page.
And the advantage of it is correct,
if you know a couple of advantages if you have to ever compute f(i) again,
you know you're going to actually do the table lookup
and you don't actually have to do any expensive computation just with [],
in fact, you know even if you do a table i plus one,
like there's gonna be a bunch of entries in the in that particular page,
they're all basically can now be free, you know just table lookups.
Of course, you keep doing this,
then you're going to consume all physical memory,
and so you know the page fault handler also has to throw out some pages,
if you're running out of memory,
so you know if much memories in use, use,
free some of them, free some pages.
And of course then you have to change, change the protection level
to make sure that you're going to get in the future page fault for those entries.
So you have to presumably call you know Prot1 or ProtN to reduce the accessibility of the page and the terminology of the paper.
Does this make sense, that's sort of a plan.
Okay.
Yeah, you would need to map it would need to request from the operating system to map it to a particular address, right,
because it can go anywhere okay.
Yeah we're going to be anywhere,
as long as you know the operation tell where it actually is.
Okay.
Maybe to make a little bit more concrete,
actually I have a little implementation of this plan.
And we can just look at it
and see what are, you know, how do you actually do that using the existing you know Unix primitives.
Let me.
Okay.
Can everybody see the Emacs buffer, is the font large enough.
I assume that as a yes.
So here's the application,
let me go to the bottom.
So here's main, main basically setup_sqrt_region,
basically allocates address space, but doesn't really allocate the physical pages belonging to it.
And then it calls this function test_sqrt_region to basically go through that table in a random order,
and you know basically checks whether the square root entry in the table for that position
is indeed the correct square root value by just computing it literally before that.
Okay?
So basically test_sqrt_region is going to run
and it's going to presumably generate page fault,
because none of the tables actually filled in so far.
So how does it, how do we get those page faults,
well here's the, sort of the fragment of code,
that you need to basically install a handler a signal handler for a particular event,
we were basically saying here install for a SIG-, you know the SIGSEGV event, the handler SIGSEGV,
and so when a segfault happens, when a page fault happens,
basically the function, the kernel will call sig handles SIGSEGV
and basically you can extract, the faulting address,
you know this looks very similar to your trap code, you've seen many many times before.
And basically the plan is very straightforward,
we map a page at that particular address,
you know because that's the address that we want to fill in,
we have to, so my expensive function here or the, the replacement for the expensive function
or the role of expensive function is the square root function,
and so we want to basically fill in you know the square root of whatever value,
it has to be there at that particular location in the table.
So we allocate a page and and map it there
and then we calculate for that page all the square root entries,
and then we're done
and this this application is a little bit extreme,
what I did is basically I run this table with only one physical page allocated,
so whatever the last page was,
would just release it by unmapping it.
And so we have a gigantic table,
that's basically represented it by one physical page.
And we can just run, you know we wanted to,
we could run this application,
it's not gonna be that particular exciting, why not.
So, compiled it, you know and basically go through and randomly bounces around in a table,
presumably causing a lot of different page faults in all the entries,
you know actually work out
and so even though there's gigantic it was square root page table,
table, virtual square root table,
the actually physical representation of that table just consist of a single page.
And this sort of example of, one of the very simple example,
of one of the cool things you can do,
if these virtual memory [payments] available to user applications.
Any questions about this?
Could you just quickly go over that last point,
on why there's only one physical page,
I guess I was thinking during it like oh this sounds similar to lazy allocation,
why, why is it different and I think that answered my question,
but I I didn't quite follow, why we ended up.
Okay, the reason,
okay, so when we start when we set it up, we have no pages,
setup square root region actually allocates address space,
but then unmap all the physical memory associated with that address immediately.
So the point of startup, there's no physical pages allocated to this particular table.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
Okay, then we get, when we get a page fault,
that means there's like one page out of the whole table, that we have not map,
we have map no pages,
but we're gonna page fault, now we're gonna map one page,
and in that one page, we're going to fill in whatever you know the square root of i, i plus one, i plus whatever,
just gonna afford that particular page.
And then, if we had a page map,
which in this case the first time around, we didn't,
there's nothing to be done.
So now the application runs, you know and look up some more entries page in the square root table
and you get another page table for another page fault,
because it was looking up a square root entry that actually is not on the allocated page.
Okay?
So that point we get another page fault,
and then we allocate a second page,
we calculate the square roots, you know for that particular page,
and then we unmap the last page.
These is of course like practice you would never do this,
in practice you would try to keep a working set of set of pages or something like that,
but just to show that you can go pretty extreme,
that you can represent like huge page, huge table with a single page of memory,
this particular fragment of code unmaps that last one but last page,
and it keeps running.
So, any point instance, at any point of time,
there's only one physical page being used.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah, I think so, thank you.
Okay good.
It's just like, it's more like,
this is clearly not something you would do in practice,
maybe there's more to show you know the power of the primitives,
you know that you can represent the gigantic table using one single physical page.
Any other questions?
Okay,, what I would like to do next,
then is talk about another example,
and in particular I want to talk about the garbage collector.
You know since a lot of questions were about the garbage collector.
And so you know yeah, so the garbage collectors are a way of
basically for programming languages or languages that basically do memory allocation and freeing on behalf of the programmer,
so the programmer doesn't have to call like C correct,
you have to call malloc and then you have to call free explicitly to free the memory,
languages that use garbage collectors, basically the application only has, only basically call malloc,
never has to worry about actually freeing the memory,
basically the garbage collector will do the work to determine if the memory still is in use,
and if the memory is not in use, then it's actually a free it.
And so it's nice, you know what are some example programming languages that have garbage collectors.
Java.
Yeah java python, you know, Go many of them actually correct,
almost you know, other than maybe C Rust,
there every other programming language basically has a garbage collector, okay.
So as you can imagine, there's a huge literature and a design space for garbage collectors
and the point of this paper is not like to use the best garbage collector possible,
but here you know basically illustrate if garbage collectors could take advantage of, you know, these user level of the memory primitives.
And so the particular garbage colloctor, the paper discusses is copying garbage collector.
And the basical plan is sort of you know the top level outline is as follows
you basically have a memory, a heap from which you know memory is allocated,
you divide the memory in the heap in two pieces,
one is the from piece, what the paper calls the from space
and the other is the to space.
And, let's say we're having started with applications to start
and so all memory is free,
basically start allocating memory in the from space,
so let's say we allocated maybe tree like data structure,
you know that here's the root,
so the tree and that maybe has a pointer to another object,
and that maybe has a pointer to another object,
and that is also pointed to by the root,
sort of just for a little cicle with of objects.
And maybe the application we introduced a lot of other memory too,
but there's no nothing pointing to it anymore
and so basically the only objects live objects are the ones that actually are basically accessible from the root.
So at some point like maybe I've allocated lots of memory before
and we allocate one more object, and it turns out there's no space anymore,
application ask for one more object, it turns out there's no space anymore for it,
because the whole from spaces basically has been used.
So then the basic idea is in this a copying garbage collector is
to take the objects and copy them over to the user to the to space
and the way you do, it is you start from the root,
because every application where every has a set of registers,
where basically this top level pointers are stored,
or maybe there's a local variables on the stack,
basically there's a set of root
and there for simplicity, I'm just going to assume there's one root
and you start tracing basically from the top level.
So you know you copy the root object over to the to space,
and you know and that's the only thing you do at that point
and then you know of course that leaves you know the pointers you know still pointing to whatever objects they were there before.
And then you're gonna want to copy the object over,
you go and inspect we scan the object,
then of course the language runtime knows exactly what type the object is and knows where the points are
and just look at these points and says okay, maybe I should copy some more pointers over,
because those are actually a clue, you know part of the live data structure.
And so basically maybe we'll take the top level pointer,
look at that object, you copy that object over you know to the to space,
updates you know the pointer here,
you know to actually indicate that actually it has been and pointing it to now copied version of the object.
And then of course later on we need to remember that we're actually this object has been copied,
so you saw a little bit of extra information
and remember that these objects are so now still work there,
in this process, you know a sort of moving an object from the from space to the to space
and leaving a forwarding pointer in the from space, is called forwarding.
Okay, so we now, so we did this,
we did fix this pointer, we fix that pointer there's one more left,
so we'll look at that object and we copy it over like before,
and it still has a pointer pointing to this object,
so now we look at that particular pointer,
look at point say ah, that actually has already been copied
and in fact we know what the new location is,
so we can just straight updated to point to the right place.
Okay, and so at this point you know all the pointers have been you know correctly updated,
you know the whole structure, you know the whole cycle,
basically of objects as we move from the from space to to space
and so at this point we're done.
At this point, we're done,
we forwarded all the objects
and basically the from space, now you know all the objects in the from space are being discarded,
and it's now free space.
Does that make sense?
That's the basic plan in a copying garbage collector.
Okay, now the scheme that is used in the paper,
couple sophistications, I want to talk about them.
First sophistication, you know is that you know they actually they're called this is called bakers algorithm it's old algorithm.
And one of the nice, you know future has
is that sometimes it's originally called real time,
real what I meant is it's an incremental garbage collector.
So, and the main idea is that,
here if we have our two from space and to space.
Main idea is that you know we have our root again,
here's root, it had two pointers, and it's pointing back.
The main idea is that it's not really necessary to stop the world
and copy everything over and then basically resume competition.
The only thing really necessary is to actually move copy over the root.
And basically do nothing else,
and so basically you know at this point you know the root has been copied,
but you know it's pointers are still pointing you know the here,
because that object has not been scanned,
it hasn't been, it's points haven't been updated yet.
And and the basic idea is
then whenever the application calls new,
you know whenever new call you scan a few more objects,
or you forward a couple more objects.
And that's sort of nice, correct,
because basically you spread the cost of actually you know copying the complete you know active or live heap from the application incremental steps,
every new ever call allocates contributes a little bit, you know to actually do a complete copy operation.
And of course the application might also be using you know some of these pointers,
for example if you know root will be dereferencing, actually this, this second red pointer,
it's still actually pointing into the from space,
and of course that is dangerous,
because we shouldn't be tracking pointers in the from space.
And so basically this means that every time you do dereference, do dereference a pointer,
you need to check, check if it's in the from space, if from space.
And if so, you do the forwarding.
And so the application is allowed to use the pointers,
but basically to run the compiler has to instrument the application that basically every pointer accesses surrounded by that check,
so that you know, we basically maintain the invariant that all,
at any pointer in the to space, you know points to objects in to space.
And we need to ensure that correct,
because when in the end we're done,
you know we want to remove the from space and have,
so that we can discard it and you reuse it as free space.
Okay, any questions about this, this is sort of the basic setup.
Okay, so, if there are no questions,
in the paper makes two points you know about this scheme
and one is you know it's annoying or too bad you actually have to do this dereference at every time.
So basically, this means load or store instruction,
instead of being single instruction actually has a bunch of instructions,
namely branch instruction and perhaps you mean calling a function to actually do it forward.
And so you know that increase the cost of the application.
The second thing that actually points out is that
it is not that easy to paralyze a garbage collector,
because maybe in a nice setting,
it's like if you're running in a multi-core machine,
where you know have a lot of free CPUs,
basically I realize that the collector you know just put in the backgrounds,
you know traverse the object graph,
and you know copy things incrementally over as it continues.
But if the application at the same time you know is using the graph,
there's a risk you know the application maybe you know,
there's one of the reference check, one of these checks starts copying an object,
while at the same time, the collectors also copying the object
and we're not very carefully, we may end up with the object copied twice
and the pointer, there's no not pointing in the right places,
you can easily see correct there's a race condition,
possible of a possibility of race conditions.
So there, paper basically describes a scheme,
it's like if you had you know the user level primitives,
then actually you could do something different,
you could do a cool trick
and you can actually use VM, you know virtual memory to basically reduce the cost of the check,
in almost get concurrency for free.
And so the basic ideas, which follows you know we have our same setup,
you know our from, and here's our to.
And what we're gonna do is
like we're gonna have we're gonna have we're gonna region, we actually divide the to space virtually
or literally we divide the to space in an area that is a unscanned.
Let me a little bit more clear.
We have an area basically, here is scanned, and an area unsacnned.
And initially basically you know the whole area is unscanned,
you know when you know start out,
you know you make the flip from the from to the to space,
nothing has been scanned yet,
because there's no objects at the yet
and so but basically scheme starts in the same way, we copy over the root object,
it used to be there
and copy it over, you have some pointers, you know basically these pointers point still back into the,
oops, yeah, in these pointers will point back into the old from space
and so that's it,
and now we're basically saying, and what we're gonna do is
for the unscanned area, which is this point everything,
we're going to basically map and map them with no permission, mapping none.
And so what does that mean, well that means that
the first time around the application,
you know after we did the flip, the garbage collected it to flip,
the first time the application is usually the root pointer,
it will get a page fault,
because you know, that part of the address range has actually unmapped.
So basically then the ideas in the fault handler,
scan one page of objects,
and forward to want and need to be forwarded.
So basically you know we in this particular setting,
where we're only copied over just the root so far,
you know we are going to copy over root,
we can scan you know the pointers in the object to which the root is pointing,
in this case there are only two of them,
we kind of copy over those two objects you know into the unscanned space,
or maybe let me drawing slightly different here,
just make it look like we've got copy over those two objects that were pointing to
and basically we update you know the you know remove this scan line,
you know from here to there,
so this is no scanned.
And so after we scan the page,
we can actually increase, you know basically protect or basically unprotect,
you can unprotect the page, unprotect the scan page.
Okay?
And you know the, and then the application,
you can just you know access the particular object,
because we translated you know the pointer that's inside of the objects,
it's safe to expose it to the application,
the application can traverse those pointers,
of course those pointers are still pointing to objects that are having been scanned in
then we'll, we'll get a page fault again
and then we scan a little bit more.
So it basically has the benefits still incremental,
you can still do a little bit of work,
you know every time we can also do it every time new we can actually allocate you know some do some work,
but it has the additional benefit,
there's no no pointer check anymore,
the pointer check is still there, but it's done in hardware,
with the page, the VM hardware does it for us.
Does that make sense?
Any questions about this, about this plan.
I have a question,
so, in, in the handler you're saying that you scan one page of objects,
but how do you know that the objects that the root has references to will be will fall into the same,
like how do you know that the objects that really need to be forwarded,
in order to not violate the invariant will be in the same page.
You'll be,
Okay, there's some set of objects in the page,
the starting,
okay but let's say you know what the.
Okay, at the beginning when we flip this spaces,
there's nothing in the to space,
what we could do is like what the right thing to do is
just copy I just tried to just copy one page,
but basically copy over or forward one page,
basically copy n objects over,
so that they fill a complete page.
Right.
Now we have n objects sitting on that one page all unscanned.
Then, at some point a page fault handler or happen
and then you know the garbage collector, you are collector, you go through each object on that one page
and looks for its pointers,
and for each pointer it moved copies over those you know objects into the, into the unscan part of the to space.
And so that if you know anybody or if the application would use one of those
instead objects will get a page fault and they can scan those etc etc.
Does that answer the question?
Yeah.
Okay.
Oh, sorry I also had a question.
Yeah, so after you do this do flip the two in the from.
Okay.
Okay, you, you start out in the from space you fill it up,
you flip to you copied over to the to space
and then you call the from, once you're done with the complete with scanning,
and you're done with the from space is completely clear,
just you flip the names
and you start using the to space to actually do the allocations
until it's full and then you flip again.
Thank you.
Any further questions?
So one of the, one of the things that one of the arguments the paper also makes,
that you know the one other thing that the VM system or using VM,
simplifies is basically concurrency,
the argument is that, basically the collector you can just go through the unscanned pages,
so we have, go through and scan pages and basically scan one page at a time
and if it is guaranteed that the application has no pointers
or cannot access in the same time that page,
because its own map.
And so, you know as long as the,
so the paging hardware, basically sort of introduces explicit synchronization or protection against races,
because only the collector can access that page
and the from and the application can actually not access the page.
So it gives a nice automatic parallelism,
where the application can run and do its business,
the collector can do its business,
and they will never step on each other's toes,
because if the application ever will touch an unscanned page and look at a page fault,
and, and the collector never touches scanned pages,
and so will never interfere with the application.
So you get sort of comparison for free,
but it actually has a tricky issue.
Although it's almost for free,
you know there's actually one thing you actually have to arrange,
which is the area correct in the unscanned area, which actually unmapped,
so we look at our picture from before here are two,
where here's are from, here's our to
and you know we have split in the unscanned, scanned the area,
and unscanned, and it has no if none, protected none.
So that raises the question,
you know how this actually do collector, go through,
because we can't actually access those pages,
because you know their own map correct protectively, they're inaccessible.
And so and the trick is basically follows,
and this is where map2 comes in.
What we're gonna do is actually going to map that same physical memory,
we mapped at once correct, we mapped at once in this way,
I'm gonna map the second time in the collectors view sort of the collective view of the to space.
So these collectors view here's the app view
and in the collector's view where I still have to and from exactly like before.
Oops, let me try.
We have to and from.
And what we're doing actually you know here's our unscanned area,
but in the collector, we map actually those unscanned area read and write,
and so that the collector actually can go through,
look at the scan the objects you know and forward pointer is necessary.
And so the users look at the place where this map2 call is necessary,
where arrange physical piece of physical memory is actually mapped twice
in the address space of an application at two different levels of protection,
to basically make things, scenario like this work.
Any questions about this?
I have a question,
do you, do you kind of give each collector in the app, different versions of the page table, or.
No, they have the same page table correct,
but they have the memory mapped in two place,
the physical memory map in two different places in the address space,
in two different places places in page table.
And, in one place you basically the mapping is invalid,
and in the other address range, you make the mapping read write.
Okay.
Would you make, make a make this a little bit more clear.
Since there were so many questions about it.
I should have a trivial implementation of actually this basic idea,
the idea that was described in the paper,
that you should make it a little bit more concrete.
And so, let me walk through this and ask feel free to jump in,
basically toy implementation of what's described in the paper
and I'm sure it has bugs, I mean, I haven't really tested this in any way seriously,
but it's mostly there's illustrates you know to make everything slightly more concrete.
So the collector the api if you will that the application uses is,
a new and read pointer and read pointer is that basically does the check whether pointers in from space,
and if it is in the from space, that needs to be copied
and of course when we're using VM tricks,
then basically this read pointer is going to be very cheap,
we basically return the existing, returns argument.
If we're just for this simple application,
I have a linked list and it has two roots,
you know pointing one to the head and one to the last node of the linked list,
it's a circular linked list,
and nothing really too exciting going on,
basically what the application for it does is
you know thousand times makes the list and makes a list and checks the list
and so it generates a lot of garbage like everytime after to make list is done,
it's going to make a new one and so the last list is basically garbage.
And so the collector actually has something to do
and make a list, you know is basically a little bit of ugly code,
mostly because you know every pointer needs to be wrapped in this read pointer check.
Normally, of course would be generated by a compiler
and I don't really have a compiler for a garbage collected language
and so I'm just simulating what may be a compiler that might have generated.
And basically you want to know the code does is,
it goes through the built a list of at least list size,
allocates a new element
and stick to the present at the beginning of the list
and then updates the last pointer to point basically to the beginning of the list,
so that's circular.
Any questions about this little fragment of code.
So the most interesting question like what goes on exactly the collector,
let's first look at the case where there's no virtual memory,
where we're not using these tricks.
And so we just have to look at two APIs,
one is new and read pointer.
So use a new, forget the mutex, that is for the VM based solution,
basically, I forget that we're assuming that we're actually not scanning,
we're not collecting for a while,
were basically, we check if there's enough space left,
in the free space, if there's enough free space left,
you know we just bump up to point a little bit,
you know to allocate object and return it.
And if there's not enough space less left,
then we basically have to flip we have to do the garbage collection run.
And so we look at flip, you know flip basically switches the to from pointers around,
and basically forward which you know the two roots that this application has,
you know to the from the from space to space,
so let's look at forward.
So here's forward,
it looks if the forward object that is pointed to by o,
it looks always actually in the from space,
if it is in the from space and it has not been copied before,
then we're gonna copy it and now we're done.
So we moved the object from the from space to to space,
if we already copied it, then basically we can replace the pointer,
you know we have the new pointer is actually the pointer to the already moved object and return that.
Okay?
So that's forwarding.
And so, then the read pointer, you know we actually ever, read pointer to basically go through,
let's see what the read pointer with the garbage collecter,
just read pointer, it's like right here,
if we're not using if we're not using VM,
basically what it does, it does a forward operation,
in the forward operation is checking if the from space,
if not in the from space, then, do nothing,
if it is in the from space, then do this copy again.
So here we see this sort of the expensive check,
is really checking if the object actually sits in the from space.
Any questions, before I jump into sort of the version that actually use the VM tricks.
Okay, let's look at actually what the VM tricks.
So the setup is a little bit, is here,
basically you know there's a call called shm_open that allows you to create a shared memory object,
it's a Linux call or Unix call,
and it almost behaves like a file, but it's not,
it behaves like a file, but it is not a file,
it just sits in memory, there's no disk space associated with it or anything,
it's like an in-memory file system, if you will.
And, basically you know what we're doing is
we allocate one of the shared memory objects,
we truncate the shared memory object to be the size of the sum of the two in the from space,
so we have a space,
and then we map it once in the, for mutator,
and we map it once you know for the collector.
So this is basically you know the sort of sequence of operations here,
you know the shm_open, the ftruncate and the two mmaps
are basically sort of equivalent of the map2 calls.
And so we look at you know.
Let's go back up to our implementation,
the read pointer in the VM case does nothing,
you know there's no check whatsoever would return a pointer straight.
And then you know of course we used [] pointer,
we're gonna get a page fault,
like as before in the [sig roots] table application,
maybe here's the page fault handler.
So it is, if it's a page on
and actually let me run a little bit here.
If you know the object was moved somewhere earlier and sitting in the unscanned area,
we're getting a page fault and basically the scan page, you know function runs.
And but you know the the scan page function runs actually with you know the address ranges of the collector
and so it actually can work,
because otherwise a mutator correct, the application cannot touch those pages,
because then we take a result in a page fault.
And once you know we can, you know once we've scanned all the pages,
then you know the, the collector actually makes the page actually accessible to the user application.
It may be helpful to look at flip again,
just to see what happens, actually flip what happens,
we switch from the from space is full,
we make basically mark the whole to space as non accessible to the application,
and then we move to collector moves actually the root head and the root last you know to the two space
that the application cannot access or at least not directly,
and you know will result whenever the application accesses root head, root last,
it will actually result in a page fault,
and then the collector can copy things over and then protect the one page.
Does that make sense?
Okay note in the handler correct,
it's actually crucial that first the pages scanned,
before you make you know the page accessible to the application,
because if you were to make it accessible before you scan that,
you know, and if there were multiple application threads,
then those applications might be looking at objects on the in the unscanned area,
of course that we need to forbid that,
that's over this code basically for scans
and then raises the protection level,
so the application can access the pages.
Any questions about the collector and tricks to use virtual memory.
Okay.
In that case I want to wrap up a couple points,
I wanna make one point basically before wrapping up.
You know, one question to ask you should you use the VM for this.
It really is it does those tricks payoff
and because many of the for example garbage collectors and many garbage collectors out there
that actually don't use virtual memory at all,
but use basic instrument,
you know the compiler is actually very aware of the code generated an instrument you know the code correctly.
And as all kinds of other tricks to reduce the performance overhead.
So the observation is that in most cases,
it can be, and most cases could have been implemented with extra instructions.
And that is, you know if you were basically a compiler or runtime, or for a programming language,
then maybe that's not so bad,
because the compiler can do the instrumentation,
but if you know there's not a runtime applications not compiler application or a programming language settings,
then, that might be painful.
So it turns out that for some of these applications where there's no compiler involved at all,
for example like check pointing or you know do shared virtual memory,
those actually you know really needs these kind of primitives.
And so in practice, you know it is the case that you know enough application programmers I find these primitive worthwhile,
but basically today's operating systems support them.
Okay?
Some people ask, a lot of people actually asking
what has changed since, what has changed since 91.
You know, one thing that has changed of course, like most Unix do support the primitives now.
And in fact there are many changes since 91,
yeah yeah, maybe hard to imagine, but basically there's a continuous development in the VM system,
so if you look at like Linux,
you know git log, you'll see you know there's a there's continued developing the all aspects of the kernel,
but including a continuous development of the VM system.
And you know some of the bigger changes, what are some big changes in the last you know whatever ten years,
there there's you know there's now five level page table to deal with really large a bigger addresses,
there's address space identifiers to deal with TLB the cost of TLB flushes. More recently a year ago or something like that something is called was introduced called KPTI kernel page table isolation,
which you know is there because of the meltdown attacks and we'll talk about later in the semester.
So, you know the virtual memory system is absolutely not a static system
almost after no aspect of any kernel kernel is static,
there's a traumatic amount of changes almost every couple months, in different aspects of the kernel
and so in systems in once in a while actually completely rewritten.
So it's always in flux.
Okay, let me stop with that
and you know anybody has more questions now, please feel free to ask them
or if you have to go, feel free to go.
Could I ask about one of the first slides,
where of, sorry I'm trying to see it,
it's VM implementation like two slides after this one.
Yes, that one.
What do you mean exactly by continuous range for addresses.
Oh, yeah continuous range of virtual addresses,
so you know the may you know VMA copies arrange 1000 to 2000,
and if you had another address range like 2100 or something like that,
that would be has its own VMA,
so every VMA covers a continuous range of addresses,
there are no holes in it.
Okay.
That makes it easier,
as you will see in the, as you will see mmap lab,
that will make it much easier to reason about things,
addressing in the range of VMA may has no hole in it.
Okay, okay, so those are for, this particular use case, for mmap, right.
Yeah.
Okay thank you.
So basically you can think about it for every mmap call,
there's one VMA if mmaps don't overlap.
Oh, okay, okay I think I think I understand, thank you.
To ask, so for for the high on the to and from like garbage collection,
when do you stop and start again,
like I guess collector runs can run all the time, if its concurrent.
Yeah, that's one of the cool things about this VM solution,
the collector can run all the time,
and it can stop once basically it has there's no more unscanned objects.
Okay, so you have but you have to go through, that means you.
So so you'll go through all of the stuff like all of the objects in the from section
and all you're either gonna collect them or copy them over
how do you know you've gone through all of them.
You, at some point you you trace the object grabbed down, correct,
and at some point you're not adding any objects anymore,
because you already copied them in the past.
Okay okay, that makes sense.
You don't add any more, basically your unscanned area is not growing,
so if your unscanned area is not growing anymore, you don't.
Okay, okay, and then when you copy it over you unmap it,
so if someone tries to access the old pointer is going to be invalid, right.
Okay, that makes sense, thanks.
Alright, I'll see you guys later.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Okay, I think that may be it for today.