I started and everybody could see my screen that I shared?
And I hope everybody can hear me.
Let me.
I think we're good.
Okay, so I'm going to talk about file system today
and going to be actually going to spend three lectures on file systems,
two in the context of xv6 and one in the context of Linux.
In fact, this is the last topic, that we're covering of xv6,
after this week, we're basically done with xv6.
So, you know file systems, you all know them, you use them,
they're one of the most sort of user facing aspects of an operating system, in addition to the shell.
And so, we want to understand now and the set of lectures actually
what it really happens under the hoods and how is the file system is implemented
and that's sort of exciting, because you know you use them all the time.
And maybe here to start off with a question before diving in any of the details,
I, in one way you know, since you use file systems are almost daily,
in one way is the xv6 file system different than the file system that you're using in the day-to-day work.
Maybe I'll collect them to people
and see what they think,
for example Kendall, Kendall Garner, what.
Did you notice anything particular about xv6 that is different or similar.
I'm not sure we can hear your, Kendall.
Here I am.
Yeah.
Yeah okay.
So one of the problems is size
or at least the size of the files that xv6 support are much less than a lot of other file systems,
also the names for some files are relatively short.
And another feature, it's more just to use [] [],
it doesn't, I don't think it has a copy-on-write for a file system.
Good, in what way is similar.
It's similar in the general structure,
so the idea of you have file names,
you have the inodes, directories, and all that.
Yeah, seems good.
And how about Adella Yang.
How do you compare xv6 file system to the file system you use.
Sorry, what is that.
The question is like how would you,
how would you compare the xv6 file system to the file system, you might be using in daily life
or on your laptop whatever computer you're using.
Any similarities.
Yeah, like the the file system paths,
system like paths and file system are like hierarchical.
Yep, that's a good point.
Okay, so you know, so let me, so dive in a little bit
and sort of talk a little bit about properties of file systems,
you know sort of stand out,
and one I think you know you just mentioned here Adella is user-friendly, user-friendly names,
in particular path names, you know hierarchy to, hierarchy to them,
to help people to organize their files and directories or folders whatever term you want to use
and it makes it easy for you know people to share files you know between users and processes.
You can name them with conveniently to remember names.
And then probably most importantly prepared at least for all the subsystems,
that we've looked so far in xv6 and they provide persistence,
or sometimes that's called durability.
With that, I mean like if you turn off your computer,
you did some work, you turn off your computer and turn off your laptop,
and then a couple days later you come back, you turn your computer on,
the files are still there.
And, if you continue working with them.
Which is different from like processes or the thing of the resources that we've seen so far,
which basically you know the computer reboots, you know they're gone
and you have to start up again,
but file systems can provide this persistence.
And so they're your, all of you using them,
and what we're gonna be doing in the next couple lectures
is actually understanding how to actually work internally.
And this is interesting for a number of reasons.
One you know the abstraction itself, it's just useful.
And so it's interesting to understand, under the hood it's actually how do abstraction is actually implemented.
It turns out there's a couple key interesting aspects,
one is crash safety.
You'd like it to be the case that you know
if for example during the file system operation, the computer crashes,
that after reboot basically file system still intact,
you know all the variants of the file systems still hold
and that you can actually get access to most of your files,
it would be a disaster if the computer crashed in the middle of file system operation, you reboot and there's no file system anymore,
or you know the data structure on disk have been garbled and you lost them.
And so this actually turns out to be a really important topic,
and involved and so we're going to talk about that on Wednesday,
this is basically the main topic for Wednesday's lecture.
Then there's sort of a general question about how to layout the file system on disk.
You know, the files, the files, the directories,
they all have to be represented in some way on the disk,
because like after if you shut down your computer, come back up,
you know all the data still has to be there
and so there's basically on this data structures
to represent the structure of the file system or the content of the file system.
In xv6, of course you know that representation or the data structures used are quite simple,
you know just do for pedagogical reasons
and real file systems more complex data structures,
but you can just think about this as on this data structures.
And so we'll see a lot of that in today's lecture.
And then finally, what makes it interesting is performance.
The devices typically on which you know file systems are stored in our storage devices are typically slow.
The meaning example to me to read or write a block,
you know on a solid-state disk, SSD disk, that's going the order a millisecond
and so in the millisecond, you can do a ton of work.
And so it's important that you're trying to avoid going to disk,
we'll see that in multiple ways,
so we see that potential, all file system will have something of a buffer cache or a block cache.
And you also see it invisibly additional forms or more concurrency.
For example, if you do a path name lookup,
you know, then that typically is involved operation required descending the directory hierarchy,
you looking up blocks for a directory,
find the file name in the directory,
then go through the next directory, etc etc,
and you wanted to be the case that if one process is doing path name lookup,
another process can run concurrently or in parallel with the first process doing a path name lookup.
And so we'll see that sort of concurrency you know shows up
again is a big topic in the context of file systems.
The other reason why it's interesting is it's going to be the topic of two labs.
So we're gonna have next upcoming lab is completely focused on file systems
and the lab after that is a combination of virtual memory and file systems
and even the lab for today or this week has a component to trying to make the buffer cache more parallel.
So that's why it's interesting
and you just you should get off the ground to understand what the file system must provide,
just let's look again at the basic file system system calls, right,
to the.
If you example if looking at you know API, these file system calls,
then we can through there's a couple of interesting properties,
that must be true about the implementation.
And so do you know the file system calls,
we've seen them early on in, in the semester
and you know we've looked at most other Unix system calls how do we implement it,
like fork and exec pipes, all that stuff,
and basically this set of lectures is really focusing on how to implement the file system calls.
So, first of all, let's startup applications with a simple scenario.
We have you know say we create a file x/y,
or file y in the directory x.
Yeah, it probably have to oops.
Yeah, in the file x, we have to provide some flags,
we don't really care about their flag, so I'm just going to ignore them,
so this will create a file returns a file descriptor you know to the caller
and the caller, the user application can then actually for example write, you know through that file descriptor,
as we've seen many times before,
there's a write fd, maybe abc, you know 3 characters.
And one things, actually you know already a couple things that we can point out right, from this two calls.
Is that first of all, the path names,
let's show up in the interface and we're going to have to implement.
Names are hum- human readable,
they're not numbers, you know they get selected by the user.
Another interesting thing here is that in the write system call,
there's no offset as an argument, so the offset is implicit.
So the file system somewhere must store the offset,
if you do a second call to write,
write will end up as you know the next set of bytes will written in that location four.
You know, so maybe some more interesting calls that we haven't looked at much,
but for example, you know the xv6 and all Unix file systems basically support calls to create links,
to have multiple names for the same files for the same file,
so for example it might call like link that basically creates a second name for the original file,
so for example, creates names z for the file y that we earlier created.
So multiple names, the file system, probably internally has to keep track
you know in some way that multiple names might be pointing to the same file.
We might actually remove, or changed name space, while the file is open,
so for example, why we could call,
user might actually call it a process where the same process might call a link you to remove a particular file.
In fact you know we removed the file x/y that we actually open earlier,
but we still have a file descriptor open
and so in fact you know we can still write to it,
so we can still write to fd, you know, for example the character whatever d e and f.
And it actually worked out fine.
So basically while you know file file was used,
the name space that surrounds it could actually be changed.
And so it has to be the case,
you know if you sort of look at this you know sort of things,
that there's a bunch of interesting things going on internally the file system,
for example the file system, file descriptor must be associated,
we have some you know object that is independent of the name,
actually because you know even if the name changes,
the file descriptor still point or you know, references the same file object itself.
And, so, in fact if you think about this, it has to be the case,
that basically there has to be some internal representation of the file inside of the operating system,
that's independent of the name itself.
And so we're looking at in a second,
but there's one other point I wanted to make here
is the goal of the file system is to be implemented an API like the ones that we're looking here
which is a sort of typical file system API.
You know, this is of course not the only way to be able to storage system
or going to store the information on this,
you know we could imagine completely different APIs.
And, for example, you know maybe use a database right,
store some data persistently,
but access to the data provides very different programming or API user API,
than a file system does.
And so just important, to keep in mind that you know,
you know there's other ways of organizing storage systems
and where our focus is going to be on file system,
which is typically provided by an operating system.
And databases are typically implemented on top of the file system
or [in] most of work around the file system,
you can't have direct access to the disk.
We have two questions in the chat.
Yeah.
Let me, [just] going to ask any questions.
So link increments a reference to the underlying file descriptor and unlink decrement.
Yes, that is correct, we'll talk a little bit more about it later.
Another question here is about a soft links versus hard links.
I'm going to talk much about it today,
but you will be implementing soft links
in the next in the file system lab that is upcoming.
So xv6 by itself implements hard links,
and you implement soft links in addition.
Any questions, other questions?
The link operates on the inode not under file descriptor right.
That's correct, link work on the item,
so let me since let's go there.
So file system structures.
So what structure does the file system maintain to implement you know this API just talked about.
So first of all the most important property is the inode,
and so this is the object that represents a file independent of the name,
so file info independent of name.
In fact, you know the way you name actually inode this [] inode number just literally an integer.
So the file system internally refers to inode by number instead of actually by path names.
And we also know this based on this discussion,
that you know inode must actually have link count,
to keep track of the number of, to keep track of the number of names,
that are pointing to that particular inode
and the file should only be deleted when the link count actually reaches zero no earlier.
It's actually slightly more complicated,
there must be also an open fd count,
number file descriptors that actually have to file open
and file can only be deleted when both of these are zero.
And we also know that basically based on you know the write have no offset,
nor does read,
you know that the file descriptor implicitly must maintain an offset.
Okay?
And so basically the central really data structure in a file system is a inode
and then a file descriptor to actually interact with the processes.
So, even though the file systems are very similar terms short of their API,
you know they're all implemented differently,
but many of them have a sort of similar structure.
And because the file systems are quite complex,
you know just helps to sort of organize them in a typically organized in a set of layers.
And you want me to think about it,
this is at the very bottom, there's the disk,
some storage device that actually holds you know the data.
And actually provides the persistence and durability
and typically you know there's something like a buffer cache, a block cache right, above it.
So now to avoid going to disk many times,
so we're gonna cash basically data inside in memory,
so this is going to be basically, you know memory.
And this is the device.
For persistence, there's something typically offer logging layer,
you know many many files that have a form of logging.
We're going to talk emotionally about it Wednesday, so I can skip that.
Then the top of the logging or [] xv6,
there's an icache where inode cache,
this is mostly for synchronization,
let's also talk about a little bit later,
so now you know typically smaller than this block
and many inodes are packed into a single disk block
provides synchronization to those individual inode,
you know xv6 maintains icache,
and then typically that you know were inode the implementation itself,
you know that sort of ranges for read and writes bytes.
And then you know on top of that, we have names,
like path names and file descriptor operations.
Anyway, every file system be slightly differently organized
and layers may be slightly different,
maybe layering is not always that strict,
even xv6 it's not always super strict,
but it is conceptually good way to think about it
and almost all file systems have components in their file systems correspond to the different pieces,
you know the buffer cache, the logging, to the inodes and to path names.
And so we basically work by through a little bit,
through these different file system layers.
Let me talk a little bit of starting with the bottom layer.
Just looking at the chat.
So let me start with a talk a little bit about storage itself, storage devices.
It turns out there are many many, many different types of storage devices,
in the difference between performance you know capacity, degree of durability,
but you know two of the common ones you know are
you know you're probably all familiar with you know the SSD,
and there maybe you know some people may simply mean choosing hard disks or magnetic disks.
And you know they provide a ton of storage,
in reasonable cost, in different performance,
so SSD have typically in the order of hundreds of microseconds, tn the milliseconds access time,
well magnetic disks tend to be more in the order of ten milliseconds to individually read or write a block.
The terminology is actually slightly confusion here,
you know, the terms sector, that are used blocks,
and so in sectors typically the historically the smallest unit,
that disk drives can can read or write in
and so you should be typically five hundred twelve bytes just a common number,
the block size is basically where a block is basically an OS or a file system idea or defined by a file system
and in xv6 for example it is 1024 bytes,
and so it's two sectors,
so typically the block sizes one or more sectors.
Sometimes people refer to the sectors on disk also as blocks
and so you know the terminology is not particularly precise.
So these devices you know basically sit you know on some bus,
and you know the bus is connected to the CPU right.
I mean there might be memory on the side here.
Maybe multiple CPUs, in the file system that runs on the CPU,
stores its internal data structures in memory
and basically reads and writes,
yeah to to the SSD or the hard disk
to actually write a block or read a block
and so to actually interface is quite simple.
So it's typically just read you know or write with block number.
There's a little bit of oversimplification,
but like the core of the interface is roughly that,
internally, of course SSDs and hard disk to work completely differently
and hardware extracts mostly away
and typically they're sort of standard protocols like PCI or PCI extended,
that's the processor or the file system user disk drivers
used to actually talk to disks
and often from the disk driver or you know most disks you know sort of look the same
and you can just read and write by providing a block number and some data
and then you send it off for a writer to control registers you know the device
and the device will do its job.
And so this from file system perspective,
although you know the the disk have quite storage device have quite different properties,
they're actually, [] from the driver's perspective,
you know so you can program in roughly the same way.
Any questions about that,
I'm not gonna talk much about the storage devices,
so if you have any questions, this is a good time to ask them.
Yes, I have a question,
is the interface for calling read or write something
that offers synchronous and asynchronous options.
Yeah, often this is the case,
in fact it's generally like it's almost very similar to
actually, basically you can think about the driver for a disk
in the same way as the console driver
where the CPU or the driver issues a command to the device,
basically say start to read or do write
and then at some point later when the device is done
and will generate an interrupt saying like OK I did to read or I did the write
and then you know that indicates the completion.
And you know of course, the driver since this device is more complicated than the console,
you know it's quite a bit more complicated driver than the console driver
that we saw in the previous lecture
was basically the same structure, bottom half top half interrupts,
and reading or writing to control registers.
Okay, thanks.
Okay, so, so from the file system perspective,
the way to think about the disk is pretty straightforward.
Since there's a read or write of block or sectors,
but we can just think about the disk basically gigantic you know array of blocks.
You know starting at you know whatever zero, you know one,
and going up to whatever the size the disk is.
And basically the file system's job is to sort of lay out all the data structures
on the disk in a way that you can reconstruct the file system after reboot.
And so you know there are different ways of going about it,
xv6 you'll see uses a very simple layout structure,
but, but not completely [user] not pretty typical in or prototypical for how file systems operate.
So typically the block zero is generally not used
or used actually for the boot sector, to boot the operating system.
Block one is often what's called a super block.
And the super block basically describes you know the file system,
and it may say like oh there's so many blocks on disk and that constitute the file system,
and we'll see in a second, xv6 is a little bit more information in it,
as in make most out of file system.
For example, in xx6 the log starts at you know block two and [runs] into block 32.
Yeah, so this is a block,
and of course the block could be different size
and in fact in the super block,
it just says like the log is whatever thirty blocks long.
Then, xv6 after that stores from 32 to basically block 45 remember correctly,
it's stores inodes as I said before,
multiply inodes are packed into a single, this block I think I notice.
I believe I don't actually remember at the top of my head,
but I think it's either 64 bytes, or 128, I believe 64.
And after that you know there's a bitmap block,
it turns out in the details way we build the file system.
This next bitmap block one block in size.
And so these basically keep track of actually the data blocks,
whether it's free or not,
and after that it's all for basically here to there, it's all data blocks
or data blocks that actually stored contents, files or contents of directories.
Often all the bitmap blocks and inode blocks and logging block, often sometimes referred to as metadata blocks,
they don't actually store actual data,
but they help you know they store meta information for the file system to do its job,
like bitmaps and inodes.
Any questions so far about this?
I have a question about the boot block,
does it contain the code for the operating system to boot or something else.
Yeah, exactly, it typically contains you know one block of code,
enough for the operating system to get going
and then load maybe more of the operating system actually from the file system itself.
Thank you.
So does that mean that the code for xv6 is actually stored on the virtual disk,
or is it like how does.
Xv6, you know the way we do with QEMU, you know we got some [corners],
QEMU actually has a flag, you know dash kernel that basically points to the where boots the kernel from
and loads, you know that at a particular address into physical memory at 0 eight zero zero zero zero.
And so basically when we're using QEMU,
the way we use QEMU, we don't really have to worry about boot sectors or anything like that.
Okay, so basically like when you run Q- QEMU,
you just you just pass in like the the program through the command line,
and then it'll just run that,
it doesn't need to read it from the virtual disk and everything.
That makes sense.
Okay, so like in the, so for example,
so assuming I know such 64 bytes,
you know for example, now if you want to read inode ten,
what do you do.
How do you read inode ten.
Anybody?
Which block do inode ten be.
You'd need to add, you take the inode number and add the offset into the disk,
so ten plus 32.
So 32, right, and it literally plus ten or something else.
Is it ten divided by the size.
Yeah, it's gonna be whatever it's gonna be inode number,
inode number multiplied times, we do it in bytes, multiply it by 64,
divided by [five twenty four],
so inode zero will end up in block 32,
inode whatever was five twenty four divided by 64,
16? 16 that's about right,
so I know seventeen where will where will it end up,
should be in, should be ing block 33 right.
Does that make sense?
So given unknown number, we can always find the bytes on disk where inode actually stored.
Okay?
Okay, so then let's look at the,
what actually is in on disk inode.
So as we know it,
before you'll see there's basically little data structure, 64 bytes in size,
and you know typically has a type, which we'll talk about it later,
but for example type file or directory and link.
You know the link count to track multiple names or pointing to the same inode,
size in bytes.
And then xv6 you know there can be slightly different in different files
and exactly how the representation is,
but in xv6 a little bit more space,
in xv6 basically is followed by a number of block numbers,
and so after block number zero, block number one,
in fact, there were twelve of those guys,
these twelve direct block numbers.
And those direct node block numbers basically correspond to the first twelve blocks that constitute that file.
So, for example if the file was only two bytes long,
you know there would be only one a block number zero
and block number zero is that, the block number of the disk block that contains
you know the first few bytes of that file.
And then there's one indirect block number,
basically that's a block number, that corresponds to a block,
which then itself block is five twenty four bytes which holds 256 block numbers.
So if block number zero, for block number eleven,
are all direct block numbers
and so then block number twelve you know stored in that, in that indirect block,
basically pointed to by the indirect block number.
And that is basically the layout of the file in xv6.
And so what is the maximum file size in xv6 based on this.
Anybody?
It would be 268 times a thousand twenty four bytes, basically.
Yeah we're just two fifty six, plus 12 12 direct times thousand twenty four
and then we get the maximum file size in bytes, right.
How much is that.
Another way of saying it's basically two 268 kilobytes, correct.
What can you store 268 kilobytes.
Can you store video in it or a song.
If it's a short song, yes.
Very short song, correct.
So these are really small file size,
real file systems and much much bigger file size,
so what would you do to file system representation
to make this to allow the files to be much more files to be much bigger.
Could you extend the indirect portions.
Yeah like for example you could have another block, seating here below, correct,
which is maybe doubling indirect,
almost like you know the sort of the page table type data structures that we've seen before, right,
then, that double indirect block points to two and fifty-six indirect block numbers,
each which point to another block number
and so certainly the file size is going to maximize this is much bigger.
And basically just turned out to be just a sort of exercise in on those data structures,
you could pick a structure like this, like a tree,
but there's also possible to like maybe implemented as B-Tree or something other sophisticated.
Xv6 something extremely simple,
in basically it's modeled after the original version six Unix Unix.
But you can make them more sophisticated schemes,
in fact in the file system lab,
you implement double indirect block numbers to support much bigger files.
Any questions about this?
Sorry, so is it 256 blocks,
because it's a like one block as a whole.
Indirect.
What this is an indirect block number, so that doesn't count,
so there's 256 sitting in this indirect block plus twelve direct block numbers that makes it 268.
Oh, sorry my question was why is it 256.
Oh, because it's a block number four byte probably.
So 1024 divided by four is 256 entries.
Okay, thank you.
Which is also a little bit ridiculous regular,
if block number is only four bytes, how big can this be.
Anybody?
Two to the power 32 right, right,
some things are bigger than that,
and so typically you know people use larger sizes for block numbers than 32 bits.
Okay?
Any questions, further questions.
For the max file size, but could you could you help explain that again like.
Okay, sure.
Could each block in the, could each block in,
that's referenced by the indirect block could that also point to more blocks,
if that makes sense.
In in the default xv6 design, that's not the case,
basically a twelve block numbers, twelve direct block numbers
and 256 indirect block numbers and nothing more.
In in the next lab, you'll be adding a double indirect block to the inode,
so you'll take one of these [bnl] 11's and turn that into a double indirect.
And that double indirect going to point to this,
we have to have 256 indirect block numbers,
which itself then point to blocks.
Now, the way file can be substantially there.
Oh okay, thanks.
Okay, so now let's say we want to implement the read system call.
And, you know basically we start from a operating system boots
wants to read say byte, read by 8000.
Yeah, how would you know, which block would you read,
which block will contain basically by 8000.
How would you compute or how you would look up,
giving this data structure, this extremely simple data structure,
how would you compute the actually the block number or find the block number that contains by 8000.
Anybody?
Do you just subtract, like, first of all subtract the number of bytes in the first twelve direct blocks.
Hmm.
And then see what the offset is in the indirect blocks.
Yeah, so okay, so in case of 8000 just what we will do correctly divided by 1024,
because that's the block size.
And that is seven, right.
And so that means that basically the seventh block actually has the second entry in this direct block number,
has the block number that contains you know by 8000 correct.
So [bn] seven whatever number is there is the block number,
that contains this particular file file,
by 8000 to actually find out exactly where that byte is inside of that block,
you know basically we have to compute 8000 delivery by 1024,
which is probably I think it's 832.
Okay, so basically to read by 8000,
you know the file system looks at the inode,
takes the byte number divide 1024,
indexes into see see if it falls below twelve then as a direct block number
and just picks up the direct block number from the inode
read that block and then fishes out you know 8000 byte by computing 8000 divided by found by module 1024 and
so it will give us an offset of 832
and that's the location for by 8000 that file.
Okay?
So basically, this is enough information to conclude from,
this is like there's enough information here now to actually implement read, write system calls,
at least to find out which disk blocks need to be read or written,,
in response to read or write system call.
Okay.
So let me talk a little bit about directories.
One of the cool things about you know file systems
where you have a hierarchical name space
and you can store store a symbolic user friendly names inside of inside of the, inside of the file system.
And the interesting aspect actually,
one of the cool design features with most Unix file systems actually does,
directory is basically the file,
except the file with some structure, that the file system understands.
In fact, in xv6 you know the structure is extremely simple,
every, the directory consists of directory entries.
And every entry has a fixed format,
namely it contains an inode number in the first two bytes,
and it contains a filename in the remaining fourteen bytes
and so the total thing is sixteen bytes.
And, this is enough information basically for,
you know we actually implement path name lookup.
So, for example just to make it clear,
let's say we want to look up the path name y/x,
how we go about doing that.
So well, you know this path name explain, indicates
that we have to start at the root inode.
And it turns out that [through] guy then basically has a fixed a fixed inode number
inode number has a [pre agreed] fixed a number
and in fact in xv6 that number is one.
So how can we find the root inode number.
Now we go back to our earlier picture right,
yeah it's number one,
you know we know that you know inode start at block 32,
so it must be thirty block 32
and so it's the by 16 to whatever by 64 to 128,
in that first block that contains the root inode number
and so the file system can just read the root inode number.
Okay?
And then basically the way path name lookups and works, it just gets the blocks.
Therefore, you know the name y,
so the file system, basically go through reach the blocks of the inode file inode one,
one by one and just looks going forward the date of those blocks a whether the string y appeers.
And how can it find all the blocks of the inode one,
well, just look at the, reach the [bn] zero the first block,
you know sees if x in that,
you know if it's not, will read the second block, etc etc,
until hopefully at some point either it finds it, or doesn't find it.
And if it finds it, let's find file x,
in the directory was going to have so inode number say 251.
And then we can just proceed from there, right,
we can say it's like, well okay, well,
now read you know block number, you know read inode 251,
and scan its blocks for.
Okay I just did my example wrong,
this was y, and it's going to block for x.
And [] was going to find us, you know, so inode number again,
we'll return that as a result of the path name lookup.
Any questions about this?
Would you say you.
So, this.
Yeah, so this is the layout of the directory in the disk,
but is there some bits somewhere in the metadata blocks
that indicates whether the current thing is a directory or a file.
Yeah it's actually in inode,
so the type of the inode says what's a directory or file,
so if you do look up on a and inode that actually happens to be a file,
then actually the file system will return an error.
I see, thanks.
Okay?
Now, clearly this structure is not a particular efficient,
you know to actually find a directory name, you have to scan,
and so a real file system, you probably would use more sophisticated data structures,
to actually make this lookups much faster than xv6 does.
But, again it's sort of almost you know a more designer question of data structures,
then is a question of operating system design.
And so you could plug in your favorite data structure
and turn it into an this data structure,
and then hopefully you're going to get better performance.
But for simplicity and ease explanation,
you know actually is very simple structure.
Okay?
Okay, so what I wanna do next is going to get a little bit more concrete feel for this
and just to see actually how things work out in practice in xv6
and this will be helpful, you know for the next lab.
I'm going to look at xv6 for a second,
usual screen.
So, the first thing I'm gonna boot xv6 again,
it's always and I did make clean,
and as you probably remember or many of you have run into this,
you know you want actually new file system, you have to run make clean,
because then a make qemu will build you a new clean file system.
So here we go.
And we'll see that xv6 has started,
but the thing I want to point out first is here,
here you'll see there's a call to basically make a file system,
so this makes a fresh disk image,
in a disk image contains you know a bunch of files, that we specify on the command line
and make it fast basically built QEMU file system
that contains those files as the contents of the file system.
And you can see you know the xv6 which brings out a bit of information about the file system,
so it basically says there are 46 mega blocks,
you know that includes the boot block, the super block,
the 30 log blocks, 39 inode blocks,
one bitmap block and then followed by 954 data blocks,
so it's a tiny file system in total of only thousand blocks.
And one of the things you will do in, the lab to support bigger files,
you also will have to use a much bigger file system.
Then I modified xv6 slightly to basically write or print something
whenever we write to a particular block.
So for example, we see a couple file system call,
we had xv6 when it starts up does a bunch of file system calls
and apparently wrote block [thirty three forty three forty eight or 32].
And we're gonna run basically command
and we're just gonna see what block numbers are being written by that command or cause of that command
and we've been trying to understand where do where do those writes make sense,
when we expect to see if they were actually, to see what is happening
is what we actually expect.
So I'm going to create a file, echo hi.
Yeah, I'm gonna create a file x.
And let me actually copy that a little bit over, so I can delineate this,
I'm going to delineate in a couple places just for help for understanding,
probably [right] here,
then probably here.
Okay.
It's basically it turns out there's gonna be a couple phases here,
one is the phase to actually create the file.
Then, there's write the file namely [write] hi file and then one more write.
Alright, actually the new line, into the file.
So you look at the echo program that is basically what it does.
Pick it up.
[Just do it] for completeness,
write to echo,
look at his arguments, writes arguments to file descriptor one
and then at the end of the [] new line.
Okay?
So, these are basically the sequences of disk writes get involved in each operation.
And let's go look at them one by one
and start to understand what's going on.
I'm going to basically maybe the easiest thing to do
actually used to, move this over.
Okay so, it's convenient to understand what's going on,
instead of looking at the code, we're going to just look at this disk layout
and trying to figure out a what might be going on in these particular operations.
Okay good.
So what do we think, this write is.
Any idea what this might actually be.
We're creating a file, so what do we expect file system to do.
It writes the inodes entry.
Yeah, so first thing I was just two,
so okay so it's 33, so what do we know about block 33.
If we look at the disk layout picture.
It contains a free inode.
Yeah, you know it contains we know that inode one lives in 32, correct,,
and so we're whatever apparently inode that's being allocated is probably and inode that lives in block 33.
Presumably the first write might just be marking
you know that this inode actually is now going to be used
and so I think the way xv6 does this it uses the type field,
in the inode to actually indicate where inode free, file or directory,
so it basically changes from free to file
and write to the disk to market as in use.
What do we think next write 33 is.
Actually, populating the inode entry would like info.
Yeah, exactly yeah, indeed populating an inode info,
you know inode probably with entries like setting the link count one and things like that, right.
In, what is 46, what do we expect 46 to be in 32,
maybe that's there.
Is 46, the first data, no actually bitmap bitmap.
No, just it's a data block and you're right it's the first data block.
So whose data block do you think is this.
See root directory entry.
Yeah correct, this is this is probably used to block, first lock, of the root directory,
you know inode one, right.
And why were we expecting to actually that to be written,
what has.
Because because we're, we're creating like x in, we're adding a new file x to the current directory,
so adding it to the file hierarchy.
Yeah, exactly, so we have we've done this
and we just added an entry to the root directory,
namely entry x with whatever inode we allocated,
you know the step, two steps before.
Does that make sense?
So what do we think is write 32 is.
To block 32, well, the thing to do is go back and look at the disk layout picture.
And one is block 32.
I know the one probably.
Yeah, well it will include inode one,
includes all the other inodes correct,
because nine is smaller than a block,
but it will include inode one.
Why do you think it's going to be written
what what might have changed in the inode
that requires that the inode actually written to disk.
Size.
Yeah, the size change exactly,
size change because we grew the directory correct by sixteen bytes directly store entry x.
Then there's one more a write to 34
and I'll leave that hanging for a second,
basically we're updating inode for x one more time,
even through nothing actually what's written yet.
Okay?
So that's the first phase,
so let's now look at the second,
you know so there's creation,
now let's look at the second phase
or the first write you know write hi to file x.
Well, what do we think 45.
Yeah yeah it's the bitmap,
so remember what happened to here is does that file system scan the bitmap block
to find a block that was not used,
so find it zero and then set that bit, you know to one
to indicate that that particular block now is in use.
And so it wrote you know 45 to to disk [] updated the bigmap block.
What block do you think the bitmap allocator picked.
[595]?
Yeah, most likely, correct, because right after it we see your write to five ninety five,
and presumably the block that was allocated to the file x.
And so basically in the inode correct,
file x now in [bn] zero will have the number five ninety five.
And, and basically what will be the first byte,
what's the value of the first byte of block five ninety five, After this write.
H.
H, yeah.
What do we think the second write is, this one.
i.
Yes, i right, there's every echoed you know there's a character by character.
Okay, what do we think this write 33 is.
Updating the size again.
Yeah, again the size of the inode,
that's because now it has two bytes in it.
Does it make sense?
Question, five ninety five seems very high up in the disk,
that because there's other stuff that's currently living there
like the kernel boot code and other things that have already been start.
Well, yeah we can go back to the this screen,
we can look at what make fs did, right,
so make fs stored a whole bunch of files there,
in the files that before we actually created file x.
And in fact we've created all these guys.
And so it was only a good chunk of the disk is already filled by the files,
the for blocks a good number of blocks already used basically by the set of files.
Got it.
Would it write down that block five ninety five is related to,
that to that I know during the last, like during the write three to that.
Yeah, exactly correct,
so there's write through three probably a bunch of things happened correct,
the size got updated.
And you know bn zero and bn one, we're updated,
we're certainly bn zero is updated correct, to contain five ninety five
and both pieces of information are updated inode then written to the disk by this write.
That makes sense?
Yeah yeah, thank you.
Good, so that's you know sort of the essence of disk layout
and hopefully you have a pretty good understanding of what goes on to make this work
and so it's going to look a little bit more in detail now at the code,
to see actually things little, one more level of detail.
Okay, so the first thing since reallocated inode,
let's first look at actually how, how that happened,
so in sysfile, let's see [].
So here're all the calls related to file system calls,
so the first thing that actually happens when it was just open,
because we're going to create a file.
Since open will call create, here's create.
Create will look at this later, resolves the path name to basically the last directory,
walks the directory and then does look up and really care about that
just to see if the file already exists,
and if the file exists, you know maybe you're turn an error.
And then it calls inode allocate
and so this is the call that is going to allocate this inode for the file x.
So let's look out it's gonna be fs.c.
And here is ialloc,
like most xv6 code, you know it's just very simple,
but not particularly efficient.
And so what it does, basically it goes for all the inode numbers possible,
from one to whatever the maximum number of inode
that as a possible on this particular file system,
and then reach block, for that inode number,
so, for example starts with one, reach, you know the block contains an inode number one
and and, then sees if that inode number is free
and if it's not, if it is free,
then it says it to file,
and that way marks it as allocated and writes it to disk,
and this log_write, you actually print statements I had, I put actually log_write,
so that log_write was the first write that we've seen,
in that sequence of writes that we did what file system do.
Does this make sense?
So interesting, so it's basically sort of the sequence of events
that get you to the first write to the disk,
interesting question of course, what happens if multiple processes are calling create at the same time,
multi core machine that can be running in parallel,
you know coming down and all get to ialloc roughly at the same time,
and then all they're gonna call they're gonna call bread,
so there has some story or how is these writes don't interfere with each other.
Yeah it's really worthwhile looking into,
because in some sense, you know this is actually the part of the last part of this lab that you're currently doing,
so it gets into the buffer cache.
So let's look at bread,
so on bread more the first thing it does actually it's called bget
and so basically bget a slot in the buffer cache.
Let's look at the bget for a little while,
because there's a reasonable tricky code.
And, so what's going on in the first couple lines here.
I imagine some of you already looked at this code quite a bit of detail
as part of this lab, the [locking] block.
So what's going on here.
It blocks the linked list and check if any of the,
things in the cache are maching with what we're looking for.
Yeah, so basically this is the cache,
in action we're looking for whatever the block number, block number 33
and we're basically seeing if the cache already has block number 33.
And and if that is the case, it bumps the ref count up
and and then release the bcache lock,
because we're done looking into cache itself,
we know it's there we know that there's a buff- buffer for that particular block, there,
and, and then the next step that actually happens is sort of interesting.
Next step, the block cache basically tries to get a lock on the buffer.
So, so what happens if like multiple processes at the same time called bget,
well one of them is going to get the bcache lock, right.
It's going to scan the buffer cache,
and so nobody can actually modify the buffer cache in this particular point.
Find if the block number is there and if the block number is there,
it bumps the ref count,
indicating that basically it has a reference, you know to this, this particular lock
and then releases the bcache lock.
So if there were a second process waiting,
all to also scan the this cache, it might not actually require to lock right away, right,
in fact it might be a second process of scanning for one also want to scan for this block 33.
And it will also get you know basically a reference to be bump the reference count,
to two or three whatever it is
and then you know both of them will try to call acquire sleep,
on that particular buffer buffer 33.
And acquire sleep, it's just basically another type of lock,
we call them sleep locks and we'll talk about in a second,
but basically you know this acquires the lock on the buffer,
so one of the two processes will get the, the lock of buffer 33.
And will proceed and that will be returned and go from [going through motions],
you know like scanning that block 33 to see if there is inode that actually is free.
And the other process will just be sitting in the acquiresleep here,
you know waiting until the first process is done with all its operations.
Any questions about this?
I have a question,
while the ref count of a block is not zero,
can anything important about that block change,
because something can happen between the release of the bcache and acquiring the lock of the block.
Yeah actually the the protocol, okay, so there's a couple points I want to make here,
the protocol basically, xv6 follows is that for any modification to the bcache itself,
you need to hold the bcache lock.
For any modification to this block 33,
you need to hold the sleep lock block 33.
And so at any particular point in time,
so after the release b ref count is a larger than zero
and there will be no modification to the buffer cache,
buffer cache will only evict or things that actually have the ref count zero,
never that has a ref count of something bigger than zero.
And so we know for sure that this block basically this buffer won't be touched in the bcache itself,
you know other processes might be looking up,
might be looking up the entry in the bcache,
but it won't be removed from the bcache, right.
Yeah make sense.
And this lock that second lock at this sleep lock is really what protects the content of the buffer,
ensuring that only one process actually will be reading or writing the buffer
at any particular point of time.
And it's important, correct,
that [can it say], would be bad if like say wouldn't be bad
if block 33 ended up in the cache twice in different slots.
Yeah, because then he could have the correct information, right.
Yeah correctly,
for example let's say process one writes inode nineteen
and the other process writes inode twenty, correct,
and so if they both get a handle on the buffer for that represents,
you know the the block 33 one might update inode eighteen,
the other in nineteen,
the first one maybe arrange, its eighteen back to the disk,
then the guy that does modified nineteen write nineteen back,
will overwrite changes at eighteen made, right,
that were made for inode eighteen.
And so that's terrible,
so it has to be the case that the block number only appears in the buffer cache only exactly once.
And there's an invariant correct,
you know you sort of have to maintain while you're doing this a block cache lab,
locking lab in this week's lab.
Does that make sense, that variant.
Yeah, I guess tangential question to this,
there might be some blocks that have multiple references to them
and then maybe one of the processes that has is touching this block
flushes the cache by forcing a write to the disk,
what happens to what everyone else sees.
Well as I did, if the write, okay so the first process is done at some point,
we'll call release [] whatever it's called,
so basically you can think about at the end when the first process done with it's reading and writing to that block 33,
I call brelse release with a buffer.
And that will actually decrease the reference count.
Well release sleep lock, and that means that if anybody was waiting,
any other processes was waiting for that particular buffer
and will now be able to get the sleep lock on the buffer
and go read it will observe the preview than you make changes, right.
So if two processes were returning to the update inode eighteen and 1919 that all both live in block 43,
then if the first process is done,
it changes eighteen are visible
and so the next and so the next guy will actually allocate [] inode 19,
because actually eighteen is marked as a file now.
Anybody afterwards will observe the changes.
Makes sense?
Yes, thanks.
And this is exactly what we hoped would be the case,
if one process creates an inode or creates a file,
then the process, later process does read, you should observe that file.
Okay, then, because one more smaller detail,
as you can see here in the code,
in the process actually takes a sleeplock on the buffer
and so the sleep lock is slightly different than a regular or a spin lock,
let's look at sleep lock for a second.
And you see what it is.
So we need to acquire sleeplock.
Yeah, and when it does,
it requires you know some field basically requires a spin lock, that is associated with sleep lock,
if the lock is actually held, okay, the spin lock is held,
then, if the lock is actually held,
so okay, let me first see h file, the h file contains a locked field,
and, and that's it.
And so basically.
That was the spin lock.
Yeah, we're spin lock.
Oh, yeah there's a spin lock.
Good good. Sorry, um, and then if the lock is actually held,
sleep lock is held it actually goes to sleep.
So it deschedules itself.
And why, why do you think for these buffers are we using sleep locks instead of spin locks,
because indirectly we're using spin locks to implement sleep locks,
but why not just use regular.
Because disk operations take a long time.
Yeah, there's multiple reasons,
there's all kinds of rules correct restrictions on a on a spin locks,
what is one of the restrictions on spin locks.
Well, what do.
Interrupts have to be off.
Yeah, they turn interrupts off, right.
And so we were we started this operation while holding a buffer,
while holding a spin lock on the buffer
and then we would never hear from the disk.
Well, maybe another core here,
but if we had only one core and we would never hear from it, right.
And for more, for the same reasons,
you know you're not allowed to go to sleep, while holding a spin lock.
And so therefore we have these sleep locks that are sort of long-term locks,
if you will for for that particular use case.
So that we can hold locks one of the advantages of sleep locks
that we can hold them across interrupts,
hold because disk operations, we can hold them for long periods of time.
And we're not if we're waiting on that lock,
we also not keeping the CPU busy or spending on the CPU,
we're basically releasing the CPU by calling sleep.
Does that make sense?
Any questions about this?
Okay, let's look at one more thing,
which is brelse.
So we looked already a little bit, you basically would brelse does releases the sleep lock,
then acquires the bcache lock, decrement reference count
to indicate that one process is not interested anymore, in this particular buffer.
And then, if a if the ref count is zero,
the, it manipulates the list of buffers a little bit,
what does it do here.
It inserts the b into the position after b head, inside of the []list.
Yeah, where does it basically go, what does that mean.
So let's go back up correctly, let's look at.
It was most recently used.
Yeah, basically moves into the position of the most recently used buffer, right.
And this is important, because when, when we cannot find the block in the block cache.
Then we need to fix something to make space, right.
And so we're going to go through the block as we go
and we basically start from most recently used one.
And think that one first.
And so we just used the buffer as very unlikely, that it actually evicted.
Why is that a good policy.
Generally systems obey a temporal locality.
Yeah right, so if the block is recently used,
it's probably a good indicator that it might actually be used again quickly.
And so it's a good idea not to evict it.
You wanna and it's generally sort of if you even you have locality cache locality
and the block that is you know least recently used
probably the block that is also most likely to be used in the future
and so that's a good one to evict.
Does that make sense?
Okay.
So, let me go back to my slides here,
so, so there's a little bit of a slight excursion in the bcache code,
or the block cache.
There's a couple interesting things at the point at to correct,
you know there's this invariant that there's only one copy of a block in memory.
And as an important variant that must be maintained by block cache,
it has these sleep locks, are different types of locks than the ones that we've seen before,
that can span IO operations that implements you know LRU,
least recently catching replacement policy,
need to have these two levels of locking,
to, in its implementation, one level to basically protect the bcache internal data structures,
and then one level of locking through sleep locks to actually lock individual buffers.
Does that make sense?
Okay,.
I'm going to run out of time, so let me stop here,
you know quickly summarized what we've seen so far
and we're going Wednesday and we're going to focus really on crash safety,
so basically you know file system is on this data structure.
Basically, most of the lecture today, we're focusing on the layout of the on this data structure
of the xv6 you know this data structure on disk
and you know we saw xv6 has a very simple one.
But you can imagine like you know implementing more complicated one
and the other thing that we spend much time looking at is this block cache,
which is crucial for performance,
because reading and writing typically to disk is actually expensive,
you know we're there for hundreds of microseconds to milliseconds
and the block cache basically ensures that, you know if a block was recently read from the disk,
we're actually not reading it again from the disk.
Okay, and then Wednesday, I'm going to talk about crash safety,
which is a fascinating other aspect of file system design,
in fact we'll spend two lectures on crash safety.
We'll see a logging design on Wednesday that's slow
and then next week we'll look at how Linux ext3 does logging
which is a much more faster scheme.
If you have any other questions feel [] to hang around and I'm happy to answer them,
otherwise you know, see you Wednesday.
Alright, thank you.
I have a question about brelse.
Yes.
So it seems like it releases the blocks lock
and after that it modifies the ref count.
Um.
Why is that OK.
Yeah, good question.
So what do we, know you know, so let's say we do release the sleep lock,
so if some other guy or some other process actually was waiting,
or what doing acquire sleep lock,
what does that mean about the ref count.
That it was zero.
No correct, so if n processes are waiting for a buffer.
Oh okay, [check out].
There was a at least one.
Yeah, more than one, correct,
if ten process you're waiting in, the reference can be ten.
Yeah, okay.
And so, is this only this only line of code
what it does is basically it updates the ref count for just one guy
which is one process that actually did the release
and it reduces the ref ref count to by one.
And if other people were waiting and never ref count was definitely not zero will do,
it will never execute this code.
OK?
OK, OK I see, I I think I see okay.
A rather question was why is why is two bits to by enough for inode number.
It's not, it's ridiculously small, correct,
because how many inodes can you have.
Two to the power of eight.
Yeah, yeah yeah yeah, whatever two byte.
Sixteen bit.
Sixteen thirteen, thirty two thousand inodes.
That's a lot inode for nineteen sixties or the sixties and seventies,
but certainly would not be sufficient for today.
And so, today's file systems use a bigger number or more bits.
Okay.
I see I guess my question was in the architecture that we have for xv6,
the those two sixteen bit for inodes like where where else do they,
where else can we see this number show up.
Well the the one that is two bytes is really on disk than it is two bytes.
Any number in when it's compiled when it's sitting in a register or sit in memory.
The disk inode is,
look at it, let's see,
so this disk inode as we said before actually the,
use a directory entry where we say is inside [short]
and others there's two byte sixteen bits,
the in-memory representation of an inode.
You know, okay, that's in, you're doing in-memory representation of an inode,
that actually number is integer
and you know the way we compile C code
and integer happens to be four bytes.
Okay, okay I see, thank you, thank you so much.