All right,
welcome to 6.S081 operating systems,
I'm Robert I'll be co-lecturing
with Frans and David and Nicolaas
of the TAs.
So, um please during the zoom lectures,
ask questions,
you can either interrupt me by
audio or enter something into
the chat window.
Um, one of the staff will see and ask
question for you.
By the way we'll be recording these
lectures and then we'll post recordings later
so you can review them or for
people who can't make this time so
they can nevertheless see lectures.
All right, I want to start by
laying out some of the goals
of the course. So,
number one is to um,
understand a design and implementation
of operating systems.
Um, yeah,
design is sort of high level structure
and implementation is really about what the
code looks like,
and we'll spending a lot of time with both.
And in the interest of getting a
deep understanding of what's going on,
you'll get hands-on experience with a small.
Um, a small operating system,
the xv6 operating system.
Um, and,
in addition to actually looking at an
existing operating system,
you'll be a in the labs
get a bunch of experience extending
the operating system modifying improving its
behavior and writing system software that
it uses the operating system interfaces,
if it works an application.
Um, So,
um, so this is what you're going to
be doing in the course,
um, um.
We're also interested in what the purpose
of the operating system itself is as
well as the course.
So for that I have a
sort of list of a couple
of things which,
um you know there's lots of operating system,
different operating systems out there,
they typically have a common set of purposes.
Um, one of them is to abstract the hardware,
um, that is what you're given
typically as a kind of starting point is
you buy a computer,
a computer has a CPU and memory
but that's a very low level.
A set of resources,
it's fantastic to have a much higher
level interfaces and abstractions that applications can
use such as processes or file systems
both for convenience and for portability.
Another very important task of an operating
system is to multiplex the hardware
among many applications.
Um, you might be running a text editor,
and a compiler,
or maybe
a multiple different database servers or something
on your operating system,
it's fantastic to be able to have
the operating system run,
both of them at the same
time or all the things are
going on at the same time
without having them interfere.
That's often called multiplexing, because
there may be a lot of
things happening in the operating system
at the same time, it's critical
that they not interfere unintentionally,
even if they have bugs and that's
a task is called isolation.
The idea that,
a different activities should not be allowed
to interfere. On the other hand,
there are times when different activities would
like to interfere,
would like to interact or cooperate,
so for example if I create a
file with a text editor,
and I'd like my compiler to read
the file and we definitely want to
allow that kind of sharing.
Um, so we wanna allow sharing [minutes],
um. Sort of what the user has in mind.
But in many circumstances,
user doesn't want sharing maybe
you're logged into a time sharing
machine like Athena,
and you don't want other people to
read your files,
um, so we also need as well sharing
we want to not share when we
don't want to um.
Which we could call security or a
permission system an access control system.
Another thing that people value in operating
systems is if you spend a lot
of money on the hardware on a
computer you'd like your application to be
able to get a sort of full
performance that a hardware ought to be
able to provide. And,
A lot of that is just application programming,
um. But,
um inevitably,
unfortunately, some of it is the operating system
has to make sure that whatever services
it provides don't get in the way
of applications getting high performance,
so you want to at least not
get in the way and maybe even
help applications achieve
good performance.
Um, um,
finally, um.
With most operating systems have to support
a wide range of different applications,
maybe it's a laptop running a text editor,
maybe it's running games,
maybe your operating system needs to support
database servers or cloud computation,
and usually because operating systems are quite
expensive to design and build, people use
the same operating systems for many different
tasks like Linux,
for example which I'm sure many of
you are running a is used in
all of the situations I mentioned so
the same operating system really has to
be able to support a range of,
um, often quite different uses.
So we're hoping to be able
to support sort of all these
different goals simultaneously.
And we'll hear more about all of
them during the course.
All right,
um, operating systems,
so people worked out a
set of design ideas over the decades
have worked pretty well sort of ways
of organizing things.
I'm going to lay out for you,
this sort of classic.
A organization sort of standard deal for um.
Um, this course and,
um, is actually quite common around
for many operating systems.
So this is sort of OS internal organization or.
The way I think about it
is in terms of a box
for the computer,
the computer sort of.
Comes with a bunch of hardware resources,
which I'll put at the bottom,
maybe their CPU and ram, disk for
storage and maybe a network interface,
this sort of hardware,
that's the lowest layer.
So at the top you want to
run various applications,
maybe a text editor I haven't use
VI as a text editor,
if you're going to run a C compiler CC,
you know if you run lots of
other things we're gonna talk a lot
today about the Shell which is the,
um, command line interface,
so we have all these different programs
that are running.
Um, and this is the sort of world
in which a applications run is usually
called user space.
Um, and as distinct from that there's
a single program.
A special program,
that's always running called the kernel and
the kernel is sort of the guardian
of the resources of the computer,
it's what first boots up you turn on the computer,
um, there's just one of it maintains data,
um. To help manage each of these processes
and the kernel also means lots of
data structures to help interface and,
um, all the different kinds of hardware.
Um, these user programs need to use,
the kernel also has built in
a bunch of services.
Um so,
for example a there's typically a file system.
Implementation inside the kernel that implements things
like file names and file contents and
directories and understands how to store the
files in the disk,
so your programs are going to talk
to the files inside the kernel and
file system implementations is going to
talk to the disk.
In this course.
Um, where we mostly focus on is all
the things that has to happen inside
the kernel and on the interfaces
between user programs and the kernel.
As well as the structure of the software,
um inside the kernel.
So um,
we care a lot about these services
inside the kernel.
One of them is a file system I mentioned,
there's also a
management of processes,
each of these running programs is called
the process and it has things like
its own memory,
for example as well as a share of the CPU time. So,
a kernel manages processes
as a kernel service.
Uh, um,
kernel manages the allocation of the memory,
the different processes need different
amounts of memory.
The kernel
multiplexes and divides up the memory
allocates the memory,
um, among all the different processes.
Um, the kernel as I mentioned a influence
the file system, file system really comes
into a three logical or a bunch
of logical parts,
but for now we can think of
it in terms of managing file content,
that's inside files,
figuring out where on disk.
Each file's content
ought to live, file system also somewhat
separately manages a name space that
each file has a name and
there's a hierarchy of directories,
every directory has a bunch of
files in it all that's managed
by the file system.
Um, there's typically some sort of security arrangement,
maybe we'll call it access control.
Which the kernel decides that when a
given process wants to read, use
some resource, maybe read something from the disk,
use some memory,
the access control machinery inside the
kernel is what gets to decide
yes it's allowed is that
not allowed, that can get pretty
complicated if we're talking about time
sharing systems like Athena systems where
there's you know each of these
processes may be run by a
different user and have different access
control rules apply to what it's
allowed to get at.
And in a real full-blown operating system
turns out to be many,
many other services,
you know there's typically some way for
different processes to talk to each other
called inter process communication,
there's typically a whole bunch of software
associated with the network things like the
TCP/IP protocols for talking the network,
um. There's typically support for sound cards there
may be drivers for hundreds of different
disk and hundreds of different network cards,
so in a full-blown operating system is
a huge amount of stuff here and
this may run to millions of lines
of code inside the kernel.
So that's sort of a quick overview
of whats inside the kernel,
we're also interested in how applications
interact with the kernel and what
that interface looks like.
The um,
a usual,
um, so this is the API for the kernel.
How applications get at the kernel,
a typically that's done with something called
system calls and these are things that
look like function calls that um
programs can make, but actually jump into
the kernel and execute a system call
implementation in the kernel,
I'll talk a bunch about that
in the latter part of this
lecture. For now just to give
you a flavor here,
what a couple of different system calls
might look like in the source code
of an application.
One might be that if you want
an application wants to open a file,
and it calls the open system call.
And tells the open system called the
name of the file,
so maybe it wants to open a
file for writing called "out" and the
next argument here saying 1
in this case. I want to
write that file,
and so this thing that looks like a function call.
It opens the system calls actually special
code that jumps into the kernel and
the kernel can retrieve these arguments executes
some kernel code that implements open,
maybe talks to the disk,
and then returns a value and that's
this file descriptor,
as fd stands for file descriptor.
Um, which is the program can
then use as a handle to
refer to this open file.
Um, if you want to write to a file,
the system call [did].
To do that is called write,
you have to pass it one
of these file descriptors the same as
was returned by open.
Um, these are arguments that are passed in
the system call.
From the program into the kernel,
and you give it a pointer,
to a buffer of characters so an
easy way to do that in the
C programming language,
which these examples are written by as
double quotes then,
um, the string,
the bytes of the string '\n'
is a new line and the third
argument is the count of characters.
Um, if you want to write so this really gets point,
pass this address in memory.
So you're telling the kernel, look,
please write 6 bytes from this
address to the file that this
file descriptor refers to.
A much more exciting system call
the encounter is the fork system,
call fork is the system call
that creates a new process.
Um, and returns actually creates a process that's
identical to the caller and fork returns
the identifier the process identifier pid,
um, new process is more
complicated than [that].
We'll hear more about this.
So again,
these are all look like function calls,
but the system calls are special because
they jump into the kernel.
Um, that's taste,
we'll see more later.
That is a sort of quick overview,
I'm a wanna.
Just mention why I find a operating
the study of operating systems,
to be both a challenging and interesting.
Why you know why it's maybe worth.
Um, intellectually worth taking a course in this area.
So, one reason why it's hard is that
the environment is unforgiving, programming environment
inside the kernels unforgiving, because you're,
your when you're programming when you're modifying
the kernel or extending the kernel of
writing a new operating system kernel,
you're providing the infrastructure that everybody
else assumes is already present to
run their programs.
And then everybody else gets an operating
system under their program when they write
ordinary application programs,
but when we build operating systems
what we get is the hardware
underneath our operating system which turns
out to be more difficult to
deal with. In this course,
we, um,
we get to use a hardware simulator called QEMU,
um, you,
um. That simulates a CPU and a computer
and that makes a little bit better,
but it's still a kind of a difficult,
um environment programming.
Another reason why it's hard and
interesting is because if you're designing
and operating system,
you have to satisfy a bunch of tensions.
Um that require real design thought,
so one is that you'd like your
operating system to be both efficient.
Um, which often means that it operates at
a low level close to the hardware,
but for ease of use,
and because real live people have to
write programs that use your operating system,
we'd like it also to be a
right abstract high-level.
A portable interfaces and it's a
neat trick to provide a abstract
interfaces that are simple.
A portable but they are also efficient.
Um, another tension is that we'd like to
provide a very powerful operating system services
so that the operating system can shoulder
a lot of the burden.
I'm a running programs like a powerful
operating system services.
Um, but,
we also want to have simple interfaces.
Um that we don't want a
tremendously complex hard to understand interfaces
for programmers to use because I'm
not going to understand them,
and they may find it hard to use.
Um, so this is really simple API,
and so this is possible to do
to provide a simple interfaces that have
powerful a machinery inside them will always
be searching for.
Sort of simple interfaces provide
a powerful services.
Hey, Robbery, we've got a question in the chat.
Um, what is unique/different about saying
system calls jump into the kernel i.e
as opposed to a standard function call
that jumps to another function.
Um. Well,
the kernel has the kernels is,
um. A piece of code that's always resident
that has special privileges that were that
because it booted the machine booted the
kernel a kernel has special privileges,
it can get directly at all kinds
of hardware like the disk device that
ordinary user programs,
can't get at, so if you make
a an ordinary function call.
Um. The function your calling doesn't get it
doesn't get any special privileges with respect
to the hardware whereas if you make
a system call into the kernel will
talk about how this works,
but that ends up as when it
jumps into when the system call jumps
into the kernel a system call implementation
in the kernel then gets all these
special privileges so that it can modify
all kinds of sensitive and protected.
A hardware resources like for example getting
directly at the hard disk.
Um, we'll see a lot more detail for all this shortly.
Okay, so a final tension that we
want that all operating systems need
to satisfy your gonna give programs
as much flexibility as you can
you don't want to constrain them,
so you want to have very flexible.
Um. Interfaces,
but you do need to constrain program
somewhat because you absolutely have to have
some notion of security.
[can]. We love for programs programs complete freedom
but it can't be complete can't be
really complete because we don't want programs
to get directly at the hardware or
to interfere with other programs or a
sort of be able to interfere with
the operation of the operating system itself.
Um, so,
these are all you know.
It's possible to do a good job
and we'll talk a lot about it
but it's always a bit of a
puzzle to provide sort of both of
these properties in both of these columns.
Another thing that makes OS design hard
and interesting is that operating systems provide
a lot of features and a lot
of services but they actually tend to
interact and sometimes in odd ways that
require a lot of thought so even
the simple examples I gave um.
With open and fork,
those two interact actually if a program,
um. Allocates a file descriptor with the
open system call,
and then that same program,
a fork.
Um, and the semantics of fork just
turned out to be that you
create a new process that's a
copy of the current process,
this file descriptor,
you opened.
If that's truly to be a copy,
this file descriptor still has to be
present and usable in the child and,
and so that has to be thought
through that is the files,
the opened file descriptors interact with fork
in this interesting way and somebody has
to figure out a should the child
be able to get at.
The file descriptors created before fork
is called and the answer has
to be yes,
the operating systems we're going to look at.
Um. All right, so other things
that are turned out to
be interesting I already mentioned
that operating systems have to
cater to a wide variety
of uses the same OS
used both for database servers
and smartphones,
for example and operating systems.
As time goes on the hardware
that you run, hardware
you get,
but typical computers changes,
maybe get superfast ssd storage instead of
mechanical hard drive.
For example,
about fifteen years ago multi
core computers went from being rare
curiosities to being pervasive and and
recently we've seen order of magnitude
speedups and how fast networks operate
and so all these require rethinks.
Um, um,
periodically of how operating systems are designed.
Now so so those are those are
sort of intellectually why you might take
the course there's also some more practical
reasons why you might be glad to
have taken this course,
one is if you're interested in what
happens inside computers,
what goes on and saw under the
hood a sort of in secret,
when you turn on your computer,
um, this is a good course to take,
similarly if you like infrastructure that
is if if you enjoy building
a sort of services that other
programs can then use them.
This is of course essentially all
about infrastructure because that's that's what
operating systems are.
If you ever need to
spend a lot of time
tracking down bugs in application
code or tracking down security
problems often that involves understanding
what was going on inside
the operating system because it's
ultimately the operating system that
enforces a lot of security
and when things go wrong,
it's the operating system has to pick
up the pieces so that's often involved
in tracking down bugs, and finally. Two
more questions from the chat,
so the first is how important
is it for application developers to
truly deeply understand the operating systems
of developing their applications for do
they necessarily need to be experts.
You don't have to be an expert,
but if you spend a lot of
time developing and maintaining and debugging applications,
you'll eventually end up knowing a lot
about the operating system,
whether you,
whether you meant to or not just,
it just comes up and you're often
forced to understand.
Um. And the second question is do
high-level programming languages like python use
system calls directly are there built
in slash wrappers for convenience.
A lot of high-level languages are sort
of at one of move from system calls
that's absolutely true,
so um.
Partially because a lot of
languages want to provide portable a
portable environment that works on many
different operating systems so they can't
necessarily commit to the specific system
calls of any one operating system.
Um, so I'm the answer,
the question I think is if you
use python, you're somewhat insulated.
From not the system call interface,
you know internally of course python makes,
has to make system calls get its work done,
um, and,
certainly in python and many other languages,
there is usually a way to get directly at
the system calls whatever your operating system,
you're running on.
And folks for questions, you can just
feel free to jump in yourself and
ask questions you don't need to go
through the chat.
Okay, Um,
all right,
sorry. I'm going to spend a couple of
minutes now talking about class structure
of 6.S081,
before switching back to actual technical content.
So there is a website for the
course which I don't want to write
out just now but it's you
can find it by looking for
6.S081 on Google.
And the website,
um, has
a schedule,
it has the assignments on the schedule
that has the lab assignments.
Um, and it has the sort of
information about course structure like the
grading policy on it.
Um the other big resource you're gonna
wanna keep track of piazza.
Um I guess,
everybody was here got here by way
piazza, um,
but as well as um,
so we used periodically for two main things,
one is as a way of people
being able to ask questions about the
lab assignments and,
a course staff will try to answer these questions,
but you should feel absolutely free to
answer each other's questions as well. And
the other big thing that happens on
piazza if there's announcements there's any announcements
about the course.
Um, we'll put the announcement on piazza so
you should keep an eye on piazza
for announcements even if, um,
you're not using it for lab help.
Yeah. Um,
The um,
one of the big parts of course
is that these lectures,
um, um,
lectures will cover basic ideas
and operating systems.
Um, some of the lectures will
be devoted to detailed a
study of the code in
xv6 which is
our small teaching operating system
and so talk about how
it works we'll look at
the code and show the
code executing during lectures,
and in addition before many of
the lectures will be assignments reading
assignments from a book that sort
of describes how xv6 operates and
why it's designed that way.
So you do the readings before the
class so they don't understand the discussion
in the class,
some of the lectures are devoted to
background to help you do the labs.
Um, no explanations about C works of how
the RISC-V, which is the microprocessor
that we'll be using.
Um that you'll find helpful in understanding
how to do the labs and towards
the end of the course,
we'll spend some lectures discussing some
operating system papers,
research papers and some classic papers in
the field which you will ask that
you read before the lecture and then
we'll sort of talk about the papers
during the lecture. For all the lectures
are almost all the lectures,
we ask that you submit a question
about the reading,
um for the lecture before the actual
time of the lecture which.
Many or all of you did for
this lecture for which thank you,
um, and we will read those questions to help us.
Guide us about what to talk about
and we'll try to answer as many
of the questions as we can,
although there's rarely time,
unfortunately for us to answer all of them.
I'm the next big part of the course of the labs.
There's a programming lab do,
um, almost every week and the point of
the labs is to help you get
hands on experience with,
implementing and using operating systems.
A lab that's due next week is
actually about using about writing applications that
make the call the system calls will
be talking about.
Whereas most of those labs after
that are involved,
you either implementing basic operating system
features or adding
a kernel extensions to the xv6
operating system,
the very last lab and one in
which you actually add a network stack
and a network driver so you'll be
able to connect in over the network
to the operating system that you run.
You should,
if you have problems with the lab's
they'll be office hours that,
TA will hold. In addition
you can post questions to piazza
and very often you'll be able
to get useful answers from piazza
more quickly than from office hours.
We welcome you discussing the labs
talking about the labs talking about
how to design the lab solutions
but we ask you please do
not look at other people's solutions.
Relapse, please all the code you write should
be your own and you shouldn't share
code or a look at other solutions.
Greeting. Of course,
um. We'll be mostly determined from the labs this year,
so 70% of the grade will be,
um. Yeah.
Um, based on whether or not your lab,
you submit passes the tests and we for grading,
we run the same tests that we
supply you so if your lab passes
all the tests that we give you
the chance to show you that full
credit for the lab.
A 20% of the grade is
going to be from lab checkoff meetings
for each of you will pick a
couple of randomly selected labs and one
of the teams will talk to you
and ask you questions about your implementation
just to make sure that um,
are you really understand what's going on.
It's a lab check offs.
There's a 10% remaining.
A lot of [cops] kind of
be like a yes or no
one or zero type of thing
or would they be,
like could someone get like if they
answered some of the questions right,
but not all the questions right when
they get in between,
so the grade.
You know I haven't thought this through.
Um, there's certainly room for partial credit
but it's not a it won't
be binary, it'll definitely be you
can receive partial credit.
Okay. Um, the last 10% is going to
be a driven by the homework and
participation during lecture and piazza.
Um. There will be no exams or quizzes,
this year.
Um, and so what,
that means is that most of the um,
you know 90% of the grade
is being driven by the lab
so you should.
Spend a lot of time in the labs,
um, make sure that you start early
and have enough time to complete
them and work out bugs in
order to get full credit.
And you know as a result of
that this is going to be a
very kind of hands-on software oriented course.
Any questions about the
machinery of the course.
Um, we've got a couple questions in chat,
so the first is a logistical
question, currently 6.S081
isn't listed as usual for the
system's concentration in the [?],
are there plans added to the list
of classes later. I think for that
because it's not an AAGS
it's an AUS, it can't be
used to fulfill arrange requirements,
so it's not a graduate level class.
So, um.
And then we have is the only
homework to submit questions looking at the
calendar that appears to be the case.
Unless I'm forgetting something.
I think that's the case,
yes. So have, um, are there gonna
be cutoffs for grades like X
percent gets an A, Y percent
gets a B etc.
No no,
um. Um,
you know we're going to try to
a free student estimate.
I'm impression of how well you've
understood the material,
um. And assign a grade based on that
so there's no predetermined cutoffs.
All right, anything else.
All right.
Just real quick for folks in the
chat asking about the
concentration requirement, I'm not a hundred
percent certain, um,
but 6.S081 is not,
it's like a temporary number before the
class gets official one, so it
certainly won't be listed anywhere,
if you need it to fulfill a
concentration, I think your best bet is
probably to fill out a petition or
to email somebody like Katrina Kurtz.
To see a what the status is, we don't control,
you know what what classes fill these
kind of requirements,
unfortunately. And for what language will be using
the class will be in C.
Yes. All right,
um. Yeah.
All right, for the rest of the lecture
I want to talk about how, um,
what system calls look like applications,
um, and you know since the system calls
are the interface to the services that
the operating system provides is actually pretty
important what those systems look like what
applications expect from system calls and how
they behave so it's worth understanding what
the interface looks like.
Um, you'll be using the system calls we
talk about in the first lab.
Um, and extending and improving the implementation
internal implementation of these system calls
in subsequent labs.
What we're gonna do is show some
simple examples of little programs.
That call system calls and I'll run
them in xv6 for you.
I'm gonna run them,
the xv6 is a, um,
it's a unix,
a simplified unix-like operating system unix
is a old operating system that's at
least intellectual basis for many present-day operating
systems such as Linux and OS X
it's in very common use.
Um, xv6 our teaching operating system is
much simpler and sort of inspired by
unix and has the same overall structure,
but is dramatically simpler than any real
unix operating system.
Um, it's simple enough that hopefully,
um, you know it would
be relatively straightforward
for you to read all the source code,
as well as read the book,
in a couple of weeks certainly
during the semester in order to
kind of understand all of what
happens inside xv6.
Um, xv6 runs on the RISC-V
processor, RISC-V microprocessor and this is
the same microprocessor that's the focus of
recent 6.004
Um, so many of you may actually
know quite a bit about the
RISC-V instruction set.
Um, in theory you could run xv6
on top of a RISC-V computer
and people done that.
Um, but we're going to run it under the QEMU,
um, machine emulator,
just write this down we got.
Our operating system is
xv6, um, runs on RISC-V.
Microprocessor and not just RISC-V microprocessor,
but we assume a certain amount
of surrounding hardware like memory
and disk.
And console interface for us to talk to it.
Um, We actually run under the QEMU
machine simulator.
So that which runs under Linux,
so I'm all you can actually.
A run xv6 without having that hardware.
Okay so kind of switch to a show the code.
All right,
so, um, first thing is I've a setup xv6 on my laptop,
I'm going to run it type 'make qemu',
'make qemu',
you'll find yourself doing quite a
bit during the labs,
um, which compiles xv6 it's written in C,
so it's compiled with
C compiler,
maybe I'll 'make clean' for you,
so you can see the actual compilation
and I might 'make qemu',
which has the effect of compiling and
building xv6 kernel and all the
user processes and then running them under
the QEMU emulator.
Takes a moment around the compiles,
yeah, and now we're up and running
xv6 and the '$'
prompt you see as the shell which
is the command line interface,
um, to xv6, modeled after the shell on unix,
which is.
um, if you log into Athena organization and
it's, um, it's like the shell that
Athena shows you.
xv6 itself tiny and it comes with
a small number of utility programs and
including for example the 'ls' program which
I'm about to run run ls and
it gives me a list of
all the files and xv6
of which there are only about
two dozen including things like grep and
kill and mkdir, rm which
may be familiar to us,
um, as unix utilities.
Okay, the first program,
I'm gonna show you to illustrate system
calls is a program called copy,
um, um,
here's the source is just a page,
um, so what you're seeing here is
a program that starts on line
8 and main is that sort
of convention for C programs,
it sits in a loop at line 12,
and over and over again, it reads
some data as input and on line
13 and then writes the data just
read his output on line 16,
by run copy,
um, in xv6, it's waiting to read input,
if I type some input,
I'm reads it and spits it back up to me.
Very simple program just does IO.
Um, it's really see as I mentioned a
if you don't already know C, it's
worthwhile getting the standard C programming language
book by Kernighan and Ritchie.
And I think there's a
more full reference to it on the
course website which explains to you and,
um, very straightforward way how to program in C.
Yeah, as I mentioned before,
we even write this program makes two
really three system calls read
write and exit, our system calls.
Um, if you look at the call to
read on line 13, it takes three arguments,
the first argument is a file descriptor
which is really a reference to a
previously opened file.
Um, and the shell,
ensures that when a program starts by default,
it's file descriptor 0 is connected to
the console input, and its file descriptor
1 is connected to the console
output, and that's why I was
able to type to
this copy program and see the output.
Um, of course, these file descriptors are expected
the program expected these file descriptors have
been previously opened and set up by
the shell for it.
And 0 1 file descriptors,
pervasive units convention many,
many unix programs expect to read from
file descriptor 1 and read file descriptor
0 and write to file descriptor 1.
A second argument to read is a
pointer to some memory,
um, where the program is asking the operating
system to read data
into that address in memory,
so that's the buff argument and line 10
allocate 64 bytes of memory on the stack, um,
for read to read into, and the
third argument to read is the maximum
number of bytes that the program wants
to read and the size of buffs
as just sixty maximum 64 bytes,
so the recall reads up to 64
bytes from whatever is connected to file
descriptor 0 and that was
my terminal in this example.
The return value from read it either
it may be sure of the number
of bytes read,
um, which would be 6 and a piece of, um,
typing "xyzzy" by
be might be reading from a file,
if it gets to the end of the file,
there's no more bytes,
read will return 0.
And then some other error occurred like
the file descriptor doesn't exist, read may
return -1.
And, so in many of these examples
like on line 16 there.
Um I don't my example code doesn't
check system call returns for errors.
But you should be more careful than me,
um, um the you should figure out how
system calls reflect errors,
it's usually a -1 return
value and check all system called
returns for errors.
And if you want to know
what the system call arguments and
return values are there's a table
and I think chapter 2 in
the book explains all of the
xv6 system call arguments and
return values.
The question regarding the read syscall,
what if we set the max read
bytes to size of buff to one
plus size of buffer or bigger,
so what if we try to read more than the size.
Yeah, then if there was 65 bytes to read,
then the operating system would happily will just
copy those 65 bytes to
the memory that you provide
and of course there's something
else on the stack up
there maybe the return program
counter or an argument or
something and so if you
pass 65,
then you're inviting a kernel to write junk.
Um to an unexpected place in your stack.
And so that's a bug and it
may cause your [firm] to crash.
Or do something else unexpected,
so as a programmer,
you have to be careful here,
there's nobody writing in C with these
kind of interfaces there's.
Um, it's very very easy to write
code that the compiler is happy
with and will run but absolutely
does the wrong thing.
Um, so that's too bad but it's the way it is.
Okay, um,
one thing to note is that this
copy program and indeed the read write
system calls they don't care about the
format of data,
they're reading or writing a they just
read and write read and write in
this copy program.
Just deal with 8 bit bytes with
screams of 8 bit bytes.
Um, how you interpret them is totally up
to the application,
so the application maybe,
a parse there data records or as C source code,
or who knows what.
The operating system,
um, the only things in terms of a
stream of 8 bit bytes.
Okay, so copy,
assumed this code,
my copy I can assume that the
file descriptors are already set up,
but we need to need to have
a way to create file descriptors.
And the most straightforward way to do
that is I'm with the open system
call and so here's the source for
a program that called open.
That um,
I use the open system call. A
question from the chat,
what do you mean by a stream of bytes.
Um, I just mean that if a
file contains a bunch of bytes.
Then read then successive spilling a pile
contains a million bytes,
if you make a sequence of recalls each 400 bytes.
You know I'll just read the first
hundred bytes and then the second hundred
bytes and then third,
the third hundred bytes.
And um.
All right,
so this program,
um, called open, I'll run it for you.
Um, what it does is a opens creates
a new file called "output.txt"
and then write some bytes to it,
I'm gonna finish this so we don't
see anything because it broke data to
this file.
But we can look
this "output.txt" file that created it and see,
um, the "ooo" wrote there,
so an 11 in the program.
Makes the open system call,
give it a filename "output.txt"
and the "O_" stuff,
um in the second argument to open
our flags that tell the open system
call implementation in the kernel, that we'd
like to create a file with its
name and we're going to write it.
Open returns a newly allocated file descriptor.
Um, and the file descriptor is just
a small number, probably 2 or
3 or 4 something.
And then we pass that same file
descriptor right along with the buffer and
a number of ways to write a that writes data,
um, the file,
the file descriptor refers to.
What that file descriptor is actually doing
is indexing into a little table inside
the kernel, the kernel maintains state for each process,
that's running each program that you run
and among other things,
the kernel remembers a table for every
running process of index by file descriptors
and the table sort of tells the
kernel what each file descriptor refers to.
Okay, a critical point is that each process
has its own sort of space of
file descriptors. So,
before running two different processes,
two different programs and different processes and
they both open a file,
they may actually get the same number
back as a file descriptor,
but because the kernel maintains a separate
file descriptor for each process,
the same file descriptor number may refer
to different files in different processes.
Any questions that open about this little program.
Now we had a question in
chat, question from someone not
familiar with C,
how are these files being described different
from normal C programs,
is it because we're only using kernel
calls, i.e couldn't we also open or
write a file in python.
Um, I don't think I understand that
it's a C program,
that's opening and writing a file.
Um, that's going to move on.
All right so you might ask what
actually happens when ... Maybe the question
is when someone is doing it
in C any different than doing
it in Python minus the syntax.
Well it's not really, um,
and, there's certainly ways to, um,
python provides nice function calls for opening
and doing all these things too.
Or opening files,
for example in reading writing files,
um, there's a layer of a higher
somewhat higher level functions typically not
pointers the memory,
for example.
Um, and python has more error checking for you.
Um, but when you open a file in
python or write a file on python, the
python calls you make.
Boil down to system calls just like these.
Is that a good answer.
Think so.
All right,
all right, um.
I've been over here talking to the, um,
xv6 is unix like shell
and the shell is what people often
call the command line interface,
um, as opposed to a more graphical user interface.
Um, the shell turns,
if you haven't used the shell,
the shell turns out to be a
pretty useful interface for things like system
management of unix systems,
it provides a lot of utilities
for messing around with files and
for program development and
on writing scripts to do all these
things. So, [some before run],
I just want to demonstrate a few
shell features ordinarily when you type things,
um. You're telling the shell to run a program,
so when I type ls what
that means is I'm asking the
shell to run the program
whose name is ls, and what
that really means is there's a
file in the file system called
ls that contains some instructions,
some machine instructions and I'm asking the
shell to run the instructions that are
in the file called ls,
one ls now ls what it actually does is, um.
Get a listing of the files in
the current directory,
and you can see up there
on the 4 line that among
the other files that
ls as exists,
and this list is a file called
ls which is in fact the file
containing the instructions I just ran.
The show does a few other things
for you other than running programs allows
you to redirect IO,
so for example if I say
'ls > out' what that means is
asking the shell run the ls command,
but with its output redirected to the
file called out.
I run ls.
We don't see any output because the
output all went out.
Um, now I can out contains a bunch of data,
um, we could.
The cat command reads a file and
displays the contents of the file,
so I say 'cat out'.
Just going to see now the now
this is the same output of ls.
You can also run a command like
'grep' and I can give it an
argument "x" and what 'grep x'.
The grep command searches for patterns.
Again a if I run 'grep x', it's gonna search for
lines of input to contain "x". I can redirect,
tell the shell to redirect its input
from the file "out".
In order to look for instances of
acts that saved ls output.
It turns out there's three files whose
names contain "x".
Yeah. Um,
we're going to spend a bunch of
time with the shell,
um, uh,
its shell is sort of the most
traditional and fundamental interface units,
because when unix was first developed, all
there was was simple terminal interfaces,
like the one we're using and
the main use of units originally was
time sharing a bunch of people logging
into the same machine,
much like Athena and talking to shells.
A question about system calls and the compiler,
how does the compiler handles system
calls does assembly generated make a
procedure call to some code segment
defined by the operating system.
Um, there's a special RISC-V instruction that
a program can call that transfers control
under the kernel,
so indeed when you write C code
that makes the system called open write,
um. And technically what actually happens is
open is a C function in
the C library.
Um, but the instructions in that function are
really machine instructions,
it's not open.
The open function that we're calling isn't
a C function implemented in assembler and,
the assembly code,
um, consists of this special instructions
actually called ecall.
On RISC-V the special instruction
that transfers control
into the kernel,
and then the kernel looks at
the processes memory and registers to
figure out what the
arguments were.
All right, the next example I want
to look at is example program
that calls 'fork'.
Creating process,
um, so this is the
very simple use of fork at
line 12, we're calling fork and
what fork does is
creates a copy of the memory of
instructions and data of the calling process,
now we have two processes with identical memory.
Fork, the fork system call returns
in both processes.
In the original process,
the fork system call returns the process
id which is, um
an integer greater than 0.
The original process for returns,
the process id of the newly created
process and in the newly created process
fork returns 0.
So we sort of break even though
the processes have identical memory,
you can break the symmetry of
old versus new process by the
return value from fork.
And in line 16 you can see code,
the checks and says if the
process id is equal 0 must
be the child,
you must now be running in the child.
Um, of course there's two processes in
the other process,
um in the calling process which is
usually called the parent process id is
greater than 0.
Um, so the child will print "child" and
the parent will print "parent".
And then they'll both exit. So when I run fork,
now here we get, so it may look like garbage.
What's actually happening is that after the fork,
both of these processes are running they're
both running at the same time and
QEMU is actually emulating a multi-core,
microprocessor for me,
so they really are running at
the very same time,
so when they produce output.
They're producing each byte of their
output at the same time as
the other process is producing the
corresponding bytes of its output,
so the output of the two processes are
inter league,
um, you can see that they're both typing "f".
Um, they're both gonna type fork return.
Um, so you can see the "f"
from both of them, in the
"o" both of them and the
"r" both and so on.
Um, one of them.
Um, you can see the 0 at the
end of that 1 line is in
the child fork return 0.
Um, I'm guessing that the parent fork return 19.
That is the child's process id is
19, under xv6 that basically means the
19 process that was created since boot.
Um, and then one of them prints "child"
and you can see the "c" "h"
"i" "l" "d" interleave with that is
the other one prepare.
So, yeah.
This is a silly use of fork,
but we can see vividly in
this output that has created two
processes that are,
and both of them are running for
returning both processes and they're both running.
But also note that one printed child
and the other parent so it's important
that fork returns differently
Um, and the two processes.
Question, um,
is the child process as a result of
fork always identical to the parent process
or could they be different.
Um, in xv6 are identical.
Um, except the return value from fork.
You know the instructions are the same
that data is the same,
the stack is the same,
um, also both.
Processes, the processor copies and they both have
their own separate
address spaces that is they both
have they both think that their
memory starts at 0 and goes
on up from there.
Um, but it's different it's different different memory.
Um, with the two of them.
In a more sophisticated operating system,
there are some details which we definitely
don't care about them,
they may occasionally cause parent and child
to differ, but in xv6
they're the same except the return value.
Um, so the memory is the same,
in addition the, um,
file descriptor table is copied.
So if the parent had some files open.
Um, and the child sees the same set
of file descriptors.
Um, although the child is seeing them in a copy.
Of the table of file descriptor information.
And so we'll see in a moment
that it's quite important that a fork
copies the table of open file descriptors
as well as the memory.
Okay so.
A fork creates a new process,
but when we run stuff in the shell,
um. The shell indeed creates a new process
to run each command that you type.
Um, but it needs to actually run the command in it,
so if I type ls,
we need to shell forks to create
a process to run ls,
but there needs to be some way.
For that new process actually run the
instructions from the ls program.
Below those instructions from the file called
ls and the example program,
I'm gonna show you in a minute.
Um, uses echo, echo is a very
simple command a just takes whatever arguments
you pass to it and writes them
to its output.
And I prepared for you a program called 'exec'.
Um, um.
Which a run which
makes the exec system call which replaces
the calling process with the instructions read
from a particular file
you specify.
Loads the instructions from that file over
the current process or discarding its current
memory and then starts executing those instructions,
so the call to exec system call
exec on line 12.
It's going to have the effect of
the operating system loading the instructions from
the file called echo.
In the current process sort of replacing
the memory of the current process and
then starting to execute.
Um, those instructions and in addition,
you can pass arguments command line arguments
echo exec allows you to pass an
array of command line arguments.
It was just an array of
pointers in C line 10 sets
up an array of
character pointers which are essentially strings and
initialize that array to be,
to contain the strings echo, this is echo, um.
And that's equivalent to calling running echo
with them and with
the three arguments.
This is echo and so when I want exec.
Um, indeed,
um I see this output,
this is echo,
but even though I ran the exec
command exec program.
What the exec program does is calling
the exec system call to replace itself
with echo and so it was really
the echo program.
I'm producing this output.
And something about the exec system call,
that's important for us is that
it exec preserves the current
table of file descriptors,
so whatever file descriptor 0 1 2
etc, were referred to before exec,
they refer to the same thing in this new program
whose instructions we've loaded.
Another point is that ordinarily exec does
not return because exec replaces
the current processes memory entirely,
um, there's nothing for exec to return to
exec you know.
Read the instructions for that file and
execute them and then that's it,
um, the only time exec turns
is if some error occurred that
prevented the operating system from running
that program for you,
so for example if the program doesn't
exist at all.
Exec can't find a file called echo,
for example an exec would return -1.
Um, Signal that something wrong it couldn't
couldn't find the file so ordinarily
exec does not return.
It only returns if the kernel
couldn't actually run the file for you.
Questions about exec.
The question in the chat is
what is the last 0 for
in argv.
It marks the end of the array
C is so low level that,
um, there's no
the C array scheme.
Doesn't have a way for
code to find out how long
the array is and so
tell the kernel that,
um, you know we met at the array contains echo,
this is echo and nothing more.
We put zero was the last strip as the last
pointer. Each of those strings in double quotes
is actually a pointer to some memory
that contains those bytes.
That fifth element of the array is
a pointer's value is 0,
the convention is that a pointer
whose value is 0 or what's
called a null pointer.
Um, sort of signifies nothing,
Um, with it.
You were gone,
so the code in the kernel
has actually walks through this array
until it finds it.
Element whose value is zero.
Okay, um,
all right,
so this is how a program can replace itself.
With another program from a file,
but actually when we run stuff in
the shell like 'echo abc',
um or ls or anything else,
we don't want to replace the shell,
we don't have a shell,
just call exec.
Um, because,
that would replace the shell with the
echo command then echo exited.
That would be end, you know
we don't want an echo to
replace the shell,
so the shell actually does is fork.
And then the child calls exec
and that's an extremely common unix
idiom program instead.
Um, want to run a program,
but regain control what they do
is call fork and have the
child called exec.
So here's a simple example,
this forkexec program.
In this program call fork line 12
in the child sort of line 14
we call exec much like before.
The child process,
um, has to replace itself with the echo command.
Um, echo,
does this thing and then exits.
And then the parent process,
regains control because um when fork returns.
Greater than zero value in the parent process,
so the parent process then continues to
execute at 19 and unix provides a
wait system call line 24 process to
wait for child that created
with fork, because when I run a
command on the command line.
We want shell to wait for the
command to finish before it prints the
prompt again, before it prints is $
prompt asking me for more input.
So it's the wait system call allows
a process to wait for any of
its children to return and this status
argument is that, um,
a way for
exiting child to communicate one integer
32 bit value from the exiting child
to the waiting parents on line 17 that
argument to exit that 1 that's the
argument to exit.
The operating system passes that one from
the exiting child
to the call to wait line
20 so wait the & wait,
is passing the address of the
status variable to the kernel,
the kernel fills in that address with,
um, child's argument to exit.
And the convention in unix is that
if a program completes successfully exit exits
with status 0.
Um, but it has encountered an error at line 17.
Um, the unix convention is that you
pass 1 to exit and so if
you care the calling process can look
at the status from wait.
Decide whether the
child completed successfully. A professor
Morris quick question.
Yes, about the exec call 19, um,
we mentioned not a bit ago that
exec will completely go into the echo
program and not return to fork exec.
Um, so,
oh, would ever reach line 16 and 17.
Well, not for this exec code because there
happens to be a program called echo,
but if I modify that code here,
let me just modify this code.
Okay, so first let me just
run forkexec.
It actually does execute echo with those
arguments we see the output,
"this is echo" and we see
the child exited to show that
echo exited successfully and the parent wait
for. Let me just
modify the program for you.
Um, instead of echo going to run some
command that doesn't exist.
Um, um,
actually the exit out of
QEMU. With 'Ctrl-a x' and then rebuild
the whole thing in order to re-compile
I modified.
Forkexec now run forkexec back again
after modifying it.
And this time because the program
we're asking to,
um, actually,
the program,
we're asking to execute doesn't exist,
exec does return we see the exec failed output.
Um, and the exit 1 you'll see
the 1 there is communicated back
to the parent which says the
child exited the status 1.
So exec returns back to the calling
function when something went wrong.
Yes. Yeah.
Okay good.
All right,
um, something that going to note
here that actually think many of you
already noted is that.
It is a common idiom here,
this fork followed by exec in the
child and it's potentially a bit wasteful
the fork copies the entire parent process.
But exec throws away all that copied
memory and replaces it with,
whatever is in the, um,
a file that you're running,
so you know if you're worried about
this kind of stuff,
the copy implied by the fork.
Is in some sense mostly wasted because
all that copied memory is just thrown
away and replaced by the exec.
And this affects actually would be significant
for big programs,
if you have a multi gigabyte program
that calls fork.
Um, and it did indeed copy all
the memory would actually take a
fair fraction of a second perhaps
to do the copy.
Um, which could be a problem.
Um, um,
but later in the course you'll actually
implement some optimization in particular something called
copy-on-write fork which will eliminate
almost all of the apparent inefficiency
of fork copying only to have exec
throw away the copy.
It turns out with a bunch of
tricks involving a virtual memory system.
Um, you can build a fork,
that's lazy about the copy and that
doesn't do in the common case of
fork immediately followed by exec.
Um, or you don't actually have to do
the copy because the child doesn't actually
use most of the memory.
Um, I think you'll find that's a fun
and interesting lab. Question from chat,
why does the parent process parent waiting
completely before the child calls exec.
Yeah. It's just chance.
Um, why is it that you know the observation is that,
um, you know.
Um, it could be that the parents output
could be interleaved with the child's output
in the same area that we saw
before with similar fork example,
um, it just happens not to be there's
no guarantee that this is the output,
we would see in fact we,
we shouldn't be surprised if we saw
the lines of the output in the
other order or interleaved.
I suspect what's going on, is
that it takes a bit of
time and effort.
The exec system caused a little bit
expensive, because it has to load all
those you have to access the file
system and access the disk and read
the contents of a file called echo
off the disk into memory,
after allocating some memory and
that even after freeing some memory
from the old process so there's
quite a bit of machinery involved
in the exec system call,
um. And apparently that takes long enough that
the parent can complete producing the output.
Before the exec is finished and
started running echo.
Does that make sense.
Another question is a convention that the
child can't wait for the parent.
There's not a way unix doesn't have
a way for the child.
There's no straightforward way for a child to wait
from a parent.
The wait system call.
Because it's the only mechanism available
well the wait system call waits
for your children.
And that's it.
And so what wait what wait does is,
um, if you have any children.
And one of them has already exited what does exit.
Then we will return but you know
if you don't have any children say,
because you are.
Because in this simple case,
um. It was just a parent and child
if the child called wait.
The child doesn't have any children and
in that case,
wait just returns immediately with a -1
error return saying this process doesn't
have any children.
Anyway, the short answer is there's no way
for a child to wait for its
parent to exit.
And another question when we say
the child copies all the memory
from the parent process,
what exactly do we refer to by
that I thought the child is going
to define the variables again.
Um, or when you compile this,
you know,
um. After compilation,
your C program.
It's just a bunch of instructions in
memory that live in ram.
Um, and so those can be copied.
Because they're just bytes living in ram,
those can be copied somewhere else,
um. And with appropriate trick having to do
with setting up.
A sort of virtual memory mapping's and
make map things look the same in
the child and the parent you can
just copy the parent's memory image to
the child and
executing the child.
And even though we're looking at C programs,
you should think of them as just
a bunch of machine instructions.
Um, which is bytes in memory that can be copied.
If a parent has multiple
children would wait just return
as soon as the first
child finishes meaning that there
could be some more interleaving
with the parent and unfinished
children with their need to
be multiple separate ways to
ensure all children finished.
Yes, yeah,
if you call fork more than one
if a given process calls for twice.
Um, then it wants to wait for both
children and has to call wait twice
each call to wait.
Will return as soon as one of
the children exits you don't when wait
returns you don't necessarily know which child
is exited the weight returns the child's
process id as its return value so
you can tell.
After we returns you know which one
it was at exit.
Um, as a final example,
um. I'd like to show,
um, how all these facilities combine,
um. To implement IO direction,
so if you remember,
um, the shell provides us with this
handy syntax I can say
'echo hello >  out'.
Um, that runs the echo command that
argument sending it.
First, um, that sends its output to the
file out and looked out.
Or yet.
Um, on the cat and with its
input connected from the out file,
we can see that saved output from
the echo command.
Um, the way the shell sets this up.
Um is,
um, as follows.
Um. It a shell first forks like on
line 13 and then in the child,
the shell changes the way the file
descriptors are set up so that the
child's file descriptor
1 which
by convention most programs used for the output,
um. This shell a changes the child's
file descriptor to 1 to refer
to this output file,
and then run whatever commands you wanted
and that leaves the parent shells file
descriptor 1 unchanged so this idiom of
forking and in a child, changing
around the file descriptors.
Um, is the usual way unix actually redirect
input an output for a command
that you run but not affect
the input and output for a
calling program because we don't want
to redirect the shell's output.
Um, we only want to redirect the
child programs output.
Anyway, the way this works we call fork unusual way,
a line 15 only executes in the child.
The reason for the close 1 on
line 15 is that in this program.
We're redirecting a just the output of
the echo command,
so when I run this redirect.
A program produces no output itself,
it ran echo with its output directly
to "output.txt".
So when I look at "output.txt",
um. I see this expected output,
the reason for the close 1 on line 15.
Is that we want 1 as
a sort of conventional output file script
to refer to something else,
it happens so we don't have a child,
we don't want to use the father descriptor
1 that the shell had that's connected
to the console.
Um the call to open on line
16 is guaranteed to return 1 because,
um the semantics of open are that
open returns the lowest
file descriptor number,
that's not currently in use in the
calling process since we just closed 1.
And file descriptor 0 is still connected
to the console,
I mean.
I'm open is guaranteed to return 1.
So after the line 16 file descriptor
1 is connected to this file.
When we exec echo, echo just writes its output,
the file descriptor 1 and now go
to this file and the cool thing
about this is echo had no idea
what's going on, echo doesn't need to
know about IO direction at all,
it just writes its output,
the file descriptor 1.
I'm only the shell
knows about
IO redirection.
This example also illustrates the sort of
kind of neatness of the separation between
fork and exec, the fact that fork
and exec our separate system calls separate.
Um functions.
Means that there's a period of time
in the child between the fork.
Between them for returns in the child
and exactly which were still running the
calling processes instructions,
so the calling process.
Even though it's running in those instructions
are running in the child,
it's still the calling processes instructions that
are executed and so the calling process
is still able to change things and
still in control up until line 19.
And this sort of interval between fork
and exec gives the show a chance
to change what the file descriptors,
refer to for example.
Any questions about this redirect example.
Yeah. All right, I'm about out of time.
Just wrap up, we look at unix is,
um. A bunch of the interfaces to
unix's IO and process abstractions, um,
thing to take away from this is
if the interfaces are relatively simple and
just pass integer like file descriptors
and process ids back and forth across
its arguments system calls,
um. But,
Well, the functionality inside the interface is
relatively sophisticated like
creating new processes and copying the current
process, and furthermore I show some examples
of ways in which the abstractions
individually simple combine in useful ways,
for example to produce
IO redirection.
There's a lab due at the end
of next week and that lab involves
writing more simple utilities like the ones
I showed that use the system calls
that we discuss.
So, have fun with that lab and I'll
see you in class next week.
Um, and that's it.
Thank you.
Since I'm the one recording,
how do I end this, first
time recording in lecture. They
will be exit.
Okay, nothing special I can just exit it
will be saved somewhere.
Yes, awesome.
I assume we'll create some directory and
sticking a file in that directory.
There's also office hours right after this right.
Yes, perfect cool.
Happy. All right.
All right,
thank you and I'll see you next week,
thanks.