okay uh good afternoon uh wherever you
are
uh can everybody hear me a quick sound
check to make sure
yup you're fine okay good thank you um
so
uh today uh uh we're gonna talk uh i
don't really have
specific agenda but basically the plan
is to
try to answer questions uh uh that you
might have
about this one the last lap or the
previous laps
so the approach i'm going to take uh
today
is i'm going to walk through the staff
solutions
in particular my own solutions and
going to discuss them and hopefully as
we go through staff solutions
you can jump in if i don't answer a
particular question
or wait a little bit because i put all
the questions
that you've asked at least before 11am
this morning
in the lecture notes at the bottom and
we'll try to go through them
um i'm going to start
with the page stable app because most
questions were about the page table lab
and partially because of joomla it was
the the hardest laughs
and so maybe a couple comments before
diving into sort of the technical uh
part of this uh let's talk a little bit
about
uh the page table live in general
and you know as you probably observed
you know there's actually a few lines of
code uh
in terms of the solution but it
unfortunately
has you know hard to debug
problems
and you know there's
one reason is that you know when
actually the block shows up
uh you know the outcomes are uh pretty
extreme
like in the worst case uh probably some
of you observed that
in the worst case um q mu just stops
or xv6 that stops there's no output
being printed anymore
uh and that's it and you know now it's
your job to
figure out actually what went wrong uh
in the best case
you know you get sort of a kernel panic
uh but depending you know maybe just
your starting point or for tracking down
what the actual
source of the problem is you know the
panic itself is probably related to
something else so the invariant in the
kernel got broken
uh but you know somewhere else earlier
probably when you set up the page tables
you know you did something wrong that in
the end caused this
pendant to go off and so you have to
track down uh what's going on
so fewer lines of code hard to do by
problems
uh and you know just a harsh environment
uh to debug in uh if you do in the
kernel debugging or
you know kernel programming you know use
the programming environment the
debugging environment is
unforgivable like as robin mentioned in
the first lecture this is one of the
hard parts
about basically doing kernel programming
um
and and that's a you know just to make
you made me feel better and this is not
just hard for you
you know it's actually a little hard for
the staff
both in terms of helping you and
actually you know when we do these labs
you know we make similar problems and
you know we
probably have more experience in
tracking bugs down uh but you know they
just
they do take time uh if they're helping
you you know the
uh it tends to be hard too because
there's some small fracking of code
there's one detail something probably
wrong and they're figuring out actually
what that little
detail is uh it's not that easy uh of
course you know some of the problems
we've seen before and we recognize you
know for example we didn't make the same
mistake ourselves
uh but other ones you know you
discovered all kinds of different ways
of sort of breaking the kernel
uh that we hadn't seen before
so this is just heart and i think this
is a you know
our in our experience um
this is historically always hard with a
virtual memory
so every time the first virtual memory
lock
you know comes around either in sov1 or
its predecessor in 6828
it has to be the case that you know that
tends to be the hardest lap
uh uh of all the labs and
you know for a number of reasons one you
know the harsh environment you know the
uh the bugs are spectacular and uh
partly because you know you haven't had
that much kernel programming experience
yet and so this is sort of the first lap
with all those things come together
uh this year we tried to make the lab
simpler uh in fact this is a new lab
uh last week we did not have that lab uh
in the hopes to actually make this
introduction or the transition into
virtual memory easier uh in in some ways
i think it's
successful in other ways you know it's
still hard uh and so we don't really
know maybe about the easiest way of
actually
introducing virtual memory programming
is
lab number the lab next week the lazy
lab
is in the lab that used to be the first
virtual memory lab
and my suspicion is that you'll find
that this year
a lot easier than the students founded
last year
because you now have much more
background in virtual memory
okay so that's uh maybe there's a good
point to stock this is like a couple
high level points i wanted to make
before
jumping into uh the more technical uh
more the details so if you have any
questions it's a great
time to ask questions
okay um then let's uh
quickly uh you know some of you asked
for this uh very quick review
exactly what you know where uh you know
what the sort of the setting is
um and so basically the setting is page
tables
and again we have physical memory i will
drive here on the
right side uh we know the physical
memory
uh consists of partly about devices
and they live you know above this ox
you know zero zero and many many more
generals
and then here basically d ram chips
and we know that the qmu actually puts
the kernel the kernel text and data
you know right you know here at the
bot above ox00 so this is where the
kernel lives
and you know one way maybe let me erase
this a little bit
and use the kernel and you know
basically literally what it means you
know what this is what the kernel is and
these are the
and the instructions versions of the
assembly instructions
that you have seen and there's also some
data
structures located at these addresses
okay so that's the memory part of it and
then on the other side
we got our cpu that executes
instructions
and so the cpu has a bunch of internal
state
and has some registers you know whatever
x0 or
r0 blah blah blah blah and you know
maybe the program counter
and you know when xv6 starts you know
the
proven counter contains this value oh
x000
um and um uh
and that's the way you know the cpu
knows that basically you know look at
that address to find
you know the first instruction that
looks at the first instruction decodes
the instruction
and updates whatever cpu state that
needs to be updated
uh you know page tables add sort of a
component to it
uh you know the addresses you know that
the cpu uh
uh others or the instructions or part of
the instructions
like you know jump to some particular
address you know those addresses
are typically or most commonly or there
will be
virtual addresses and those virtual
dresses
go to that proven you know something
typically called the mmu
and then you translate it to physical
addresses
uh and uh that is allows us to index
into
either the i o part of the memory or the
dram part the memory
um the uh to control
how this translation happens you know
there's this satp register
which contains uh the root of the
page table of the current running page
table and if there's zero
then there's basically no translation
going on and
uh the virtual address is literally
directly a physical address so when the
processor actually starts up
there's no value in satp and so when the
program counter
as an ox xox you know basically the
physical address is also integrated
and basically the product the cpu
fetches the instruction
you know from that particular location
as soon as you know the
uh as soon as the satp actually contains
a non-zero value
then uh you know for example maybe
uh so somewhere in here it's like
drawing make something extend the
picture a little bit further
uh we know that the kernel actually has
a maximum of
128 megabytes and so basically this is
all
free memory from here to there
is free memory and free memory is
putting on the list in catalog.c as
you've seen before
and so somewhere in here is also the
root page table
for you know a kernel page table so
maybe here's home page
and that is the root
page table directory
uh and as soon as we load that value you
know the address
of the physical address of that value
into the sap address
and register so let's say this and maybe
this address is
ox 7 you know ff
blah blah blah something just below 120
mega megabytes so in that free space of
memory
reload that address in satp
then at that point
you know the processor or the mmu will
use the root page tables to actually do
the translation you know from virtual to
physical address
um and you can think of this you know
this particular whole thing
sort of being a single sort of box you
know integrated
you know uh together
any sort of questions about this high
level picture before uh
keep them going so one of the key points
that sort of remember here is that the
page statements themselves also live in
memory
okay okay so let's uh
jump down to uh
the first part of the page table app
namely
part one where you have to print uh
the page table for the
init program and
and you know explain it basically in
terms of this
figure three four and the figure three
fours are right here
three four uh and this is figure three
four shows the user address space
so just let's look at the user address
days for a second before we uh go into
detail
uh so we have the text at the bottom so
this is the instructions
uh of the program starting address zero
above the instructions are you know data
global variables
uh live there uh then there is something
called the guard page
we'll talk about and then there's the
stack of the
user program so the kernel has its own
stack uh but the usual or multiple
stacks
uh the user program has its own stack
and above again is basically what's
called heap
memory you know free memory you know
that we can you know get more
uh memory uh using s-brick so s-break
basically points to
the top of the user address space and we
want to grow it
we call the s-break system call to grow
the
uh grow the top of the to grow the
bottom part you know up
uh into the heap we also know that at
the
top there from the last lecture that
there are two pages two special pages
uh the trampoline and the trend frame
track frame page
and the trampoline page you know
contains these instructions to basically
transition in and out of the kernel
and the track frame is uh is a
convenient place you know to
store some state and when we jump into
the uh
kernel because we need the kernel ones
that use the registers we can't use the
registers because the user space program
still has them
in use so i'm not going to talk much
about the trend frame and the trampoline
at all but you know they're there
um okay so here the this picture a
little bit below
uh you know is actually the uh
the printout from uh when i read it
uh from in it like this the first
successful call of exec right so like we
know that in a code make some system
called exec
for the program in it and just at the
end of
exit we're printing out that page table
now so there's a couple things that we
uh
many things we can observe about this
particular page table
so first of all you know we in addition
to
printing out the physical the pte's and
the physical addresses i'm also printing
out the flags
uh and you can see here that here's the
flag is one
and it basically says that this
translation or this uh intermediate page
is about similar here that is an invalid
independent page and they basically
correspond you know to the
level two page and then the second one
for the corresponds to the level
uh
i'm sorry i just screwed the arrows
wrong so that's why it paused 20 seconds
okay so the top this is the top level
page table
uh this kind of points to this
particular page table
and then this points to that particular
page table
or that's the address we're pointing to
sort of a short
hand for saying uh that is the base
address for that particular page
and as you know each of these pages is
bytes uh that's the size of page size
and so divided by 64
bits you know you get five in the twelve
entries
um okay so we'll see is that the bottom
part of this
address space for init basically has
actually all this has three pages
only three pages uh and we've got a
couple things that we can
uh discern from the three pages uh we
know that the
so the bottom page which basically
corresponds to virtual address zero
uh lists physical address you know eight
seven six uh
four zero uh and you know we know from
our previous picture that is somewhere
in that
uh free memory uh that the kernel has
available to allocate pages from
and then the final thing you see we see
the flags we see the flags have one
f so it means that the read bit is the
val bit is set to read that is set to
the
w bit is set to execute data set and
ubid is set
so this page can contain both data and
text
and these permissions allow the user
program
to execute instructions from it read the
right memory
and do it from user space okay so then
maybe the most interesting question is
like what's up with page one
and you know as a hint you know we see
that page one
uh only has f and not the u bit set
so uh you know what is the page one
anybody
is it the card page yeah it's the guard
page right
so the guard page uh is mapped because
it has a vmip but it has not the ubit
set so
any user instruction that tries to so if
a user program
runs off its stack so the stack grows
from the top down
so if it actually has more you know the
stack is bigger than 496
completely full and if then uh the user
program you know pushes something on the
stack stack on
the ground it will grow into the guard
page and because the view bit is not set
uh we're going to get a page fault or a
trap into the kernel
because the mmu cannot translate to
address
uh to cannot address cannot
translate any addresses on the guard
page to a physical address
because the met the not having a unit
basically forbids the translation
okay and what is that in page two
any anybody
stack yep that's the stack page and so
again the stack page is
uh four four four four five and 96 bytes
and
you would see that's completely
elaborate in terms of permissions
uh it has you know everything could we
set it up tighter if we wanted to
yeah i think you could disable the
executable bit
yeah you probably could execute the the
xbit
that would forbid having any program
code on the stack
so if you like generate code on the fly
and put it on the stack you know you
wouldn't be able to execute it
you know that's maybe probably a good
thing
and so we could have been a little bit
tighter okay
um so that's the basically the bottom
part of this
uh thing uh of the page table so now
let's look at the
remaining entries so basically only two
remaining entries
um and maybe the flag bits are the most
telling part of this
uh so seven uh you know means you know
read
right and valid
work uh and so
what do we think that one is and maybe
i'll do the other one too
uh so b is i think one zero zero one so
presumably x
invalid so what do we think
511 is
anybody
the trampoline and trap page yeah so the
[ __ ] that's clear that's the trampoline
uh and probably 511 is definitely the
trampoline correct
because it has the xbit set so we must
be executing or we're allowing
instruction to be executed from that
page so that wants me to trampoline
and we're allowing read and write you
know to the
uh to that page so that's probably the
track frame page because that's the one
we use to restore
and uh save registers in
okay one of the probably the thing the
main
the most important thing to notice is
there's no ubit
right there so that what does that mean
that means that the user program can
actually not execute the instructions
uh that are actually at 510 and if at
the
trampoline page and can't be the right
to that page
so only the kernel can execute
instructions from there and it can only
read it right
so basically like the kernel is going to
be doing this before
the while still using the user page
table right that's kind of the point
yeah exactly as you know robert
explained in the last lecture
this is like just for the transition
from user to kernel and before we jump
to
before we load to the kernel page table
in the satp
register we need a little bit of you
know the kernel needs a little bit of
memory to actually do his job
okay so a couple other things that may
be interesting of this picture
um so we all you know all these
addresses right
87630862471
these are all pages or memory in that
range
of the kernel memory that is not you
know that's basically free
right are these addresses contiguous
in physical memory
anybody uh no they don't have to be
no they don't have to be and they aren't
correct you know look at this you know
seven six four zero zero it reconfigures
then the next address would have been
eight
seven six you know six five zero correct
and it isn't
uh so there's no one of the cool things
about page tables is
that even though maybe the virtual
address space is contiguous
the physical address space or the
physical pages that go along with the
contiguous virtual addresses are not
don't have to be continuous
and so this gives the kernel a lot of
flexibility in terms of you know
allocation
and uh three pages
okay any questions about
this part one i had a question yeah um
could you explain the sbr k a little um
also if we are going to cover it in a
future lecture then maybe we can
like just a small yeah actually let me
i'm going to talk about it on wednesday
and it actually will be the topic of the
lazy lab
uh so let me maybe respond that question
a little bit to wednesday
uh and then that's not clear enough
please ask it again
sounds good thank
uh you also had a question
so uh i remember that
the book said the trampoline and the
trap frame were at the top of the
address space
yeah uh but here
it stops at like the first the root page
table it indexes at two five
five not five one one yeah brilliant
question very good i'm glad you asked it
uh i saw it in here in
the q a questions and i was planning to
talk about it but of course i forgot
so yeah what's going on here you know
why is two five five not five eleven
yeah you know we you know we always say
the trampoline lives at the top of the
address space well
the top of the address space correct is
you know point
is actually entry 511 of the to the top
level directory
and it is only 255.
anybody any ideas why this is the case
we said that one bit that we said we
were going to use we actually aren't
using because of sign extension problems
because it just makes it easier and we
also don't need that memory yeah so uh
so that's
exactly the right answer so this is
basically stupid
technicality um so the virtual addresses
are in principle uh i think 39 bits
right and but we actually in xv6 only
use 38 of them
and as a result you know the top of the
max va
for us is basically the 255 entry
and the reason we don't use the 39 bit
is for no particular
uh good reason other than that basically
if you have the 39th bit set
then all the remaining uh bits in the
64-bit address have to be once
and so we just didn't want to deal with
this problem that if we ever set the
39-bit we also have to set the 40 41st
42nd to 43rd etcetera until
the 64. um
so that's the excavation does that make
sense yes
yep that's a very good very good
application though
so i also had a question about why is
the text and the data on the same page
ah very good question also uh that seems
stupid right i mean you know why not put
them in separate pages so that you can
actually set the permission bits
uh more carefully the
main reason we're not doing that is for
simplicity
just makes exec more complicated and we
wanted the simplest exact possible
so a real operating system would you
know not have data and text in the same
uh page in fact we have to specify
you know if you look at the loader flag
uh in the make file you'll see that it
has the desktan
option and that forces is actually data
and text to be in the contiguous
and not in separate pages
any more questions about this i had a
follow-up question regarding the number
of
bits we are using um so you said we're
using just 38 bits
is it is like the hardware still
provides for us to use
39 bits but we are designing our
operating system
such as that we're using 38 yeah so we
basically if the machine had more
uh ram than two to 38
we would not be able to use that ram now
we're already running with we're
assuming basically much less memory
than 2 to 38 so it's not a big deal for
us
but the real operating system would have
done better
so just pure for simplicity we want to
make it as easy as you
for you as possible by reading the few
lines of code possible
okay yeah makes sense
okay so now uh let's uh switch to uh
part two and so let's
bring up you know a picture you probably
have looked at a lot
uh the kernel dress space correct on the
left
is the virtual dress space on the right
is physical memory
uh you know here are your i o devices
and then from here on is you know dram
and you know and basically running until
what actually uh
120 28 megabytes um
for us because we just assume that
there's no more than 250
to fix 128 megabytes of memory and so
this part of the physical memory is the
free memory
and that from now is where the kernel uh
whoops i drew it a little bit wrong let
me be a little bit more careful
uh so here we basically have you know
kernel
text and data and then you know this
memory above you know it's basically
a memory that the kernel allocator has
and from there
we allocate memory for user programs we
allocate them for page tables etc
the kernel allocates everything from
there until it runs out of memory when
it runs out it gets to 128
megabytes and then it starts returning
errors or system calls
okay good uh so let me
pull up my uh first part correct in some
sense of this assignment again it was
the part two of the assignment was just
to
run with or copy the kernel page table
so that every process
has its own kernel page tables
and that was the basically that's the
the assignment here so let me
before jumping into the code let me
actually say a couple things uh
more general things about it uh so
part two
um uh
and you know maybe the first question
really that uh sort of getting get your
head around is like in
some way it's gonna do something trivial
right we already have a kernel page
table we just have to make end copies of
it you know for one copy for each
particular process
um and you might say well you know how
hard can it be
uh and it turns out i think it was a
little bit harder for a couple reasons
some good ones some less good ones uh
hardening seams
and you know one reason is that uh you
know the xv6 code
is sort of specialized for one kernel
page table
and you know you saw that in kvm init
uh and so that makes it a
little bit uh uh you know generalizing
you know
actually a little bit of work because
you actually have to modify the xv6 code
um kvm in it as you also saw
is not the full story you know for
building the
uh page table uh for the kernel you know
there's also stuff in prop unit
that actually adds mappings to the
kernel page table
and there's even something in uh virgi
io disk
that actually interacts you know with
the kernel page table
so basically there's no one single place
in the kernel where actually the kernel
page table actually is built
then the third reason why you know this
is slightly complicated is because you
also have to deal with cleanup
uh so there's the aspect of actually
creating these copies
but whenever time a user process exit we
also have to clean up
those uh page samples that were in use
because we want to return them to the
pool of free memory so that we can use
them later uh so that we can keep on
running processes
and so that is the and that makes
things a little bit complicated because
you know we got to be a little bit
careful in actually
freeing the kernel page table or a copy
of the kernel page table
but you certainly don't want to you know
free uh memory that's actually still in
use or page table entries that's still
in use by other page tables
so we've got to be careful there and
then uh
you know basically it's easy to make a
small error
in your page table when you copy those
page tables
uh you know if you get a little thing uh
you know visually you get a hard
hard buck
and and one of the problems here is i
said a little bit earlier is
uh the hard part shows up and much much
much later right you built the kernel
page table so you built a copy of the
kernel
page table all looks fine you look
loaded in satp
then even maybe the kernel runs for a
little while and then it panics
and it turns out you know the reason it
panics is because you know you made some
small mistake
in the page table a long long time ago
and so this is
one reason why it makes uh makes life
difficult
uh for kernel programming
and you know and basically you know
these hard debugs basically are just
time consuming
to track down
because at the point that the bug no it
happens uh that's actually not the real
cause
uh of the bug but about you know the
real cost is you know someone was way
earlier when you set up
the page tables
okay uh so it turns out
uh there's two approaches to go about it
now to this lap which is sort of uh
two solution approaches
in fact some of you have probably used a
mixture of them uh
but one you know approach what i'll call
the copy approach
and the copy approach basically
literally makes a copy to the kernel
page table
uh so every time you uh
you can do a kernel page table you
allocate pages for the page table
you fill them in et cetera et cetera
and there's a that's one approach the
second approach
is basically to share
uh the kernel page table and in this
case what you do
is like instead of trying to make a
literally nice clean copy of the kernel
page tables
you share all the entries that are
basically uh are going to be unmodified
uh you know from the assignment that
basically anything above
uh claimed or the click address is
actually going to be unchanged or
unmodified you know there's nothing you
have to load there
uh in part three so you know what
basically
all the entries from above zero are
probably identical and so you can share
those entries if you will
um so both approaches are i think
perfectly fine
uh it's not abundantly clear which one
is the better one
my solutions take this approach uh
and um i don't really have a great
justification for it
other than maybe uh you know partially
laziness
i didn't want to think too hard what's
in the kernel page table and
so i figured all the things that are
going to stay the same why do you just
i'm copying them over
or you know copy the ptes over
and then i have to think too hard what
actually isn't that part of the kernel
address space
and you know leads to short codes but
you know i'm not sure it actually is
shorter than for example the copy
solution
but it's important to realize that
basically there are two different ways
of going about this particular
uh problem in either case uh
you know whatever approach you use you
know there's sort of an implementation
strategy to it
and you know the implementation strategy
that i use for almost any
uh kernel program is to do everything in
baby steps
so i might have sort of a general plan
in my head about how i go over the whole
uh you know all the changes i want to
make uh but once i start making those
changes
i do like one or two and then make sure
that those work first and then
uh you know keep going and the other
thing i do is mostly here's as a
strategy is keep the existing code
don't really modify it certainly not
initially i just add code
and switch to this new code and then the
little baby steps and the reason i'm
doing that is that i can easily compare
all the new code and i always have a
working old solution that i can just
roll back to
uh so in case of some strange bugs
happens then i can go back maybe one
step
uh and then try again and see figure out
like actually where my reasoning was
wrong
uh but basically you know baby steps
what partly because these blocks are so
hard to track down
okay let me switch to
like code um so
maybe start in vm dot cd uh so
the here's the uh existing kvm in it
uh and actually uh can everybody see the
code
okay okay uh
and um the
assignment that we are asked for correct
is to make a copy of it
and the way i do that is
let me see where that is
so here's my uvm create that was the
boring part that's basically creating
uh allocating to the top level page
directory for the l2
page directory and then uh
here's my kvm the sort of equivalent of
kvm init
so i get the top level page directory
here uh
in this site then basically i copy
the top 511 entries
from the kernel page table that was
already set up by
kvm in it and so that gives me most
of the kernel page table and then uh
i just have to map in all the devices
that live
[Music]
in the zero entry uh because the zero
entries the entry that we're going to
modify later or we're going to map the
user pages into the bottom
um and there's a couple devices that
live in that in the zero of entry and
those you know devices need to be added
you know to the uh
to this poor process page table kernel
page table
and so maybe if i come back to this
picture earlier
so let me pull up the kernel page table
again
uh yeah maybe this picture is good
as any uh so if you think about my
solution
uh basically these entries
i just share with the existing kernel
page table
so i don't have to allocate any l1 or l2
or l0 levels
they already exist and the only thing i
do is basically literally
copy that ptd entry and so only
the bottom part or the bottom
entry that's the piece i need to
actually rebuild
or copy explicitly instead of copying
ptes
and that covers you know the bottom one
gigabyte
right the address space it's a one page
coverage in a 496.
uh and so this you know this entry you
know covers five into twelve
but this is the two megabyte
and this is one gigabyte and basically
only one of these entries i need to fill
in
does that make sense
so returning to my code here basically
that's all i do in kvm create
and in case my kvm 3 is maybe no
they're not maybe clean the solution but
i take full advantage of the knowledge
that
uh i don't have to do anything from the
entries one to five and eleven in the
top eight level directory
the only entry i can do anything about
is the
uh bottom entry of the kernel of the the
top level directory
that points to one l1 uh entry in the
dot one l
and one tree i just need to go through
and
uh freehold the l2 or l0 entries
and then the end you know free l1 and
then the kernel page table
and so that's my key kvm 3 and my kvm
create so that allows me to create a
kernel page table per process
and then free freeze one is uh when
we're done
sorry quick question could you explain
again the reasoning for
uh only using one to five twelve and not
zero
yes uh okay so uh maybe the easy thing
to do actually let me go back to the
picture here
uh so we have our kernel dress space
correct
uh and you know this is ox8000
blah blah blah in uh
what entry does ox00 fall into in the
for the top level page directory
it's like the uh
zeroth entry no not the zero of entry
correct
so what do we know so the zero entry
like this entry how much does it
cover this entry
how much address space does the bottom
entry of the zero entry of the top-level
page directory cover
i think clint is uh it's free between
zero and zero x two zero zero zero
yes okay so maybe i think you're
absolutely in the right direction so
the bottom entry cover is one gigabyte
correct
and we know yeah like maybe i can
we so the bottom entry is one gigabyte
uh
which
in that one gigabyte is the cleaned and
the click correct
the uart and uh virtio disk i believe
um and then current base actually
already sets up
in a higher uh entry right and we could
compute it if we wanted to we could take
ox
8880 correct shift it uh 12
shift at nine shift at nine and i i
think i don't remember at the top we had
what it is
but we could try to figure it out we
want to actually
maybe we'll try this is always very
risky to do in
lecture but uh it's a gtb
uh i need to so let's go to
layout here's current base
uh so we could print
so shift is 12.
that gives us the uh that offsets oops
okay this is that so then we'll
shift that guy i think you can say this
nine right now this is the next entry
one more so this is entry two
does that make sense so we go back to
our picture here uh
basically current base is entry to
in the top level page directory right so
and we know from the third part of the
assignment that basically we don't
really have to worry about
anything above click
and you know all that stuff uh falls
actually in entry zero
okay so that answer the earlier question
yes thank you
okay so now we the only thing we have
left to do is you know uh
double check where we are going to call
uh this function
uh kvm create and
uh and you know that's going to be in
alloc proc uh
so and
that's
so here where's the new process
initialized and you know
i'm sure all of you do this exactly the
same way you know you enter
you allocate we declare field in the
proc structure
and basically the result of it is
actually what we stick in the kernel
page table
okay and then the only other thing that
we have to worry about is of course we
need to use the page table
and so we need to look at the scheduler
and basically the assignment
more or less told you what to do which
is before you switch
to that user process you need to switch
to kernel page tables
which basically means loading you know
the disk process kernel page table in
satp
and then when you're done uh switching
and running the other processing you
come back from running the other process
and you're going to go back and run the
scheduler
you got to switch back to the main
kernel page table
the the kernel page table because that's
the one that actually used by scheduler
and why do we need to do this switch why
is this important
anybody
so it picks the right kernel page table
uh because the sat
when you go to the page table entries it
picks the right
it picks the right page table to pick
from
yeah hold on
hold on
uh yeah so okay so
when we're stopped okay maybe another
way to ask this question
when is this kernel page table freed
when the user process is done so if we
didn't switch that would mean that
we could be using a page table of a
process that was being freed so the
page table was freed so we don't want to
be dependent on the process we're not
running right now yeah exactly correct
we can never free the page table of a
process that's currently running
uh so we have to have some plan you know
to actually free processes
uh at the point that they're not running
anymore and
your the weight system call is our way
out basically the way it calls
looks if there's any children that are
uh not living you know
that can be cleaned up and then it
cleans them up
uh and but that means that basically uh
when the you know payment process from
the police officer process we've got to
make absolutely sure that you know that
uh the page table that is loaded in the
satp
register uh is not you know one of the
it's not that process you know page
table or actually currently
free now it could be the case there's no
process running at all
correct and so the scheduler basically
has his own page table
uh so that you know all processes can
actually be cleaned up
does that make sense
uh sorry i had a question um is it
that you are mapping the cl int
into the new process kernel page tables
yeah i do
why um because i think the assignment
said like i only have to
uh user processing will not be bigger
than the
[Music]
clint was that it when i met i'm not
both the click and the clint
right and so but i think the assignment
told us that
so which is the lowest one i think the
click is the lowest one and basically
the sign told us that the user process
will not be bigger than the click
address okay
just to make it easy you know we could
have then uh we wanted to make it as
easy as possible for you clear and you
could have done
better if you wanted to
but you know that was the simplest thing
to do
so you have to make diffuse
modifications to get it to work
any further questions uh i have a
question
um is it possible that you can
copy 0 to 512 and then every time you
switch so you're still using like the
global
root page table except you only copy the
first
root page table and every time you
switch a process
you copy over the um users addresses
over
to yeah is that possible to do
in principle i think you could do
something like that so instead of
basically
doing when you allocate a process and
free it you could do it sort of
dynamically
during the scheduler switch uh
it seems complicated
[Music]
that might be more costly because that
means that every time
you switch between two processes you may
have to make a copy of parts of the
kernel page table and so that might be
perform is not an ideal thing the
assignment didn't really say anything
about it
uh you might have timed out in user
tests if you did that
okay i was just wondering because i
tried that approaching it was
a bad experience i was wondering if that
was passive i can imagine uh but
i i think it's in principle possible you
know you could just allocate a new page
table correctly and switch
any every time and upgrade when you
switch out
um i don't think it's the simplest but
you know
your principle it's possible i think
perhaps there's some other modifications
to xv6 but you know
any other questions
because the only other change that you
of course have to make is you use your
trap red
you got to make sure that actually you
run with
the processes kernel page table
okay okay so let's switch then to
i guess part three
[Music]
so um switch back to actually
uh here um
okay so uh actually that's maybe not a
helpful picture
let me see i okay so part three
uh so basically what our plan is is we
have our kernel page table
as before and uh you know we have the
click entries sitting somewhere
and what we're going to do is we're
going to use you know everything below
click
to actually store the user uh
page table where we're gonna map the
user page table into all the user pro or
the user program actually in the kernel
page table
in the bottom
uh and that's the goal and it was the
first question to ask
you know why the heck do that um
you know is there any you know any
advantage of it and
uh you know i think there may be the
middle easy way to
see why it might be interesting is to
core compare the copy ends
uh the new copying and the old copy in
so uh if you know so what happens in
copying correctly copy in copies data
from the user space into the kernel
address space
and but you know
if the kernel does not have the user
address space mapped
basically the kernel has to do this uh
page at the time
correct because the pages in virtual
address space might be continuous but in
physical address space they're not
continuous
and basically what the kernel does in
copy in it basically translates the
virtual user address
into a physical address
since the kernel has all physically
memory mapped with an identity mapping
the physical dress is also a valid
kernel
virtual dress and then it basically
moves whatever part of that page
physical page that needs to be copied
that actually copies it
and so if a data structure for example
spans you know to
a page boundary like for example this is
infostruct that you used in lab2 maybe
it spans
a page table boundary it will copy like
maybe
you know some bytes from the first
physical page and then some bytes from
a second physical page does that make
sense
so that's what the current copying does
and the goal was basically to get into a
new copy in
where the kernel program doesn't really
have to worry about
uh the physical layout basically off
the user address space uh and then in
this new copy and you know we see we
basically do nothing literally nothing
else then just
copy uh the from the user addresses
straight into the kernel uh and we don't
really have to call walk anymore
uh because we can rely on the we set up
the page tables correctly you know the
page table hardware will do the walk for
us
right and so that was the the goal
um and so it makes life for kernel
programmers a little bit easier
are there any other advantages to this
approach
is it also more performant because the
hardware is going to do
the walking and not software yeah well
one way to
i think there are performance
implications for sure uh one way to
think about this is that
in copying correct if the kernel data
structure
or the data data that we copied from
user space to
uh kernel space is big uh we have to do
that you know page at a time
right in every page we have to call this
function walk adder and then then does
the internal walking
and so this might actually be reasonable
expenses
expensive what examples are there
examples of where
the kernel copies a lot of data from
user space
which system call might copy a ton of
data from user space
right yeah right right you write you can
give an arbitrary
number an arbitrary buffer
of an arbitrary size and you know the
kernel wall may have to copy this you
know into
for example the file system or into a
pipe
uh and that could be you know reasonably
expensive
the other thing what is another
advantage i think if the user
uh we didn't explore that in this
assignment you know we assume we could
have
uh what is another advantage
so if you think about you know some of
these this code here correct when it you
know takes a structure out of user space
it copies the whole structure into
kernel space
if user space is mapped into the kernel
page table do we have to do that
for example if we have to update one
field of the structure
so with if the data structure is just
mapped into the kernel address case
right then we can just like
read and write you know with story
instructions to that particular data
structure and we can just update one
field
unlike what the kernel now does
basically it copies the structure from
kernel space to user space and then
maybe back out using copy
out right so if we map the user space
into
the user program into the kernel address
space we can just manipulate it much
more
freely than uh the way we do it now
does that make sense in terms of
motivation why many kernels actually
have this particular structure where
they map the
bottom part of the user uh or where to
map the user programming to the bottom
part of the kernel address space
okay
okay so so let's see little look at my
code
and so you understand what actually uh
i did so there's basically one function
that is the key correct
uh you know assuming we're building
somewhere a valid
user page table and then we just have to
map uh
the entries from the user page table
into the kernel page table
uh or the processes kernel page table so
a function kvnet map user that exactly
does this
and it's pretty boring um but the main
couple interesting points to point out
uh and work you know uh it has the same
sort of
uh interfaces uh
uh uv analog or whatever or basically if
you know you go from the old size
up to the new size page at a time
you find the uh
upte you know the pointer
to the pte for that particular virtual
address in the user page table
right so if we look at the uh
if we look at the picture that we had a
little while back you know look at the
this picture basically what this is
going to return correct is
we're going to walk the user page table
and we'll find for example the
pte that maps you know that particular
virtual address and we get a basically
pointer to that entry into the page
table
um so that's what block does
and so if the uh thing is mapped if it's
not zero that must mean you know it is
there so this is just a
check to double check that actually the
mapping is there
um we check this valid just like there's
debugging
help in some sense you know it should be
the case that it is valid
uh and then i do the same thing in the
kernel page table i look up that virtual
address also in the
processors kernel page table but i call
this time
block with one so it actually allocates
intermediate pages if necessary
uh then once i got the pointer to the
kernel pt
i just copied the user pt into the
uh so probably a lot of you called map
pages
uh but i just copied directly the pte
into the kernel ptd
and of course you know i got to disable
some bits which we'll talk about in a
second
uh but um the essence of it is i just
want to copy the kernel page
the pte entries and so that means that
for example the physical memory for the
user program is just shared
between the kernel space and user space
okay does that make sense
okay so then in terms of switching up
some bits uh i'm
a little bit uh more than necessary but
i switch off the execute bit
i switch up the right bit this copy in
only
needs to read uh never writes to it or
copy out does that
and then uh you have to switch up the
ubit
and that is a sort of risk 5 specific
thing
that if you're running in kernel mode uh
and
the u-bit is set in the ptv entry the
kernel can actually not
access that particular page
in fact you can this is almost a choice
you can also actually program the risk 5
hardware but basically in kernel mode
it ignores the u-bit
and but xv6 doesn't do that
and so you have to switch up the u-bit
any questions about the ubit because the
required number of you are asked about
it
so is this done just to make sure that
the kernel doesn't do anything bad to
user
memory yeah so why is this the case
right is this you know
so the question is like is this for
debugging reasons or is there sort of an
isolation reason to do so
and uh i think this is mostly for
debugging reasons
uh because the kernel is in full control
anyway right the kernel can
change to the satp register it will it
can disable paging as it wants to
uh so it's not like you know the user
space is protected
from the kernel i think it's mostly to
basically uh help kernel developers so
for example in xv6 case correct
unmodified xv6 should never dereference
your user page period
uh and uh and and so that you know
and basically this just just helps you
know if you
happen to do that by accident anyway you
know you would get immediately a page
fault and uh
you know or kernel panic and it will
help the kernel debugger
or developer to debug the the kernel
does that make sense
yeah thank you i have a follow-up
question to that
uh i think the part about the user bit
makes sense
but what about the write and execute
bits
yeah uh so does the execute did have to
be on
what does the kernel do at this page
it only reads from it right the only
thing the only instruction that
basically
grabs data from this page is this
manmove instruction and copy in
so it only you know does execute load
instructions from it or
load values you know from that
particular page
and the page should only contain data so
there's no reason
that the kernel should be right into
that page and so just to be conservative
i disable the right bit and there should
be should never execute instructions
from that page
so i disable the execute bit too again
this is mostly
i think for debugging reasons uh not you
know for isolation reasons
okay make sense thanks
um
okay uh so now the only thing we need to
do is basically there's a bunch of
places where
this code is being where this function
is being called and we need to
look at these uh places where it's uh
called to understand what's going on
uh or how it should be used and i think
maybe the one of the interesting ones
that
a number of you asked about is fork
and exactly we'll talk about both of
them
the first fork
uh so here is uh the call to fork
or to call 2k kvm map user in fork
uh and it takes the end so the main
main interesting question i think a lot
of you asked is
why does it have to be the new process
kernel page table
why does it have to copy from the new
process
page table instead of from maybe the
current process page table because it's
anyway an identical right going forward
but basically does it just replicates
the
user part of the page table and so why
can't we use the
current uh page table for doing that
and why and actually turns out the case
you actually have to use the
new you know the child's user
participation
the child's user page table and why is
that the case
move you notice what what bug do you get
wouldn't you get a remap error you could
um
maybe not remap error uh well the thing
maybe not too but again the bug i'm
thinking of is not the remap one
remember if you tried it out what was
your personal experience
anybody on the call who tried this out
and remember about the resulting
experiences
i think the resulting i i i did not have
this but like
i think the resulting experience is that
somewhere in user test
uh particularly usage has to do a lot of
forking and exiting
you're going to get a problem and you
get a
an error and the area
the thing that goes wrong is that
if you copy from the parent process if
the parent process
exits before the child processes us then
the parent process page table will be
completely
cleaned up right as we saw before and
but then the child still has
pointers to the parent process
uh page table and so
basically you're gonna be basically
pages in this child's process
page table have been treated and they're
still in use and so that results in all
kinds of bad behavior because
the kernel one that frees a page
actually writes ones in it
everywhere for debugging reasons and so
now basically you have
invalid you know ptes sitting in your
kernel page table
does that make sense
okay one more thing to
look at is exact.c uh in my solutions
uh are pretty straightforward always
made no modifications to exec
uh the only medication await is of
course you know the first thing for
you know part one and then here for part
three it's just basically
mapping the new user page table
into the kernel page table and exit
basically what it does is
basically builds a new user address
space
and you know this one line copies that
new user address space into the kernel
page table
and that's it
any questions
so i hope in the meantime uh i've
answered many of the questions that
you uh submitted
we can look and see which ones uh there
were a couple more questions that i
haven't talked about yet
so maybe we can look at those or unless
you have questions right away
um don't we modify
the grow proc as well yes yeah the
couple more changes that necessary
uh uh you know in s-break
or group rock there's a
i added a line right here a very similar
style
and there's presumably a similar change
in
i think that might be it actually or
usually in it of course probably has a
change
because you have to map that one page
from the init code into
the your the kernel page table for you
that process
because the first process is special
okay so uh i'm going to walk through
some of the questions here that i put
them on the
screen so you can hopefully see them so
that i don't have to feel
uh read them out completely i think the
first question is a question that
actually came up quite a bit
about the pteu bit uh flag uh i think
we've
covered this we also cover the fact that
it's not malicious but it's mostly for
debugging reasons
uh similar question about like
well if you're in supervisor mode can
you do anything uh because you can
switch the
satp you can uh and the answer is yes
it's all possible so really you know
this ubis
is not about the user program being
protected from the kernel it really
has a flag to help the kernel developer
and build the kernel
uh one other specific sort of risk five
question
which is why are the entrepreneuring
property dates why in the register sort
of in a
uh in a strange order uh and
the reason that is uh i think we
mentioned this a little while ago in the
previous lecture that
uh there's basically there's something
what's called the risk five compressed
instruction set and that has a set of
fewer registers
and uh something you have to have a more
compact encoding of the instructions
uh and uh this strange ordering reflects
the fact that they're basically two
there's the compressed version which is
some set of registers and then sort of
the uncompressed version which is what
we're using
that has the complete set of registers
and the compression
version the example has s1 and s0
as 0 and s1 but not s2 from s11
so that's the main reason uh
[Music]
i think it went through most of these
questions but if you see a question that
i should have covered and i didn't
please interrupt me where if you ask a
question that i haven't covered yet
please ask these questions are basically
in order that you submitted them so
these were
okay here may be uh so here's our
question through operating systems
usually article called page tables have
to set up the page table pages so that
the lower parts of the hierarchy are at
least partly shared
and uh you know you're clearly starting
my solution correct i share
the entries 1 to 5 11. and so this is a
standard trick
and lots of operating systems do that
i think we talked a little bit about
this particular issue that's important
that you switch
you know to this main kernel page table
because the scheduler
uh there might be no user processors to
run at all anymore
and the schedule of course still needs a
page table and so it runs with the main
kernel page table
we have a question in the chat yeah go
ahead what is that when you
pull up the chat
i can read it yeah yeah i got it so i
think you know uh okay so the question
is doesn't the risk uh privilege specs
say that part of the separation is to
prevent bugs that allow the user program
to make the kernel jump to arbitrary
coding user space
uh yes uh that's a good point uh
uh and so you know you can debate here
whether this is an isolation property or
a kernel debugging property
clearly the kernel should never jump
into any uh part of the address
in the user address space uh directly uh
and so uh you know i view this as a
tool to help the kernel debugger catch
those kinds of bugs
and in some reason that's why in xv6 we
also uh
disable or you know set the view bit and
don't allow the kernel to refer to any
pages
that protects you know us you know if we
did reference every
user address that the kernel would
actually default
um
i think i've covered the scheduler point
uh
two uh
uh so here's a question how are pipes
implemented in xv6 and shoot the changes
to page table implemented in the phablet
effective implementation
um so pegs are basically a buffering
memory in the kernel
and uh right when you write to your pipe
basically calls copy in
and copy in or copies the bytes you know
from user space into the pipe
and in some ways you know the whole part
of this pageant blob which they
basically
streamline that code so that you don't
have to do
many walks when you actually write from
user space into the
pipe
uh this is an interesting question i
think a lot of people ask you like why
does uvm three and free walker
originally panic at the leaf
uh and the reason is that you know the
we put that panic in there because it
broke uh that was an indication that the
variant in xv6 would be broken and
that's an invariant for unmodified xc6
in this particular case uh that is not
true
and so you had to basically get rid of
the panic and realize that it was not
important to panic there you should not
get it there
i think we talked quite a bit about like
why vm copy news
you know why the new vm company is a
good one uh
uh okay here's another question
um let's say and this is maybe an
interesting uh
one question i was asked if sort of more
design question uh and
it helps have a picture we look at the
kernel address space
or we eliminate let's see if i can find
my pen
we limited user address user programs
can be bigger we said basically user
programs can grow to the clean address
no further
let's say we actually wanted to grow
like all the way to here
how could we do that and what what how
should we change the design
that would allow that
anybody
uh could we remap the the stuff
uh like clint and plic and you are
yeah where would you mark up so where if
you wanted to
free up basically that part of the
address space what could you do
map it to like a custom thing before
current base and after
like before physical stop and after
current base
yeah or uh it may be actually better to
after fish stock
here's a huge amount of free space like
address space is unused like this from
here to there is basically used for
physical memory
and we basically could set up mappings
here right for example we could put the
uart
here like you are zero we could put
just above this page and basically set
up a mapping that
maps to that particular physical address
right and then that will free up this
mapping and we could use it for user
space and so similarly we could do that
for ui zero or converge io disk you know
for click and click
and real kernels do that
does that make sense
is it isn't that problematic though
because we would
we want the same same mapping as the
original
uh kernel page table has
uh well we have to do it in every every
kernel page table correct if we had
copies we have to map it
everywhere at that particular location
i'm not sure that is a i'm not sure that
answers your question but
i don't think that's a problem i see so
you you do that mapping
also in the original yeah yeah we would
have to do it also in the original one
and that's easier like if the whole
kernel uniformly thinks about
you are zero sitting on the top
you know a number of people ask this
like why do we map the kernel stacks
high up
what is the reason for that like so we
can proc in it correct we
uh map these uh kernel stacks high up
and if you did the copy approach you
know you actually have to modify cop
proc in it to actually copy over that
mapping
and why setting it up high in the
virtual address space
anybody
is it specifically because the uh the
stacks in risk five grow
downwards and so you place it high in
the address space so that it has space
to grow downwards
how much is it the right direction how
much phase does it have to grow
downwards
that shouldn't matter because it's just
one page right yeah it's only one page
so what happens if you go beyond
one page
you run into the cart page correct
and the guard page is not mapped and so
the kernel will panic
which is better than actually writing
over its data structures
and so the reason it's high up is uh
because we put a guard page below it
is there actually any physical memory
associated with that guard page
no no there's no physical memory
associated with the guard page right so
that's one of the cool things about
putting it high
is that we can put a guard page below it
that actually doesn't consume any
physical memory
okay does that make sense
oh so basically the cornell stuff page
will be
physical somewhere but the card page
won't exactly
again one of the cool things you can do
with virtual member
is it possible to overshoot the guard
page yeah
that's a great question you know what
one for example if you know you
allocated the guard uh
a buffer on the stack that actually uh
is you know way bigger than the guard
page correct and sort of
goes into the next kernel stack page
uh and yeah you would have a serious bug
uh most likely you will run into that
anyway
right because you presumably would use
the first entries of that buffer
and then you would get the page fault
but you could get unlocking so this this
is not a
bulletproof kernel debugging technique
but it has proven to be
extremely effective
great question
any more questions we'll go back to the
list
you see we have a couple more minutes
and then actually one more minute
um i have a question so once we have
our kernel page tables for the processes
does that mean that in the um
trap code we don't need to
switch page tables i think that's a
great question it's a good design
question uh and the answer is yes
you don't need it right because uh
the main reason that the kernel or in
the trampoline code we go for all this
trouble is because we have to copy the
user
uh we have to switch from the kernel
page table to the user page table in the
user page table
or a page table doesn't have the rest of
the kernel mapped
uh and so uh the downside
wait i'm not sure if that's true because
the cornell needs to have the user black
uh user flag on set yeah yeah okay so
there's a couple of points i wanted to
make
so in principle uh you could simplify
the
uh trend let me put it this way you can
simplify entry and exit
uh if you have a single page table that
maps the user and the kernel
in a single page table because then you
don't have to switch you will have to
make a couple more modifications to xp6
to make that happen
uh but in principle you could and in
fact linux
until very recently used you know this
sort of
strategy of where the kernel and
the user code are sitting in a single
page table
uh and relying on basically the ubit you
know to make sure that the
uh the user program couldn't actually
modify any kernel pages
and the entry exit code in that case is
slightly simpler
because you don't have to switch page
tables when you enter or release the
kernel
uh one thing that happened with for
example the meltdown attack
if you might have heard it off
this side channel attack uh in response
to the actually side channel attack
uh linux switch or has an other mode of
running there are two modes of running
one is called the kpti mode
and in that mode basically that reflects
basically what xv6 does
you know having a separate page table
for the kernel and a separate
page table for user space
right so i still don't understand why
does that work so let's say the
user process and the kernel uh use the
same page table
if the user memory has to have the user
bit set
the cornell will not be able to access
that user memory right
ah okay the uh on
so there's a this is uh okay on intel
processors that is not the rule
so for example in intel processors if
your bid is set the kernel can still
write and read that page
oh that's just a risk five thing ah and
even on the risk five you can change it
uh there's a bit in the s status
register that you can set
the take to some bit and if you set it
then basically
in kernel mode the view bit is ignored
okay so you're telling me that there's
just one bit in this
cmu processor that made me stay up four
hours later yes
i'm very sorry about that i should have
realized no no no it's okay it was it
was a fun realization
when you reported it uh it reminded me
of a bug that i actually have during the
summer and it was exactly that book
but i forgot about it
so my apologies for that no no it's okay
it was
it was fun figuring it out for sure but
i i at some point i was just like okay
like either i'm crazy or something's
completely wrong so i'm just going to go
to sleep and submit this piazza post and
hopefully when i wake up someone will
answer and
fortunately that was the case so i was
able to just continue right off when i
when i did okay so i think we
ran over time a little bit uh and
hopefully uh this was helpful
and reaffirms you know things with
virtual memory
i think it was important to do because
we're gonna get three more labs
involving virtual memory and my hope is
that after this one
you know those are going to be easier
than uh this experience
can i ask something very quick yeah so
i'm staying on so everybody wants to
stay on and ask more questions
please feel free to do so if you need to
go to the next class please go
so basically uh in all the labs like
there's a lot of mention of like oh
we this might be useful in future labs
but we never actually use any of the
code that we
write like what's what's the plan on
that like should we just import our code
from a previous lab or
like i don't want to because what if
it's buggy i don't want to you know
impact the next lab
yeah so the one reason we don't do it
you know why the build labs don't build
on each other even though they could
uh is to avoid basically dependencies
like if you had a bug in an earlier lab
that you know was not exposed by user
tests
or any of our tests and but would be
exposed to that new lab then you know be
painful
um the reason i'm mentioning that is
that basically
the real thing what's going on is we're
going to do more stuff with page tables
so for example this lab looks at
simplifying copy in uh
later labs gonna look at exchange to
s-break
they're basically orthogonal to the
changes you made to the kernel
for this lab but you know the fact that
you've been thinking about kernel page
table user pages tables so much
will help you plus really what helps you
is of the experience debugging these
kinds of problems
due to incorrect page tables
okay i just wanted to make sure that
it's not like i'm missing out because i
didn't copy over my x arch code from lab
one
or something it decided on purpose that
the labs are not dependent on each other
okay thanks i'll see you on wednesday
i had a follow-up on my question about
mapping mapping uh using the
modification from the page table app um
would it be then
needed to have the trampoline
mapped in the user page tables
uh okay so i haven't really fought this
through uh
so if you the kernels let's say the
kernel exit so let's say we have a joint
one single page table that's the one
year shown correct and we're jumping out
of the kernel
uh through useret uh and our goal is to
uh we're still running in kernel mode so
this page certainly accessible correct
in the by the kernel the guard page
i'll show you not the card page what i'm
saying the trampoline page is there
and presumably uh somewhere
we need to map maybe
the
uh well the user trap train we don't
really
uh we have access to anyway right
because we're running kernel mode we
know where it sits in the proc structure
or
we can get it so i think we can just
exit
and when we return uh
then the user code can just run you know
we of course the ubit is a bit of a
well the ubit is only set on pages that
actually sit in the user space so that's
fine too
so when we enter the color back in you
know we're still with this page table
that page table already has
all the kernel now mapped and we could
just you know copy
you know the registers that we need to
save into the proc structure directly
instead of having to go through the uh
have a separate page with the proc
struct in it so i believe the change
would be
pretty straightforward okay
i see thank you but of course
i could be wrong oh yeah i'm
i'm now gonna try it now to