Alright.
Good morning or good afternoon everyone,
I'm like to get started, can people hear me.
Yep.
Thank you,
alright today, what I'd like to do is
give you a chance to ask questions about xv6
and about the recent labs,
in order to give us something to talk about,
I'm going to do as much as I can of the copy-on-write fork lab here,
just to give us something to chew on
and you should feel free to ask any questions you like,
you can ask about why my solution is different from your solution
or why xv6 works the way it does
or why the bugs that we encounter show up in the way they do.
So just to remind you,
although I'm sure this is I'm sure I don't need to remind you,
the point of copy-on-write fork is
to avoid copying costs for pages and fork that are never modified,
I put in a few lines of code
to measure the reduction in the number of bytes
that mem copy had to copy during usertests for my copy-on-write solution
and found that actually reduce the amount of copying by 90%.
And this is for usertests which is kind of a weird program but nevertheless,
and I think a lot of it is reductions in's copy of the instruction pages,
because the instruction pages for are never modified,
so there's never any point in having copies of them
and I think that's where a lot of the [win] was from.
And copy-on-write fork also reduces RAM use,
the sort of maximum amount of RAM you ever need to use
and it reduces the amount of time you spend in fork,
and so fork returns more quickly,
you know on the other hand, of course the total cost may be larger,
because if programs end up modifying all the copy-on-write pages,
you end up having to do all the copies plus take all the page faults,
which can be a little bit expensive,
but nevertheless people found that in general it's a net benefit.
And as you know the main challenges are,
one challenge is how to avoid freeing memory
and now we're sharing pages among processes,
have not de-allocate them, have not free them, until the last process is finished using them,
so anymore, bookkeeping and the other interesting challenges
that there's a in copyout in particular the xv6,
modifies user memory without actually going to the MMU paging hardware.
And we have to mimic page faults here.
I'm gonna go to the lab,
starting at the beginning the copy-on-write lab ,
before I start I just wanna,
just mentioned the strategy that I think of myself as following when I do labs
and I do a lot of labs from one year to the next,
I don't remember the details of how to do the labs.
And in addition labs change.
Alright, so, when I'm doing the labs,
I always take small steps,
I may find you know some sort of next subset of the problem to solve,
maybe five or ten lines of code,
I programmed up and run it and try to get to working,
before I go on to the next, proceeding to the next step
and this is you know as opposed to for example thinking through and writing a complete solution,
before starting to test and debug,
it always test and debug a little bit at a time,
a lot of the reason for that is that ,
even though you may , you may have sort of thought through a lot of things,
a lot of the challenges,
and a lot of the design,
for what you're going to have to do to solve the lab,
I find at least there's often surprises.
And so if I implement everything first,
I may find then that I've wasted a lot of time,
because I didn't fully understand the problem,
until I actually got into debugging it.
And the way I choose the next step at each point is
usually driven by whatever panic or crash a test failure,
I see next sort of tells me what I need to fix next.
Well I'm doing this lab,
I'll make a few mistakes,
that I actually made the last time I did the lab,
so that we can do a have a little practice debugging together.
Again, feel free to break in at any time and ask questions about anything.
I'm starting here with fresh copy of the copy-on-write lab,
source the same as all of you did.
So, I'll just fire this up.
And, run the copy-on-write tests
and you know maybe I'll get lucky
and all the tests will pass and don't have to do anything,
Too bad on the test failed,
okay, so not too surprising .
And you know a good step at this point is to go have a look at the tests
and figure out what it's trying to do,
and the sad truth is some of the tests are complicated and hard to understand
and don't necessarily test anything specific,
they just sort of try different things, see if something will break,
but luckily with this simple test, it's pretty clear what its doing.
A question.
Yeah.
You need to show your screen, we cannot see anything.
Oh gosh.
I'm sorry about that,
thank you for thank you for letting me know.
How is that better.
Yes. Brilliant, alright.
Okay, well, that's bug number one.
Okay, so I'll just,
here I am, in my copy-on-write test,
I ran copy-on-write test, and it fails.
Look at the test, this simpletest on the screen right is actually failed,
and this test we're lucky enough it actually tells us what it's doing
and allocates what it knows to be more than half the available memory in xv6 and then forks
and of course, the reason this fails is that fork makes a copy,
then ordinary xv6 actually literally makes a copy
and so if we have to copy more than half of memory,
there's just not enough space for that.
Okay, so, of course, this is what copy-on-write all about,
and we know that the basic game is that instead of copying the process's memory,
we want to just copy its page table and not the memory,
the child just has a [carbon] copy of the parent's page table instead of memory,
referring to all the same physical pages.
The place where, fork does it's copying is in vm.c and uvmcopy.
And so we can just modify this code,
to instead of allocating a page memory,
here, and copying onto it,
we're going to eliminate those three lines.
And instead,
I just copied page table entries,
so um,
actually just gonna hack, this, um,
copy of mappages,
since we didn't actually allocate memory here,
going to get rid of this free,
I'm going to fix this mappages, to instead of mapping mem at address i,
I'm going to map the pa, which is the physical address, we pulled out of the parents' page table.
So is that clear?
And so this will just have the effect of
mapping all of the parents pages into the child's address space.
Isn't pa already uint64?
Probably.
Or is it is it bad, if you were to cast its already that type?
The cast does absolutely nothing other than [shut] the compiler up,
since it's already, since addresses or 64 bits
and you want sixty four, sixty four bit,
that cast doesn't change the bits.
It just makes the type checker less upset,
but [] you actually don't know whether any of these types are.
However, one thing is we don't need this mem variable.
Okay, so you write about pa,
gosh, I wonder if we're done now.
Let's run the cowtest and see what happens,
definitely not done.
Okay, so, we got here is, this user trap, with scause of two.
Anybody remember what scause two is?
I'll just tell you.
Structure failure.
It's an illegal instruction,
so why would we getting an illegal instruction now.
Is this what we expected.
Did we overwrite them like portion where we have instructions.
Yes, something is damaging the instructions of the user program.
And of course the fault, we're not surprised we get a fault here.
But we're hoping for write, for stored faults
to drive the copying process and copy-on-write.
We're not getting the store fault.
Any other hypotheses for this? It's not really fair, because like this, my bug not your bug, but nevertheless.
Does it have to do the flags.
Yes, it does.
Okay, so I'll just leave that to the side,
they'll actually come up again ,
another question is we're hoping for store page faults,
which will drive the copying process.
Why didn't we get a store page fault.
Alright, um.
Why would we get a store page fault.
Under what circumstances does the RISC-V generate store page fault.
We would get if the write flag is not set,
but now we can just write to everything normally.
Yeah, left the write flag set,
alright, so that's bug one which I did actually make last time I did this lab,
so I've left the write flag set in the parent,
I've done I haven't done anything to the write flags,
this flags variable here is ,
it's just the way we pulled out of the parents' page table,
it's all its pages are writable
and so that means that it's going to be writable on the child too,
we won't get store page faults,
so just sharing a page read, write, which is not what we wanted,
so how am I going to turn off the,
how am I gonna write protect these pages.
Any proposals, what should I type.
How about.
You can do flags and equals the wave sign underscore w,
yeah yeah we're gonna need a tilde there,
I call that wave sign tilde,
the we need to the waves,
the it's clear we need to clear this bit on the flags
were going to leave all the other flags set.
Okay so that's gonna with this clear the flag and the parent of the child.
Child?
Just child.
So how do I clear do I also need to clear the flag in the parent.
Yes, because we want the child to be independent for the parents,
if we write something we don't want the child to also get them modification from their parents.
That's absolutely right, we need to write protect the page at the parent as well,
because we don't want the child to see the parents modifications,
were trying to mimic, having completely separate copies.
So what can I do to clear the flag in the parents' page table.
You can do something like star pte and equals not pte, right.
Yeah, so I have the parents p-, a pointer to the parents' page table entry right here in pte
and so I can clear the PTE flag here too,
so that's pretty convenient.
And my belief is that enough to make both copies of the page,
are both mappings of the page read only.
So hopefully now we'll start getting write faults.
Is it possible to do to clear the PTE_W bit before you say flags equals pte flags of pte,
and that way like the original flag is just the correct thing.
Oh I see you put away up here.
Yeah.
Yeah, I'll get that shot,
seems to work, that makes sense.
Okay, so now I get my write fault.
Which is what we're hoping for
and hopefully what this write fault means is that one of the other processes tried to modify the page
and the RISC-V generated a page fault from that.
And, we're gonna want to [react] to that by making a copy of the page
and mapping it read write.
Before we do that just to make sure that what we're seeing,
you know this, this, this f here, this scause,
that is sort of making me imagine that we're seeing what we want to see namely a store fault,
let's actually go look and see where that happened.
We know it's process id three,
process id one is init,
process id two is the shell
and so maybe process id three is going to be cowtest.
We can look in, we can look in cowtest.asm.
And look for 9da and see if it makes sense,
as a instruction that could generate a store page fault.
Oops, don't look so good.
I can't remember what auipc does,
but I don't believe it performs a store.
Any guesses what's going on?
It'd be nice, if the page fault who are seeing actually made sense.
I'll tell you, it turns out this page fault occurred in the shell after the shell fork,
but before it exec cowtest
and so we're really looking at the wrong asm file,
turns out the right asm file is shell.asm file,
we'll look for 9da there.
Yes, and in the shell 9da, is a store instruction
and it's at the beginning of this parsecmd function,
that actually parses the cowtest command that we typed
and figures out what to do with it, namely called exec,
as doing a store into the stack,
it's the preamble that stores the callee saved registers.
And not surprisingly that this should be the first page fault we get,
because it's on the stack,
you know the very first thing those functions do after fork
returns is they modify their variables in the stack
and boom, unsurprisingly that causes a store page fault.
Any questions about why we're faulting.
I have a quick question,
how did you figure out it was in the shell rather than in cowtest?
Because I looked at 9da in cowtest and that is not a store instruction.
I thought gosh what could possibly be going on.
Now, look at process id.
Three, so is pid three to shell or is it.
Pid three is, p two is the shell that printed that prompt,
pid three is the next process that's created
and so initially the shell forks to make pid three.
But after the fork, it's still running the shell,
it's a child of the shell running a copy of the shell,
it's going to call exec to run cowtest,
but it hasn't done it yet,
it hasn't been able to get that far without taking a store page fault,
when it writes to stack.
So, can you clarify, does that mean that there's an error with the shell related process id two,
because it doesn't have the proper data in order for the child to have the right data
or is it a error with process id three.
It's a page fault, that occurs in process id three. Right, but the bug that we're seeing right here like.
This is implementing copy-on-write fork
and what we just did in vm.c was write protect every single page in the parent and the child, right.
That's what this line is doing,
so the next time either the parent or the child has a store from user code,
it's going to be a store into a write protected page,
because every page is write protected,
and so it will cause a page fault.
Oh, so this is the proper page fault that we want.
This, right and I was just all I was doing was checking that,
that what's going on is exactly what we think is going on,
as opposed to some other bug.
Okay alright.
So we took a page fault here in this store
which is presumably the first store the shell does after the fork.
Okay, so now we have to handle these ,
now you want to do something useful in this page fault.
So, where's the page fault handlers in trap.c and user fault.
I think it pretty much doesn't matter where we insert code to .
I mean, there's all these different cases here that uservec,
this uservec or usertrap,
the usertrap is dealing with just going to throw in another else,
we only interested in write faults, we're happy to read these shared pages,
because all that is there, it's just write to on catch,
so.
Now, it turns out as, I'm sure you know, that we're going to need to use the code,
I'm about to write from two different places.
I'm going to just wrap it up in the code,
that makes the copy of this page in a function, I'm gonna call cowfault.
It needs to know the current page table
and it needs to know the virtual address that we faulted on stval.
Sometimes it can fail because say it runs out of memory,
maybe chaos [chaotic] will fail, so we need to prepare for return value
and pretty much no matter what the failure is,
we're gonna kill this process, right,
if we didn't kill it, we'll have cowfault return minus one, if there's a failure,
returns zero if there's no failure,
there's no failure then we're going to rely on cowfault having made this virtual address writable,
so that when usertrap returns, the process can actually continue successfully.
What's that you put, like is there a reason why you put this line above the else if which dev- devintr.
I don't think so ,
whether it's correct depends on what devintr does,
just take a look, the risk is that devintr might, see a device interrupt for some reason,
even though we are on a page fault,
so we just gotta check that devintr .
Looks at scause, and scause f, it's going to return zero.
So, just want to make sure that if.
Yeah, if devintr returns zero then, it's gonna go on to our code, that's fine.
Okay.
Okay, now we only need to write.
Actually this one thing I want to observe here
and that's that if there's a failure, we kill the process.
So, this is unfortunate,
it would be fantastic,
if instead you know most of the time processes allocate memory or whatever by calling system calls,
the system calls can return some error value negative one or something,
if there's a failure and the process can then do something appropriate,
if it knows how in order to deal with that failure,
here though because there's no system call,
there's not any obvious way to tell the process that something went wrong,
which is [irritating],
you can imagine solutions to this,
for example in some more sophisticated operating system,
we could have something like the alarm user fault handler that you implemented,
that we could call up into to say look you know we can't continue your process,
because we can't fix this page fault,
but we want to tell you something went wrong.
But we're not gonna do that now,
it's much simpler to just kill the process.
Okay, so we have to implement page,
this cowfault program takes a, on a page table
to current this page table, this argument, the virtual address that the fault occurred on.
Okay, so the first question we always have to worry about,
when dealing with virtual addresses that the user program produced,
like this one is what if it's a completely crazy address,
like way up above the top of the processor,
what if it's an address like in the trapframe or in the trampoline page,
in the page, the stack guard page.
So can anybody sort of outline a strategy
for defending ourselves against the user process intentionally faulting on crazy addresses.
Isn't there like a max virtual address. Yes, yes there is and that will actually come up,
but the top of the user address spaces below MAXVA,
and the like the stack guard page, which we shouldn't be allowing,
you certainly shouldn't be treating as a copy-on-write thing.
Alright, I will, I'll show a solution here.
We're just gonna call walk for now.
And one thing that can go wrong is walk doesn't find a page table entry,
so for most illegal pages that a process might refer to,
theres no pte, and there's only a few exceptions to that,
so if we detect the illegal, if we detect detect the pte not found return value from walk and return minus one ,
we've handled almost every case,
the only cases, I'm aware of where walk would return a page table entry,
but we don't want to allow writes to it
are for the trampoline trapframe and stack guard pages,
and those all have PTE_U clear.
So the way I'm going to detect crazy addresses illegal addresses is
by checking that PTE_U is set,
and also, just checks look at PTE_V.
And if either of those is clear,
then we know this is like, not an okay address.
And just return minus one, so killed process,
so I believe taking care of all the, illegal addresses,
the user process could use, try to use.
Alright, how can we find out,
we want to do a copy, now we want to make this process copy of the page,
how do we find the page to copy from.
A I have a question here.
Please.
Wouldn't the strategy of using the PTE_U to judge if the pages,
if they're if it's a legit page for copy-on-write,
wouldn't this strategy not be very good for the long-term process,
maybe you add some other part to the address space,
which is which is supposed to be a writable,
which are only supposed to be readable,
but that doesn't get taken care of here,
as in you'll have to come back here again.
You're absolutely right,
if we are to add any other interesting paging feature like maybe lazy page allocation,
for example we have to revisit these decisions
and come up with some other strategy for deciding
is this a copy-on-write page,
is this a lazy allocation page,
is this a paged out to disk pages, to say memory map file.
And we need more sophisticated,
yeah we're.
In the end I think, and most serious operating systems actually keep their own data structure,
nothing to do with, you not a page table,
but sort of mimicking a page table,
that describes the processes address space and sort of describes what each page means
and what its state is
and we have to consult that table.
But for this lab since we don't have those other features
and we're not sure what they would be ,
I'm just gonna do something straightforward
and indeed we would have to come back and fix it,
if we made xv6 more sophisticated.
And wouldn't that panic if va is more than MAXVA, because of the walk.
[] me you would.
Now, look at that, yeah, maybe it's the process.
Yeah, I think you're right.
That's too bad.
Okay, so we're certainly, you're right,
alright, well I was wrong about this.
Wait, can you just return a negative one if you just check the MAXVA.
I think the observation is that if the user tries to intentionally program tries to write to very large address.
Of course, you can't expect to survive that ,
but what we would do here is called walk with a very large address
and looking at here, the implementation of walk in the, and it's going to panic.
Then we can just use the same approaches walk address,
does I had this same bug,
you can just return minus one like other people are saying,
if va is greater than MAXVA before walk.
What I'm upset about is that the tests don't seem to test this.
Because I didn't put this in my solution.
Okay.
Okay, so how do we find that we need,
we want to copy the page,
how do I get a pointer to the page
to the pointer to something I can copy.
The PTE2PA.
Yeah, so, it's just in the pte,
where am I gonna copy to.
What should I copy to.
A nearly allocated page.
Yeah, so I just called kalloc,
of course kalloc is likely to fail, so I'm gonna catch that,
we're actually gonna see this.
So I'm gonna put a print statement, so we know.
Okay, we.
Is that pa two, that equal.
Hey, I actually made this error and I wanted to reproduce it,
so that we would have to track it down,
but you're too clever for me .
I want to copy to, pa two from pa one.
Okay, so how can I, what do I need to do
in order to map this page, this new page pa two into the address space.
What should I type.
There's like two broad ways,
there's either an mapping and then mapping with the built-in that exist,
or you could manipulate the bits.
Yeah I am way too lazy to figure out,
how to use them on mmap and map,
so I'm gonna just cook up a new page table entry right here.
I have a question,
so actually I ran into this issue in almost every lab
in which I somehow needed to re-map things
and because it occurred so often, I implemented a map that which could re-map basically,
and I was wondering is that a bad design choices, like dangerous, don't.
No, no, that's totally reasonable,
you know the functions in xv6 are,
are you know specialized to xv6 as it exists,
and so they you know they make assumptions about how the other code works,
they have panics in them that are intended to catch other code using them in unexpected ways,
but if you change the way xv6 works and you need to do different things then,
it's totally reasonable to modify you know you need to be able to re-map this without a panic,
well old xv6 never needs to do that.
If your code does so, you should feel free to modify anything you need to.
Okay, so okay, so the deal is here,
we had a write protected page that was probably shared with another process,
what do we have to do to that other process at this point,
what do we need to do to the other process.
We can just not do anything, and then when it page faults,
we allocate a new page and remove the original one.
That's absolutely right,
so you could imagine doing something but it would be quite complex to do it correctly
and so we just do nothing,
and if the other process never raised this page, well it's not a problem,
if it does write a page, then it will go through all this,
it will make a copy and it'll proceed safely as well,
so doing nothing is totally reasonable.
Okay, so now we're going to return the return value of zero since there was no error
and hopefully the process will.
Maybe we should should free the physical page right, or are we not there yet, or.
We are not.
I guess we're going steps, we shouldn't, yeah.
So if I did this, what would happen well they would definitely crash, right alright.
So let's not do this
or I don't know if we'll crash,
but we would then be if we if we free the page it would be presumably pa1,
because we don't have free pa2,
because we're using pa2,
if we free pa1, that means the other process has got a problem,
it has now mapped into its address space
and presumably using executing instructions in, I don't know what,
a page that we just freed and might be reusing for some other purpose,
writing something else over,
so I'm reluctant to free it, although it's.
Oh yeah, so sadly, among many other things,
xv6 walk is never called from outside of the vm.c, in ordinary xv6,
but now we're doing it.
Alright, where were we.
Okay, remeber the very first page what we got was scause two,
why are we getting scause two page faults.
It's an illegal instruction,
like this is the next problem,
we have to solve this problem now.
What's gone wrong,
or what are what are some plausible guesses for what might have gone wrong.
So the sequence we when I type cowtest,
what we think happens is that the shell forks is copy-on-write fork.
We have a child running the shells instructions,
probably taking store faults, but for handling those store faults correctly
and then the child execs, the child copy the shell execs cowtest.
What bad thing might that do to the parent shell.
Well, when you call exec, the implementation of exec freeze up all the processes current pages,
and then allocates new pages to load the file into your exec.
What's going to happen in the child, the child shell calls exec,
it frees all of its pages,
what's that gonna do to the parent show.
Is it gonna end up.
Essentially, oh sorry.
Is it going to accidentally free the shell's page pages.
Yes, we're gonna free every single one of shell's pages except the one or two that the, that were written.
So this includes the shells instruction pages,
and then we're going to reallocate them,
they're going to be instantly reallocated by exec to hold other stuff,
loaded from the file that we're running cowtest,
so that's going to totally change everything in the show underfoot
and unsurprisingly it's going to instantly crash.
So, we have not free those pages somehow.
They don't see that.
A quick question,
what does the SEPC here point to which assembly file,
would you find that instruction.
Well. You said its shell right.
It's the last time was for some other fault,
somewhere else it would show, what it is here I actually don't know,
I never, I did not unfortunately take the time to track this down.
The o-, so one problem with any answer even if I could give you an answer,
so the answer is either the shell or cowtest ,
for process id three, that again is the it's probably cowtest.
I just say I don't completely know what's going on here,
looking at the asm file is unlikely to be helpful,
because the whole problem that we believe has happened is that,
the page holding instructions was freed and reused,
and so they were therefore not executing the instructions in the [].asm file anymore,
or executing some garbage,
so we could look at address 1004 but it,
it wouldn't really tell us what had happened.
We might we probably could find this out using the debugger,
we could break in gdb
and then look at the instructions,
it's actually a at whatever virtual address 1004 points to.
Quick follow-up question, about that [],
so my understanding is that we're getting an invalid with instruction fault,
because like we're changing the instruction page instruction physical memory underfoot,
and like the memories just being written to something else,
is it possible that, like in some lucky case
that they are being rewritten,
but when we look at it again it's being rewritten to valid instruction pages,
so we actually to start executing like random instructions
and we don't actually get an invalid instruction fault,
we get some other fault.
Yes, absolutely absolutely.
Yeah, yeah I mean really we're now, like anything could happen .
I see.
I would not have been able to guess,
if I had not done this lab,
I Wouldn't be able to guess what will go wrong at this point.
Indeed I think I've seen other strange things happen at this point.
It's maybe the data, may be the first page, that has garbage
and it actually has data in it
and shell trips over some complete garbage data like stack instead of instructions.
Okay, so we don't want to free the page right away,
we we only want to free the page when it's really not being used anymore.
So can anybody propose criterion
for when we should or shouldn't free the page for each page of memory.
We could keep track of like how many times are
like basically whenever in kalloc whenever you,
you should increment and decrement some type variable
and keep an array of like all the different addresses.
Yes, yeah exactly.
So, one way to think about this is
that we want to only free a page when there's zero page tables that refer to it,
but there could be many, if a program forks and forks again forks again,
[] we can now have like three or four different processes,
that all refer to copy-on-write fork to this one page,
so that this, you know this count of how many times how many page tables refer to a page
and go up due to fork
and they can go back down when a process exits or calls exec,
you know it clears all these references out of its page table entry
or if a process actually does a write and causes a write fault,
that's also a situation in which we have one fewer reference,
fewer page tables referring to a page.
So we want to keep a count,
and we want to count by counting the number of page table entries that refer to a page.
So we need to think about how to maintain this count,
and when to increment it exactly where in the code to increment it and decrement it.
Okay so they ,
if there's as you maybe aware,
there's multiple ways to maintain this count,
the way I do it is I make an array called refcount,
just gonna have it for every page a count.
We need to know how many entries are in refcount in xv6,
so simple, that it just has it just uses a fixed amount of memory, physical memory,
we only need to keep a count per page of physical memory,
we know that, from inspecting kinit that,
xv6 uses only PHYSTOP, amount of physical memory,
we only need to keep a count per page, not per byte,
so we're going to divide PHYSTOP by 4096.
That's how many array elements we need.
In a more serious operating system,
we don't know how much memory is available, until we inspect the hardware,
we might have to, we would have to allocate this array dynamically.
Any questions about, where to put the counts.
Alright .
Actually.
Yes.
I'm wondering is there a reason that you're using 4096 specifically
and not the page size macro.
Yeah the reason is that I can remember 4096
and I don't remember the name of the page size macro,
but I'm happy to use it, if you like.
It actually if if xv6 was intended to be portable
and to be able to run on all kinds of different machines with different page sizes,
we have to be much more careful about this,
but there's 500 ways in which xv6 is totally not portable.
So, I don't worry about it.
Page sizes determined in hardware and I guess where.
The hardware, that RISC-V manual says, how big a pages.
Yeah, because the , it's the MMU that takes a virtual address
and uses it to index into the page table.
Oh, right right, because the address translation happens in hardware,
so the hardware has to know how big pages are, OK.
It's configurable, but you know there's a couple different strategies you can tell the hardware to use,
but we tell it to use 4096 byte pages.
Okay.
We're sorry profession, so where are, I guess is a C question,
so in where our global variables like refcount stored,
like what, like are they associated with specific process or.
This is the kernel, what's going on is that the file the executable file,
that the compiler and the loader or linker produces,
has this sort of this, indicates how much data how the total size of all the global variables in the program.
And, so we don't see the code for this,
but when QEMU loads the kernel,
well what's really going on is that when you compile,
the program called the linker figures out based on ,
look at all the global variables and their sizes
and assigns an address in memory, yeah, to each global variable.
And that's where it lives in memory.
I mean, and, we just arrange that the you know,
so xv6 kernel uses you know 10,000 bytes of various global variables,
and wherever the boot process loads it into memory, say at address a million ,
it just uses those addresses for the global variables.
I see, is this is this similar to how,
like there's only one copy of like the instructions for a program on disk
and there's only like one copy of a kind of global variables for that program on this.
Well, a program this,
well, I'm not really sure how to answer this,
I mean the the, when you declare a global variable, like int x,
when you compile the compiler and the linker just decide
based on who knows what or it's configurable,
but they decide the address for that variable,
they decide alright boy x is going to address 1000,
and then the code that reads the write x,
you know if we have code that says refcount of zero equals one,
you know, but that compiled into was just setting the memory at address a thousand
or wherever we linker decided to put refcount
which is does a store to set the memory address 1001.
Yeah, it's not, it's actually almost exactly the same thing that happens when you run an ordinary user program.
You know the linker and compiler decide where memory global variables are.
They just being right there and, and it just works.
I'm sorry, that's not much of an explanation.
Alright, so just a define this global array of counts one per physical page
and we need to modify these counts in various places,
certainly when we first allocate a page,
we're going to say that it has one reference,
because we return the address of the page to whoever called kalloc
and at the moment only that program has a reference to this page,
so I'm just gonna set the refcount for this page to be one.
So first of all I'm just going to calculate the page number,
which is the address of the page divided by 4096, the page number.
And then I'm going to set the reference count for the page,
we just allocated to one.
Any questions about this code.
Just because I know that I'm going to have bugs with reference counting,
I'm actually do a little bit of a sanity check here
and I'm just, the you know the reference count really should be zero,
if the pages we just allocated a page was free,
boy it better have a reference count of zero.
Any questions about this code?
Alright, so in general we want to increment the reference count
when we add, when copy-on-write fork adds a page table entry that points to an existing page
and we want to, actually, we want to decrement the reference count,
as it turns out in many places,
for example when a process exits, we need to decrement the reference count of all its pages,
when you call exec, and that frees all the current memory,
because it's going to replace it,
we want to decrement all those reference counts,
when a copy-on-write page fault happens
and we make a copy we want to decrement reference count on the old page,
it turns out these are all the same places that concurrently free a page,
because the current xv6 think there's only ever one reference to each page ,
so in most of the places we care about where we want to decrement,
there's concurrently a called kfree,
so what I'm gonna do is modify kfree to be have somewhat different semantics
and to have kfree be, sort of a function that decrements the reference count
and free the page only if the reference count has dropped to zero.
I mean, I'll just automatically fix all the places that call kfree.
Alright so, we need to actually do the check, before we fill the page with junk.
So, this makes a little bit more complicated,
because even though there's a critical section with locks and kfree already,
we can't use it, because it happens after the point at which we filled the page with garbage.
So, we need to lock,
because we could be free in the same page at the same time from multiple different cores,
again I'm gonna find the page number by dividing the physical address by 4096.
I want to panic, again, just a sanity check.
Gosh, you know if we're freeing a page, that better have more than zero refcounts.
We need to return if the page has more than one reference count to it.
Actually, let's decrement the reference count,
we want to return after we release locks
and we have to remember a variable,
I'm gonna remember whether the page has more references and then release locks and then return,
so I'm gonna make a temporary variable which has the and release,
then say if there's still references this page,
let's just return and not free it.
And only if the reference count drop to zero, we free it.
Any questions?
Can you explain again, why you have to acquire the kmem lock this process.
Why have to acquire it all.
Yeah when you're doing the page number calculations and.
It's this line, really is this line, the next line of the problem,
the issue is that on this page, we now is likely has more than one reference to it
and so if two processes with a reference to the same with the page table entry point at the same page,
if they both exit at the same time on different cores,
they're both gonna call kfree for the same page at the same time.
Could you just create a new lock for the reference count variable and use that as well.
Yes.
Yeah, basically everybody, you know all code that manipulates these counts need to use the same lock,
but I don't think it matters what lock is.
Okay, so this takes care of decre-, most of the decrement,
we care about every time the page is free,
we're really gonna you know only free if the reference counts [] to zero,
we also need to increment the reference count,
where do we need to increment the reference count.
Well, because I know we're going to need to do it right,
the function that anybody can call .
Again I want to panic if something is weird,
so if the address is wacky, I'm certainly don't want to go beyond the end of the array.
Or if we don't want to increment the reference count of page,
reference counts currently zero, that's also an error,
I'm just putting these in there,
because I know from experience with my code that this is exactly the kind of place, I'm going to have a bug in.
All right, where should I call increment from.
You have uvmcopy when you.
I think uvmcopy is the only place that makes another reference to a page.
Alright gosh, I'm going with this well, it almost doesn't really matter.
We're making another reference to pa,
so I want to say incref pa.
Or, likely to run into trouble from the compiler,
if we don't put a definition for it in traps.h whatever.
Okay,
let's see.
That was pretty quick, that was kfree ref, kfree is unhappy.
Okay, well here's the time we don't know, is very early in the boot process
which is maybe a hint it to what's going wrong.
If anybody has any guesses, I'd be happy to hear them,
meanwhile just fire up the debugger try to get backtrace.
It is during kinit,
because you're trying to put things into the linked list and you haven't allocated yet.
So you in when you trying to load everything into a linked list,
you haven't called kalloc before that.
Yeah that's exactly right,
so, see that in action here, okay I got the panic,
type where and it's in , here's kfree being called and paniced
and it's being called from freerange right at the beginning,
when we're initializing a the free list indeed,
so there's something to be fixed in freerange,
the problem is I'm calling kfree as,
as you said I'm calling kfree but of course, all the reference counts are zero
and kfree panics at the reference count of zero,
so I'll just, I'll just hack this to be.
How about that.
Oh okay, we managed to boot now , by wonderful done,
let's see.
Okay, so let's run the cowtest again.
Um, we pass this simple test,
aha, so we passed the simple test which is great.
And we passed one time through the three test,
but we didn't pa-, we can make it through the second time to the three test
and the three test triggered a the print statement that I added to trap
which said cow kalloc failed, which only would print it if we're out of memory.
So we're out of memory.
Why are we out of memory.
So we've updated reference counts every time we've allocated,
but we haven't called a decrement counts whenever we've tried to hree right.
So where should I add .
Well, with your current approach, I think pa1 that reference count needs to get decrement,
so we would need to kfree it.
Yeah exactly.
So, I think somebody actually possibly brought this up , 45 minutes ago,
let's see, let's free pa1, not p2.
Okay, and so now what kfree means, now is don't is not free this page,
it's what kfree means is decrement the refcount on this page
and free if it's zero
and so forth in a simple situation where there was just one fork
and so there were two references to the page,
and we've taken a right fault to make a copy,
where now all kfree is going to do is decrement the count to be one
and now the other process can use the page,
we're not actually gonna free it.
Okay so hopefully now,
We'll, not run out of memory in the cowtest.
Um, I love it,
okay, we made it through the three test, without running out of memory.
Alright,
we're not done, sadly ,
we have this interesting error in the file test,
so let's take a look at the file test.
Yeah. Alright, so here's the filetest
and it says right in the comments of the test that it's investigating copyout,
so, good hint of where our problem is going to be,
the thing that actually failed is,
I mean you have to use your imagination a little bit,
but, the error message seems to be this one,
printed from two different processes at the same time.
And indeed, this is a loop, this test is a loop,
that for four iterations, just forks
and so it's going to produce four concurrent processes,
this error message will be interleaved ,
so we need to know why that read failed,
if we want to understand what the bug is,
we need to know why the reed failed,
the first step is maybe to figure out what the read actually returned,
all we know is that, it, returned something other than sizeof i,
but we don't know what it returns,
so I'm going to capture the return value,
and I'm going to print the return value, at least know.
Oh, I have a question, sorry,
it seems like three of the threads failed,
but, one of them didn't end, it's like still running,
why is it not failing.
Why did the third [thread] not fail.
The fourth If you, if you do cowtest and then echo,
that other one is still going to be running and you're gonna see more output.
Yes, three failed and one didn't .
Um, let's just finish investigating why any of them failed,
and then I can make a guess although I don't really know why one of them didn't fail.
Okay, so , what's happening here is that readers returning minus one.
So why is read returning minus one.
You might hypothesize that the you know we were passing this buffer into read,
you might imagine that the you know read,
and read needs to do something namely called copyout to copy file data into this into this buffer,
that we passed to read,
maybe something's going wrong with that and its relationship to copy-on-write fork,
so let's take a look at read, and see why it's failing.
Track down, why read,
alright, so let's capture the,
read all sys_read does this calls calls fileread after fetching a bunch of arguments.
So we'll fix this to ,
take one step closer to understanding why things are going wrong.
We are expecting cc to be minus one.
Um, that's interesting, we never saw cc minus equals minus one.
In fact, the failure occurred, a failure starts occurring here,
before we get any corresponding cc print statements
and it's not minus one at all, it's four, which is a non failure value.
So what that means is that something before the call,
the fileread must have caused must have triggered this return,
so one of these functions here, has caused read to return minus one.
Please feel free to guess while I'm typing.
This was a complete surprise to me
by the way when I tracked it down.
Oh I think the file is descriptor.
Yeah the file descriptor, I saw,
what I expected was that fileread was failing due to something
and copyout not doing the right thing with copy-on-write pages.
But that is not at all where the failure is.
OK, so now, if we want to find out like it's either argfd or argint or argaddr, that's failing,
let's start with argfd, I'm just gonna stick print statements in here,
to help me , figure out which one of these failure cases actually triggering triggering,
so like two places it returns minus one,
this one there's something wrong with the fd itself.
So we're gonna get these print statements on cases where. argfd returns minus one.
Yeah, what is this mean, fd-.
Alright, so the that we expect these fd printouts to occur, just before the error,
so we saw is fd nine, it was fd nine, this causes the error,
so fd 9 failed one of these three tests,
but we know it's not less than zero,
I happen to know it's not greater than equal to NOFILE, a number of open files,
and so that means that the ofile array, a for nine file descriptor nine must have been zero,
that is in this process, there is no file descriptor nine.
So somehow, copy-on-write test,
this code and copy-on-write test is passing an invalid file descriptor to read.
So, file descriptor in comes from fds,
fds comes from a call to pipe.
How could I usually pipe, if it doesn't fail, it leaves the file descriptor in the array,
so how could this go wrong.
Oh, we all know the answer has to be blah blah blah copyout.
So what's the missing piece.
I mean, I guess like one thing that help me track this down
as I realized at least first of all fd should not be nine,
on every iteration nine is kind of the value that you would expect,
kind of add on the last iteration, that's kind of like the highest call to pipe.
Yeah yeah, they all got nine, you're right.
There's something they're kind of touching each other's memory strange.
Yeah that's exactly right.
So, you know the fds pipe, the way pipe turns the file descriptors is that it calls copyout,
to copy the file descriptor number that is allocated into the caller's address space.
Well, we're using copy-on-write fork here,
so if we're not careful,
so at least initially there's just one page and it's shared among all the processes.
So the first process that calls pipe,
if something goes wrong, the pipe system call might conceivably write the shared page.
And that value that file descriptor will then be seen by all the processes,
instead of just the process that actually allocated the descriptor.
They really see this as a kind of at least hypothetical risk.
So let's look at what, try to imagine,
so first let's look a sysfile to see how pipe, copies out the file descriptors that allocates
and indeed down here, these two calls to copyout
to copy the two elements of that pipe array,
so pipe is using copyout to copy the file descriptor numbers into the array in user space.
So what is copyout do.
Well, it looks up the virtual address to find a physical address.
And then its writes, copies over that physical address and that's it.
So, one thing it is not doing is checking for write permission, doesn't look at PTE_W.
And so with this page, at this virtual address refers to a copy-on-write shared page,
copyout just has no idea it just goes ahead and writes it.
So I mean indeed, when pipe calls copyout,
it's going to be writing a shared page,
that all of the forked processes see this modification not just the process that called pipe.
Any questions about, why this is happening.
Okay.
Alright, so as you all know we need to modify copyout
to since copyout is looking up a virtual address and translating into a physical address,
but it is not using the MMU,
so the MMU doesn't catch the right fault, because the MMU is not involved,
walkaddr looks at the page table itself
instead of basically getting there MMU to look at the page table for it.
Okay, so , we need to modify copyout,
we don't wanna call walkaddr, walkaddr just produces a physical address,
we actually want the page table entry, because we want to look at the permission bits,
to see if it's a copy-on-write protected page,
so we're going to call walk instead.
We need to check all the usual errors,
so maybe there's no mapping at all,
maybe it's not a valid mapping,
or maybe it's a mapping that the user code is not allowed to use,
in all those cases, it's an error,
but this time we can actually return an error,
actually call read to return minus one instead of killing the process,
that's nice.
Next we need to know how to check whether it's a copy-on-write page.
Any, any ideas for how we can
check whether we should apply copy whether we should do a copy at this point.
What's different about between copy-on-write pages and just sort of ordinary unshared pages.
Would the reference count to be large.
Um, that's a good point, if the reference count was greater than one,
that's certainly a very strong hint, that's a copy-on-write page.
But if the reference count is one does that mean it's not a copy-on-write page.
It turns out if you fork and the child takes a copy-on-write fault
and makes a copy that reduces the reference count to one,
but the page is still write protected in the parent.
And actually probably we could get away with modifying in that case,
so I think we actually could check the reference count.
And only treated as a copy-on-write page, if the reference count greater than zero,
but what I'm gonna do is different, even easier shortcut
and say if the page is write protected, the only way a page can be write protected
and have the PTE_U bit set,
in this version of xv6 is if it's a copy-on-write page.
So this has saved me a little bit of typing compared to checking the reference count,
we already wrote the code to deal with this in trap.c.
So I'm just gonna call that code from here.
We still have to deal with the possible error return,
if it's a, a crazy address.
Oh, actually, we don't.
Alright.
Alright, so the pages not right at all,
we're just going to copy-on-write fault
and copy-on-write fault does the copy and it makes the page writable,
so I think we're, we're almost done at this point,
however if copying, if cowfault did make a.
We gonna get rid of this.
If cowfault did make a copy, it's going to modify the physical address in the page table entry,
so we have to pull that physical address out of the page table entry again,
in case it was changed,
I'm just gonna do that,
since we have the page table entry right here.
And I think this is more or less enough.
So, any any questions about the modification to copyout.
Alright I got to make a global declaration for cowfault.
Ah beautiful.
Alright that's looking great .
Anybody happen to know if we're done.
We may or not be, we also have to pass usertests.
Oh alright, let me get rid of this print statements.
I think the execout test intentionally allocates a lot of memory.
Alright any questions while we wait for the verdict from usertests.
Oh, usertests was unhappy,
I think this is a familiar piece of damage
which somebody's brought up already it's a , it's the panic at walk
if the user process, usertests actually I think does intentionally.
We'll take a look at usertests ,
and it's the copyout test.
And even says in the comment,
it passes ridiculous pointers to system call.
Alright, so what we're faced with is copyout ,
we pass in a ridiculous pointer,
it's simply called walk with that ridiculous pointer
and walk panics, if you give it a ridiculous pointer.
So, as somebody mentioned, we need to not call walk with ridiculous pointers,
what is it, MAXVA or something.
Alright.
Of course, we're totally entitled to return an error
if the user process pass this or how to [] pointer.
Alright, I'm just hoping it passes now.
I'm not aware of any other problems.
Okay, questions.
I guess my question is more broad,
like we saw when we were doing that with small steps,
we're getting random bugs at this point that others have,
and if we're doing the lab from scratch, then wouldn't it be confusing to get all of those weird bugs,
and how would how would you, how do you know whether it's bug with something you wrote
or a bug because you didn't write the rest of it.
I'm afraid I cannot answer your question.
The the sad truth about bugs, particularly bugs caused by doing funny things to page tables inside the kernel,
is that every bug, you know every bug is different.
And how you know what turns out to be the winning strategy for tracking a bug down.
It just depends totally on the nature of the bug.
My usual, you know I'm not, I have some,
I have a collection of strategies that are sometimes helpful and sometimes not,
like I'm a huge believer, I'm putting print statements into the code
in order to gather information or to verify hypotheses.
I'll often spend time just looking at the code,
just for the purpose of generating sort of brainstorming with myself,
just try to generate you know things that could possibly be going wrong at this point,
and then put print statements in [] panics
or something to try to rule in and rule out various guesses at what the problem might be.
Another possibility is that you know you've made some you know your code worked
or didn't show this error or something,
you know half an hour ago and you made some changes,
and now you have some bug,
another possibility is to if you can, you know back up to a version of the code that didn't have the bug
and sort of add your changes bit by bit until the bug shows up.
Now, these are, I don't know any strategy that always works
or even works more than a fraction of the time.
But the truth is part of what you're learning in this class
as well as learning about operating systems,
you know you're getting experience writing and debugging code.
Sorry, not to be more helpful.
Other questions?
Alright , we're at the end of class time.
I'm happy to talk more,
but we're done with the formal part of this class.
Alright and to see you all on Wednesday.
Oh, sorry I actually have another question,
when we were a seeing our first write fault,
we also saw after that for the shell illegal instruction fault
and then something for the init process, what was that.
Well, I don't have a theory.
Init process, I don't think would share pages with anything.
I I just don't know I'm sorry.
We could .
I would have to back up,
this happened very early, when I was doing the lab,
we just had to copy the page table, nothing else.
Yeah.
I think it was, like scause f for the shell
and I think scause c for the init process, maybe.
Alright, let me let's see if you really, let's let's we can .
Let's reconstruct the lab from scratch,
clone.
Okay, this point we've just made,
I just made a change to uvmcopy right.
So we were, what are we not doing here,
we're not allocating and we're not doing memmove.
But we are, we're gonna pass pa to mappages
and I think the very first the very first time I ran anything.
I think this was the state of play.
It was after we did the flag, so so.
Okay.
Alright, so let's clear.
That looks good.
Alright, we got a c, well let's see c instruction page fault ,
so okay so scause two, you know, as you know we think a shared process id to,
man you're right, it's process id one.
I just don't have a theory for why process id one.
[Later on], it's trouble.
Let's let's let's look at what it does.
I just see it.
Okay, it exec this shell.
I don't know.
You know, okay, oh here's an idea,
process id two is taken a fault and it's exited.
[] later.
Yeah, so that means that this way to init, it has returned, right,
let's go back around the loop and call fork again
and so you know after fork we're now sharing or you know depending on all this damage code.
Oh okay I see.
Oh yeah that's that's very confusing.
Oh yeah, these errors are just like complete [bananas],
because we violated all sorts of intuitions about how things should work.
Okay.