For a function already signed in whose curiosity,
how is your experience been with thee?
translate afternoon?
If you really?
I started on their lazy allocation.
While how,
how is that going?
Here to here,
what did I ever saw?
Less painful than the peach table?
Laugh.
And you don't want to say something about that.
I thought the drops lab was okay.
It was just.
Making sure that I've actually used the trampling page properly was a little annoying,
but once I figured that out then,
then I just like going to work.
Yeah,
they don't go with the lab was sure to really expose you to the year.
Trap handling into entry and exit.
How about an I'm here?
What was your experience to be shared with me?
I thought the trap slump was good,
very much more manageable than the page table.
I noticed that there were like opportunities to be clever about some aspects of the implementation,
which is nice,
and the lazy love is good.
so far of debugging,
but both better than the page table of moving him.
Why did you hear that?
I'm sure you are glad to get up at quantico or two.
How about the right?
Yeah,
these two previous lives have been lot better than the page table one.
Oh,
I guess.
The hardest part for the latest slump,
though lazy one was to read and write.
and all that stuff.
But it's not.
It's not that that,
in my opinion.
Ah.
How would you,
Catherine,
to trap Latin laser Lab for your readers in comparison to the picks up a lab?
Are you there,
Catherine,
Like its Kathryn Weeks?
Hello,
I'm doing well,
so I didn't know which Catherine you're talking to.
I guess it's really too many people,
so you're not likely that there's another one I'm doing quite well to get.
His life is less painful than a Phd in Lahore.
Yes,
it is definitely less painful.
Looks like.
The one the one after a page tables that love is that traps that was definitely much simpler.
OK,
I'm glad to hear that and just wanted to get rid of any formal ball.
See the pitch staple turned out harder than we thought a wood and so like you get at these ones are better OK.
So what do we get going and welcome to the next lecture in a situation now,
wherever you are,
so the topic for today is about interrupts before jumping into you sort of talking about interrupts.
I wanted to share a little bit.
one thing that I wanted to talk about last week,
which I didn't get around to it through,
and you know what you might find interesting.
Let me see if I can get my right screen Europe.
So here you see my screens here on the bottom left,
I make a longing to Athena through the dialogue machines,
and there's a couple of things I wanted to talk about.
It turned to how memory is being used by real operating system.
since we talked a lot about that last week.
In particular at the end of the lecture.
We're a lot of questions about,
you.
know,
pick out,
finding free memory and all that kind of stuff,
and so this isn't a one.
Have you seen a change?
You're wanting to know that if you look at a memory line,
I guess it tells you how much I could a program running school talk if you used it,
you see how much machine memories in the machine and as you can see,
there's quite a bit of memory in this machine,
and if you look at it,
it will be carefully he actually.
Most of it is used.
A large part of the memory that's not being used by applications,
but it actually used by the buffer cache,
and so this is quite common in an operating system.
You don't really want to leave your physical memory sitting idle and do nothing.
We might as well use it for something useful.
And so in this case you know the a good chunk of it is actually used for the buffer.
Cache is a little bit of memory free.
not march refraction of light from the total memory that actually is in the machine,
and so this is a very common case for,
like most operating systems are run.
Ah,
we basically almost no memory free at any particular instant in time.
And so in a move,
for example,
if an application or the kernel needs some memory and we'll have to throw out something,
maybe it has enough.
If a few pages were a handful of pages.
but at some point it needs a lot of free memory.
It will ask the evict something either from the applications or from the buffer cache.
As I was looking at this river,
and so the main point here are basically used that year,
when the kernel needs to allocate memory for you,
there's actually not generally not a cheap operation,
because the memory is not.
There's not a ton of memory free available.
You're doing this sort of interesting to look at it.
I sorted the output of a top by the amount of resident memory.
so you look at every line for every process you know.
you see that this is the size of the address space,
and then the next line that tells you how much memory is actually being used to like the amount of physical memory,
the fraction of the dress beta actually easy in physical memory and as you can see it.
Actually,
you know,
it's typically way smaller than the address space.
So the tricks that we talked about last order,
the cool ideas.
If your memory provides are being used here.
and I'll use demand paging the sheriff call me shared pages from the shared libraries and using general that basically the resident memory is much much much smaller than the virtual address.
Space.
Maybe a couple of other interesting things that you should note just like looking at this machine.
The load is very low,
even though the one hundred twenty years until one hundred two years in London.
And you're going to see there's a lot of processes,
no nine hundred fifty year Earth roughly nothing to know how long the machine has been up like two hundred forty,
nine days.
you're actually strikes.
Colonel was probably not up that long at all ever.
Okay,
any questions about this to sort of cover,
the main point being that,
like most families in use and the resident memory is typically much smaller than the virtual address space.
You can afford to run this in yourself if you want to and see you an extrovert.
Any questions.
You see some of the cyclical weighed one still being locked in and if you look around and you see a whole bunch of few years right.
Okay,
no questions!
Let me go back to the topic for today,
which is sure interrupts.
And the basic idea is wearing a very straightforward or what we want to enable is that there's going to be cases where two hardware.
I want attention.
I want to tell you now.
A pack of comes in from the network and answered the network.
The network at card generates and interrupt you to talk to a key on the keyboard and the keyboard generates and interrupt.
And you know what the chauffeur has to do.
using the software has to save its work.
Whatever he was doing right now.
Put it on the side.
You know,
process the interrupt.
An resume or a store into the work that it is doing.
And basically,
that saving and restoring it was very,
very similar to the mechanisms that already have seen before,
namely for system calls.
And traps.
Pitfalls,
you'll use the same mechanism.
So in that sense,
you know,
interrupts are no different whatsoever compared to traps.
The system calls when a couple things that make them a little bit different and why it works from spinning in a lecture on them.
So the free basically thinks not make interrupts.
Slightly different from system calls and exceptions,
one we can forget a word I'm going to call their asynchronous.
And we've got a mean that the system called the interrupt that happens when the hardware actually generate an interruption,
and the interrupt handler runs that interrupt handler might actually had nothing to do with the current running process on the sea view.
so it would like your example when you do a system call her when the system call happens and then you jump into.
The kernel,
then were running in the context of the calling process.
and this is not true with interrupt.
They might have been completely unrelated to actually the process that you know it was running and Scipio might actually have nothing to do with the inner handler may not even have cost it.
So that's a different second of all,
there is much more concurrency that we have seen so far.
In fact you know this is a starting stock in a place where you're talking about concurrency,
and we'll talk about it in Wednesday's lecture a lot more.
The basic observation is that basically to seek you and the device that generate this operate in parallel the yard with another card.
Here she's doing its thing.
Europe needs a new picking packets on the network and then at some point,
generating an interrupt and at the same time to see if he was running.
And it also is doing you don't see anything.
So we have a true parallelism going on between the device and the sea view.
And we have to manage that parallelism,
as we'll see in a second.
Finally,
I'm going to focus mostly on external devices,
like network cards in Yorkshire,
and that would have to be programmed.
And it basically going to every device has sold its own programming manual in the same way that it would risk five has manual with instructions in which registers do what every device actually has a similar type manual describing what register it has,
what operations you can perform and what the device does get a response to reading and writing patrol relative.
Unfortunately,
often the manuals for the devices are less clear and there is five manual and which makes it a complex programming even more complicated.
And so what I'm going to do in these lectures and it's a pretty straightforward if you want to talk about how the front shows up when you know the shell,
the prince to try out front,
and then if you take a less,
you know,
how do these characters get red and actually didn't being displayed in the console and in fact,
so basically the rest of those lectures about these three characters.
But you all the mechanism that's necessary to actually make it happen.
Any questions so far before I struck it guide anymore a little deeper.
Okay.
So let's say so the first question,
maybe due to ask,
is where do the interrupts come from?
And since I'm going to be focusing,
most of the intellectual and external interrupts are not timely.
Interrupts war which operates the rot,
external interrupts here has come from devices that are sitting on the board and you are safe.
I board Kim you more or less emulates filled with some small modifications,
and we see it,
particularly if you look around so this the board,
There's a lot of actually different devices there that can be connected to notice this for you.
Here are even its connector.
In fact,
here's a micro USB.
It's over there,
others SD card buttons into their organs of serves lines that must be really running from those devices.
no into disrepute.
and most of this lecture is basically sort of understanding what happens at the CP knew when at the device generates and interrupt and how to be the right,
then information from the device,
I believe,
like these lower the two Pins Year at this expansion connector,
I think one of them,
as you are.
You are a tent or transmission,
and the other one is New York.
Zero received why?
And I think it's actually connected to both sides to my Community as well as through this extension cord,
and I think that you are chip itself,
you know,
might actually be in sight of this.
Trip over there.
Okay,
so it's basically there are a bunch of lines running it on the board into the city that we going to zoom in a little bit more in detail.
In this view,
you can use a schema from thee so five documentation for the board and a word processor to corded ware,
which five project we're using.
And we looked at this a little bit before we see here.
Basically here are the device's skirt on the right side here a huge zero,
and you know,
we know that basically,
does humour,
Zeros,
Memory mapped some war in the physical respects,
like all the Durham,
yes,
it's in his side's winner without a dram sits above a wax.
zero zero,
zero and blue,
while we take zero are the different devices basically with lots of stories,
instructions to the physical dress I was given,
and we can actually program that you are to look at that in a much more detail on the sand.
All the device is going to basically come into the processor and really,
what happens is this platform level Internet interrupt controller which is called the plague,
for short,
is the one that's sort of general managers that interrupt coming in from external devices.
Zoom in a little bit more.
You're a diagram of the the quick and cheap devices,
so you are receiving this fifty three.
interrupt lines coming in from different devices,
probably ever devices,
an owner of line,
they come into the plague,
and the public and route interrupts.
So,
for example,
in a depending,
so here are our particular course.
The way we run it,
we run it in a free course.
In immediately the plate can be programmed so that the political reality interrupts to either one of these course or two,
the first core that can take an interrupt and a bit of flexibility,
and if none of the court can take an interrupted at this point,
for example,
to have disabled in Iraq's because they're processing another interrupt and the public will behold that interrupt processor is available to figure in Iraq.
So let's look at some internal state to keep track of that.
If you saw the documentation a little bit here in the way the real things are happening is to pluck indicates that the region interrupt,
upending what the course bitterly claims it,
so they will tell the public not to give to any other core.
I once did probably done with it.
It will say,
like OK,
I'm done with this particularly interrupt and the flexible and informed the public that narrowed.
It can forget about this.
Interrupt.
Any questions about this,
they sort of the internal risk.
five.
In rup structure.
Yet when each heart holds the plague,
does the play have some enforcement mechanism to ensure fairness?
It is all up to the kernel to prevent the public in whatever way it wants.
The public doesn't really.
it's just a surface of delivering interrupted writing them.
But it is.
The kernel of the programs to play compels we're in rough,
should be delivered to,
etc.
I bet you know interrupted priorities.
The kernel can decide which in rup is more important than another interrupt.
There's a huge amount of flexibility.
Any other questions about the hardware.
Okay.
Because you know sort of the hardware side of it,
we'll talk little bits here at a high level about the software side.
So typically learn to code that manages his device is called the driver.
It is just code,
typically according nerve going into the kernel that we'll be looking at here.
She code and an extra six in all.
The drivers are in sight of the kernel in the courtyard.
Basically managing or the drivers are all inside of the kernel.
So we got the point that we're going to be looking a little bit today.
Here is your Karachi.
is the driver for viewership?
And if you look at the structure of the internal structure of the code,
most drivers have a structure we're going to draw this,
not as an address.
Space are not intended to be used in address space,
particularly when people talk about drivers.
There's a bottom part.
And the top part.
And basically,
the bottom parties of the interrupt handling.
So when the interrupt handler,
when an inner comes in the process of this,
a few house interrupts enabled the interrupt will fire near the posture of wool.
I guess we've seen the second rule actually here called the interrupt handler for that to be device basically calls into the code here.
An interrupt handler runs in,
doesn't doesn't run in any context of any specific process.
I just processes are just part of the Internet.
The interrupt.
The top part,
if you will of the driver,
is where user processes or going to the rest of the kernel calls into,
for example,
and it consulting is a great pair of where you are.
There's a meteorite interface.
That actually higher level code actually calls into,
and then typically cage is actually.
There are some few often in the driver and the top of your code,
you know calls in the sticks.
you know characters into the into this queue and interrupt handler puts girls or depending on sending and receiving receiving,
made an interrupt.
and one also will stick.
It's actually kind of these interviews.
It will see it an excuse that are basically used to decouple the top and the bottom part from each other and allowing the device to run in parallel with the rest of the code.
on the sea view.
In the inner a panel that typically under some restrictions on the Internet peddler because,
though,
to run in any context any process context with therapy,
you can call a copying or copy out because.
The current page table might actually not be reflective of the page table that the product to which character should be copied.
And so it's the upper part of the driver generally,
does the interaction with usual awful prosecution may become calls,
copying a copy out.
Any questions about this sort of this high level.
Picture.
We'll look at is quite a bit more detail,
but this is sort of going to mean.
Organization of a typical driver.
If you do need to realize that there are many drivers in an operating system.
In fact,
quite common that near the sum of the driver code is quite bigger or larger than the core kernel itself.
It mostly because going for every device you need to drive,
you need a driver and most computers,
you have a lot of devices.
Okay,
so let's talk a little bit about programming devices.
So the typically programming is done using memory method.
So as we've seen in risk life or in the safety Board,
the device to show up at particularly addresses in the physical address space can and this is decided by the device,
went overboard manufacturer and it would not bring system needs to know what those weirdos device are located in a physical law in memory space and then basically programs them use using ordinary load and store instructions to those addresses.
But basically what these lonely story structures do?
Is they read or write a meteorite control register.
Of the device.
And so typically,
one year,
ladies like store something you mean,
the one of the control registers that causes a package to be sent.
So instead of reading or writing memory,
just wanting a strong structure typically have side effects.
The cost of the device to do something.
And you know,
you have to look basically in the documentation of the device to actually figure out what the device does.
Sometimes this documentation is very clear that sometimes these documentation is less clear.
but you should give you a little bit of a sample.
Two things I wanted to show you here on the right side of the screen you see the memory mapped.
physical memory mapped space can afford a sofa and a board.
I and you see what the addresses are,
where particular things are mapped.
Why we're going to show up in the physical dress days soon.
Use the word.
Backwardation actually show up in the physical address space,
and so,
for example,
to see to clean to Skinner.
Is there at zero zero?
We pick out another one.
Applique was somewhere there to again.
Here's the public at Alex.
since you were two,
your hero,
that's the platform,
the platform room and even a controller,
and she actually.
You are zero here at this particular dress.
It turns out that the cumulative we're using.
It has the right action at a different location,
and that's because we use vacuum you who doesn't actually literally emulate to satisfy aboard,
but something that is very close to decipher.
Or it's just a memory mapped the memory map or physical addresses to two devices.
And then on,
the website is just a piece of documentation for New York.
This is the sixteen fifty five one,
six point five zero.
that's actually do your chip that sits on the accumulation that we're using to actually interact with a keyboard and consult,
and this is a reasonable sample chip.
There's not too much going on in this device,
even when there are no complications here on this table.
Here.
The registers that the chip has the control rate assertion is an example in a control registers zero zero zero.
When you do a lone instruction,
it halts its will.
Hold the data if you do a store instruction.
As the register got mauled.
basically to date,
it will be copied into to be transmitted outside on the wire,
and you are basically a device that allows you to send bits over a serial line.
St Line is one line and the received line is not a line.
Invisible you to take a bite,
and basically there a multiplex or she realized on this is a single line sent over to the other side as he marched to the chip sitting on the other side and basically assembles the big back into a single byte.
In a couple of other things that you can control a device,
you can actually control the moderate after the device.
But due to some degree,
and probably most important for us is the register.
Register one or more to sit here,
which is the ant interrupt enable register,
and so we can program it to actually a cause that you are to generate interrupts.
Scroll down this document,
you'll see that we're gonna be able to get out the document.
actually more detail,
basically described with every bit in a register means including four years in the interoperable registered.
I are the register which the acronym for it you know they basically do system she's learned,
stated,
interrupt and transmit holding register,
interrupt,
but the between and it just goes on and on and therefore what the documentation tells you,
what do you tell what the registers are and how you can use entity in falling voter in remote?
We'll talk about a little bit of the work you have to program in an up,
enable rather foolish,
etc.
so that we started out to be a short version of the real documents.
The hill documents from the chip manufacturer is much more has much more stuff in it in much more detail a minister of sufficient for us to actually be able to talk about how to program the EU art.
and you can see.
this is one of the most simple devices and even that document or you know it's quite a bit to it.
I'm sorry I was wondering if your rights.
so if you raise something to the transmit holding registered and then you write a game like right after that.
It makes sure that,
like the previous number,
it didn't just like.
get overridden?
Yes,
just just to know it's part of you actually,
this is one and one of the things that we're going to pay a bit of tension to the EU.
Tell basically load instruction,
you lose some value.
we're storing,
So if you're losing value in a creditor,
ah and in the EU are chip,
you know it goes off and it's going to send off that bite counting the line on the serial line brick and when it's done,
it will generate an interrupt.
seeing through the kernel.
OK,
I'm done with that right now you can give me the next byte.
Into the kernel and the device has been sort of a normal protocol to make sure that actually everything works out.
This particular,
you aren't,
you know that we're using has a fixed sixteen.
Fifty,
five,
five fifty eight actually internally has a fatal and I think it can buffer a bunch of character.
Shall I come to pick up to sixteen?
But you still have to sort of play this game of life.
You can't stick more than sixteen characters into it until the device actually play has told you.
Well,
I have seen one character.
Because that makes sense.
Oh,
yeah,
thank you.
So I'm going to talk a little bit more before we look at.
When the more detailed the case study,
you know that I'm going to go through four,
explaining how devices,
an interrupted work users dollar.
I'll ask,
you know what happens.
How actually how you print?
And so basically,
what happens is that the device,
as we actually sort of discussed in the second ago,
has basically puts the character of the dollar in this case into the yard.
In fact,
in the render service that we just looked at,
and then the York generates an interrupt.
the way that leaves us the way that we're going to set things up generates and interrupt when the device,
when the character has been sent.
And then on the other side,
and so basically the way things are set up in Cuba and communities that are on the same line on the other side of the same wine.
another your shipment that actually connects due to console to the virtual virtual console.
On the other side.
You know what happens when Alice is going to pay me to do the input,
and so the keyboard actually is connected to the received line.
There she is lying.
And so basically the keyboard you know when you hit a key on the keyboard,
the keyboard,
the virtual keyboard.
in this case you know your chips on that site you know well civilized,
the character Hell send it to view it on the other side.
the other side puts the you know the bitch you know together again into one night and then generating an interrupt.
Generate an interrupt to tell the processor hate is a character available from their keyboard.
In an interview panels,
the interruption will reach the debate from the yard.
as we'll see in a second.
and so there was a new sort of two things.
If we want to sort of understand a more detailed and actually how they work.
Okay,
any questions about this.
so.
The response has a bunch of support.
Support raindrops.
And numerous reddish fish that we'll see here in more detail.
I asked they could do is we're going to be useful to know which ones they are there is that as I E supervisor interrupt an evil registered,
and that has a bit you know one bit for.
External interrupts,
but from devices like the EU art from the suffering rocks,
which I'm going to do is we're going to talk about it.
But it is possible from one sea view from one requires core to send an interrupt to another.
Is five core and timer.
Interrupt.
And I'm not really going to talk about either.
The supervisor of the suffering,
the ropes nor the timing interrupts are going to focusing externally for us.
Then there's another very interesting that we've seen before.
It's faulty.
Supervise her status,
register.
And that has a bit to disable and enable interrupts.
On this particular core.
So every courthouse near these registers and in addition to these three bids for individual control,
when you want to have external interrupts or something to read for ten minutes,
there isn't one beer to digital controls that you're going to receive interrupt at all,
and so you can automatically switch from not getting rid of interrupts to having written a rupture with the other way around,
but just changing that.
One bid in the US state of repetition.
Separator cut the supervisor,
your inner pending registered.
And basically,
the process you can use that I want to interrupt is going to happen to me in a profit and look at the years I came to see what one interrupt actually has come in and in addition,
there will be even in Europe happens in the s cars registered that we should have seen competition for now.
There will be an indication of one interrupt actually came in with a look in the second,
and,
of course there's the Sdg Vic registered that basically holds the program were also addressed to which the processor switch once either trap or trap of system call or a page fault happens when an interrupt habits because basically uses for all three cases the same mechanism.
I'm not going to talk too much about its cause and effect because we know we've seen a tear in detail before and the business operates in exactly the same.
We asked.
A system calls in the page,
faults or other exceptions.
OK,
so let's see you're going a little bit of a sense of how this stuff,
the sort of initialized.
So we're not talking even about how the drivers actually work,
but just to see how exactly six programs,
these research said that we were going to be in a position to take interruption.
Courses in the church.
I think a little bit behind on the chat,
so let's see you get a little bit on what they have.
Programs,
these research reports and code you get rid of there.
No,
actually,
they don't really need that eater,
so I'm not going to use d to be to walk through things,
and we are going to look at the particular functions that are irrelevant.
So probably the first thing is in start.
Dot C.
So when the machine boots were to process your boots.
Start function is called it's runs in the emerald and disables.
Paging in the right way.
Because you know sort of leader on the kernel has set up the page tables,
and when she heard a basically delegates,
all interrupts and exceptions to supervise the mood.
And then it's programmed the supervisor enabling an interop Enable register to take suffering ruffs tamer interrupts and external interrupts.
And then we could have a good measure a timer interrupt it actually happened to coming to him are handled in emerald.
Emerald Code actually a program's Tyler registers,
and so that Tamerlan rupture and generated no,
no,
We want to talk about that next week,
so I'm gonna go to me.
Not see.
So see how external devices are handled and so our first external devices to console them,
and that is where we print too.
What can you conceive?
It was all in at us.
So here's control in it you can easily get to walk here.
We actually care not much about that at all,
at least not for this lecture,
and it actually can basically cause the yard in it and you aren't in it.
He is right here.
It actually sets up the newer chip or configure for your chips.
It is ready for use at first actually disables in roskilde.
This is just a sequence you have to go through when you program.
It is at about rate,
then you set in six or seven bits,
seven or eight bits bytes while prepared.
You're not and ah.
You set the internal five folks that you aren't having to clear out anything that it actually might be in there,
and then we receive when evil interrupts for transmission in interruption.
I mean,
I think you raise your hand.
And I'm wondering what the baud rate is exactly of the speed at which you know the line runs.
Oh,
I see.
Okay,
so that's what you were doing it now.
At this point you know you are.
In principle a component can generate interrupted,
but of course we haven't been actually programmed the interrupt enabling stuff on the on the risk by project itself.
and yet we haven't programmed to public yet mere from nothing really happens.
At this point yet,
and so the next thing,
if we are going to move back to may not see it,
we'll see a little bit scroll down.
We'll see actually that the public is initialized,
and so let's look at that.
And basically in a goat,
you looked at this table that I showed you a little while ago with the physical memory or the memory leak out to get to the public is in some particular location record.
The location is incredible.
Many lay out what she did.
The flick is here.
Oh,
here is zero,
zero zero breaking it literally copied from the document,
and it went away.
We write stuff to the plate is basically you're taking.
The number would be dressed for the plague castles to thirty two pointer,
endured because the plink of registers are free to bit,
and then you're basically write a one to it.
So this class is basically I want to be written to the register.
You aren't zero error.
queue.
And basically,
what this does is it enables interrupt request from the yard,
but remember to play kunar busily routes,
the interrupts,
answered.
The interim might come in from the left side from that picture into the plane or into places like this program to actually accept note in a rush.
Similarly,
had actually programs to play ducks,
accepting risks from the Iowa disk,
which I'm not going to talk about at all.
OK,
and then we go back to main dot C.
Right after the publication of the machines is blinking at heart,
and invisibly for every core.
Specifically,
every core individually owned one core that is first core actually initialize.
This disparate aspect there was a basement were taking,
interrupts when those devices and in every core individually has to say I'm interested in those devices too.
And so,
for example,
here every core extra calls dysfunctions of every course,
as I mentioned in an interrupt from do you aren't in a minute interrupts from the video.
You can see here basically does you are just prior to basically is a unique number,
and for New York and I argue for what you are to him,
I think you would live on.
The commune is number ten.
We're basically ignore priorities,
and so we just set it to zero.
OK,
and so does every ship you a record individually has to indicate to the public that it actually is interested in receiving interrupts.
Now,
at this point,
you know we were basically green basically have to program the device to generate interrupts.
We have programmed the click through the pass in rocks on between the individual while she abused,
but she views itself haven't actually are not accepting inner of yet because we haven't set the bid in the estate of rhetoric,
and so let's go back to main got Sheen.
And you know what,
I mean.
does he does a bunch of organization?
But he ended agriculture scheduler.
So let's go look at Procter Dot C.
And the skin color.
And what we see here is like when we're out.
Basically,
the whole machine is sort of.
The prosecutors has been set up and schedule your schedule,
but your process to run before any of that actually enables interrupts.
And so we look at risk life,
and you'll see there is basically this.
Is there.
C function.
And that basically Naples interruption.
If you can not surprising,
you know basically,
the only thing it does.
it sets the interrupt enable bit in the status register.
So at this particular point in time,
right at this instance,
if there were an inner appending at public,
then this particular core would be interrupted.
We'll see that in a second later,
but this is this point.
Interrupts are enabled.
And so those are the basic setup.
Any questions about this.
Outside,
he interrupted when at that point so every quarter runs his camera removed wreck and whatever coracles interact on,
were all cordial,
calling and rub it on.
But let's say there's only one core gets there first,
like one.
And if core one sets its interrupt,
enable bit at that point,
it could receive an interrupt.
And we'll see in a second what happens exactly at an interrupt.
Mesa,
thank you.
OK,
so what I want to do is look at this.
how to print the dollar?
The prompt at the shell prompt and so for that we want to go back a little bit and I will just want to look at in it again,
so this was the first process that actually is being your inner code execs in it.
and so that's basically the first process running and one of the things that in the dust it makes a device that represents to console some here that the file is created using to make not operation and returns.
A file descriptor file the script to zero.
Because it's the first file descriptor open and an adopted.
You know,
first hand it out and then pushed in an error and dumped it again.
And so this basically sets up a file,
the script of zero,
one and two to correspond to the console.
You know,
so you know,
then the force of the shell.
So once you get to Shell for a second.
So the shell opens,
it will start running with your father.
I want to a free sort of zero one or two open pointing to the console and then the shell prince,
the character dollar in the space to file the script or too.
And so even though the console and you are in a rough sort of all you to blow all this to the application programmer with the shell.
Although the person who wrote the shell,
it just looks like a regular file to effect to show itself,
since its rights to fathers is no idea,
what actually sits in the other side right?
And we have seen in Utah Lab and you can do all kinds of cool stuff with it.
But here's an example we're going to.
Basically,
the device in UNIX is represented as a file.
It's not different than anything else.
OK,
so let's see how this actually printing networks so that a printer is actually six user application if a tiny little C library which include scenario print stuff and you're enough,
as you've seen,
these have been a tram flap.
You know sort of interesting function in itself but Indians and basically calls the write system call.
and in our case,
for example,
write system.
Call will be found to skip the two.
And he would be.
I hold the character dollar as we're past the address of the memory location that holds the dollar to the file descriptor to right,
and we ask him to write one character.
So basically,
every character written by the shell in a result in system call,
and so now we can go.
And see what actually happens so you've seen the system call before.
But since its file.
She is right.
So here's the write system call it grabs his arguments,
the file descriptor.
then it requires to be written in the address of there.
They addressed,
it contains the character dollar has been file right.
Let's quickly look at file right.
We're getting close to actually wear the thing that we want to talk about and you know here.
If I'll write it.
looks for the type of the founders cutter is it's a pipe recalled a pipe functions,
and if its device,
which will make not dusk,
then it will call the right function for that particular device.
And so we know that you know that I think it's going to call the right function in the console.
And so let's see what happens there so useless.
All right.
Gratz walk,
you know we would care about that right now.
It copies in the one character you to eat or copying.
in animals you are twitchy.
So that these were calls into the EU art and so you can think about the end of the console is being the driver.
We're looking sort of at the top end of the driver and makes a call an interviewer to see two actually printed character.
And so here's your two Let's see so this is going to be a little bit interesting basically eternally keeps a buffer,
so let's go back and back up a little bit on the top.
In fact,
it into a buffer for transmission and the buffer size is thirty two characters.
And there's a pointer and the write pointer in the read pointer now would be used to put this in a characters into the circle of circular buffer if a little bit about that in more detail,
but such a pointer for the producer and is a pointer for the consumer and in this case you know thee shall,
if you will,
is the producer and it actually checks.
The first thing it does is actually checked whether the circular buffers for so long and weighed the checks of the circle,
the preferred tool,
so it started out in the original state is both the write pointer and the write pointer is zero corrected zero induction to dump buffer if they're equal.
You know,
it's there.
The buffer is empty.
But if he had wanted to write pointer and it's the same as the receive pointer.
So,
for example,
is you're feeling a zero one,
Two,
three,
four,
five,
six,
seven,
eight,
nine thousand,
nine hundred and eighty one.
And then you're about to wrap around Harry and one.
and it's still equal to the receive index or the reading that you know that the buffer is full,
And so there's no point and you can write anything at that point,
because I found that you are still busy working its way through trying to send off the preceding thirty one characters or refer to characters,
in this case,
the Buffett rule.
Basically we would put to sleep and put on the site.
And the kernel would run some other program until the shelves be woken up in the notes actually ready to set.
When you are just ready to send more data now,
of course,
in this case,
this is not the case because it's like this.
The first few characters that are being print since the space in the buffer and so basically to the driver,
puts the character into the mother and teach them at the right point in time to go to the next slot and then calls your start.
And basically your charge is nothing else and sort of kicking the device and saying,
Go do some work for me and immediately.
It first checks the mightiest of busy sending the current character that until recently,
if if the device is busy,
you know we just go back and it will go to sleep probably won't going to sleep.
and otherwise we'll read the character out of the buffer.
Ah and put it in the transmission register that we saw earlier.
The transmission managed to introduce it like this before.
Let's look at that for a second.
You know,
we usually write,
register you know,
casts.
Particularly registered to do the will of a wrench type and then right near the value into it.
Do you charge to transmit all the medical is that it's the zero waste himself before from the documentation?
Okay,
so so basically.
Where I was,
I didn't start.
Ah,
you should start basically kicks the device in saying,
like,
Hey,
I got a register,
I got a bite for you available to shut off.
and that's basically all there that that basically,
if you will to shell,
you know their system called the shell called Will do,
and you know at once it actually kicked off the device.
and these will return to user space,
and the shell can go on and do whatever he wants to do.
And generally the next thing Michelle will do is called the read System,
call to actually read input from the keyboard.
and so the shell will return to use a space using the standard mechanism I've seen before.
like user read,
it just goes off and does its thing.
And in the meantime,
the device has not gotten a kick to actually send some bites off.
And so.
So at some point,
you know we're going to get to interrupt.
Well,
hopefully,
you know because we programmed the hardware to actually generate interrupts.
what's it going to look back and talk a little bit about the direction?
What happens now when it interrupt happens?
I'll get you.
So what does the hardware do?
In this particular case,
the risk life do you want an interrupt.
It actually hasn't happened,
so we set these interop enable bid in the estate of editor,
so the process can be interrupted.
You know,
let's say a keyboard and it raises the inner applying you know,
go through the plague can arouse the interrupt you a particular core and a core.
Last year as a new bid set.
So in Europe enabled it said.
The supervisor,
in a remarkable bit said so If the bit is set,
the following things happened and this it will look very similar to what we've seen before.
But the first thing the hardware does is clear.
As I eat it.
This stops any further raindrops coming in,
so we can just deal with it,
interrupt first and then,
if we want more interrupts,
get up,
we have to learn,
We enabled a bit,
but I used to stop for doing a rupture can visually interact,
interrupting to interrupt.
Then,
as the PC to the exception from encounter to the current PC.
Over generally we were interrupted together.
Let's say Michelle,
return to user space looks happily running in user space,
and interrupt comes in because that one character resent.
Then the programmer found the shaved his.
whatever program counter was in user space.
It saves the safety occurred mode.
In this case of being in our example would be,
you will see that actually the processing supervising amount of in user mode then it's just a moment to supervisor.
and visually sits the program counter to SD Vic,
whenever values in SDB back then that's going to be either.
use a trap or use your back or kernel.
Vic.
I'm depending whether the interrupt happened in whatever.
We're a new kernel space where in Hughes about,
but in our example where maybe she'll return to use a space,
effectively contain the user.
pick a dress and basically,
the hardware level using the kernel at the instruction that is located at the back.
and then we remember from previous lecture.
basically a student you know it goes off and calls user trap.
Okay,
so in the end will basically end up in your trap.
And that's where we start to pick up the story,
because I don't really want to talk too much about the saving and restoring anymore because one,
we explained it in detail in the previous lecture to you already played me,
but also in there and this last traps and laughed and said,
You know,
you know exactly what's going on.
Any questions.
Okay,
so.
So here we go back and use your track in function,
you looked in detail at in their traps,
your love,
and we've dealt with a case of system calls and what we're going to do is basically the only thing we're going to do is look at this case.
We just did a device interrupted,
so we're going to.
That's a little bit lower here in the file.
So here's a device to interrupt and it looks basically at s costs,
register and sees if this is an external interrupt,
and if it's an internal interrupt,
it calls a function we'll play claim to.
Basically,
I clean that particular to clean the interrupt.
So let's go back to the public.
Look at the claim,
and basically what it boils down to is that this particular shampoo will tell the plague.
Hey,
I'm claiming it will distribute zero if you want,
It will tell the plate that's if you one is claiming this particular interrupt and was claim an interrupt and the bleak returns which interrupts it gets down.
your queue for the interrupted actually came in.
And so in this case,
that will be an interrupt.
Or do you aren't in the Arctic,
you tend to duplicate.
the same plane were basically return ten,
and then here in this code will look,
you say,
hey,
is this?
In return?
he was interrupted.
Oh,
that must be a.
you are an interrupt,
and we basically called ewart interrupt function and you are neither a function.
Runs and basically gets the character off your heart,
and we had guessed the character.
If you already has basically looks in the first registered the receive register and gets the character out of there.
And that is an integer and n.
It calls Kosovo interrupt to do the rest of the world.
Okay.
Actually,
I just get did the wrong thing and we were talking about transmission.
So if there was a character on the right side and then the inner wall Tile,
the console era.
But there is no character correct on the read side because we haven't read any keyboard hasn't done anything yet.
I were just transmitting a character.
So doesn't want you return of minus one fall through and then basically,
when the whole thing in the loop it's called,
you are start to basically set and use any other color characters that might be in the buffer that the shell and it might be stuck in there and grooming.
There's another character in there because after the dollar is to space and the write system call might forget how to write.
This space might have happened concurrently while the device for sending off.
And so when the interrupt transmit interrupt complete,
it's going to ask you know that you will find in the buffer yet another character,
the space character animals in that space character off.
Okay,
so it makes sense.
I have a high level question actually,
so I understand your tears like useful,
if I am,
you like using a keyboard and like characters from the keyboard goes through the yard and then through the sea for years and then the kernel code that we wrote.
But I am not sure I understand what the point of the report is.
When the shell is printing characters like the keyboard isn't being interacted with.
No,
it is correct,
but the display is actually.
there should have two devices here.
One is that a keyboard and wanted to display or to console and and the way you interact with.
the console is by York.
just by sending a character to the console and then the consoles job,
especially to draw that character on the display.
I see other things.
And it might take a time during those Why,
again of this thing,
you are sort of interrupt driven.
Okay,
so a couple of things.
Now I want to step back a little bit and think moving at a higher level.
it's going on,
so we should walk through the code,
we get a feeling for the lay of the land,
and like,
How did you guess?
The details before file to step back a second and think a little bit about what it all means.
And particular,
what is interesting is interrupted concurrency you sort of think about interrupt from the perspective of concurrency.
This is one of the things that actually makes interrupts tricky or and difficult to program.
So first of all,
if you mention a little bit earlier,
did the device,
you know the New York?
In our case,
the device in the shampoo.
Run in parallel.
So,
for example,
in this scenario,
when you've talked about you already sending off the character to the console,
and while that's happening,
distribution skill going about its business and indication of returning to the shell that Shell may make another system called Attempt to write up a space character and all happens in parallel.
And so we need to manage the parallelism a bit.
and we already saw a little bit.
But I can talk a little bit more in detail.
And the type of parallelism that actually shows up here is typically called a producer and consumer parallelism.
Now let me talk about it in a second.
so now we're going to talk about that a little bit more detail.
The second is.
That the interrupt.
Stops the current running program.
The current program is running.
So in the case of the shell,
the shell might be executing extraction like fear of two hundred and twelve and boom.
Interrupt comes in at a meager at that point.
Is you stopped?
If a user space code is not a particularly big deal because when we return the interruptible,
we restore on the state after the usual of a program,
and it will resume at that address,
where which I got interrupted.
And so we have seen that therewith attracts a page fault into actually worked reasonably well.
But there's a little bit of a tricky case when the kernel itself could interrupt it.
So you're running in kernel mode and the Colonel gets interrupted.
That means that you've got a little bit more detail.
that even the kernel doesn't really sort of executed straight sequentially.
If you see one kernel instruction,
followed by another internal instruction,
he may be those between those two instructions.
An interim might happen,
depending when an interrupt are enabled or not in the winter and some piece of code,
and it's not good to have an interrupt in between in an occasion.
The kernel might actually have to disable or enable interrupts to make basically consequences atomic.
So interrupt.
Enable and disable.
I'll talk about it in a second in the more detail and then sort of deferred sort of concurrency problem.
It shows up.
Interrupt handler.
For me to say,
let me say it differently The top of the driver.
In the bottom of the driver.
may run in parallel.
So,
for example,
in our example.
The shell is going to call the write system call again near to pry the white space after it printed the dollar.
And while you may need to go back into the top level of the driver,
it might want to remain on Earth.
You know this white space to that queue you are actually house,
but at the same time,
on another sheep,
you knew it might actually take interrupt uniform you art and basically also be running in parallel,
and that's sort of roughly the same code and looking at the same queue.
and so it's really true that basically,
the interrupt handler can run in parallel with the bottom.
half of the device driver must run in parallel in different views on a live interview with the top half of the driver.
And so we have to manage down a bit in the way you know,
we're going to manage that.
He's using locks.
And because there's a shared data structure here,
namely the buffer.
and then we're going to make sure that you know the buffers of data to correctly and you need to make sure that the only one she view at a time basically manipulates.
dump on a particular buffer.
If we're going to use locks and locks is going to be the topic of Wednesday's lecture.
so I'm going to talk much about it at all.
But it will show a big time.
on Wednesday.
The thing I want to focus on is actually a dispute consumer.
Parallelism,
and this is a typical thing that shows up in the drivers,
and it is extremely common to see them.
so producers,
consumer.
And I think it's pretty straightforward,
so what you've seen.
there's basically a buffer in the driver.
You know,
in our case,
I think it over thirty two entries in it,
so the zero to one and there are two pointers.
There's a read pointer and the write pointer.
And here's the write pointer read pointer if they're equal,
the buffer is empty and to win near the shell right in her pussy.
Basically puts the character like the dollar here and bumps up here,
the write pointer to the next entry.
Then I started to produce a part and a producer can keep going,
and you are feeling up.
You know all this and all you know and all hit if the next incremental hit,
the read pointer.
we know that there's this circled buffer is full,
and at that point you know the producer must stop.
and we started happening in the code I second ago where the user basically the euro Cup of Sleep and we'll put this.
Shell on the site and started running another process.
So the interrupt handlers me like you aren't in it or enter.
In this case,
at the consumer immediately every time,
or you would start basically when you are an interest,
it will look at the end of the read pointer.
If the read pointer is behind the write pointer to the write pointer are any further.
Let's say to space if you're too now,
and I know I can know how to draw a space for two years of space.
It's where the write pointer might now be here till after the always mean you're changed at all.
You know,
I'm behind the right order.
That means I got to send the next one.
And so you can think about this as sort of these right in a pointer and the write pointer is chasing the write pointer,
and that's what's gone now.
It could be the case that at some point you keeps up with the write pointer and return them when they're equal.
And then he noticed that the buffer is empty and there's nothing to do.
So it makes sense.
So so this Danish pressure is the same for all course.
OK,
so let me go back to the code works since the height of the picture,
and let's go back to your heart.
So this data structure that I just talked about is this buffer.
And the two pointers get the right in the read pointer are used to point out indexes using Pcs.
Okay.
And this data fractured Lucy Memory.
And there's only one ram right until all the course might be interacting with this data structure in parallel.
As why we need locks.
OK,
I see a rather question was for a sleep.
How does it know to I'll make the shell sleep won't like what is written.
There is just the address.
Yeah,
basically,
sleep color puts the current process running on the sleep in a sleep state,
and we'll talk about it next week or the week after in a great amount of detail,
and it passes in the thing that is waiting for,
and in this case he had on his d the dress you know.
Basically,
it has a channel idea where,
like a way of communicating from one and actually sleeping on this cases of teacher is the dress of new artists are in and start function.
It wants their space again in the buffer.
Ah,
it will wake up corundum call the corresponding call and wake up with the?
U.
R T are charged to indicate that any process that actually sleeping on this address should be woken up.
How does exactly is implemented is something that we'll see a little bit later.
It's a mixed history.
goal is going to get our sleep and wake up.
Sometimes called conditional synchronization.
Any other questions?
Okay.
Good.
Let's say so,
let's see.
So that is basically the whole story for printing and daughter,
and as you can see,
it's actually quite involved.
There's a lot of pieces I'm working together to actually get this dollar out into the console.
And something similar basically happens on the read side.
so at some point to Shell has printed the above the door and the white space and minimal coverage to basically read input from the keyboard like this one.
And we wanted to see what happens when that had been happening.
So the starch,
basically Indians with filed again.
That's what they noticed.
There's a read system call.
If its scale reading for the console,
it will cause a more accurate CT file.
Read not right.
The device,
which in this case is a case,
hits the console.
Then we call the read method for that device,
and that is a console that C,
and so we're going to go from.
Two personal read is being called and basically it has the same structure business you are.
there's a circular buffer.
On the top here it is,
it's an input buffer from the two thousand and eight characters in it.
and basically it's the same game to produce a consumer parallelism.
but in this case the shell is the consumer unity.
It actually is reading characters off the buffer and the keyboard is the pollution and it sticks to characters into the butter.
And so you know let's go back to console read if there's nothing.
If the read pointer would read.
Index in the right index are the same in the buffer is empty and it goes back to sleep again.
And so after its print,
the dollar in an important the shell is going to go to sleep.
Colonel will put the shell to sleep until a character comes in.
And so at some point,
let's say you know a user types in l.
you know the first character from Alice on the keyboard that will cost around and the L to be sent into the yard cheap on the on the board that will be routed through the plate to some core.
That horrible thing to interrupt that will go to death inner that that inner we'll see how that viewer had interrupted,
and it will call the function that we looked at a second ago.
It's goes back to the bottom where I got my confused myself just for a second.
So in this case,
we will write.
It won't get a character from the device from the unit of ice cream will get the character hell and we'll call the console interrupt function using the character hell so we can go back to control.
And because you know it gets the character so now we have an L.
If the control P,
you know an act of Princeton list in the preceding list,
implements control,
age and control you to do that space and control whatever.
But in all other cases going to basically what it does,
it echoes to the character back to the user by printing it to the console and then eventually sixty character into the buffer and wake up the process.
That's waiting for that buffer.
If there's a process weighting if it has hit new wine and there's a process waiting and will wake up the waiting process and then the waiting process will reach.
you know the characters out of the buffer.
So here again we see this sort of decoupling using a buffer between the consumers and the producers show that the precision of consumer can just run in parallel.
independent each on their own speed.
and you want to go very fast.
You know that you know the button will be inferior,
fool and it will block,
wait until the other guy catch your shop.
Any questions about this.
Okay.
Can I talk basically like one more thing?
In earnest.
You know,
I'm going to talk a little bit about sort of interrupt evolution.
What has happened over the last decades?
So if your interviews to be relative to not do across a reasonable fast.
Tickler.
Fast Times the original UNIX was developed.
You know that's the case and then basically meant that the hardware is very simple.
Because if any really serious work needs to be done so hard,
we could just interrupt the posture and you know the project would do it on the work and its old,
but they get an art in itself could be reasonable,
Illustrate fork.
Now interrupts are slow.
Compared to the process,
you can see that right because the interrupt handler you need to save,
restore registers,
it makes you take the interact.
so there's a couple who you know.
This is a whole bunch of instructions that it is being used to actually serve the interrupt.
And so ah,
if a device generate interrupted a high speed,
then the process is going to have a tough time keeping up.
And so you look at today's devices.
Basically,
the hardware of the device is a lot more work.
And so basically without too much of the work on the device itself before actually generating an interrupt.
And just to avoid interrupting the process or too much.
Now,
if you really have a high performance device like saying you have a gigabyte kick a bit.
Even it?
And you know that card.
If you use a lot,
a lot of small packages packets,
then you know you can actually generates weren't even itself could generate about one fire.
At one point,
five million packets per second.
For animals like sixty four even a pack,
achieving you do the math you can roughly out to.
Basically you're generating one point.
five million packets per second thing you could receive.
and so that basically means you know one interrupt.
If you did it for every packet per microseconds.
In fact,
a little bit more narrow than it loses less than a little bit more than that.
You basically,
you know we're going to think about it because one interrupted or three microseconds is basically to operating system.
The kernel basically has a budget of like one microseconds,
obstructions to actually process the packets and the fact that it's one point,
five million such a little bit less than a budget of a microsecond.
So you could compute out on me,
I'm an obstruction to ideas,
and it's not going to be that much.
and so in that case you need to have a different plants like what do you do with the package would interrupt her actually coming so fast that the pressure really can't keep up and the solution to that you used to you.
for these fast devices,
it's actually something that we use.
It's called calling.
And instead of lying in Arabic,
so if you also could do you,
just keep in reading that control register and to see if there's a byte,
dare like a new art registered.
We used to keep reading that in each are registered and just check if there's a right there,
and you know what the spinal boils out extends to distribute your spins.
The spins on the device and the old device as input.
Test data.
In this waste,
so if you say it goes crazy,
because?
Yet while we're checking that register over and over and over again to see if they're tackling a year and you data,
you are not using those cycles to run it on an application and before and what you're seeing is that you know if there's nothing here basically to a kernel which to shout to sleep so that another application could run.
But do we do pulling then what did happen now for a slow device you clearly want,
you know,
not spin forever until the slides,
if I finally get around to actually doing its work.
Ah,
we really like to basically switch out into the shell and so that we can run something else.
But if the device extremely fast,
then the overhead of the interruption is high,
and we'd better off actually wasting basically pulling the device because very quickly,
we're going to get success.
And so if we should be able to devise a slow.
Butt.
But if the device is fast.
It seems safe saving your story.
Who says the old entries entering an Egypt costs?
It's over time will help you get through a high performance network cards on a wall if it's a stream of packets coming in and it actually you will use falling and more.
and the most sophisticated drivers are basically they dynamically switch.
Switch between polling and interrupts.
Okay.
Any questions.
Close to my eye,
my eye does my time.
Roger de job.
And your remaining questions?
Okay,
then I'll see you on Wednesday and visually Wednesday we're going to continue the story off currency,
and we're going to sort of have their parallels.
And we're going to see some mechanisms to actually manage the parallelism to make sure that's shared.
Data structures get them data correctly.
So I'll see you On Wednesday.
Oh,
I'm sorry,
I was trying to find where my question was because I lost my question was,
and the so I saw it.
you are in,
it is just being called once is out Y.
There is just one,
a buffer for all thee,
of course,
to share together.
Well,
there's also the only one you are device.
Other men in a critical response to the one you are device that action is being shared between all the course,
are likely to make multiple processes running on different course.
All trying to print to the console.
OK,
I see,
Oh,
yeah,
my sense,
I make sense.
like only one.
A quarrel do stuff with you are at a time.
Yeah,
well,
it's a slightly complicated,
but let's look at,
so let's say there are multiple guys writing just the forward one experiment.
correct.
Ah.
And what we see there are multiple all.
Let me actually.
So here,
if you are twitchy,
convicted,
the first thing you see is actually it actually required for lock.
So a multiple cores are trying to have put a character into it in a buffer,
and one of them is going to get to walk and none of the others were getting to walk.
That's about one guy you know the one sea view that actually got to lock her quiet.
A lot successfully is able to go in and look at the write pointer.
Stick a character in it and if possible,
and otherwise go to sleep.
and then if it's done,
you know,
religious,
the moc and in the next you know a coworker can go in and acquire the lock into its work.
And so basically these lock and civilize the concurrent access to New York.
That makes sense.
Yeah,
thank you.
On Wednesday,
we'll talk in detail about locks.
Thank you.
Any further questions.
I have a question.
So I,
as far as I understand why we need the lock inside the interrupted because me there's only one console and they can be multiple.
Cores lights.
You mean the words this luck,
I think so right because usually we don't want to lock things inside interrupts right.
Yeah,
yeah,
you asked this question by email.
Yes,
the economy is that the US has mentioned earlier the bottom half.
During the interim,
Henry could run in parallel with the top half,
and so one core.
if you could be doing you are Pucci and another core could be used in running.
You are an inner.
We've got to make sure that they sort of don't get tangled up together so that they shared.
Realize correctly in the lock basically ensures that they get serialized OK.
that makes sense.
That does mean that sometimes like all course could potentially be waiting for one of them to be handling this right.
Is the integral test the weight and that nothing else can get scheduled?
Oh,
well,
I'll get to bloom into.
Some other process may be running.
It's unlikely there's no deadlock.
OK.
There is a risk of Denmark.
that's not this one we'll talk about on Wednesday.
Butt.
Recently,
one of these means,
like if there's multiple guys.
I told you I could see in the buffer pool,
then some point is interrupted.
The actual release didn't walk.
So,
for example,
let's go back to your Gucci.
What actually,
what happened,
Greg is that they will call sleep and sleep actually takes the walkers and are an argument,
and we'll see later why.
But internally,
before sleep actually puts the process definitely to sleep and will release the lock.
Oh,
I see,
so basically you call sleep with the law,
and then that means okay.
Release the law while you sleep with so someone else does them.
It's like an interesting.
Your name when you return from sleep,
you just read it again.
You get to walk back as bright,
bright media fast asleep has a separate story that we'll talk about in a week or two weeks.
Then I said,
Yeah,
so I guess.
So I guess I wasn't that clear to me until she feels.
get interrupted when somebody you like to send something through you are no well depends depends on how you program the bleak the way you actually six US program to places that only one seat for you.
I'll see if you might get interrupted.
One is going to clean the interrupt.
Okay,
so if you go back to the place you know when you're going to get an interrupt,
you and you call display claim,
and that's if you knew that particular quarter is going to get the,
it's going to get their dire que.
and basically the bleak will remember that no.
then I accused him of being served and won't give it to anybody else.
I see OK,
so we'll just one of them will get it randomly or no.
Ah,
you can program to place.
You could say maybe predators.
Once all I see the blood I see as he saw inside that.
yeah,
inside the plague,
as the code that actually the size and who they recruited bother.
If you had to pick a shirt,
but there's no code in the public,
I think you know it's all.
Yeah,
alright,
OK,
if you prove it.
Yeah,
I've grown up,
OK?
Yeah,
I was just going to say,
Where does the play cold run by?
Yeah,
it's not called its hardware.
I'll get that make sense.
All right,
thanks,
I'll see you.
On Wednesday.
So I've got a question and related to the thinking about multiple cores running at the same time,
so I think I,
we're calling them one of them to the labs with say,
the crime suppression actually liked interleaves style.
But often is that because the locks are only around,
like the policy,
not at the glitzy caused from multiple course could interleave,
meaning that,
like a single print,
cash is not guaranteed to be a tensor You got it.
I thank you.
I have a quick question,
so I remember reading that the meeting said something about the timer interrupts being handled in machine learning,
and I was wondering where that was handled.
When we're doing the chops up.
I'm like what were they switch to?
Machine mode was happening during the chops lab and then what we were doing.
Yeah,
that's a great question,
so I'm pulling up the code.
So if you look at your star to correct and dessert,
Start rooms in edit mode at the beginning of time,
when the machine boots and IT programmes the time of chip,
your time,
reading it and the time read,
it basically prevents the plate of the Clint,
which is the local interrupter to generate interrupts when a clock interrupt happens and and basically years,
probably the most important function here it sets the machine will trap him or to dysfunctional timer back so there's written assembly and when a timer interrupt happens,
that function is being called.
and so when you're a kernel,
running in user mode or in supervised mode and cleaned,
generates and interrupt,
raises the line and it will switch to machine mode and call this function time effect in same way,
basically as almost equivalent to what we have seen for supervisor mode and user mode.
OK,
and then if you look in awe,
Colonel Vic done s.
We looked a girdle back a lot like me.
They'll start function to saving stores a lot and he hears timer event.
Basically,
the same sort of type of idea that sees a couple of registration that it could do a job and the only job does not actually have these sort of six lines of code here or whatever five satellites code,
and this is what it does so using a reprograms too claims to generate future interrupts,
and invisibly,
raises a software interrupt to the supervisor.
So this goes to supervise a moat.
OK,
so then at the point and Internet can emerge.
Let's say the colonel was interrupted during a time of chip,
though at a time a chip so we went to machine,
moods and red,
then returned from machine,
moved back to supervise a moat and if interrupts,
enabled and supervise a moat.
And that point,
maybe that supervisor in the supervisor refer in.
Europe will be generated.
Oh,
OK,
I'll go.
Basically.
The kernel does the same thing.
Grant Mitchell.
He would go to Colonel back.
You know,
save restore all the registers and ah,
and then go to Colonel Trap and the kernel trend,
we'll see how there was a time when interrupt.
I see,
and so what was the point of switching to machine code in the first place?
What exactly does it do?
I don't know what the point is,
but this is actually going through a little bit.
There's some reason to think why the temperature textbooks,
machine mode,
but from our perspective,
it would be great if you could have delegated to the time or in the refrigerator,
treat to supervise your mode and never had to deal with a time.
But that doesn't work for this article,
chip and exempt.
Thank you so much for your welcome.
Fall off on this to keep us in persons.
Please.
Yeah,
I saw it in algebra two.
You went sixty forest.
but it only seems to be using for no three of them.
Right,
it's hard to see a scratchy access.
It allocates more than is necessary scratches fruity to scratch area the region,
so.
Ah,
so for every shampoo correct,
there has to be some scratch space because we have three or something like that,
she views showed basically allocate a little bit too much.
But there's no harm in allocating too much.
Okay,
oh,
he's like you don't scratch zero.
Scratch one's crashes ill with a little wine,
so it uses free.
OK,
so if you were to free,
that's for four or five groups of six and a six hundred years,
and because we have been running,
we could run before she'd be used,
but we're running with free,
but we could run it for six hundred,
forty and twenty four like a skater.
This,
whatever allocating a bit too much memory.
I don't remember,
I've thought about this a while back and go,
and I don't remember exactly where there.
For the two came from.
On the double check.
See if I can reconstruct that.
Over the same period,
there are four,
after all,
a bicycle to work.
Yeah.
And it.
I don't want to let me get back to you.
I can recall writer to top my head.
You know why it is the way it is.
Okay,
thank you so much.
You want a good question.
Thank you.