Alright, actually, it's time to start.
Alright, okay as Franz were saying for you, feel free to interrupt with questions
and feel free to leave your camera on,
so that we can see each other people.
This is going to be another lecture about logging,
this time a case study of the current logging sys- system in Linux is ext3 file system,
which is extremely widely used
and will try to dip into some of the kind of real-world design problems,
that a high performance file system has to deal with,
when it adds logging to the file system.
I'm just gonna go spend a few minutes,
basically reviewing why we're talking about logging,
the reason, that we feel logging is pretty important is that,
it's been a tremendously successful and important idea,
it's almost like logging is kind of a magic way
to add crash recovery to any almost any existing storage system.
Sort of, in many ways pretty orthogonal to whatever it is, you're actually trying to store
and so you see logging applied in a huge number of different storage situations,
certainly databases and file systems,
but also many very specialized systems that need to store things and recover after crashes,
you also see logging used a lot in distributed systems,
as a way of organizing the recovery from failure,
because among other things logging is a structured way of saying,
well here's all the things that happened just before the crash
and if we can understand them, then maybe we can recover from the crash more easily.
Plus there's a huge amount of interesting stuff to chew on,
when you try to build high performance logging systems.
And as I mentioned a few minutes ago,
just as a point of terminology when we talk about log,
it's talking about this exactly the same thing as today's reader,
reading was talking about when it said use the word journal, they're just synonyms,
and furthermore the today's reading talked about adding a journal to ext2,
the modern name for the resulting file system is ext3,
which is how I'm going to refer to it.
Okay, I want to spend, the way I'm going to talk about ext3 is by contrasting it to some extent with xv6
and explaining ways in which ext3 fixes some performance problems, that xv6 logging has
and along the way changes a few of the semantic of, what happens during crashes.
Alright, so this is xv6 log review, should remember,
this disk, the file system disk for xv6, there's you know you can think of it as having two parts,
it's got a file system tree on it, with a root directory
and under the root directory, maybe there's other directories
and in those, this might be directory one and directory two,
we can think of this as file system is just a data structure, is a tree structure data structure,
may be it has files, sitting in the directories
and each file has a block number of a bunch of blocks in it
and there's some other data, that's not really tree structure,
like, there's the bitmap, in that indicates for every block, whether that block is you know free or allocated.
And the inodes and the directory contents and the bitmap blocks are going to refer to as metadata,
contrast blocks that hold file content which we'll call file content blocks.
Okay, so in addition to the file system,
xv6 log near the beginning of the disk
and xv6 log is relatively simple,
it has this header block, and then some number of blocks,
that contain updated versions of blocks from the file system data blocks and metadata blocks.
And in this [initial] header block, there's a block numbers,
where these blocks in the log ought to be written to,
like maybe the first one should go to block 17 and then 29, who knows whatever it maybe
and then in the computer, we have some user process, that's maybe calling write, create,
some other system call that modifies the file system.
And, there's a block cache in the computer and initially the writes just go to the block cache.
It's just copies of a block from the disk,
so initially write updates file blocks or inodes or whatever,
those writes go there, and then at the end of an operation,
these blocks are copied to the log and when we've copied all the blocks log,
then we write the block numbers to the header block,
to indicate that a this transactions [worth of] updates is complete
and in the code for the file system, you'll see,
that every system call that modifies the file system,
somewhere has a begin_op which says about to start a group of updates to the file system,
please don't do any of them until I finished,
so we have and then there's a bunch of blocked reason writes
and then end_op, which tells the file system logging system completely done all the writes I'm gonna do,
so between the begin_op and the end_op, the writes only go to the cache
and when the system call makes this end_op call,
then the file system copies, the modified blocks from the cache into the log.
And after it's written all these modified blocks into the log,
only then does the file system write the block numbers in a single disk, right, to the header block.
And that's called the commit point, this is the point before the file system wrote these blocked numbers to the header block,
if the crash had happened, then none of these writes would have been applied, after the crash and reboot.
After the file system writes these block numbers of the header block,
after that disk [write] is complete,
then it's guaranteed that even if there's a crash at this point, the recovery software will look at the log,
see that there's block numbers in the header block
and write all these blocks that are mentioned in the header block to their home locations in the file system.
And so what's going on here is a technique to allow all of the writes,
that happen in the system call between the begin_op and the end_up to be atomic with respect to crashes,
that is either all of them happen,
because the file system got as far as writing the header block before the crash
or none of them happened, because the crash happened before the file system wrote the header block.
And so it's important that after a crash and restart,
there's some recovery software that runs that reads the log,
looks at the header block and decides is the header block actually block numbers in it or not,
if it does, writes possibly rewrite all these blocks to their home locations,
if the header blocks doesn't have any blocked numbers in it, then the recovery software does nothing.
Any questions about this quick review.
Okay, there's a couple of super important points,
to remember about xv6 and indeed most logging systems.
One is that xv6 all logging systems, essentially obey what's called the write-ahead rule.
That is whenever you have a bunch of writes done by some operation
and those writes all need to be atomic,
the system has to write all of these updated, all the updated data to the log,
before it is allowed to apply any of those updates to the home locations in the file system,
that is that we're required to sort of pre declare all the updates that we want to have the atomic,
pre declare them in the log, before we can apply any of them to the file system,
as called the write-ahead rule.
This is really the foundation of how logging allows crash recovery.
So the write-head rule allows this collection of updates to appear atomic with respect to crashes,
there's another rule I haven't talked about, which is that we can't free or reuse the log,
you know we xv6 use the log over and over again ones for every system call,
we cannot allow to reuse the log, until all of the writes that are in the log have actually been written to their home locations on the disk.
So this is also what I called freeing rule,
which says, we can't overwrite or reuse the log until, or the part of log that holds a particular transaction,
you know set of writes that need to be atomic,
we can't reuse that part of the log until all the writes that are not part of the log,
all of them have been reflected into the actual home location in the file system,
so the deal in xv6 that, what end_op does actually triggers a whole lot of work first
and the file system, you know as I mentioned writes all the blocks, the log writes the header log, writes the header block,
and then the file system writes all these blocks their home locations,
this is assuming no crash which is the ordinary case,
so then the file system, write the second time you know all these blocks to the home locations on the disk,
and then after all the home locations have been updated,
only then does the file system go xv6 file system, erase these blocked numbers from the header block,
to indicate that we're done with this transaction and we can reuse the log
and it's critical to erase the block numbers, before writing anything new to the log,
because we wouldn't want to be in a position,
where there were some block numbers from a previous transaction in the header, but blocks from a new transaction,
presumably different block numbers sitting in the log,
because then a crash would might apply these contents to the stale block numbers left over in the header block,
so if you erase the header block first,
so this is freeing rule that says before we're allowed to erase a transaction from the log,
we have to write all these blocks to the file system.
Okay, so the net effect of this is to make file system updates,
which can be complicated and require many writes
and the net effect is to make each system call essentially be atomic,
all its writes are none of them with respect to crashes.
Okay, so, so the sort of bridge to Linux is
logging scheme, is the question of what's wrong with xv6 logging,
why doesn't Linux just use exactly the same scheme, the xv6 does.
And the answer is basically that it's slow, the xv6 scheme is quite slow,
every system call, before a system call like write or create can return in xv6,
all of this stuff I just talked about has to complete,
so before your file creation system call can return to user space,
the has to finish all the stuff that end_op does,
which means write every block to the log, write the header block,
write all those blocks to the locations here,
and erase the header block,
and then you can return.
And during that time, not only does each system call take a long time,
but nothing else could happen in the file system,
while any system call is committing and then writing its blocks to their home location,
so the system calls really occur one at a time
and each system call requires many disk writes.
And the technical term for every system call has to wait for all of its disk writes to complete is called synchronous.
Um, this, probably spelled differently from that.
Anyway xv6 system call are synchronous with respect to describe,
so they're very very slow, and they were horribly, so with mechanical hard drives,
because each write you know basically take ten milliseconds,
we're talking about many writes for system calls,
so xv6 could only do a few file system modifying system calls for a second.
And I wonder if we ran xv6 solid state drive to be faster,
but still not nearly as efficient as it could be.
Another more detail thing to notice about this is that every block is written twice in the xv6 scheme,
it's written once to the log and then at second time to the disk.
And so this is also something that, there's good reasons for that,
but it's something that ext3 partially fixes.
Okay, so on the Linux is, under the today's reading and it's sort of,
I'm going to talk about the this ext3 file system,
which is what the today's reading had turned into a few years later after a bit more development,
and was widely used.
Okay, so ext3, it's actually a modification previous log lists file system,
so they really did play this game of taking existing storage system
and sort of layering logging on top of,
it in a way that left the underlying ext2 file system, almost unmodified although not quite,
so in a sense, the logging was a very kind of easy,
you know this principle, easy upgrade for them,
ex3 keeps data structures that are similar to xv6's,
in memory, there's a block cache, a write back cache,
there's a bunch of cache blocks,
some of them are clean in the sense that they have been modified, since you know identical to what's on the disk,
some of them dirty, the sense that they've been written to, since they were read from the disk
and some of them were pinned and that they're not allowed to be written back to disk,
because of the write back rule, I mean because of the freeing rule, the write-ahead rule,
ext2 also [cause] maintain some transaction information,
you can maintain information actually about multiple transactions that are concurrently in different stages of execution,
so, there might be a number of different transactions that the ext3 system is,
keeping track of each one, each transaction has a sequence number,
a set of block numbers that the transaction system is logging system is remembering are blocks modified by that transaction,
so these are set of block numbers.
And this really refers to cache blocks,
because any modifications at least initially you know happen only in the cache.
And then a set of what are called handles,
which are information about system calls that are still concurrently executing
and as part of this transaction and reading and writing cache blocks.
And on the disk, on the disk, just like xv6 there's the usual file system tree,
inode directory blocks and files and whatnot,
and there's bitmap blocks indicating, you know whether each block, is data block is allocated or free
and so these are what I'll be calling the home locations of file system blocks
and then on a sort of designated part of the disk, there's the lock.
And so, so far this is pretty similar to xv6,
the main difference is the ext3's ability to keep track of multiple transactions at the same time in different stages of their execution.
Now I want to look more closely at what's inside the log in ext3,
is a bit different from what's in the xv6 log.
There's a log format,
at the beginning of the log, there's something called the super block,
and the super block, this is the log super block different from the file system super block.
The log super block contains the offset and sequence number of the first valid transaction in the log,
so it's gonna have an offset, just a byte number, block number in the log
and then this lo- sequence number, remember I said that every transaction has its own sequence number,
and then the rest of the log, the log is just a bunch of sequential blocks on disks of a known size.
Every transaction, the rest of the log consists of transactions, each transaction consists of a descriptor block,
which contains block numbers just as in the, much like the header block in the xv6
and then the set of, for each of these block numbers, the actual updated content block, corresponding that block number
and then finally for transaction that's actually finished and committed,
they'll be a commit block, this is a separate block in the log,
and because there can be more than one transaction log
that commit block may be followed by the next transaction's descriptor block
and then some data blocks
and then maybe the next transmission, transmission's commit block.
So we have multiple, log file can be quite long and contain many transactions in it.
So this we can think of this offset and sequence numbers basically between them,
pointing to at the very, the first the beginning of the earliest lowest numbered valid transaction log.
A little detail here that will become important a little while,
is that these the descriptor blocks and the commit blocks,
in order to be able to help distinguish them from data, from data blocks,
if when they're scanning log after a crash and recovery,
the description of the commit blocks start with a magic number, which is just some 32 bit number,
that is unlikely to occur in data,
and that helps the log software distinguish descriptor and commit blocks from data blocks.
Okay, with this in mind, with this structure in mind,
I'm going to talk about the high-level the ways, that ext3 gets good performance.
And there's really three main.
But, a question,
is it possible for at least this system to have a descriptor block before they commit block,
let's say two transactions going on at the same time.
There can be multiple transactions in the log.
That's a transaction to finish before the next one can start.
Yeah we're talking a moment about that,
but it is the case, yes, that there's there's only one open transaction at a time,
and this is really not quite the right picture for that,
because the current open transaction, the current open transaction is the transaction into which system calls are performing their writes
and so the current open transaction really only exists in memory,
and because current system calls are sort of updating,
their just updating block the cached block file system blocks in memory,
when the ext3 system decides to finished the current open transaction,
you know after it decides to finish it, it'll do two things,
one is it will start a new open transaction which will be the next transaction
and it will then write the the just finished transaction, start writing with just finished transactions to disk, may actually take quite a while,
so, so you know the full story is that there's a bunch of older transactions on this,
that all of which are closed plus one open transaction really only exists in memory.
And at least initially, these transactions that are on disk, may only exist in the form of the log records
and haven't initially at least been written to their home locations
and then after a while in the background, the starting with the oldest transaction,
the logging system will you know write these, update blocks in the log to their home locations
and then once that's been done for each complete transaction,
then the logging system can free and reuse this space in the log
and so this is really a circular log,
when you get to the end of the log, the logging system start using the blocks at the beginning
and you have to free them, free these blocks by writing them to their home locations before it can be used.
Okay.
Okay, so there's three ways that the system gets ext3 gets good performance,
one is that it has asynchronous system calls, that is system calls return before they've written the disk,
the system call just updates cache blocks in memory, and then returns,
never never has to write the disk, never has to wait for disk writes,
although may wait for disk reads.
The next big idea for performance is batching,
we can batch many system calls into a single transaction.
And the final big idea for performance is concurrency.
And these are all the things, these are basically the things that ext3 does, that xv6 doesn't do.
Okay, so I'm gonna talk about each one of these three performance techniques.
Oh, sorry I wanted to ask about batching,
xv6 allow for there to be multiple system calls that do start_op end_op, like at kind of the same time,
so then they will commit together.
Yeah, that's true, xv6 is a limited amount of batching.
Right, thank you.
OK, so first asynchronous system calls,
this just means the system calls return, but they were modified blocks in the cache then return,
don't particularly, don't trigger disk writes.
So this has the obvious advantage of the system calls return quickly,
it also allows for IO concurrency, that is, the application can make some file system system calls,
that imply that the file system to do a bunch of disk operations disk writes,
but the application can then return to computing at in parallel with the file system doing whatever the writes are that are required by those system calls,
so this called IO concurrency.
And without asynchronous system calls, it's hard to get IO concurrency,
hard to get overlap between disk operations and application computing,
if the applications always have to wait for the disk writes to complete.
The other thing that's nice about asynchronous system calls, is that they allow, they make it easier to do large amounts of batching,
so there's help batching.
The downside of asynchronous system calls is that,
it means that just because the system calls return doesn't mean
that the work that you, the system call ought to have done, has actually been completed,
so for example if you write a program that creates a file and write some data,
and then closes the file, and then prints done on the console to the user,
and then you pull out the power plug on your computer, have to restart the computer,
your data may not be there even though all the system calls returned
and even though the programs are just said look you know I called those system calls they returned.
And this means that in a world with asynchronous system calls,
applications have to be written more carefully,
if they if they care about their behavior with respect to crashes,
this is actually kind of a big deal in, in xv6,
if a write returned, the data was on the disk and would be there after a crash,
in ext3, if a write returns, this,
you don't know anything about what will happen after a crash, may or may not be there.
So it is possible despite asynchronous system calls to write careful programs,
like databases need to be careful,
text editors need to be careful,
if I write out a file, you know I do not want, if there's a power failure while I'm writing out a file in my text editor,
that I don't want after be starting to see garbage or a partial file
and I want to see either the old file or the new file.
And so the file system also provides some techniques for careful applications,
to get predictable behavior despite crashes,
and the main tool for that is called system called, called fsync,
which you know all unix systems have,
and what this basically says is that you pass it a file descriptor,
and it tells the file system look actually do all of the writes,
I may have called write a bunch of things and call fsync,
I now want you to actually do the writes
and don't return from this system call until the writes are on disk
and are guaranteed to be still there, if there's a crash.
So if you look at the source code for databases or text editors,
a number of other programs that really care about their data,
you'll see sort of carefully placed calls to fsync,
in order to sort of overcome this,
to fight back against these asynchronous system calls,
most programs are like your compiler, it's no big deal if a the output of the compiler goes away, if there's a crash,
there for many many programs, you don't call fsync are very happy to get the good performance of asynchronous system calls
and are not worried about their crash behavior.
Okay, so.
This is this also called like flush sometimes,
because I think that that words, I've heard that word before.
Yeah you could, a reasonable way to explain what fsync does
is that it flushes all previous writes to this file to the disk
and only returns, that flushes a reasonable world for this, flushing writes to disk.
Okay, so that's the asynchronous system calls.
The next technique, the ext3 uses is batching.
And, the game here is that, there's at any one time,
there's always one open transaction in the ex3 ext3,
a transaction in ext3 can actually hold the writes of many different many distinct system calls,
so the what ext3 does is going to start a new transaction now
and then for the next couple of seconds all system calls that execute are,
their writes are part of that one big transaction,
I think by default, ext3 only creates a new transaction every five seconds,
so each transaction may have up to five seconds worth of system calls it, all has a huge batch,
and then at the end of the five seconds,
ext3 will commit this single big transaction that may have hundreds of updated blocks in it,
commit this transaction to this, [] as a single transaction.
And so the reason why this is a win,
first of all, it spreads some fixed transaction costs,
amortizes some fixed transaction costs across many system calls,
so for example you have to write the descriptor block and the commit block
and then you have to seek on a mechanical drive,
at least you have to seek and let the drive rotate to the place where the log is,
and those are significant costs and they only have to be done once for batch, instead of once per system call.
So it lowers the impact of those those costs.
The other big deal is that, another big deal is that it allows write absorption,
that is, it's often the case that you have a whole sequence of system calls,
that end up modifying the very same blocks over and over again,
so for example if I create a whole bunch of files,
I need to allocate a bunch of inodes
and that means all inodes are small, maybe 64 bytes,
so many, many inodes fit in a block,
so creating a bunch of files in a row is gonna dirty many inodes in a few blocks,
because there's many inodes for block,
similarly if I'm writing a bunch of data to a file,
I may need to allocate a lot of data blocks,
I may [h] flip many of the bits in the block free map
and if I allocate blocks that are next to each other,
their bits are going to be in the same block.
And so I may put many bits in just one block,
so many system calls again may operating the same blocks over and over again,
and in the system with batching, those many many writes the same blocks, just happen very quickly to the cached,
just the cache copies of blocks because we're not writing the disk
and then we write the those small number of blocks to the disk only once at the end of the transaction
and the single block write into the, on the writing of the log,
reflects many many system calls worth of modifications to the same block,
so this write absorption can be reduce the amount of the total number times,
we have to write the block dramatically compared to a synchronous system, like xv6.
And the final big win is dis scheduling,
in general, even if we are,
suppose we have to write a thousand blocks to the disk,
it turns out to be much more efficient, certainly in mechanical drives,
but even in solid state drives, to write a thousand blocks all at once in sequential locations,
as you would do to a log,
as much faster to do that than to write a thousand blocks, one at a time to different locations
or even a thousand blocks, you know even write the same block a thousand times in a log.
So by handing up the disk, large batches of writes to do,
this can be much more efficient,
there's also not only do we get an efficiency from writing a large number of blocks sequentially in the log,
but even when we go to write the home locations for this for a batch of writes,
resulting from a batch of operations in a single big transaction,
even then if we can hand a very large number of writes to that drive,
even if there are different locations, because there to the home locations, you know referred to by many different system calls,
if we allow the disk to schedule a large number of distinct writes,
it can pick an order to do them in,
that's particularly efficient on a mechanical drive, this would done.
Involve sorting them and sorting them by track number on the drive
and doing you know just a little seek from one to the next,
and they can do this sort, if you get all of the blocks at the same time
and but even on a solid state drive, it turns out there's a smaller winds to be gotten from keeping the disk lots of work to do.
Anyway, so this you can only really get this kind of disk scheduling,
if you have very large batches of write to give to drive,
so there's another win from batch.
Alright,,
and, a final big win from the ext3 gets concurrency,
it's really get two kinds of concurrency that it benefits from compared to xv6.
One is that it can allow many system calls to execute at the same time,
so we can have many individual system calls in parallel.
Because at least, until, ext3 decides to close out and commit the current transaction,
the system call don't have to wait for each other,
they can all modify blocks that are part of the current transaction
and all these many many system calls can execute in parallel and contribute blocks to the current transaction,
that's particularly important on a multi-core machine,
where we don't want to have the different cores, we're waiting for a lock,
in xv6 we often, it's often the case that you're not allowed, system call can't proceed,
because the current transaction is busy doing something else.
Most of the time in ext3, many system calls can modify the current transaction.
The other way that ext3 gets concurrency is that
there can be multiple transactions, older transactions in different stages of execution.
So it's true, system calls only the one open transaction can receive system calls,
but the other transactions that are writing things to disk can go on in parallel,
so many older transactions and the different sort of stages in a transaction's life, that can go on in parallel.
First there's the one open transaction,
there can be some number of transactions that are recent
and the file system is committing them,
but they're still writing their blocks to the disk,
so we have some number of transactions are currently committing to the log.
And we don't have to wait for these to finish,
that is we can continue with system calls in the new open transaction,
while the previous transactions still writing to the log hasn't actually finished, committing yet.
Of course this stage ends when the transaction writes its commit block to the disk, the log.
There can be a transactions, that are even older transactions that are writing,
they're blocks from the cache to the home locations, the modified blocks
and finally this doesn't take much work,
but there can be the oldest transactions are being freed.
This doesn't really take work itself,
the work is, it's really writing a transactions to their home, the blocks of their home locations,
but anyway there's typically multiple transactions existence in these different stages
and so in particular, new system calls can execute without waiting for older transactions
to either finish committing to the log or finish writing their blocks, their home locations,
in contrast to xv6 where new system calls had to wait for this to complete for all,
for the one previous transaction.
I have a quick question,
so how does it work, when there's an operation or when something is writing to a cache block
and the block is also being written to the disk.
OK, so there's a so that is indeed a problem,
and the, there's a potential difficulty here,
because a transaction you know, stuff that a transaction writes to the log
should only include updates made by a system calls that were in that transaction,
shouldn't include any any block updates made by system calls that came after that transaction,
because if you did, you risk sort of committing, but having the log updates that only represent partial system calls,
as we want to make sure that a transaction only contains all of any given system calls updates,
so we can't afford to have a transaction include updates made by anything that happened after the transaction started to close
and the way you see three deals with that,
is that at least notional ie, it makes a copy when it decides to wrap up the current open transaction,
it makes a copy of all the blocks for that transaction as of the time it closed out this transaction.
So it sort of makes copies of all the blocks
and then it's though that copy of the blocks that the transaction commits into its log
and any newer transactions have their own copy of that block that they modify,
it's different copy from over committing to the lock.
And in order to make this efficient the system actually uses a kind of copy on write scheme
to avoid making the copies until it actually notices that a newer transaction needs to write that block.
Cool, makes sense.
Okay.
Good, and so the the reason why concurrency helps performance again
is that it can help us if we can run system calls in parallel,
we get multi-core parallelism,
and if we can run applications and system calls at the same time,
we're writing a disk, then we can get IO concurrency that is overlap between CPU,
and CPU execution and disk IO.
And all these sort of help, use the hardware resources, the machine more efficiently more intensively.
Alright any questions about concurrency.
Alright, I want to just give you a taste of what the actual file system code,
if you look at the Linux source for the file system,
sort of somewhat abstract level,
this is the way each system call looks,
so you might have unlink system call,
and this is you know, pretty familiar from xv6,
we need to every system call needs to say, here's the beginning of the sequence of writes,
I'm about to do a sequence of writes and they need to be atomic with respect to crash.
So every system call on any transaction system,
there has to be a clear sort of begin endd,
everything between these two points needs to be atomic.
And there's a start call the system called code makes.
And it turns out that ext3 has to be aware of the different system calls that are active,
for reasons I'll explain that in a minute or two,
so every system call, when I call started actually gets what's called a handle,
this is a unique identifier of this particular system call,
and the writes that makes are logging is the file systems for keep track [echo yeah], that write,
was done by this particular system calls
and then the system call these read and write blocks
and so it makes a get hold of a block, or really a buffer a block cache buffer,
makes it get call
and it tells the handle and then the block number it needs to read or write.
Then it may do a bunch of these write if you need to modify many blocks.
And then modifies so then modify the blocks in the cache.
And when it's done, this, this particular system calls done, it makes a stop call.
And pass the handle to stop call.
So, a lot of what this is about is informing the logging system,
you know once a system call starts,
a transaction is not allowed to commit
until all the system calls that started in that transaction have finished,
so and because they're gonna be multiple transactions,
the system has to be able to assess one of the reasons for the handles,
so the system the file system can remember for each system called which transaction it was part of,
so it knows, oh and this just finishes,
that's one of the system calls a particular transaction was waiting for before it could actually commit.
We pass the handle to the get system call,
so that every system every transaction has a bunch of blocks,
that are associated with with blocks modified as part of that transaction,
so what we're saying here among as well as getting a pointer to the block
is we're telling the logging system, look this block number is part of the transaction that this handle refers to.
This stop call doesn't actually calls a commit,
it just tells that logging system look you know you have one fewer system calls that are active in this transaction.
And so a transaction can only commit, if all of the system calls that started in this transaction have called stops,
the transaction has to do some bookkeeping has remember all the handles that started,
so that it can sort of check them off as those calls finish.
So with this structure in mind, I'm just going to lay out the complete sequence
of what it takes to commit a transaction,
so you know at some point when all the,
every five seconds, the file system is going to think to itself,
oh now would be a good time to commit the current open transaction.
And so here's what happens when the, here's what's involved in the file system committing a transaction,
so these are like steps.
So first, we have to block any new system calls,
we need to have our transaction reflect only entire system calls,
so we don't want to let anything new start,
when we're trying to commit the transaction,
we want to only include system calls that have already started,
so you need to block new system calls,
there's actually another reason, I'll talk about,
why we need to block new system calls.
This is actually a little bit of a performance defect,
there's going to be a period of time here,
when system calls have to wait and are not allowed to execute,
so that's too bad.
The second step is that, there are a bunch of system calls have already started that are part of this transaction,
that we need to wait for them to finish,
so we need to wait for the outstanding system calls,
that are in this transaction.
Because of course we want the transaction to reflect all of their writes,
so we need to wait for them to finish.
The next thing that happens is you know once all the system calls for this transaction are finished,
and have done their writes into the cache,
it turns out then it's okay to start a new transaction and let these blocked system calls continue,
so now we're gonna open a new transaction for these, for any subsequent system calls,
but now this, I'm continuing the story with our original transaction which is now closed,
so remember the log next in ext3 contains descriptors and data blocks and commit blocks,
so now, we know the full set of blocks modified
by all the system calls that were in this transaction,
because they all called get with a handle,
that told us about what transactions are part of,
we know the full set of modified blocks for this transaction,
so now we can write a descriptor block,
that has all the block numbers for all the blocks dirty to this transaction.
We're also going to write the actual modified blocks from the disk cache into the log
and in fact if somebody somebody asks a question about oh what happens if the next transaction modifies this,
what we're actually writing in this stage is the sort of saved copies of this transactions blocks as of the time when it finished.
So I'm gonna write the actual blocks to the log.
Now, we're gonna wait for these wights to finish.
These need to finish, Before we can proceed.
Once the descriptor and the data blocks are guaranteed to be on the disk,
then we can write the commit record to the log.
And once that write is finished, we have to wait for it to finish.
So we're waiting for the waiting for the commit write to finish,
at this point, once the commit write is finished,
this transaction, with the sort of technical term is that this transaction has reached its commit point
that is, it's guaranteed the writes and transaction are guaranteed to survive a crash at this point,
if the crash had occurred before this before writing the commit block,
the writes of the transaction would not appear after a crash and reboot
and running the recovery software,
if a crash occurs now after the commit point after the commit block has written to the disk,
then they're guaranteed to those writes all the writes in the transaction are guaranteed to appear after crash reboot and recovery.
Okay, and now not, only now, in the background all this kind of happened in the background,
no process was really waiting for this stuff,
now we can write the transactions blocks to their home locations in the file system.
And, I ll talk about in a few minutes after all of these writes have completed,
for all the blocks that are part of this transaction,
then only then can we reuse that part of the log.
So in a very busy system,
if the head of the log catches up with the tail,
there may actually may not be able to start a new transaction
until all of these writes have finished for the oldest transaction,
because we may need log space, so we won't,
we may need to reuse the oldest transaction log space,
we have to write for it to write all the cache cache blocks their home locations,
this usually you, people try to make the log big enough, this happens pretty rarely,
so that this stuff can go on in the background.
Any questions about these steps.
Oh sorry, where are those run.
That's why.
We write for, doing this file system stuff.
Oh, so you said that no process is waiting for those things to get done,
so where, where are they scheduled where they run.
Oh, there's a background thread, ss a background thread, in the kernel dedicated.
Thank you.
I get question actually about reusing part of the log,
so let's, let's say eventually we start using a particular section of log, and lo-, the that particular, as I think just mentioned,
that particular log of particular part of the log actually in my new transaction, actually,
end up using the whole log part was just freed up
and there's nothing else, there's number space for the log,
but the log then like with the system just wait
until the another portion of log is freed up,
or would it do something else to.
Yes, it'll wait,
let me though, let me just draw a picture
to help me make sure I'm answering the right question here,
we can think of the log as just this, [] [] part of the disk
and any given time, you know maybe maybe the oldest valid transaction is you know t7,
then there's t8 in this region and we have t9
and we want to start,
you know, we want to put t10 here.
The.
Let's see what one you know, we'd like to start a new transaction put it here.
The, we may have to wait for t7 to write all it's blocked to their home locations,
so that we can free it.
And that may mean that the transaction stuff in transaction ten may have to pause,
waiting for this space in the log to free up.
Is that what you're talking about?
Yeah, so let's say that,
so it could be the case at the beginning,
you can put in blocks for a transaction ten in the actual free space right now,
but eventually, if log grows big enough, it's just going to run out of free space
and at that point it's just going to wait for transaction seven to.
Yes.
Be recorded, OK.
Yes yes, certainly if there's enough activity going on
and the log wraps around quickly enough,
you may end up having to wait for a new new system calls,
we may not even be able to start the system calls,
because before we can free up space in the log for the blocks that they're going to modify
and you know if you care about the details of this it turns out there's some potential deadlocks here.
That require that mean ext3 ends up, system calls have to pre declare how many blocks they're going to need,
so that the logging system knows, how much,
you can reason about whether or there's enough space for this transaction,
because we don't want to allow a transaction to start that,
we wouldn't actually be able to commit into the log.
Okay.
Let's let's say it's the new log or the new transaction you're trying to put,
goes to like eight transaction and eight,
so you will have to wait for seven and eight right,
so how does that work.
You mean, okay so, it's transaction seven and transaction eitht transaction nine at least in this diagram have all completed
or that all the system calls have finished.
And these transactions are committed in the log, because these are the old transactions.
So, in this picture at least we're just starting transaction ten.
And so new system calls are going to be writing into a transaction ten.
Right, but you said that, transaction ten is not big enough to fill that space,
so you need to free transactions seven right,
you need to wait for that to like commit to disk.
Yes.
But what happens if you if it's, if ten is like bigger than like seven like it goes to eight transaction.
We have to wait for to, yeah, we may have to wait for,
however big transaction ten is, you know we need, we need enough space on the disk to fit
and not enough space in the log to fit
and so indeed if transaction ten and it turns out being big,
it may need to force multiple transmit multiple of the oldest transactions to write to their home locations
and free themselves.
I guess how, how does code for that work,
like does it just run through how big it is
and like say hey there's a transaction here and a transaction here
and it's like I have to wait for both of them.
The file system knows, knows how big all the transactions in the log are.
And it remembers and remember,
I mean actually the file system remembers quite a bit about each of these older transactions,
it knows for each one whether it's written,
for file system keeps track of for every block in all of each of these older transactions
whether it has written that block to the home location.
So that it can know, oh I've written it could know whether or not.
And recognize the point at which is finished writing all the transactions seven blocks are transactions these blocks,
so there's quite a lot of bookkeeping going on here.
After the file system to understand in detail the state of every old transaction.
Okay.
Okay, so, indeed there's there's on the topic of how to reuse log space,
there's one little detail here that needs to be said,
if you remember at the beginning of the,
let me let me writing diagram,
is actually a super block though, log super block at the beginning of the log.
And so in any given time, you might have the log super block,
and then, some set of transactions.
You know, maybe those transaction four which is the newest transaction
and then a transaction one, the older transactions,
so what this means is that, of course the log is wrapped around.
And you know the, yeah, the rule for whether we could reuse a part of the log,
now I've mentioned this project want to say it again
is that we can reuse the log so we can reuse this part of the log,
that transaction two is in, if t2 has committed
and all of t2 blocks have been written to their home locations in the file system,
so that there can never be any need after a crash replay.
These blocks, right.
And if all transactions prior to transaction to have also been freed.
So if those conditions are all true,
then we can free and reuse the part of the log that t2 sits in,
so we can only use t2 and after t2 is after t1 has finished all committing and writing its blocks to log in to the home locations also,
and then this super block for the convenience of the recovery software after a crash,
now if we decide that we can, if the file system decides it can free and reuse a particular part of the log,
it rewrites the super block to super block as a pointer to the begin the first transaction log
and so as part of freeing part of the log,
file system modifies a super block point to the new beginning of the of the now oldest transaction in the log.
And then there's crash, at the recovery software reads the super block, finds the beginning log.
Okay, so if there's a crash, of course a crash, causes everything in RAM to evaporate,
so all that bookkeeping that the file system is keeping about what blocks have been written to the home locations,
that's all lost if there's a crash or power failure,
however so that one of the assumptions is there's nothing useful in RAM,
the only stuff that's can be preserved across the crash is whatever's on the disk,
but we are absolutely in all these discussions about logging,
assuming that the disk is completely intact,
that nothing went wrong with the disk.
So, so maybe the right model for you to think in terms of is that there was a power failure,
that everything was humming along and then the power failed,
the system just stopped at some point
and the disk is after power is restored, this just has whatever it had on it, at the point of the power failure.
So we're absolutely not considering situations
in which the disk was somehow corrupted or destroyed by the crash.
And so the crash of course may interrupt,
yeah whatever transactions were in the middle of committing are not yet committing yet
or whatever the crash may interrupt,
either the commit of a transaction or the writing of a transactions blocks into their home locations.
So, what that means is that the on disk log,
when the power is restored and recovery sufferers run,
it's going to have a bunch of complete transact older complete transactions,
you know may be t1 and t2.
Let me take a new example for for recovery.
Let's say we have the again the super block.
And, maybe at the time of the crash,
the oldest transaction was t6 and then there's t7,
then we wrapped around still before the crash t8 and there was a t5,
but t8 has, let us imagine has started has overwritten the first part of t5,
because t5 was, we know that t5 was freed before the crash,
but the recovery software doesn't necessarily know that.
And let's say the super block points to t6 as being the start of the oldest valid transaction,
t5 is free.
We're going to reboot with an attack disk,
the recovery software reads the super block
and so then it knows the where the beginning of the log is
then the recover software's going to scan forward in the log
to try to find the end of the log.
We need to have a way for it,
to actually figure out, oh you know that's the end of the log,
the way it does that, is we know that every transaction consists of a descriptor block
that indicates how many data blocks are on the transaction,
such as descriptor blocks says, oh yeah there's 17 data blocks
and we expect 17 data blocks and finally commit record.
And then another descriptor record
and then the number of data blocks implied by the descriptor block
and then another commit block,
and so the log software in the scan forward, maybe t6 and t7 are fine,
then it's going to look at t8 t8 got some descriptor block.
And, then the recovery suffers gonna look forward to where the end of transaction,
it should be and look for a commit block
and so there's a couple of things that may have happened here,
it could be that transaction it did commit
and that the recovery software finds the commit block,
it'll then look for another you know it doesn't know that transaction is last transactions needs to figure that out,
so it's going to look at the very next block
to see if this is a valid descriptor block,
now we know that this block was really just a random block in the middle of transaction five
and not a descriptor block at all,
then the question is how can the recovery software reliably distinguish between oh this is a, just some data block in the middle of an old transaction
or it's the maybe the descriptor block for transaction nine.
Any guesses for a reliable method to do that.
Is that the magic number.
Yeah.
Or is there just a reserved bit.
There is indeed every { descriptor commit block starts with some magic number,
just just a 32 bit value, that the recovery software is looking for,
I don't actually know what it is,
so, definitely the game is that we come to the end of transaction eight
if the very next block starts with the magic number,
then the recovery software's gonna assume that oh this is a valid descriptor block.
Could you, sorry quick question,
would it be unreliable to try to like, interpret it as a descriptor block,
try to read the number of data blocks that specifies them,
like see if there's a commit block at the expected location after the number of blocks.
Well certainly if this log does look like a descriptor block,
then it will skip forward and try to read the corresponding commit block,
and if that commit block doesn't look like a commit block with the right magic number,
it will not believe in this transaction.
The the the the the thing that's one little remaining detail here,
is that this block that we're looking at here and we're wondering
or the recovery software wondering if it's a descriptor block,
this could be just a block right in the middle of transaction five containing any arbitrary bit pattern,
it could be just like the data block from a file
that just happens to begin with the magic number.
So you know as a final detail,
the logging system needs to be able to distinguish between a valid descriptor block that starts with this magic number
and just some data block that starts with the magic number.
And you can imagine various ways of doing that,
in fact what ext3 does is whenever it's going to write a block to the log,
that's not a descriptor blocker or commit block,
if that block starts with the magic number it replaces that with zero
and sets a bit corresponding to that block in that transaction descriptor block,
then that bit means this particular data block started with the magic number and we replace it with zero.
And then if the recovery software ever needs to replay that block,
so let's say transaction eight had one of these blocks that originally started with the magic number,
it's going to set the bit this magic flag,
corresponding that block and the descriptor block and replace magic number was zero,
if recovery has to replay this block,
it'll see that flag and before replaying this block to its home location
will replace the zero with the magic number.
And therefore, no block other than a descriptor or commit block can possibly start with a magic number,
in this logging system.
So we never have this ambiguity,
if the block after a commit block, starts with a magic number,
then it must be a descriptor block.
Okay, alright,
so recovery, we were doing recovery,
it starts at the block,
that the super block says is the beginning of the oldest transaction scans forward,
and it'll scan forward until you, you know it,
look at the descriptor or is their corresponding commit block
and it'll stop as soon as it sees oh the block following a commit block wasn't a descriptor block at all,
or yeah the block following a commit block is a descriptor block,
but the what should have been the corresponding commit block,
is not in fact a valid commit block, doesn't have the magic number,
so at that point it will stop, recovery software with clear the log to have ended,
at the point where the last valid commit block.
And we'll ignore there may be a partial transaction after this,
that started to come it didn't finish,
but the recovery suffer ignores that partial transaction,
because it doesn't have all the writes,
so it can't restore it atomically,
and then the recovery software will go through go back to the beginning of the log
and replay each block, rewrite each block to its home location,
all through the log, to the last, up to the last valid commit block.
And then it can restart the rest of the operating system,
start the rest of the operating system and ordinary programs can run,
before recovery finishes, you can't you can't run any programs,
because the file system isn't valid.
Any questions about recovery.
I I have a quick question,
I think you mentioned this before, but what parts of this logging transaction scheme is missing, in xv6.
The main thing it's missing in xv6 is the ability to have multiple transactions in the log,
so xv6 there's only ever at most one transaction in the log
and so you you can't you don't get this concurrency in xv6,
where while I'm executing system calls from transaction seven,
you know that are going to go into transaction seven in parallel,
with that ext3 can be committing transactions six to the disk.
That's not available of concurrency, is not possible in ext-, in xv6,
because the the log holds just one transaction,
so we have to completely do all the work for one transaction,
before we're allowed to start anything with the next transaction.
So it's correct and simple, but you don't get a lot of parallelism out of xv6.
Okay, thank you,
are you saying that, it can still have multiple transaction blocks,
but it just can't execute them asynchronously, would that be correct.
xv6?
xv6.
Yeah it, it only has the, once it decides to,
I mean the picture a little bit confused,
because xv6 can allow more than one system call into a single transaction,
so xv6 does have some of this can concurrency in it,
and some of this batching,
but once xv6 decides to start committing a transaction,
it has to completely finish with that transaction,
committed to this, you know write the header block write the blocks to the home locations
and then erase the transaction from the log,
it has to do all that stuff before it can execute any new system calls.
Because there's nowhere you know there's nowhere to put the modifications for the new system calls
until the previous transaction is completely finished,
so xv6 sort of alternates between it can run a few system calls and then commit the transaction,
and then run a few more system calls,
with the can't serve overlap those to.
Alright.
ext3 can.
Thank you.
Okay, so that was a relatively straightforward part of ext3 design.
It turns out there's also a bunch of a tricky details,
a few of which I want to talk about.
So I mentioned before that you know there's an open transaction,
but when ext3 decides that it wants to close the open transaction,
it has to wait for all system calls and that transaction to finish before it.
Any trans-, any new transactions are allowed to start,
so that maybe a picture for that is that, you know we had original old transaction t1,
then there were multiple system calls executing in transaction one,
if we want to close transaction one, we have to stop accepting new system calls,
because we want to wait for the existing ones to finish before we can commit,
but until these all these system calls finished,
no new system calls are allowed to start in ext3,
so if there's some transaction two here,
nothing is allowed to happen in transaction two,
nothing allows to, system calls are allowed to start until these system calls have finished,
and only then can transaction to start accepting system calls.
So, there's a period of time here,
in which new system calls are all blocked that reduces performance,
because it could have been executing system calls but we're not allowed to,
then the question is how come ext3 doesn't allow new system calls to start in transaction two,
until all system calls in transaction one finished.
And you know it's a good question because it limits performance,
so let me give you an example if if the ext3 didn't do this,
then the following bad situation could arise.
So let's suppose transaction one says one system call in it,
and it's a create, a system called the create file,
maybe a file called x
and the idea is that before this create is finished,
the file system decides it wants to start a new transaction, open up a new transaction
and it's going to accept any system calls after the create in in this new transaction,
transaction t2 is going to say t2 starts, before t1 finishes,
and we start executing system calls now in transaction two,
maybe transaction t2 calls unlink on some other file,
well then unlink will free the inode associated with y, right,
and so maybe maybe I'm having time go this way in my diagram.
Maybe at this point in time transaction two marks the inode does free, marks the inode for y is free,
create of course has to allocate an inode for x,
maybe it allocates an inode at this point in time.
Well, because the create is allocating after the unlinked freed,
it might reuse the same inode,
so maybe x gets going to get the same inode that y had,
say maybe inode 17, right,
and then, which is OK, because unlink free [design] inode.
So, doesn't look like a problem yet,
you know the point is, we're trying to close transaction one,
so then when the create finishes, we close transaction one
and we're going to write let's say transaction actually commits,
we write all of its modifications to disk.
Fantastic, however I'm supposing after the unlink takes a while hasn't finished yet,
supposing after this commit finishes, there's a crash, right.
When the recovery software runs, it's going to see that transaction one committed,
and that transaction two didn't,
so the recovery software gonna just completely ignore transaction two,
so that means the unlink never took place it's writes,
the recovery software won't won't perform the unlink writes to the disk,
therefore won't free the inode,
won't won't delete y, after the crash and recovery while still exist, it will still be using inode 17,
however the create transaction did complete and therefore x is going to be using inode 17 as well
and so now we mistakenly have two files that happen to be using the same inode.
Which means I'll share content or write to one will mysteriously show up in the other file.
Which is completely the wrong thing, right.
The whole point was we wanted to unlink y and use a freed inode x not inode that was already in use,
so something's gone terribly wrong here.
And you know the one way of thinking about it
is that the unlink in transit in what should have been transaction to wrote a block modified a block
and essentially that modified block was used by an earlier transaction,
so a later transaction, modified a block and that modified block was seen by an earlier transaction
and indeed information base on this modification from transaction two was incorporated into transaction one.
But that means that we've lost atomicity here,
because the whole goal of this was
that all the modifications for the unlink should occur or none of them,
not just some of them,
but what's essentially happened here is
because transaction one committed the free of this inode,
it means that some of transaction to modify modifications actually occurred,
but others did not, we broke atomicity by including a later transaction's write in an earlier transaction
and you can actually imagine multiple different ways of dealing with this right,
maybe create could notice that 17 had been freed by a, you know a future transaction
and not use that inode,
in fact ext3 takes a pretty simple approach to this,
it doesn't allow any system call to start
until all system calls from the previous transaction have finished,
so there's no possibility of a transaction, a system call from transaction when seeing a modify seeing an update from a system called the future transaction.
Essentially, all of the unlink is pushed, is blocked not allowed to start until t1 commits.
Any questions about this?
So I have a question about what exactly happens when you close an open transaction,
does it like snapshot, like the current state of like the cache.
Yes, that's exactly right,
so when we close this transaction at least in principle, the system makes a copy of all the blocks, that were modified by system calls in this transaction,
logging system makes a copy of them in the cache,
sort of private copy just for this transaction commit them.
And then future transactions execute sort of on the real cached blocks,
this transaction commits from its private copy of the blocks it modified.
And then when it's done committing those it's private copy those blocks to disk,
you can throw those copies away.
Yes.
Okay,.
There's it turns out this is one of about half a dozen or a dozen sort of similar little [quirks], that ext3 has to deal with,
because in order to support concurrency, there's a whole bunch of kind of similar little ordering [nickels],
that have to be the special cases that ext3 has to get right.
Which we don't have time to talk about,
but the [take home] points that I want people to remember about logging about ext3,
first, the general point that, what logs are all about is making multi-step disk updates atomic,
all or nothing with respect to crashes,
like, yeah that's the main thing to remember about logging,
the logging the correctness of logging depends on this write-ahead rule,
it's another critical thing to remember you'll hear write-ahead log and write-ahead rule a lot in the kind of crash recovery business.
And the write-ahead rule says that you have to commit all changes to the log,
before you're allowed to make any of the modifications to the home locations in the file system.
And recovery absolutely relies on this rule,
a lot of the point at least for file systems, a lot of the point of logging is simply fast recovery,
log may have a couple hundred blocks in it,
you can replay a couple hundred blocks in way under a second
and then boom your file system,
even a very large one is now fit for use.
Now the final point for a more detailed point about the ext3 is
that it uses batching and concurrency to get considerably better performance than xv6 does,
although at the case of considerable considerably higher complexity,
to support concurrency then xv6 has.
And that's all for today, I'm happy to take questions.
Um, hi, I had another question is about,
so you said that, thinks that there's a file size like a file system thread that does all this stuff,
there must be only one of these threads, because otherwise it could it could do basically what it just talked about right.
It may indeed be that there's just one,
I actually don't know how many there are,
one is certainly a particularly attractive number,
because you know a lot of the rationale for why the logging is correct
is that you know the older transactions or you know, committed before newer transactions,
I I don't think it's a logical necessity that there be only one thread,
so you could imagine, old transactions committing in an overlapped way,
you know essentially using multiple threads one for each transaction.
Oh okay I see.
Okay I see.
I have a question,
in when you're talking about crashes
and you had that diagram of t8 rewriting t5 that was being freed,
so what happens if t8 hasn't actually committed at the point of the crash,
because there could be maybe t5 if it's being freed as something needs to rewrite it,
then there could be a commit block from t5 that exists,
it may be a location where t8 would have predicted it to exist,
and then couldn't that inaccurately represent that t8 was actually had actually been committed.
Okay, so let me try to draw out the scenario,
so we have this ancient transaction t5, right,
and, you know, maybe t3 here,
and then we're you've wrapped around t8.
And you know t8 started somewhere now it's because t5 is free, t8 is starting the [eat] up,
t5 that is the end of t8 is overrun the beginning of t5 is that.
Okay, and the worry is, OK, of course it, t8 did commit, then it'll end up in a commit block,
and it all look pretty reasonable,
if there's a crash in recovery and the scenario worried about t8 did not commit.
Right. Yeah okay, so the [juicy] yeah exactly, so t8, t8 just happens to be going to put its commit block in exactly the same place where t5 puts commit block,
but it didn't quite get the write income, it blocks all good,
except this, we have a totally correct t8,
but its t5's commit block.
Yeah.
You're wondering, gosh looks just like a commit block,
okay, the answer is that the descriptor blocks and commit blocks as well as everything else have the sequence number of the transactions,
so this descriptor block has an 8 in it,
and but t5's commit descriptor, doesn't matter, but t5 commit block has a 5 in it.
Okay, yeah.
And so yeah it's looking eight as well as the magic number.
Good question.
Wait, but in this case, wouldn't you also have the descriptor block of t5,
so you don't really need the numbers.
Well, in this particular case,
so yeah t5 used to have a descriptor block here, with a 5 in it,
however t8 is so large that t8 overwrote, this descriptor block,
with one of its own data blocks.
So that t5 descriptor blocks have gone and been replaced by t8 block.
So yeah used to be evidence for transaction five, but now it's now it's gone.
So do we know the size of transaction eight before we started.
Mhm mm, um.
Sorry, this is a complex question,
the it's probably the case that [he accept],
okay, when t8 was opened as the active transaction,
the system calls were writing into
at that point in time, the system didn't know how big t8 was going to be.
When the system starts committing t8, it does know, it does know, it does know how t8 be t8 is,
the system doesn't start committing t8 until after t8 is closed,
all of its system calls are finished.
And at that point the system knows, I mean it's all the writes that were done, all the writes for t8 have completed, all the system calls are completed,
so the system knows how big it is.
One reason why that must be is that the descriptor block holds the complete list of blocks in that transaction
and so at the time the descriptor block was written,
which is first the logging system knew how many blocks that we're going to be in t8.
Yeah.
Oh okay I see I see, thank you.
Why don't we just kind of like have the commit information into the descriptor block and avoid this kind of problem,
because I know I know it's not great that we have to go back
and like write back to the location, like not in sequence,
but wouldn't that help.
Okay so the proposal is that instead of having a commit block,
we basically have the descriptor block act as a commit block
and xv6 actually is very much like this.
And I, you know you could do it, and and and in fact I think you can do it,
without at least an ext3 without sacrificing efficiency,
however, you have to play the same, you have to structure this in the same way that xv6 does,
namely you, you, you, if there's a you have to be something in the descriptor block that indicates this is a commit transaction
and we're not allowed to set whatever that flag is, until after all of the data blocks have been written,
so the routine would have to be, we don't write the commit block first,
instead we write all the data blocks for transaction eight first,
and then we go back and write the commit block with the block numbers,
with a descriptor block, whatever it is now
and some kind of magic, this is really a committed transaction.
So we can write all the data blocks and then go back and write the commit block,
that descriptor commit block, whatever,
I don't know any, I don't know any reason why this couldn't be made to work.
It I I don't think it, it doesn't, I don't think it really eliminates any of the problems we've discussed,
because we still have this problem,
the original problem was gosh how do we distinguish this commit block,
this stale commit block from transaction 5 from a true commit block for transaction 8,
we're going to have the same problem here,
you know this it could be that what's sitting here,
you know just happens to be the descriptor block from transaction 5.
And so you know maybe we've gone ahead and written all the data blocks for transaction data and then there was a crash,
the recovery software still needs to be able to tell the difference between,
to be able to look at this descriptor block
and say wait a minute, you know there's something wrong here,
even though this looks like a valid descriptor block, it's not really.
And so we still have to have the magic number and the transaction number, the sequence number.
Oh yeah, that makes sense,
yeah I was just thinking like we'd have we kind of have like to commit part in the description block,
but obviously like when we start t8, we write the description block saying it's uncommitted,
then we write the data blocks,
then we say it's a committed [right] block, now.
The thing that could be saved here is the expense of waiting for these writes
and then writing a commit block right,
that wait is quite expensive, we're not allowed to start the write of the commit block
until the data blocks, are on the disk
and I I I don't think we have to have the same wait before we end here, in this sort of new single block scheme,
we have to have the same [] wait, before we're allowed to write this new descriptor block,
so it saves a block, but it doesn't save, I don't think I would save much time.
The trick I, the trick that later versions of the Linux file system play that,
sort of does do what I think you're hoping for.
You know the the, this is looking into the ext4 does the following for better efficiency of writing the commit blocks.
It ext4 will write out the all the data blocks and the commit block at the same time,
that is it doesn't wait for the data block writes to finish before writes the commit block,
so it doesn't have this long pause,
but then there's this terrible issue, what happens if the disk,
the disk is free to do writes out of order,
a what if the disk writes the commit block first,
before it actually performs the writes for the data blocks
and then there's a crash then we have a commit block without having to discover having written the data blocks
and the way ext4 solves that,
is it has a checksum, in the commit block,
over a checksum over all the data blocks.
And so if there's a crash happens after the commit block was written,
before the data blocks were written the checksum won't work out.
The recovery software look at this checksum and then it'll compute the checksum over the data blocks that are,
actually, in the log if they're not the same, it knows that something went wrong.
And so by doing this ext4 basically saves on a mechanical drive saves an entire rotations,
that would happen if it had to wait for the data blocks before it commits.
Okay, thanks.
Oh that's cool.
I love this stuff.
This is very cool,
I wanted to ask also about the data blocks, just the content blocks,
so I think I got confused, but where in the steps that we were talking about, on your one of your previous boards, where would that be done.
Where would which be done.
So like, not the metadata blocks, but the actual.
File content, alright, okay this is, - sort of multiple answers to this,
in ext3 has multiple modes, for what happens to the data blocks,
I think there's three two of which I remember,
there's journal data and order data, in the,
and when you configure an ext3 file system, you tell Linux which you want,
if you um ask for journal data, then file content just goes write into the log,
there's nothing special going on, if you write data to a file and that causes the inode to be updated in the,
log is gonna contain your data and the updated an inode,
you know everything, everything gets modified goes in the log, that's journal data,
but of course it's quite slow or slower than you might hope,
because you know now, if you write a whole bunch of data, it has to be written once to the log and then a second time to the home location,
so the journal data scheme is straightforward but slow.
Then there's this other order data scheme, that people that's actually the most popular mode,
avoid that doesn't write the data to the log,
in the order data scheme only metadata like inodes and directory blocks are written to the log
and file content block is just written directly to the home locations in the file system
and so it's a lot faster,
because you don't have to write the file content twice,
it does lead to more complexity though,
because if you you can't just write the file data anytime you want,
because then there's a risk that, if you don't worry about the order in which you write the inodes,
there's the file data there's the risk that you might do a write that causes a new block to be allocated for file
and have the updated inode be written into the log
and committed and then have a crash happen before you get around to writing the actual file content to the disk,
and then after recovery, what you would see is the inode with the new newly allocated data block,
but the old contents of that data block from whatever file previously used that data block,
and so if you're running a system that has multiple users like Athena system,
then it could be that one user will end up having a file that contains contents from another user's deleted file.
If we're not careful about the order in which we write the data versus the inode.
A ext3 order data mode solves this, by not committing a modified inode until after the file content has been written to disk,
so if your application and you write to a file and that write causes a new block to be allocated,
the file system will write the new file content to the newly allocated block,
and once that write is finished, only then will it commit the transaction.
That causes the inode to be updated to have the new block number
and that means that a crash, if there's a crash is going to happen between when you wrote the data, after you wrote the data and before you wrote the inode,
therefore won't reveal somebody else's old deleted data block to the new user file.
Okay I see.
Okay I see, but I could still have the data but not the inode.
Yeah you might all-.
Yeah, it was a crash after you after you wrote the data block before you wrote the inode,
then you have updated the data block, but it doesn't matter,
because not only did you not write the inode, you also did write the updated block,
free bitmap block blocks will be free and could be allocated for something else,
so would not even lose a block.
Alright, and if it's an old block, then it's still okay, right.
Say it again.
If it was just, it is the same, the same block just write some new data to it, but same block, same size, same same location,
but we already wrote like it's not that we created a new block, but in the old block, we just wrote some extra data,
but it was a little bit, so it didn't need to create anyone.
Yeah, we wrote data we ended up writing to a data to a block, that was not in use by any file, it's not visible.
Right, okay I see, thank you. Goodbye.