anyone hear me can hear you
thank you all right um i'd like to spend
today's lecture
talking about um threads and how xv6
does thread switching
this is a sort of one of our under the
hood um
lectures about x36 we've had lectures
before about how system calls interrupts
page tables and locks work um today
we're going to talk about
how it is that xv6 switches among
different processes now
the reason for this the highest level
reason for this is that people like
their computer to be able to do more
than one task
at the same time so the reason might be
that you're supporting time
sharing like a female allows many users
to log in at the same time and then you
know they can all run processes
um or even on a single user machine or
even your iphone
um you may run many different processes
and expect the computer to
to do all the things you ask of it not
just one thing
another reason that people like to
support multiple tasks
is because it can ease program structure
threads in particular today's topic
are sometimes used as a way to help
people to help programmers
put together a program in a sort of
simple elegant way to reduce complexity
and you actually saw an example of this
in the first lab with the prime number
sieve which
didn't use threads exactly but used
multiple processes in order to help
structure this your prime numbers
software and arguably it's sort of a
more convenient or elegant or simpler
way to
write that software and a final reason
why people use
threads is to get parallel speed up from
multi-core machines
so it's common to break up your program
in a way that
using threads to allow different parts
of the same program to run
on different cores and you know if you
can maybe if you're lucky if you can
split your program up to run on four
threads on four cores
you might be able to get a factor of
four speed up and how fast it runs
and indeed you can view the xv6 kernel
as a
multi-core parallel program so
what threads are is an abstraction
to simplify programming uh when you have
many tasks when you want to juggle many
tasks
so what a thread is is a you can think
of a thread as just being
a single serial execution if you just
write a program that does one thing
after another and you run that program
that you know you can view the program
as a sort of single thread of control
so um and this is a loose definition
because there's many different sort of
flavors of what people mean by threads
but we'll say it's one
serial execution so it's what you get if
you
um fire up one cpu and have it you know
just execute one instruction after
another in the ordinary way
we often talk about a thread having
state because it's going to turn out
we're going to want to save away a
thread state and restore it later
and so the right way to think about a
threat state for the most part
the most important part perhaps the
thread state is its program counter
because it's an execution we care a lot
about where is it in its execution
and what address is it executing
instructions
but also we care about the rest of the
microprocessor state that's required to
support this execution
and so that means it's um
the state of a threat includes the
registers that the compiler uses to hold
variables
and also because the just the way the
compiler generates code
a thread state includes a stack so
typically each thread has its own stack
dedicated to executing that thread and
the stack records
the record of function calls uh that the
reflect the current point in the
execution of of that thread
um and so what a threading system xv6
includes
you know a threading system inside it
what a threading system does is
manages this interleave automate the
interleaving
of multiple threads we'd like to be able
to fire up
two or four or 100 or a thousand threads
and have
the threading system figure out how to
juggle all those threads and cause them
all to make progress and all to execute
and there's really two main strategies
so we want to interleave
this is going to be a big topic here is
how to interleave threads
many threads one way to enter these
execution of many threads is to have
multiple cpus
maybe as on a multi-core processor
and then each cpu can run its own thread
so if you have four cpus
then an obvious way to run sorry four
threads is to run one thread per cpu and
then each thread automatically gets its
own
program counter and registers that is
the program counter and registers
associated with the
cpu is running on but if you have four
cpus and you have a thousand threads
then um
you know how using one corporate thread
is not going to be
enough of an answer and so so the other
main
strategy that we'll see indeed the
topic of most of this lecture is how
each cpu is going to switch
among different um threads so if i have
one cpu and a thousand threads
we're going to we're going to see how
xv6 builds a switching system
that allows xv6 to run one thread for a
while and then switch
and set aside and save the state of that
one thread and switch to executing a
second thread for a while and then the
third thread and so forth until it's
executed a little bit of each thread and
then go back and
execute more of the of the first thread
and so on
and indeed with xv6 like most operating
system combines the sex v6
will run threads on all the cores that
are available and each core will
switch among threads because there's
typical
typically although not always there's
typically many more threats than there
are
cpus
one of the many ways in which
different threading systems or instances
of threading systems
differ is in whether or not they share
memory
so this is a important
point one possibility is that
you could have a single address space
with many threads executing in that
address space and then they see each
other's changes
if one of the threads sharing some
memory modifies a variable then
the other thread sharing that memory
will see the modification
and so it's in the context of threads
running and sharing memory that we need
things like
the locks that you saw in the last
lecture
um xv6 kernel
is shared memory so xv6
there's a actually because has a
supports a notion of kernel threads
there's one kernel thread
per process that executes system calls
for that process
all those kernel threads share kernel
memory
so xv6 kernel threads do share memory um
and on the other end
xv6 is another kind of threads each user
process
essentially has a single thread of
control that executes the user
instructions for that process
and indeed a lot of the xv6 kernel
threading machinery
is ultimately in support of being able
to support and switch among
many user processes each user process
has some memory and a
single thread that runs in that memory
so xv6
user processes
each process has one thread and so
there's no
sharing of memory among threads um
within a single xp6 user process of
course you could have multiple processes
but
each of those processes is an address
space with a single thread
the processes in xv6 don't share memory
in other more sophisticated
operating systems for example linux
linux at user level
does allow multiple threads in a process
and the processes
and those threads share the memory of
that single process um
and that's super cool if you want to
write user level programs that
use level parallel programs that you
know get speed up from multiple cores
better requires sort of another it uses
you know a lot of the same basic
techniques we're going to
talk about today but there's a certain
amount more sophistication in linux to
get it to
keep track of multiple threads per
process instead of just one
okay at a sort of high level i just want
to mention
that there's other ways to support
the interleaving of multiple tasks on a
single computer
and we're not going to talk about them
but if you're curious
you can look up things like event driven
programming or
state machines and these are non-thread
techniques
to share one computer among many
different tasks
it turns out you know in sort of on the
spectrum of different schemes for
supporting multiple tasks on a computer
threads are not very efficient those are
the more efficient schemes
but threads are usually the most
convenient way the most programmer
friendly way
to support lots of sort of different
tasks
okay there's a couple of uh
challenges that we're gonna have to bite
off if we want to implement
a threading system
the so this is just high level
challenges
um one is as i mentioned before how to
actually
implement the switching for inter the
um the switching that allows us to
interleave
the execution of multiple threads
and this sort of broad name for this
process of
switching deciding oh i'm going to leave
off one thread and start executing
another thread
it's often called scheduling
and we'll see that xv6 and detects as a
actual piece of code that's the
scheduler indeed it has multiple
schedulers one per core
but the general idea of how do you drive
the decision to switch from one to
another how to pick the next thread to
run
is called scheduling
another question is if you want to
actually implement the switch from one
thread to another you need to save and
restore
so we need to decide what needs to be
saved
and where to save it when what needs to
be saved when we leave off executing one
thread and restored when we want to
resume
executing that thread at some later time
and final question is what to do about
compute bound threads
the many of the options um
many of the most straightforward options
for thread switching involve the thread
sort of voluntarily saying well i'm
going to save away my state and sort of
run another you know let another thread
be run but what do we have a user
program that's
you know doing some long running
calculation that might take hours
um it's not going to be particularly
thinking about oh now it'll be time to
good time to let something else run
so um it's most convenient to have some
way of
sort of automatically revoking control
from some long running compute bound
process
setting it aside and maybe running it
later
all right so i'm going to talk about
these i'm actually going to talk about
the machinery for dealing with compute
bound threads
first and the
scheme for that is something you've come
up before
and that's timer interrupts
and the idea here is that there's a
piece of hardware on each cpu on each
core
that generates periodic interrupts
and the xp6 or any operating system
really arranges to you know have those
interrupts delivered to the kernel so
even if we're running at user level and
some loop that's you know
computing the first billion digits of pi
um
nevertheless uh the timer interrupts to
go off at some point maybe every 10
milliseconds
and transfer control from that user
level code into the interrupt handler in
the kernel and so
that's the sort of first step in the
kernel being able to
gain control to switch among different
user level processes through user level
threads
even if those user level threads aren't
cooperative
and the basic scheme is that in the
interrupt handler so we can have a
kernel handler for these interrupts
and we'll see that uh
the kernel handler yields
this is the sort of usual name for this
it yields
the kernel handler sort of voluntarily
yields the cpu back to the scheduler and
tells the schedule look
you can let something else run now
and this yielding is really a form of
thread switch that saves away the state
of the current thread and
so can be restored later um
you know as we'll see the you know the
full story here actually you've seen a
lot of the full story here because it
involves an interrupt
which you already know about the full
story somewhat complex but the basic
idea is that a timer interrupt
gives control to the kernel and the
kernel voluntarily yields
the cpu this is called as a piece of
terminology preemptive scheduling
what that means is that with the
preempted means is that
even if the code that's running doesn't
you know doesn't want to
you know doesn't explicitly yield the
cpu
the timer interrupt is going to take
control away and we're going to yield
for it and the opposite of preemptive
scheduling
might be called maybe voluntary
and the interesting thing is that the
you know the implementation in xv6 and
other operating systems of preemptive
scheduling is this time interrupt which
forcibly takes away the cpu
and then the kernel basically does a
voluntary
yield or thread thread switch on behalf
of that process
now um another
just piece of terminology that comes up
here is that
while the thread's running there's a we
need to
distinguish the system needs to
distinguish between threads that are
currently actually running on some cpu
versus threads that would like to run
but aren't currently running on any cpu
but you know could run if a cpu became
free
versus threads that actually don't want
to run because they're waiting for i o
or waiting
for some event and unfortunately this
distinction is often called state even
though
the full state of a thread is actually
much more complicated than that
since this is going to come up i just
want to
list out a couple of states that we'll
be seeing
and these are states that xv6 actually
maintains there's
a state called running which means ah
it's actually executing on some
core on some cpu right now there's
runable
which means not currently executing
anywhere but and just a saved state
but would like to run as soon as
possible and then it turns out there's a
state which won't come out much today
but will come up next week called
sleeping which is
means the threads waiting for some i o
event and only wants to run after the i
o event occurs
so today we're mostly concerned with
running and runnable threads
and what this preemptive switch does
what this timer interrupt does
and yield is basically convert a running
thread whatever thread was interrupted
by the timer
into a runnable thread that is thread
that's
by yielding or converting that thread
into a thread that's not running right
now but
would actually like to clearly because
it was running at the time of the
timer interrupt
okay so um running thread it's program
counter and registers are
actually in the cpu you know in the
hardware registers of the cpu that's
executing it
a runnable thread though has no you know
it's not doesn't have a cpu associated
with it
and therefore we need to save for every
runnable state
we need to save whatever
cpu state whatever state the cpu was
keeping
when that thread was running so we need
to copy the cpu contents
you know which is not ram but just
registers really um from the cpu
into memory somewhere to save them when
we
turn a thread from running to runnable
and again this is the
basically the state we have to
explicitly save here's
just the state the executing state and
the cpu which is the
uh program counter and the
registers and the cpu so these need to
be saved
when we convert a thread to runnable
when some scheduler finally decides to
run a runnable thread then as part of
the many steps and getting that thread
going again
and resuming it we're going to see that
the program count the saved program
counter registers are copied
back into the cpus
actual register on the cpu that the
scheduler decides to run it on
all right any questions about these this
terminology
all right i'm going to now sort of talk
about a
sort of more xv6 oriented view of things
i'm going to draw two pictures really of
threads in xy6 a kind of simplified
picture and a more detailed picture
so as usual we have the user
stuff up here and the kernel down here
um we might be running you know multiple
processes
at user level maybe you know the c
compiler
and the ls and a shell
they may or may not be all wanting to
run at the same time
at user level each of these processes
has
you know it has memory and of particular
interest to us each of these processes
has a user stack
and while it's running it as registers
in the risc 5 hardware so pc plus
registers
all right so while the program is
running you know there's
this essentially a thread of control
that's running up at user level
um and the way i'm going to talk about
it is as if
there's a user thread that consists of
the
user stack user memory user program
counter user registers
if the program makes a system callers
interrupted and
goes into the kernel then this stuff
saved away in the
this program's trap frame and a
kernel the kernel thread for
this program is activated and so this is
the
the trap frame holds saved user stuff
after we saved away the user
piece program counter registers then we
switched the cpu to using the kernel
stack
and you know we don't need to restore
registers because
um the the kernel thread for process
isn't
really running and has no real save
state um
when the user thread is running um
instead it's sort of the
kernel thread is kind of activated on
its stack the first time in
the trampoline and user trap code
and then the kernel runs for a while
maybe running a system call or an
interrupt handler or whatever it may be
and sometimes uh if it's a system call
in particular we'll just simply return
from this point back to the
same process and the return to user
space will restore
the this program's program counter and
registers
but it could also be that instead of
simply returning
for one reason or another maybe because
it was a timer interrupt we're actually
going to switch to another process and
the very high level view of that is that
if the
xv6 scheduler decides to switch from
this process to a different process
what the first thing that really happens
is that we're going to switch
kernel threads from this processes
kernel thread
to the other processor's kernel thread
and then the other processes kernel
thread will return back to user space so
supposing that the c compiler rsa needs
to read the disk
and so it's going to yield the cpu while
it's sleeping to wait for the disk read
to complete
maybe ls wants to execute and is in
runnable state
what the xv6 scheduler maybe may do is
that well
um if ls is in runnable state that means
it left off somewhere and its state
was saved away possibly by a timer
interrupt and so the ls will actually
have a saved
trap frame with user registers and its
own
kernel stack and as it turns out a seed
set of
kernel registers associated with the
kernel thread which
is going to be called the context so if
xv6 switches from the compiler
kernel thread to ls's kernel thread
xv6 will save away the kernel registers
in a context for the
seat the compiler's kernel thread
switch to the ls thread to a complex
scheme which i'll describe a little bit
later will restore
ls's kernel thread registers from the
same
previously saved context from when ls
last left off
maybe ls will finish whatever system
call it was executing you know what
on the ls's kernel thread stack
um and then return back to ls from the
system call and on the way to return to
user space it'll restore these
previously saved
user registers for ls um and then resume
executing ls so
there's a bunch of details here which
we'll talk about but uh
maybe the main point here is that
whenever in xv6
see direct user to user context switches
when we're switching
from one process to another always
the sort of strategy by which xv6
switches from executing one process to
another process
is you jump into the kernel save the
process state run this
process as kernel thread switch to the
kernel thread of a
another process that's suspended itself
and then return and restore user
registers so it's always the sort of
indirect strategy
it's actually even more indirect than
this to threat switch
where the net effect is to switch from
one user process
to another user process
questions about this diagram or anything
the switch to the scheduler that happens
in between
those two right yep all right
let me talk about the scheduler so the
real picture's actually
um significantly more complex than that
um this is a more
going to be more full diagram let's say
we have process 1
which is executing and process 2 which
is runnable but not currently running
now the additional layer of details we
actually have multiple cores
um in xv6 let's say we have two cores so
that means that sort of at the hardware
level
um we have cpu0 which is one of the
cores
and let's say cpu one
and the more full story about how we get
from
executing user space
to in one process executing user spaces
in another runnable but not yet running
process
now the first part's about the same as i
talked about
and they say a timer interrupt forces
transfer control from the user process
into the kernel the trampoline code
saves the user registers the trap frame
for process one
and then executes user trap which
you know figures out what to do with
this trap or interrupt you know system
call
let's say it's a for a little while
we're executing
ordinary kernel c code on the kernel
stack of process one
let's say process one the kernel code
for process ones decides it wants to
yield the cpu um it does a bunch of
things which we'll see the details of
um that end up in a call to this routine
switch
just sort of the one of the central
routines in this story
switch saves away this context the
registers
for the kernel thread that's running in
context want so there's two sets of
registers the user registers
the trap frame the kernel thread
registers in the context
switch doesn't actually switch switches
from one content from one thread to
another but in fact
the way xp6 is designed the only place
that a user thread sorry the kernel
thread running on a cpu can switch to
is what's called the scheduler thread
for that cpu
so we can't even switch directly to
another process we can only switch to
the scheduler thread so there's a
the complete thread apparatus
dedicated to the scheduler for cpu zero
since we're running on cpus
this switch is going to switch to the
previously saved
registers for the scheduler thread so
let's say it's scheduler 0
and in the scheduler for cpu 0
switch will by restoring these registers
since the registers include the stack
pointer
the return from switch as we'll see will
now actually
return up to the um scheduler
function
on cpu zero and this scheduler function
will do some cleanup to finish putting
process one to sleep then it'll look in
the process
table for another process to run a
runnable process
and if it finds one and so we've
sort of gone down here and up into the
scheduler if the scheduler finds another
process to run or even
finds if process one is runnable and
still wants to run it may find process
one nothing else nothing else wants to
run
but in any case the scheduler will call
switch again to
switch contexts to say process two
in the process of which it will save its
own registers again
in its own context there'll be a
previously saved
context too from whenever process two
left off
that those this set of registers will be
restored
process two will have made a previous
call to switch
um to switch to the scheduler thread
just like process one did when it left
off
that call to switch will return to
whatever
system call or interrupt process two was
in when that's finished
there will be a previously saved trap
frame for process 2
that will contain user registers those
will be restored and will
return back up into user space
and there's a complete a separate
scheduler
thread for each cpu so it'll also be
saved
context for the scheduler thread for cpu
one
and a scheduler loop
running on scheduler one and whatever
process you know process three or
something
is running on cpu one when it decides to
give up the cpu it'll switch into
the scheduler thread for it for its
cpu all right there's a question where
the context stored
it turns out that for the operations
i've been talking about
the saved in fact always the
for a thread switch um
these contexts these saved register sets
for kernel threads are in the process
structure
so any given kernel thread can only have
one
set of saved kernel registers because
each thread is
only executing at sort of a single place
and its context
kind of reflects that place that it was
executing when it left off because
a thread is a single thread of control
so a thread
really only needs one context full of
registers so it's in the process
structure it's p
arrow
procontext
and the scheduler each scheduler thread
has its own context which is actually
not in the
there's no process associated with this
scheduler thread
so this is actually the scheduler's
contacts is stored in
the struct cpu for that core
there's an array of these cpu structs
one per core each one has a
context
uh question why can't we include the
registers in the trap frame for the
process
that is uh you know actually the
those registers could be stored in the
trap frame which is made because there's
only one saved set of
kernel thread registers per process we
could save them in any data structure
for which there's one you know element
of instance of that data structure per
process
now there's one struct proc process
there's one struct trap frame for
process
we could store the registers in the trap
frame
but i mean just sort of for maybe
simplicity or clarity of code the trap
frame
i think entirely consists of uh
data that's needed when entering and
leaving the kernel
and the struct context is consists of
the stuff that needs to be saved and
restored when
switching to and from between the kernel
thread and the
scheduler thread okay question is yield
something that's called by the user or
the kernel it's called by the kernel
so the user threads there's not really a
direct way in xv6 for user threads to
talk about um yielding the cpu or
switching
uh it's done by the kernel kind of
transparently
you know at points in time when the
kernel feels that it needs to happen
if there are threads um there are some
times when
you can sort of guess that probably a
certain system call
will result in a yield like if a process
does a read on a pipe where it knows
that really nothing is waiting to be
read on the pipe
then the reed will block you can predict
the read will block and that the
kernel will run some other process while
we're
waiting for data to appear in the pipe
and so the times when yield is called in
the kernel there's really two main times
one is
if a timer interrupt goes off the kernel
always yields
you know just on on the theory that
uh we should interleave the execution of
of all the process that want to run on
timer interrupt
uh periods so tom renner also always
calls yield
and whenever a process a system calls
waiting for i o
like waiting for you to type the next
keystroke you know does a read of the
console and you haven't typed the key
yet
then the the machinery to wait for io
calls yield it's called from sleep
something we'll talk about next week
all right um
okay another question yes
oh if it is asleep is it gonna do the
same thing roughly
so it's gonna be some um system call and
then it's gonna save the traffic
and um then basically the same picture
but
it's just um that the thing that
made the process go into the kernel was
not a timer interrupt but
um the processes own decision
yeah so if the process make does a read
system call and that's why it's in the
kernel
and the read requires the process to
wait for the disk
to do to finish reading or to wait for
data to appear on a pipe
then actually the diagram's exactly the
same as this
the enter the kernel with a system call
a trap frame
hold the save user registers will
execute the system called the simple
realize ah
i need to wait for the disk to finish
reading something
the system call code will call sleep
which ends up calling switch
which you know saves away the kernel
thread registers and the processes
contacts and switches to this
current cpu scheduler to let some other
thread run while this thread
is waiting for the discrete to finish so
everything we're going to talk about now
except for the timer interrupt
um is pretty much the same if what's
going on is we're in a system call and
the system call
needs to wait for some for i o and give
up the cpu
for the purposes of today's discussion
the two situations are almost identical
okay so the question does each per cpu
scheduler have its own stack
yes there's a stack
for this scheduler and a stack for this
separate stack
for the scheduler for cpu one
yeah and indeed the stacks for the skies
are just set up
in fact all this stuff you know the
context and the stacks for the scheduler
threads are set up in a different way
than for user processes
they're set up at boot time if you poke
around in
start.s or start.c start.s probably
you'll see some of the setup
for each core's scheduler thread
there's a place with a stack very early
in the assembly code during boot
where the stack is set up for each cpu
and it's on that stack that this
the cpu boots on and then runs its
scheduler thread
okay
one piece of jargon when people talk
about context
switch they're talking about
usually um
this act of switching from one thread to
another by saving one set of register
sets for the old thread
and restoring previously saved registers
for the thread we're switching to
so that's what's usually meant by
context switch also though sometimes
it's applied to the complete
dance that goes on when switching from
one user process to another and
occasionally you'll see context switch
apply to
switching between user and kernel but
for us we mostly mean it
for switching from one kernel thread
typically to a scheduler thread
just some pieces of information um
that are handy to keep in mind um
every core just does one thing at a time
each core
you know is either is just running one
thread at any given time it's either
running
some processes user thread some process
kernel thread
or that core scheduler thread so at any
given time the core
is not doing multiple things it's just
doing one thing and it's this switching
that sort of creates the illusion of
multiple threads running at different
times on that core
similarly each thread
is running up it's either running on
exactly one core or its state has been
state has been saved and we've switched
away from it
so so you know thread just to be clear a
thread never runs on more than one core
thread is either running on just one
core or it's not running at all it has
it has saved state somewhere
another interesting thing about the xv6
setup is that
these contexts that hold saved
kernel thread registers they're always
produced by a call to switch
and so these contacts basically always
refer
to you know the state of the thread as
it was executing inside a call to switch
um and you know the way we'll see that
come up
is that when we uh switch from one to
another and restore
the target threads context the first
thing it will do is return from a
previous call to switch
so these contacts sort of always save
state
in as it is in switch
okay um
any more questions about the sort of
diagram
level situation
um i have a question so we're using the
term thread all the time but
it seems to me like our implementation
for xv6
process is it is only one thread so like
could it be possible that
one process could have multiple threads
or am i wrong here
in xv6 right now
there's definitely some confusing things
about the way we use the words here
in xv6 um
a process
a process is either executing
instructions
a user level or it's executing
in the kernel or
it's not executing at all and its state
has been saved away
into this combination of a context
and a trap frame
so that's the actual situation now what
you want to call that
well you can call what what you like i i
don't know of a simple explanation for
this
structure um we've been calling it i've
been calling it
i've been saying that each process has
two threads
a user level thread and a kernel level
thread and
and that's a process there's this
restriction that a process is only
is either executing in the kernel in the
user space
or executing in the kernel in an
interrupt your system call
but never both yeah
okay that makes sense yeah i apologize
for the kind of complexity of this
okay okay so let me switch to code
looking at the xv6 code
right so first of all
um i just want to just to
show some of the stuff we've been
talking about i'm going to look at the
process structure and we can see in the
process structure a lot of the things
we've been talking about
um just for review there's the
wrap frame that saves the user level
registers there's
a context here that saves the
kernel thread registers when we switch
to the scheduler thread
there's a pointer to this process is
kernel stack which is where you know
function calls are saved
while we're executing in the kernel
there's this state variable which
records whether this process is
running or runnable or sleeping or not
allocated at all
and then finally there's a lock that
protects various things as we'll see
for now it we can observe that it at
least protects
uh changes to the state variable um
so that for example uh two scheduler
threats don't try to grab
a runnable process and run it at the
same time one of the many things this
lock does is prevent that from happening
i'm going to run a simple demo program
for you
this spin program i'm using it mostly
just
to drive the to sort of create this
issue predictable situation in which
we switch from one thread to another but
this is
this program spin program creates two
processes and the processes both compute
forever
you know call fork here
i make a child um and then
forever both children both children just
sit in this loop and every once in a
while they'll print a character just so
we can see they're making progress
but they don't print characters very
often and they never
sort of intentionally give up the cpu so
what we have here is two
essentially two compute bound processes
and in order for both of them to run i'm
going to run them on a
single cpu
xv6 that is only one core and so in
order for both of them to execute
you know it's going to be necessary to
do switching between the two processes
let me fire up the spin program
under gdb
run the spin program and you can see
it's printing one of the
two processes prints forward slash and
the other prints
backwards slash and you can see that
every once in a while
xp6 is switching between them it only
has one core the way i've configured it
so it we see a bunch of forward slashes
printing and then
apparently a timer in or up most go off
um
switch the one cpu to the other process
and then uh prints the other kind of
slash for a while
so what i want to observe is the timer
interrupt going off so i'm going to put
a break point
in trap
and in particular at line 207 and trap
uh which is um the code
in um
trap in dev inter that um
recognizes that ah we are in an
interrupt and the interrupt was
caused by a timer interrupt
so i'm going to put a break point here
at
trap.c 0.27 and
continue um boom the height triggers
right away
because timer amps are pretty frequent
and we can tell from where that indeed
we're in user trap and user trap
has called dev enter to handle this
interrupt
um i want to type finish to get out of
dev internet back into user trap
um because in fact we don't that
the code and different of our timer is
almost nothing
however once we're back at um
in uh user trap
we can see that from this line here that
we just returned from dev enter um
and the interesting thing about this
is that um what we're about to do
i mean looking forward we're currently
at this line here and
we're looking forward to this called the
yield
when dividend to return to you can see
from this
value return is two that two is
basically the device number
and we're going to see that by and by
because which devices too
user perhaps going to call yield which
will give up the cpu
and allow switch another process so
we'll see that in a moment
meantime let's look at what was
currently executing when the interrupt
happened
so i'm going to print p the variable
p holds a pointer to the current process
is struct
proc um
okay we have a question what makes each
process's kernel thread
different every process has a
separate kernel thread so there's really
two things that
differentiate different processes kernel
thread because more than one could be
executing on
different cores one is indeed that every
process
has a separate kernel stack and that's
what's pointed to by that
k stack element of struck proc and the
other
is that
uh early in
we're in user trap which is you know the
c code that's called
by trampoline when an interrupt occurs
we can tell by this call that my any
any kernel code can tell by calling
myproc
what the process is that's running on
the current cpu
and that's another thing that
differentiates um
that allows each cr that allows kernel
code to tell what process it's part of
that is
which processes kernel thread is
executing and what myproc does is
basically use the tp register which you
may recall
is set up to contain the current core's
heart id or core number it uses that to
index into an array of structures that
say for each core that the scheduler
sets whenever it switches processes to
indicate for each core which process is
running on that core
and so that's how different kernel
threads are differentiated
okay so i was going to use that p value
the name and that p-value to figure out
what process is running
xv6 remembers the name it's that spin
process just
exactly as expected there were two of
them
i think with process ids three and four
oops we're currently executing again
process id3
so after the switch we'd expect to be in
process id for
the other spin process how can we can
look at the saved
user registers in the trap frame
and these are just the 32 registers that
the trampoline code saves away to save
the user state
there's the user ra return address
register user stack pointer
user program counter at hex 62.
these are all familiar things from when
we looked at
traps and you know maybe of the most
interest
is that
the trap frame saves the user program
counter it's at value 62
if we cared
we can look in the assembly code for
spin.c
just spin.asm and look for 62.
now we can see that oh the interrupt
time or an interrupt occurred during
this ad
instruction in that infinite loop
in spin so it's not too surprising
okay so back to
the trap code they've entered just
returned i'm going to type
step a few times to get us to the
to just being about to execute this
yield
and yield is sort of the first step in
the process of giving up the cpu
switching to the scheduler letting the
scheduler
choose another kernel thread and process
to run
all right so let's actually step into
yield
now we're in yield yields um if you have
a question
no
oops
okay we're in yield um
yield does just a couple of things it uh
acquires the lock for this process
because it's about to make a bunch of
changes to this process and
it doesn't want any other and in fact
until it gives up the lock the state of
this process will be sort of
inconsistent um like for example it's
about yield is about to change the state
of the process to runnable which
would you know indicates that the
process is not running but would like to
but this process is running right i mean
we're running the process right now
that's what's executing is the kernel
threat for this process
and so the one of the many things that
acquire in this lock does
is uh makes it so that even though we
just changed the state to runnable
no other core scheduling thread will
look at this process
and because of the lock and see that
it's runnable and try to run it
while we're still running it on this
core which would be a disaster right
running the same process
um on two different cores and that
process has only one stack
so that means like two different cores
are you know calling subroutines on the
same stack which is
um just a recipe for disaster
so we take the lock out
we yield changes the state to runable
um and what this means is that you know
when we finally given up the
um when we finally yield
the cpu and give it up and switch to the
scheduler process this state will be
left in this runnable state so that it
will run again
because after all this was a timer
interrupt that interrupted a running
user level process that would like to
continue computing
so we're going to leave it in state
runnable so that it will run again
as soon as the scheduler decides to
and then the only other thing the
yield does is call this scheduler
function
so i'm going to step into the scheduler
function i'll show this
whole thing here
um this scheduler something does almost
nothing it does a bunch of checks
it does a whole bunch of sanity checks
and panics
and the reason for that is actually that
this code in xv6 over its many year
lifetime has had a
been among the most bug prone and had
most surprises
um on unhappy surprises so there's a lot
of
sanity checks and panics here because um
because there's often been bugs
associated with this code
all right i'm gonna um skip over these
um
sanity checks and proceed to the
call to switch this call to switch is
where the real action happens this is
called the switch it's going to
save away the current kernel threads
registers
in pro context which is the current
processes
saved kernel thread context save set of
registers
c arrow context c is the pointer to this
core's struct cpu
and struct cpu has the context the save
registers
of this core's scheduler thread so we're
going to be switching from this thread
saving this red state restoring the
threat state of
discord's scheduler and sort of
continuing the execution of this score's
course scheduler thread
okay so let's see what uh
let's take a quick preview at
the context that we're going to be
switching to
and i can get that turns out that i
can't actually print cro context but i
happen to know that c
prints to cpus zero just
because we're on the zero with core
there's only one core
um and i can print its context
and so this is the saved
registers from this course scheduler
thread
and of particular interest is the ra
because the ra register
is where the current function call
is going to return to so we're going to
switch to the scheduler thread and it's
going to do a return
and return to that ra and
we can find out where that are where
that return address is by looking in
kernel.asm
actually that's uh
and as you can see this x slash i you
know prints the instructions that are at
a certain address but it also prints the
label
um of the the name of the function that
those instructions are in it so we're
going to be returning
uh to schedule or buy and buy that's
just
you know as you might expect
okay um
i want to look at what switch actually
does we're about to call switch
so i put a breakpoint on switch i'm
putting a breakpoint because there's a
bunch of setup code
like that pulls the values of context
out of those structures
i'm going to skip over it okay so now
um we're to break point and switch
the gdb won't show us the instructions
but we can look in switch.s
um to look at the instructions we're
about to execute so as you can see we're
on the very first instruction the store
of
ra to the address pointed to by
a0 you may remember in the call to
switch
that the first argument was the current
thread's context and the second argument
was the
context of the thread we're switching to
the two arguments go in a0 and a1
and so the reason why we see all these
stores through
register a0 is because we're storing
away a bunch of registers
in the memory that a0 points to that is
in the context of the thread we're
switching from
and the loads load from address a1
because
that's a pointer to the context of the
thread we're switching to
okay um and so thread
you know uh switch saves registers
loads registers from the target threads
context and then return
that's that's why the ra was interesting
because it's going to return to the
place that ra pointed to namely into
scheduler
all right so one question is you may
notice here that
while switch saves rasp and a bunch of s
registers
one thing it does not save is the
program counter
there's no mention of the program
counter here
so why is that
is it because the program cutter is uh
updated with like the function calls
anyway
yeah it's it's the program counter
there's no actual information value in
the program counter we know
that where we're executing right now is
in switch
right so there'll be no point in saving
the program counter because it has an
extremely predictable value namely
this instruction the address of this
instruction and switch
what we really care about is where we
were called from
because when we switch back to this
thread we want to continue executing out
whatever point switch was called from
and it's ra that holds the address of
the instruction that switch was called
from
so it's ra that's being saved away here
and our a is the point at which we'll be
executing out again let's switch returns
so we can even print that we can print
our a
we can print our a and you know we
haven't actually switched threads yet
you remember we came here from the sched
function um
so our a is as you might expect a
pointer back into the sched function
another question is how come switch only
saves 14 registers i counted them
and only saves and restores 14 registers
even though the risk 5 has 32 registers
available for the
for use for code to use why
why only half the registers are saved
well when switch was called it was
called as a normal function so whoever
called switch already assumed well
switch might modify those so that
that function already saved that on its
stack
meaning that like when we jump from one
to the other
uh that one's going to self-restore its
caller saved registers that's exactly
right the switch is a
called from c code we know that the c
compiler um saves on the current stack
uh any caller saved registers that have
values in them that the compiler is
going to need later
and those caller saved registers
actually include
i think there's 18
depending on how you count them they're
somewhere between 15 and 18
caller saved registers and so the
registers we see here
are all the registers that aren't caller
saved and that the compiler
doesn't promise to save but nevertheless
may hold
values that are needed by the calling
function so we only have to save the
callee saved registers
when we're switching threads
okay um final thing i want to print
is the we do we do save and restore the
stack pointer
the current stack pointer it's like hard
to tell from this value what that means
but it's
the kernel stack of the current process
which
i don't know if you recall but is
allocated is mapped by the virtual
memory system at high memory
okay so um
okay so so the we're going to save away
the current registers and restore
registers from
uh the scheduler threads context um i
don't want to like
execute every single one of these lows
in store so i'm going to step
over all the 14 loads the 14 stores and
the 14 loads gonna
proceed directly to the return
instructions okay so we executed
everything in switch except the return
before we do the return we'll just print
the interesting registers again to see
where we are so
stack pointer um now is
has a different value the stack pointer
now points into this stack
zero area in memory and this is actually
the place very very early in the boot
sequence
where start.s puts the stack so it can
make
call the ferry for c function so
actually back on the original bootstack
for this cpu which just happens to be
where the scheduler runs
okay the program counter
not very interesting or in switch
because we haven't returned yet and
the ra register now points to scheduler
because we've loaded
uh we've restored the register set
previously saved by the scheduler thread
and indeed we're really now in the
schedulers right if i were on where
where now looks totally different from
the last time we ran it we're now
indeed in a call to switch but now we're
in a call from swift to switch that the
scheduler made
at some point in the past and the
schedule was run long ago during boot
was called as the last thing that maine
did during the boot process
so i'm going to execute one instruction
to return from
switch now into scheduler
so now we're in this course scheduler
let's look at the full code
so this is the scheduler code this
function called scheduler and now we're
executing in the scheduler thread
for the cpu and we're just at the point
we just returned from the from a
previous call to switch that the
scheduler made a while ago
uh when it decided it was going to start
running that process you know pid3 which
was the spin
process that was interrupted so
it's this switch you know process id3
that spin called switch but it's not
swift that switch that's returning that
switch hasn't returned yet
it's still saved away in uh
process ids threes stack and contacts we
just returned from this earlier call to
switch
all right so the stuff that happens here
in the scheduler um
we're stopped running this process and
so
uh we want to forget about the various
things we did
in the process of running this process
we want to forget the cro proc equals
zero
basically means that we're forgetting
that you know we're no longer running
this process in this course so we don't
want to
get have anybody be confused about that
we set this
per core proc pointer to zero instead of
this process the next thing that happens
is that um
you remember yield acquired the lock for
this process
because it didn't want any other core
scheduler to look at this process and
maybe run it
until the process was completely put to
sleep
um we've we've now completed the switch
away from this process
and so we can release the lock on the
process that just yielded
that's the release at this point
um we're still in the scheduler if there
was another core
at this point some other core scheduler
could
find that process because it's runnable
and run it
but that's okay because we've completely
saved its registers
we're no longer executing on its that
process is stacked because we're now
executing on the
um discord scheduler stack so it's
actually fine if some other core
decides to run that process okay but
there is no other core so
that doesn't actually happen in this
demonstration
um i actually want to spend a moment
talking about the pr lock a little bit
more
pr lock actually does a couple of things
it does really two things from the point
of view of scheduling
one is that yielding the cpu
involves multiple steps we have to set
the state to run up
change the state from running to
runnable we save the registers
in the yielding processes context and we
have to stop using the yielding
processes stack
there's at least three steps you know
which take time
in order to do all the steps required to
yield the cpu and so one of the things
that lock does
as i mentioned is prevent any other core
scheduler from looking at our process
until all three steps
have completed so the lock is basically
making those steps atomic
that either all happen from the point of
view of other cores
um or none of them have happened
it's going to turn out also when we
start running a process
that the pr lock is going to have a
similar
protective function we're going to set
the state of a process to running when
we start executing a process and we're
going to move its
registers from its process context into
the risk 5 registers
but if an interrupt should happen in the
middle of that process the interrupt is
going to see the process in a weird
state like
maybe in the state of mark running but
hasn't yet
finished moving its registers from the
context into the risk five registers
and so that would be a disaster if a
timer interrupt happened then because we
might switch away from that process
before it had restored its registers
and switching away from that process
would save now uninitialized risk five
registers
into the context processes context
overwriting its real registers
so indeed we want starting a process to
also be
effectively atomic and in this case
holding the lock
holding pro lock across switching to a
process
as well as preventing other cores from
looking at that process also turns off
interrupts
for the duration of firing up of
switching to that thread
which prevents a timer interrupt from
ever seeing a process
that's only midway through being
switched to
okay so we're in the scheduler we're
executing this loop in the schedule
there's this loop in the scheduler that
looks at all the processes in turn to
find one to run
and in this case we know there's another
process because
there's that other spin process that we
forked
the but there's a lot of process lots to
examine
um so i want to skip over the actual
proc the scanning of the
process table and go direct to the point
at which
the scheduler finds the next process so
i'm going to put a break point
at line 474 where it's actually found a
new process to run
here we are on the schedulers scan the
process
table and found another process to run
and it's going to cause that process to
run you
can see it line 468 it acquired that
process is locked
so now it's entitled to do the various
steps that are required to switch to
that process
in line 473 it set the processes state
to running
it's now at 474 going to record in the
cpu structure
which process the cpu is executing
and then call switch to save the
scheduler's registers and restore
the target processors registers so we
can see what process it found by looking
at
the new process's name surprisingly it's
spin
this process id is now four we used to
be running three we're now running four
and we've already set the state to
running so
so the state's running
we can see where this thread is going to
switch to in the call to switch at line
475.
print this context he saved registers
so where is the ra the course we're
going to call switch but
switch as we know returns when it
returns it returns to the restored ra
so we really care about is where is it
that
ra points to we can find that out by
oops um using x slash i
uh it's going to return r a points to
some point in sked so that's not too
surprising since
presumably that other spin process
was suspended due to a timer interrupt
which as we know called sked
which calls switch
all right so we're about to call switch
let me just bring up the switch code
again
um
actually enter switch we're still uh
where shows that we're still in the
scheduler's context
i want to again execute all of the
instructions of the switch this time
switching from the scheduler to the
new process so we skip over the 28
stores and loads
just convince ourselves that we are
actually about to return to sched so now
since we're about to return to sched and
not scheduler
we must now be in a process kernel
thread and no longer
in the scheduler threat and indeed if we
look at the back trace
we had a user trap call there must have
been a timer interrupt
from long you know sometime in the past
that
as we've seen called yield and sched but
it was the timer interrupt in the other
process
now not in the process that we
originally looked at
okay any questions about
i think i'm going to leave off stepping
through the code at this point and
any questions about the any of the
material we've seen
oh sorry if if it was for example this
kyle
then we would see that our
array would point somewhere to like
sleeve or something like that right um
uh yes well
we see that the where at this point
would include
some system call implementation
functions and a call to sleep
as it happens i think i mean this is
this is
you're basically the answer your
question is yes if we had just
left off executing this process for some
reason other than timer interrupt
um switch would be basically returning
to some system call code instead of to
scan as it happens i think sleep make
calls get so
the back trace would look different it
would just happen includes get but yes
so i've chosen just one way of you know
just
one way of switching between processes
due to timer interrupts
but you also get switches to wait for
user i o or to wait for other processes
to do things like write to a pipe
okay one thing to you probably noticed
is that um
scheduler called switch and we're about
to return from switch here
but we're returning really from a
different call to switch
than the one the scheduler made we're
returning from a call to switch that
this process made a long time ago um
so you know this is potentially a little
bit confusing but
you know this is how the guts of a
thread switch work
another thing to notice is that the code
we're looking at the switch code this is
really the heart
of thread switching and
really all you have to do to switch
switch threads is
save registers and restore registers now
threads have a lot more state than just
registers they have variables and
stuff in the heap and who knows what but
all that other state is in memory and
isn't going to be disturbed we've done
nothing to disturb
any of these threads stacks for example
or
heap values so the registers in the
microprocessor are really the only kind
of volatile state
that actually needs to be saved and
restored to do a thread switch
all the stuffs in memory stack for
example will still be in memory on
undisturbed and so it doesn't have to be
explicitly saved and restored
now we're only saving and restoring this
microprocessor the cpu registers
because we want to reuse those very
registers in the cpu for the new thread
and
overwrite whatever values they have so
the
register that that's where we have to
see the old threads registers
uh what about um other processor state
so i don't know if the risk 5 processor
that we're using has other
flags but i know like some x86 intel
chips have like
like the floating point unit state and
like things like that
do we do we just not have that in
response absolutely
your points very well taken on other
microprocessors like x86
the details of switching
are a bit different because you know
they had different registers in
different state
um and so the code you know this is very
very risk five dependent code and
the switch routine for some other
processor
might look quite different like indeed
might have to save floating point
registers
now risk five actually uses the general
purpose registers or
actually i'm not sure what it does for
floating point
but the kernel doesn't use floating
point so it doesn't have to worry about
it
but yeah this is totally microprocessor
dependent
a question about the timer interrupts so
it sounds like the the core
of all of this scheduling working is
that there will be a timer interrupt
uh what happens in cases where that
malfunctions
there is going to be a timer interrupt
um so the the
i mean uh so so um okay so the the
reasoning for how come
preemptive scheduling of user processes
works
um is that user processes execute with
interrupts turned on always xv6 just
ensures that interrupts are enabled
before returning to user space and that
means that a timer interrupt
can happen if you're executing in user
space so
there's nothing a user process you know
if we're in user space the timer and
error
just will happen uh when the time comes
it's a little trickier in the kernel
the kernel sometimes turns off
interrupts like when you acquire a lock
the interops are going to be turned off
until you release it so
um uh so
if there were some bug in the kernel the
you know if the kernel turned off
interrupts and
never turned them back on and the code
in the kernel never gave up the cpu
you know never called sleep or gave up
the cpu for any other reason
then indeed a timer interrupt wouldn't
occur
and that would mean that this kernel
code may
you know we would never give the cpu but
in fact uh as far as we know
xp6 is we wrote xp6 so that
it always turns interrupts back on or
you know if there's code in xv6 that
turns off interrupts it either turns
them back on
and so uh timer interrupt can then occur
in the kernel and we can switch away
from this kernel thread
or the code returns back to user space
kernel code returns back to user space
we believe there's never a situation in
which kernel code
will simply like loop with interrupts
turned off forever
i got it my question was more about like
so i assume the interrupts are actually
coming from some piece of hardware
like what if that piece of hardware
malfunctions no
now it's all right then your computer is
broken and you should buy a new one
okay i mean i mean that's a valid
question for me there's
you know 10 billion transistors in your
computer and
indeed sometimes the hardware just like
has bugs in it but that's
beyond our reach for i mean
if you add one on one and the computer
says three then
you just have deep problems that xv6
can't help you with
so we're assuming that the computer
works
the only time when that when software
there are times when software tries to
compensate for hardware level errors
like
if you're sending packets across a
network you always send a checksum
so that if the network hardware you know
flips a bit
malfunctions and flips a bit then you
can correct that but
for stuff inside the computer that
people tend not to
it's just people basically don't
try to make the software compensate for
hardware errors
oh i have a question why uh so like
in trampoline dot sending switch we
write the code in assembly is that why
is that because
we want to make sure that exactly this
thing's happening so we cannot you
cannot write in and see because
we just need those like those exact
things to happen basically
um yeah yeah
uh yes certainly we want this exact
sequence to happen
um in nnc it
it's very hard to talk about things like
r a and c
or sp um certainly there's no way within
the c
language to talk about changing the
stack pointer
or the ra register so these are things
that
just can't be you can't say it in
ordinary c
the only way you can say it in c is
there is it's possible in c to sort of
embed
assembly instructions in the c code and
so we could have just embedded these
assembly structures in the c function
but it would amount to the same thing
we're basically we're operating at a
level below
below c so we can't really we can't
really use c here
i have a question about when a thread
finishes executing i'm assuming that
happens in the user space when we call
the exec i'm sorry
exit system call and
um that also ends the process in the
thread i'm assuming in the kernel space
but if the thread ends
within before a new time interrupt
happens does it still
like um is this
like the cpu still acquired by that
thread or do we end that thread and
start a new one before the new time
interrupt
oh yeah the
the thread um the thread yields the cpu
does the exit exit yields the cpu so
there's actually many points that
even though i've been driving this
discussion with the timer interrupt in
fact
in almost almost all cases where xv6
switches between threads it's not due to
timer interrupts
it's because um some system call is
waiting for something or decides
that that it needs to give up the cpu
and so for example
exit does various things and then calls
yield
to give up the cpu and it does that
there's really nothing it does that
independently whether there's a timer
interrupt
yes
all right the time is up for this
lecture i think i'll
continue some of this discussion next
week but i'm happy to take more
questions
right now if people have them
so let's say the operating system
actually um
takes on the thread implementation so
so for example you want to run multiple
threads of a process
on multiple cpus like that has to be
handled by the os that cannot just be
handled in user space right
how does that kind of switching work is
each each thread mouse becomes the same
as the process it's like is it always
going to loop through all
existing threads or you know because
like each cpu will still switch between
even if one process has give me eight
cores like it's still going to switch
switch each of the cpus between
those and then couple of other processes
and then also we don't want to really
switch
like between one and the other thread on
the same cpu
or do we i don't know wait
can uh um i'm not sure what the question
is
yeah i guess i guess can you just
explain more like how does that happen
sorry how does what happen um
let's say we have multiple threads per
process so that they can and they can
run on
different gpus like how do what do we go
how to go about there
yeah so linux for example supports uh
multiple threads
per process and in linux the
implementation
is a complex implementation but maybe
the simplest way to explain it is that
um each uh it's almost as if each thread
in linux
is a complete process and
the the threads of a given what we would
call the threads of a particular process
are essentially separate processes that
share the same memory
so linux has sort of separated out the
notion of
the thread of execution from address
space and
you know you can have them separately
and
if you make two threads in one process
it basically makes two processes
that share one address space and then
from then on the scheduling is
not unlike what xv6 does
for individual processes i see and then
is there anything like does the user
have to specify like
okay pin each thread to a cpu uh
or or how does the os make sure that
different threads of the same process
don't run on the same core because
that's kind of
defeating the purpose or not i guess i
don't know the
the uh it's actually just like it's much
like xp6 namely the
um you know there's four cores and
linux will just find four things to run
on those four cores
they may be you know if there's not much
going on then maybe there'll be four
threads of the same
process or if there's 100 users logged
in on an athena machine maybe it's
one thread each from multiple different
processes
you know there's not any one answer
or the kernel basically finds something
for each core to do and then
that core does that thing okay that
makes sense
you can you know if you're if you want
to do careful measurements there is a
way to pin threads to cores
but people only do it when they're up to
something strange
so they share this little virtual table
you say it again memory so they say they
have the same
page table those threads
yeah yeah yeah yeah if you're on linux
if you create two threads in one process
then you have these two threads that
uh i don't know if they like literally
share the exact same page table or
whether their page tables
are identical one or the other
is there a reason why they would have to
be separate ever
if you manually map memory or
i i don't know enough to know whether
which which linux does
okay i have another question about like
a small detail um
so basically like from my understanding
when you call switch
you switch from one call to switch to
another so the first time you call
switch
you have to like kind of artificially
create that
other endpoint to come back to right yes
because you can't just randomly jump
into write any code
yes you want to know where that
where that fake
where that context is cooked up probably
somewhere where the process is
uh created now i guess i don't know yeah
yeah yeah yeah maybe user internet
or let's see not using it lock proc
there's something called fork trap or
something yeah
look at this yeah yeah well yeah fork
red okay so an alloc proc which is
called both
for the very first process of blue time
and by
fork um alloc proc sets up the critical
elements of the context
for the new processes
it sets up the new processes context it
actually doesn't matter what most of the
registers are
but it doesn't matter what ra is because
that's where the switch
the very first switch and that process
is going to return to ra
and that process is going to need to use
its own stack so ra and sp are set up
are faked essentially so that the very
first switch
into a process works so so if i
understand this correctly like when the
switch will happen then
it'll basically just start executing the
first instruction
inside of the four cred as if red just
called switch and returned from
yeah yeah yeah yeah the return from
switch is
going to be a jump to the beginning of
fork red
right interesting do we ever
call fork red or is it always hap
it always happens like this i don't
think anything ever calls for credit for
real i think it's
just yeah it's only executed in this
weird way from
first time a process is run it is really
its job is to
release the lock that the scheduler took
and then return and then this user trap
red of course is also
fake in that it's
it's you know yeah it's like it's as if
returning from a trap except the trap
frame is
faked also to have to like jump to the
first instruction in the
user right code
oh but the trap frame it's again the
same like you don't need to initialize
any registers because it's like well
we're going to the beginning so you
don't need to assume anything
yeah the program counter i think is uh
yeah it needs to be initialized to zero
i don't know what else
maybe it
i mean probably if we call them it
doesn't right because if we already do
the
call then that's going to set the broken
counter yeah yeah so here's the this
only happens oh because four copies
fork copies the program counter the user
program counter
and so the only time when we're not
doing a fork is for the very first
process where
it's like explicitly deceptive oh a
stack pointer oh yeah also needs to be
set up
oh yeah because it's that's epc that's
not pc that's the one that's going to
get swapped by the trap
trampoline yes oh i see
because the real pc is actually going to
be in trap like inside traveling
but then we're going to switch it to
jump to there
yeah interesting
uh can i just ask like can you go back
to the alloc proc
um i think there's a oh no sorry
uh four cred uh there's something there
that happens i think for the first
process only
uh what's this for a first call
i wasn't really sure what happened let's
see the file system
the file system needs to be initialized
and in particular some stuff needs to be
read off the disk
in order to get the file system going um
like the there's this thing called the
super block which describes like how big
the file system are is and where the
various things are in the file system
and there's also a
crash recovery log that needs to be
replayed
in order to recover from a previous
crash if there was one
but in order to do anything in the file
system you need to be able to wait
for disk operations to complete but the
way xv6 works
you really can only execute the file
system code in the context of a process
in order to like wait for i o and so
therefore the
initialization of the file system has to
be deferred until we the first time we
have a process running
and that occurs in this very first
process in fork read
i see and i'm guessing we'll learn more
about this uh
later yeah not about this horrible
but about uh how file systems work
all right okay well thank you i'm sorry
for holding off the oh
sorry is that going to be the in that
process when this thing
is executed