all right why uh why don't we get
started
uh you know if people want to turn on
the camera again or
well i'm going to do that i'll be great
just to create sort of a
class atmosphere uh as best as we can
okay so this is uh uh i'm going to talk
today about this paper you know the
benefits and cost of writing a unix
kernel
and i love the language um uh
you know this is a basically a paper
that was partly written because of
uh s081 or 828.
uh and uh this is a paper that you know
we've written
uh robert and i and but the main person
was
the main lead offers cody cutler who's a
t8
uh this class many many times
it's always a little bit you know i
don't really enjoy actually particularly
talking about
you know papers that we worked on
ourselves but you know they again this
paper came about
basically of a r81 and a28 and so
i'm going to use some slides uh this
time instead of actually writing on a on
a whiteboard
and so the really the source of this
paper is
this question and then what language
should you write
a kernel and this is a question that you
know many
many of you asked uh or your your
students in the past uh 808 or s8
uh asked many many many times uh partly
you know because you know you have bugs
in the operating system
or in your kernel and you're like well
if i would written in this other
language then you know maybe i would
have not had those bugs
um and so this is a question that often
comes about
and it turns out you know in the
operating system community at large you
know this is a
sort of a hotly debated question but not
that many facts you would actually make
a sort of an
any informed discussion and what we'll
see at this
at the end of this lecture or during
this lecture where you as you read the
paper
i you know we don't really have a crisp
uh
answer to this question uh but we have
sort of a you know this paper
contributes
you know a bunch of data that you know
allows you to have a sort of a little
bit more of an
in-depth discussion uh about you know
what is a
uh what is a good programming language
for the kernel and so that was really
uh the origin of this paper and uh
and that's over
and the the source you know of this
paper is basically you guys so
i tried to answer this question
uh we wrote a new kernel
um and you know we did it in the
language uh with automatic
memory management that means with the
guard collector so you don't actually
have to call
free and that avoids a class of books so
that's one of the properties that a
high-level language typically has
and so we wanted to have we picked a
language that has that and we
followed basically the traditional
monolithic uh unit
organization so we could do a sort of a
fair comparison
and in fact some ways you could think
about what we built is
uh something like xc6 uh much much more
more features and more high performance
i mean as you know xp6 has all kinds of
uh
quadratic algorithms or linear search uh
type algorithms and you know of course
you know if you want to write a gfi
performance you can't have those
uh so that was the origin of this paper
and the reason why we built uh biscuit
you know trying to answer that question
or at least shed some light
so i'm first going to talk a little bit
about sort of more general background uh
a lot of questions over email we're sort
of
trying to get a little bit more context
and then i will dive into
uh biscuit in a more in more detail i
feel free to
jump in you know with questions in any
particular point of time uh
you know as i said you know this paper
was motivated
by questions that you asked and so you
know please please ask keep asking
questions
um so uh as you
know just through sort of the setting of
this paper is that you know a lot of
kernels are written in c and you know
xc6 is written in c you're programming
in c
uh but most popular kernels that you
know sit on your desktop or
you know your phone are written in c you
know windows lindex all
linux dual uh you know the various forms
of bsds
and uh and the reason um
they've written or written in c is that
um
you see it provides you a lot of control
as you know seen in the
labs you have complete control over
memory allocation and freeing
uh there's almost no implicit code you
know you can almost sort of imagine when
you're reading the c code like what the
corresponding risk five instructions are
uh you have direct essays memory you
know you can read and write you know the
pte bits you know or the registers of
devices uh and you know see itself you
come through very few
uh dependencies you know there's no
large run time that you actually have to
have you know to be able to run a c
program you can almost run it almost
immediately on the bare
you've seen that like when xv6 boots you
know it's basically a few lines of
assembly and then basically you're
running c code
um so there are all the sort of good
virtues
of c and you know one reason that we
like c a lot
uh but c also already has some downsides
um
you know it has been proven over the
last you know sort of decades
uh writing security code is difficult uh
you know there are types of bugs
that can you you can
often be exploited uh whether it is
buffer overruns which are probably the
most well-known one like you're writing
behind
the past uh an array bound or you're
writing you know below
you know your stack um use after three
bucks you know where
you know the your freezer memory uh but
it's still in use
uh and someone somebody scribbles on it
and you know you may scribble something
bad on it
uh and generally you know when uh
threats are sharing memory it's
typically difficult to decide you know
one action the memory can be freed
some of these bugs you know don't really
show up that
uh you know some debug manifest
themselves explicitly in xv6 some less
so
you know uh you know xv6 is very little
dynamic
uh memory allocation you know almost
everything is pre-allocated right up
front
uh but buffer overruns and usually after
three bucks you know definitely
do show up um and so
in fact you know if you look at uh cves
you know these are the uh you know
there's a website where there's an
organization that
keeps sort of controlled that checks and
uh keeps a record of all sort of the
security exploits
and you investigate that you know you'll
find that in 2017 when we were doing
this paper that
uh there were 40 linux kernel uh
bugs that can actually lead to a an
attacker running
uh you know take a complete control over
the machine
and clearly you know those are serious
bugs and then those bugs came out of
buffer overruns
and uh other type of memory safety bucks
um so you know that's sort of too bad
you know that you know if you write code
in c you know that actually is hard even
you know for people that do this
professionally and uh to actually get
this uh right
uh and then of course you know i'm sure
you've seen this in the lab you know
probably certainly i remember from some
of the
the piazza questions you know the number
you run into this used after three bucks
you know
in particular in the copy and write lab
uh they showed up a bunch of times
so you know so one reason that a
high-level image would be attractive
uh is that a high-level language you
know provides memory safety
uh and so all these bugs or the cv
exploits that i mentioned on the
previous slide would just not be
would not be possible you know it could
just you know if they happen they either
would result in a panic
you know because you know the run time
would say like oh you're writing past
the rate you can't do that
uh or you know you're just you couldn't
manifest itself at all
you know because these languages will
allow you to write that kind of code
so there are of course other benefits to
a high level language
which often is also mentioned by you
know
students in this class when they're
doing the labs in addition to type
safety you know there's the automatic
memory management of your garbage
collector
uh so freeing is easy you just don't
have to think about it the developer
selector does all the work for you
uh it's good for concurrency you know it
has good abstractions
you know whether it's like in go you
know with interfaces or some other you
know classes or some other form of
you know that forces you or encourage
you to actually write modular code
um the downsides and you might be
wondering like well if you know there's
so many upsides to high-level images
you know why not you know why is xc6 not
written in
you know java go python or whatever um
and the reason is you know the
or linux you know the reason is this is
poor performance you know
there's a cost you know to actually uh
high level language you know sometimes
this is referred to as the
high level language tax um and you know
these are basically
you know if you do an array bound an
array index you know you have to
check the bounce you know you have to
check no pointers
you have to have more expensive casts
and you know garbage collection itself
is also not free you know there's going
to be some cycles spent you know
tracking down which objects are free and
which are allocated and you know
that's the cost uh
so that's you know sort of from the
performance side and a lot of the paper
focuses on this
uh and then in principle you know often
you know i mean
it's perceived that there's sort of
incompatibilities with linux with kernel
programming
no direct memory access you know because
nothing principle could you know
violate type safety uh no handwritten
assembly and you need some handwritten
assembly in the kernel
you know whereas the context switch
between two threads or like to get off
the ground
when the machine boots um in
um uh you know i can
you know the language may have a
particular plan for
a concurrency or parallelism that might
not line up you know with the
plan that the the kernel needs were
concurrently in parallelism you know
we've seen for example in the
uh scheduling lecture the you know
one thread passes a lock to another
thread or you know there's sort of a
couple
you know there's patterns of currency
management that are sort of unusual in
user programs but they do show up in
uh in kernels um and so um
so the goal basically of this you know
uh paper was to sort of measure the
high-level
uh language trade-offs you know explore
the total effects of using high-level 11
instead of c you know both in terms of
uh safety programmability but also for
performance cost
and of course if you'd like to do this
you know this kind of an experiment you
know
you need to do that sort of on a
production grade kernel you can't do
that on xv6 because it's so slow that
basically you probably wouldn't learn
anything you know
if the program the current written
slogan c you know you're writing a slow
in
uh go you know it doesn't really tell
you much about you know the c first go
question it just says like well xp6 is
slow
and so you don't want to like to do that
in a more you know high performance you
know
oriented kernel or the kernel is
designed for high performance
and so you know uh you know one of the
things that was surprising because like
many of you
asked this uh your predecessors asked
this
and uh you know you would imagine well
this question must be answered in the
literature
and you know that turns out that it
actually isn't uh it is
there's quite a number of studies that
look into
the question of like high-level language
trade-offs in the context of user
programs
uh and uh but you know as you know
the kernel is you know quite a bit
different than from user programs uh so
for example memory management careful
manual manager is really important
uh these different types of concurrency
may be slightly different so we
wanted to do it in the context of a
kernel and you know we're going to
actually really find any sort of papers
that really
answer this question the closer you
could come to is there
you know there are many kernels written
in high-level language you know there's
a long history of doing that they are
dating back even to sort of the early
list machines
uh and you know and but many of the sort
of
uh recent versions of these kernels
are not really written with the idea of
evaluating this high-level language
tax question but really to explore new
os designs
or new os architectures and so
none of them sort of really measure
directly you know sort of
do a head-to-head comparison and keep
the structure the same
so that you can really focus on this
issue of the language as opposed to
some other issues
in fact we used to read you know some of
these papers actually in
in the past um
so uh you know turns on one reason maybe
that you know there's not a lot of ton
of work
uh that actually answered these were a
ton of papers that are answering this
question is
uh it's actually tricky to do it uh uh
you know basically if you really do it
right you know you want to compare it
with a production grade c
kernel that means like something like
linux uh
or something in windows or whatever but
then you have to build
a production creates you know kernel and
you know clearly for
a small team that's very hard to do
i mean you know there's lots and lots of
linux kernel developers
they make many many changes you know
week by week day by day and so it's
going to be hard
to uh you know to do the same thing and
build an equivalent you know
type of thing so you have to settle for
something slightly
less than uh
uh so um so so the best move you could
do or the best we could
to do is you know build a high level
build the kernel in a high level
language you know keep most of the
important aspects the same as linux
the performance roughly optimize the
performance until it's roughly similar
to linux you know even though maybe it's
not identically exactly identical
features but you know gets into the same
ballpark
and then you know measure the high level
along with tradeoffs
and of course you know the risk you know
this approach is that you know the
kernel that we built you know actually
is slightly different than linux you
know it's not gonna be exactly like
linux and so you know you gotta you know
there's uh you gotta be very careful
when
drawing any conclusions and you know
we'll
and this is one reason why you cancel or
give a really crystal clear
uh answer to this question that
basically this paper poses uh but
we can hopefully you know get a little
bit more deeper insight than basically
you know saying almost nothing about it
does this make sense so far any
questions
that's sort of the context you know of
this paper and you know
why we went actually often did it
okay so uh if there's no questions i'd
like to
talk a little bit more about the
methodology uh
and uh so uh so basically you know the
sort of setup is you know here's on the
left side you know we have our
uh this is gonna be you know biscuit uh
you know we're gonna in in our
particular case you know we wrote
for this paper to colonel in uh go um
it provides roughly a similar uh you
know subset of the system calls that
linux provides but you know
the way that uh but they have the same
arguments you know the uh
same calling inventions and we run
basically the same applications on top
of that interface
so you know one of the applications is
ngx which is a website web server
and so the idea is that you know we run
the same
uh application both on biscuit and linux
you know the the application will
generate the same system called trace
with exactly the same arguments
and both biscuit and linux you know
perform
you know all the necessary operations
that are invoked by those system calls
and then we can sort of you know look at
you know the differences basically
between
you know the high-level language kernel
and linux and sort of talk about like
you know what are the trade-offs
so that's sort of the core of the
methodology and again
you know because linux and biscuit are
not going to be exactly identical
uh you know there's going to be you know
some uh differences but you know we
you know the we spend a lot of time uh
in this good trying to you know make the
comparison as fair as possible
yeah or whatever possibles we could
think of
making it so a lot of
you know you asked this question on
which high level language you use you
know for this kind of uh
work and you know we pick go
and for a couple of reasons it is a
statically compiled language so
unlike python uh there's no interpreter
uh and the reason that would like you
know standard for compiled because that
basically compiles actually high
performance code in fact a particular go
compiler is pretty good
um so basically you know it's sort of a
high performance language furthermore
you know the go
designer is actually intended for
systems programming and you know kernels
are foreign assistive programming so you
know that needs a good match
and so for example you know aspect that
uh
why it's so good for system programming
it's actually easy to call assembly or
other foreign code
uh it has good support for concurrency
you know quite flexible
uh and then another reason that we
wanted to use it because it has a
garbage collector you know so like two
you know one of the things that you
think about a high-level language and
one of the virtues of the high-level
language is that you don't have to do
memory management
and then garbage collector is typically
in a central role in the uh
uh provides a central role in that sort
of memory management story
um by the time we started this paper
uh or we started this project uh rust
was not very popular the ross was
actually not very stable and mature at
that point then he actually could write
a real
kernel in it uh in retrospect no now
you know you do it again you know you
may would write it in rust
because it's also designed for systems
programming uh
it has a small runtime it produces good
code
um although one thing that actually you
know might may still make it very
interesting to go for go is that
uh rushers takes the starting assumption
that uh
that you know you wanna high perform
systems programs then
you can't do that with a garbage
collector and in fact the
rush type system is set up in a very
clever way in a very interesting way
so that actually a garbage collector is
not necessary and in some ways we really
were interested
in just answering this question like
what is the cost of guard collection in
a high-level language you know on kernel
programming
and it's really impossible to use or
what does that cost and in some ways you
know sort of rush sidestep that question
and just like you know
use the language without garb's
collection they have to don't think
about this particular cost
any questions about this in terms of the
programming language
we decided to use
yeah there were lots of email questions
related to this topic so
this this is a theoretical question that
maybe doesn't
have an immediate answer but if the
linux kernel were to be written
and rust not go and like
optimized in the same capacity would it
be able to achieve
higher performance then
then the ground current then then c like
a linux c kernel
uh i doubt it would be a uh okay uh
hard to know i'm just speculation
correct because we haven't done this
experiment
uh my senses you know would be not
higher performance than c
uh but you know you know probably
roughly in the same ballpark
uh because i see so low level you can
presume
whatever you were doing rushed you could
also have done this c uh
does that make sense yes thank you
okay um okay so let's uh move on them
uh unless there are any other further
questions about this and again you know
feel free to interrupt and you know
this is a bit of a discussion based
lecture you know and so i would
you know it was intended to sort of
stimulate intellectual interest and so
you know
jump in if you have anything to think
about this topic
so actually before you know maybe a
question i want to ask
uh maybe i'll come back to that at the
end of the lecture closer to the end of
the lecture
uh partly you know the whole
uh reasoning we want to use high level
language is to avoid a certain class of
bugs
and one question you should ask yourself
were there bugs
you know in the labs that you had that
would have been avoided if you had a
high level language
you know so you know think back you know
i'm sure you can come up with some
bugs that you know you're costing a lot
of time and a lot of pain
uh and you could ask yourself for those
kind of bugs you know
if we if the xv6 were
rewritten in the labs will be done in
another high-level programming language
would have life you know would you like
me a lot easier
you have a lot more spare time to do
other things
so let's keep that question in your head
and you know
we'll hopefully return to that at the
end of the lecture but if you have
opinions right away that's fine too
okay uh so let me talk a little bit
about biscuit um
and uh you know how it sort of works
uh and sort of the surprises where the
things that we ran into
while building biscuits you know things
that we anticipated and some things that
we actually did not anticipate
um so the user programs you know there's
a classic external
uh monolithic kernel in the same way
that linux or xv6 is
and so there's user space and there's
kernel space uh
user space programs are uh you know
whatever you know it's your compiler
gcc or in our specific paper again it's
mostly a web server
and some other benchmarks uh
and the user programs are actually all
written in c
although it could be principle in any
language you know but since they are
just a benchmark
you know we took c versions and
most of the programs are multi-threaded
so unlike in
xv6 where basically there's one fret per
user program
in biscuit actually you support multiple
user level threads
and for basically for every user level
fret there's a corresponding kernel
thread
in the kernel and
these kernel threads are actually
implemented by go itself
and go calls these go routines
but you can think about go routines just
as ordinary frets you know in the same
way that xv6 has and the kernel
has threads
the go routines are sort of similar the
main difference here correctly is that
in xv6 you know the threads are
implemented by the kernel itself
and in this case you know the go runtime
basically provides them so they go run
time schedules them
go run them have support for like things
like sleep and wake up or condition
variables they're slightly different
asleep and wake up but there's some
condition variable
synchronization mechanism and there's a
whole bunch of other you know things
primitives in the go run them and just
provide
it by the go language itself and should
have not be implemented you know by
biscuit itself we just get them from the
go runtime
the go runtime itself runs directly on
the bare hardware
and i'll talk a little bit about that uh
more
in the lecture uh but like so you think
about this as the machine boots you know
the first thing it actually boots is the
go runtime and
that causes a little bit of
complications because go runtime
normally runs in user space as a user
level program
and assumes that the kernel there's a
kernel there for where they can ask some
services so for example it needs to
allocate memory to
uh for its heap uh and so there's a
little bit of uh yeah so i'll talk a
little bit about that there's a little
bit of shim code
that you know actually the biscuit has
to basically
trick you know the go runtime into
believing that it runs on top of the
operating system even though it's
running on the br hardware and basically
get it to boot
and then the kernel itself you know it's
a very similar you just think xv6
i think there's a group model except you
know it's a little bit more elaborate
and
more high performance and it has a
vertical memory system you know for
example implements map
you know the know it has a laptop system
except there's a more high performance
file system it has a couple drivers you
know it has a disk driver
it has a network driver it has a network
stack um
so a little bit more complete and the
way you can see that is
it has like 58 system calls you know and
like i don't know i can't remember how
much xc6 has but certainly in the order
of 1819 or something like that
uh and the total number of lines of code
is 28 000. and your xc6 is like not in
i think below 10 000 so you know there's
more features
any questions about sort of this high
level overview
oh sorry i wanted to ask about the the
interface
so the interface is just like in xb6
right
so like the the process is they have to
put something
in some register and then they
call the e call or whatever it is yeah
yeah i'll talk a little bit more about
this but it's exactly the same like
there's no difference
okay i see thank you
uh so some of the features you know
already mentioned them a little bit
maybe
more uh talking about so it's multi-core
goal is good support for concurrency and
so you know the biscuit is multi-core
in the same way that uh xv6 sort of has
at least limited support for multi-core
uh in this could we have a little bit
more fine
grade synchronization or coordination
than actually in xv6
uh it has threads you know usual level
threads uh
backed up by uh kernel threads uh which
xv6 doesn't have
and there's a general file system a much
higher performance you know i think you
know
you you're called the ext3 paper uh sort
of like you know the hd free
uh journaling file system uh it has you
know quite
you know reasonable sophisticated
virtual memory system you know using
vmas
uh and you know you can support nmap and
all that stuff
it has a complete tcpa stack you know
good enough to actually
talk to other you know network servers
across the internet and it has two
drivers with high performance drivers so
like a 10 gigabit nic
in the next lap you're going to actually
implement a little driver for a very
very simple
nic and this is a much more high
performance and sophisticated driver
and a pretty sophisticated disc driver
you know more sophisticated than the
virgil
vert i o disk driver uh that you've
sort of seen or you might have looked at
in the labs um
that's great
uh so in terms of uh the user programs
as i mentioned before every user program
runs with its own page table
uh user kernel memory is isolated by
hardware so
you you use your kernel bit basically
and every user fret has a corresponding
kernel thread so that for example when a
user fret makes a system call
it will continue running on the
corresponding kernel thread
and if the system call blocks then
another user thread in the same address
page and the user address space might
actually be scheduled by the kernel
and as i mentioned earlier kernel
threads are provided by the go
runtime and so they're just go routines
so if you write ever
uh usually have you ever written a user
level application in uh
go and you're using go and you use the
go call to create a
thread you know that those those go
routines are the ones that were actually
being used by the biscuit kernel
so talking about system calls you know
this question that uh
was just asked um so it works exactly as
roughly you know as in uh xv6 you know
the use of red boots and arguments in
the registers
uh using a little uh library you know
that provides a
system called interface uh then the user
threads execute the cis intercall
you know this biscuit runs on an x86
processor not on the wrist processor so
the assembly instructions for
actually entering their system kernel
are slightly different than on the risk
fi
on the risk five uh but you know it's
roughly similarly similar
to the wrist bike and then the control
passes through the
kernel thread uh that's you know that
was running that user thread
and then the kernel thread executes the
system call and then returns
you're assuming his exit it's a roughly
similar thing you know there's a track
frame that's being built and all that
kind of stuff okay
any questions so far before i dive into
sort of
the more sort of you know things that
were unexpected or expected but were a
little bit more challenging than
or different than i think would go than
in xv6
i have a question um i guess
i think um go wants you to use
channels more than uh mutual
locks i guess so would you like would
there be like
will the design of some things in xv6 be
like could use as
channels instead of holding a lock for
something yeah so
this is great uh great question so we
i'll come back to it a little bit at the
end
uh further down and uh we have some
slides about like what features of go
did we use
in this kit uh but you know the
in the index we didn't end up using
channels that much uh we mostly used
locks and condition variables so in some
sense closer to like the way xc6 looks
then actually uh you won you would then
you would do it with channels
we did experiment actually with designs
of the file system that were much more
channel heavy and but it didn't work out
that great
we got bad performance and so yeah we
switched back to sort of more
uh you know similar style of
synchronization as xv6 does
or linux uses
um okay so there were a couple sort of
uh little puzzles
or implementation challenges uh as we
went through
uh one uh we got to get the runtime to
work on the bare metal
and you know the required we wanted to
make of course like zero modifications
to the runtime or as little as possible
so that you know
go come out with a new version of the
runtime we could just use it
and in fact you know through the uh
years you know that we
worked on this where the coding worked
on this we upgraded the runtime many you
know a
number of times uh and that was turned
out to be a good thing and it turned out
not to be too difficult actually to get
it to work on the bare metal
uh you know go in general is designed uh
pretty carefully to sort of be mostly os
agnostic because they want to be able to
run
the mini operating system so it doesn't
rely on a ton of os features
and we basically emulated the features
that actually needed it
and mostly you know those are the
features that actually just get off the
for
go run them to get started and once it
started it runs just happily
um
we have to sort of arrange the go
routine run different applications you
know
normally in go program correct
uh there's all one single application
and here now we're using go routines to
actually run different user uh
uh different user applications uh and
uh but you know these user applications
have to run with different page tables
uh
and the little you know wrinkle here is
that you know the
we don't control or basically doesn't
control the scheduler because we're
using the go
runtime unmodified so we're using the go
runtime scheduler
and so in the scheduler we can't switch
page tables
and so what the xv6 is actually
basically what the biscuit does is very
similar to xv6
it actually switches heat stables or
when it changes from current to user
space
or the other way around so when an
entry and exit of the kernel you know we
switch page tables
and that means like in x36 and then when
you need to copy
data from user space to kernel space or
the other way around you have to do that
sort of using those copy in and copy out
functions that we also have in xv6 so
basically you do the page table walking
software
another sort of challenge or little
challenge was the device interrupts
not go run normally runs in user mode
you know doesn't really get interrupts
right from the hardware but we're using
it on the bare
metal and so we're going to get
interrupts time clock interrupts uh
interruption the network driver
interruption the disk driver etc
you know from the uart um and so we need
to
deal with that and uh and there's also
no notion
and go you know for you know switching
off interrupts like while holding a lock
you know that because it just doesn't
show up in user applications
and so we have to be a little bit
careful with how to actually write uh
device interrupt and basically the way
we did it is
we do almost nothing in the device
interrupt we don't take any locks out
basically we don't allocate any memory
uh the only thing we do is basically
sending a flag somewhere that wasn't
interrupt and then wake up
a really functional go routine to
actually deal with the interrupt
and that go routine of course you know
can use all the go features that it
wants
because it doesn't run in the context of
an interrupt handler just it runs in the
context of a normal normal go routine
then one thing that surprises uh it was
a bit more of a surprise
you know the first three things we
completely anticipated that we would
have to deal with when uh
building biscuit the hardest one that
actually hadn't
surprised us um and we learned a lot
about
it was this puzzle of the heap
exhaustion so i'm going to talk mostly
for a little while about heat exhaustion
and you know what it is you know how it
comes about
and you know how we solved it but maybe
before diving into that
you know any any questions so far
so crystal clear
okay so let's talk a little bit about
the heat exhaustion i'm not going to go
with full depth as in the paper but
at least to give you the flavor of like
what the problem is
um yeah
so in the heap exhaustion uh you know
let's say you
the blue box here is the kernel again
and you know the kernel has a heap uh
from which it allocates dynamically
memory
uh in xc6 we don't have such a heap
because we don't have a memory allocator
in the kernel every statically allocated
but the any other kernel
will have a heap so that you know you
can call malloc
you know m3 in the kernel
and you know the things that actually
get allocated on the heap are for
example
uh you know socket objects or file
descriptor objects or
process objects like you know struck
proc you know struct fd
all the structures that we basically
statically allocate and actually occur
xv6 normal kernels they dynamically
allocate them
so when you open the new file descriptor
it will be a file descriptor object you
know allocated in the heap
and so then the problem is like you know
if you're running many applications you
know they might open many file
descriptors maybe you have mini sockets
and they sort of start filling the heap
basically slowly and so
and then the issue is that at some point
like the heap is full you know there's
no
space anymore for allocating a new
object so when an
application asks for example opens new
file descriptor and there's like no
you know a new processor like this new
fork and the kernel wants to allocate
his truck proc
in the heap he's like there's no space
anymore
um and what do you do then you know what
is the
uh you know how do you deal with that
particular case
and this is typically you know this is
you know maybe in common cases doesn't
show
up that often uh but like if you're
pushing machine hard you may have you
know a couple heavy consumer processes
around user level processes you might
end in this situation where basically
you know all the available memory is
just in use and
uh your heat is just full and no process
is calling me
free yet you know because they're all
running and trying to allocate more
you know resources for their for their
particular jobs
and so all kernels face this problem
whether it's like a c kernel or a
biscuit
or uh anything and any kernel must solve
this particular problem
uh the reason they they sort of showed
up for us as a serious issue in
uh biscuit was because
in many kernels the
[Music]
you could return an error on a malloc
and in fact xv6 does that correct once
in a while but you know in
the go runtime when you call new to
allocate a go
object there's no air condition you know
new succeeds
uh and so there's no way to fail it so
let's talk a little bit about you know
possible ways to solve this problem
um the you know
we've seen it actually in xv6 once in a
while like if you remember
the b cache uh if you know x36 can't
find
uh a new block you know to free block to
use you know for storing a disc block in
and actually sometimes just panics uh
now this clearly is a
completely undesirable uh solution
and it's not a real solution so here's
like why we call it astronomy solution
uh the other sort of straw main solution
is to
uh when you call let's say you allocate
a new piece of memory
you know you can go to call alec or new
to actually allocate it
you could actually you know wait for
memory in the allocator i'm gonna
be one proposal to do it it turns out
not to be a good proposal
uh and and the reason it's not a good
proposal is that you may deadlock you
know
assume the following scenario you're
holding some let's say the kernel has
one big kernel lock
uh and you call malloc you know you wait
into the
memory allocator then basically no other
other process can run
uh and you would have a sort of deadlock
type now and your next process that
would actually try to run for example to
freeze some memory
uh you know couldn't run the next good
deadlock and of course this is if you
have a
kernel or a big kernel lock that is an
obvious problem you know but even if you
have a very
small uh you know fine-grained locking
is easy to run in a situation where
basically
the person or the process that's waiting
in the allocator
is holding some lock that somebody else
needs to actually free the memory
and that can get you basically in this
deadlock situation
um and so again strongman 3
is to basically fail uh or when you're
uh there's no memory anymore alec just
returns like a null pointer
you check with the null pointer it's no
point do you fail and use your bailout
uh but bailing out is actually not that
sort of straightforward uh
you know the process might actually have
allocated memory uh already
uh you need to get rid of that uh you
may have done some partial disk
operations like for example if you do a
multi-step you know file system
operation maybe you have done some of it
but not all of it you have to bail out
of that uh
and so it turns out to actually get very
it's very hard to get right
um and sort of interesting uh
you know when digging into this uh and
trying to think about like how to solve
this problem
you know linda sort of uses you know
both of these solutions
um and you know both actually have uh
trouble or problems
and indeed you know kernel developers
actually have difficulty to actually get
this all straight if you're very
interested in this and we want to see
some interesting discussion about this
uh google for too small to fail uh and
then you know there's a little article
that
talks about some of these complications
you know uh of
freeing memory or waiting in the
allocator uh
and uh the problem that can cause
now it turns out uh for us you know so
strongman 2 would be sort of the
solution that you could imagine doing
but then for us to just as mentioned
earlier
for biscuit was not possible because new
just cannot return
cannot fail it just always succeeds so
we got to range in some way that just
this cannot happen uh plus
neither of these two solutions actually
particularly ideal so we wanted to come
up with something
that was potentially better
any questions so far about the setup uh
around heap exhaustion before i talk
about like i said
how the way biscuit does it
does this problem make sense
i will interpret the signings as yes and
then keep going but
if you figure to interrupt any time
okay so what is the biscuit solution um
you know
at a high level the biscuit solution is
like almost straightforward
uh but biscuit does like when you
execute a system called like say
read or fork uh
before jumping actually into the forex
system call like right at the beginning
of the fork system call if you feel like
in the system called dispatcher
in xv6 then first thing it does actually
it calls reserve
and it basically reserves enough memory
uh
to be able to execute the system call uh
so there's reserves free memory
uh in enough that that connects in
whatever amount of memory that actually
the system call needs
uh the reservation will be big enough
that actually it will succeed
so so once the system call goes off and
actually successfully reserving memory
uh it will actually run all the way
through and we will never with the
problem that there won't be enough uh
memory or a heap exhaustion
and if there's not enough memory at the
point you want to do the recitation then
basically it just waits here
uh but at the beginning of the system
call the system call doesn't hold any
locks it doesn't hold any resources yet
so it actually is perfectly fine
you know it waits there so there's no no
risk of
uh deadlock and
while it's waiting you know it can of
course you know doing it it can call
uh the kernel can actually uh evict
caches you know
to try to reduce the uh basically make
free of hip space
maybe uh as you know you've seen that
maybe kill
a process that to force you know memory
to actually be freed
um and then once you know memory is
available and the kernel decides well
you know i can
meet the reservation then it will let
the system call basically goes off and
runs
and basically executes you know whatever
needs to be done and then at the very
end you know when the system calls down
it's just like okay i'm done
and all the memory that was reserved
basically goes back to the pool
uh available for subsequent system calls
and so there's a couple nice properties
about this particular solutions
uh there's no checks necessary in the
kernel itself right like you never have
to check you know whether
memory uh and memory allocation can fail
which is particularly
in our case good because you know and go
they can't fail
there's no error handling code
unnecessary at all and there's no risk
for deadlock because you're
avoiding in the very beginning without
when you actually hold no locks
of course you know this is all wonderful
and well
the only thing is like how the you know
there's a challenge of course how you do
the reservation you know how do you
compute
you know how much memory a system call
might need to uh to
execute it and so that was sort of a
puzzle
um and you know that it's important that
that
uh the amount you reserve you know one
one you could do is like you can reserve
like half a memory or something like
that like some
ridiculous amount of memory for every
system call but that means you limit the
number of system calls you can execute
concurrently so you want to sort of
do a pretty good job at actually uh
computing a bound
of the amount of memory that the system
call
might need so
the way uh we
ended up doing this and turned out like
sort of the high level language
helped us here uh turned out like go is
actually pretty easy to
statically analyze in fact the go uh
runtime and go infrastructure ecosystem
comes comes with a whole bunch of
packages
to analyze go code and we use those uh
basically to compute uh the
amount of memory that the system call
needs so you can think about just
let's say like you know you have to read
system call right you know
and you know we can look at the call
graph of the system call you know call
some function f calls the function g
calls the function h or blah blah blah
might continue with a whole bunch
and then do you know at the end of the
system also it rewinds to stack again
and then
goes back to the and returns to user
space
and basically what we can do is like you
know allocate you know or figure out
like what the
maximum depth you know of this this
call graph is uh at any particular time
and then basically for that maximum
depth you know computing you know how
much you know live memory each of these
you know functions need so like if this
function calls new
you know that i'll allocate some memory
you know we know what kind of objects
there are here's a high level language
so we can compute what the size of that
object is you know we can just add them
up
and that gives us some number s that
says like the total amount of memory or
the
maximum amount of memory that it can be
live at any particular point in time
for uh that call graph
and the reason is you know it's slightly
tricky it's not as simple as this
because for example a function
h you know might allocate some memory
and then
pass it back you know to g and so you
know h finishes
uh and uh but you know g actually you
know gets
uh the memory that h is allocated and
this is called escaping or the memory
escapes from
you know from h to g uh and it turns out
like you know there are standard
algorithms for doing sort of this escape
analysis to see determine which
variables escape to the callers
and uh and in that case you know
basically whatever memory was allocated
by age and that's
still alive we have to add you know to
whatever g is
uh so you know it has to be added into s
a quick question about this so
let's assume we're in some function like
depending on different workloads that
the function is expected to have
there might be different memories memory
amounts allocated
so what is there like a worst case web
memory allocation process
yeah that's basically it it's sort of
conserving the scheme correct i mean you
know we
we compute the the tool computes
basically the
uh worst possible uh depth of function
calls
um and you know for that in the worst
case it analyzes how much memory that
reach system call
might need you know in practice it might
mean the resistance might need a lot
less
uh but you know for uh you know to be
conservative you know we have to
allocate the work
we plan for the worst case and so
we've come to a couple of uh important
points here because
uh you know some system calls for
example execute the for loop that's
dependent on an argument to the system
call
right and so you can't actually
statically figure out what the bound is
and so a number of cases you know we
annotated the code to say like well this
is the maximum bound of this loop
and you can assume it's no more than
that and you use that to actually
compute this number s
uh similarly you know for example if you
have a recursive function
you know who knows how deep the
recursion is right and that might also
be
dependent on a dynamic variable or an
argument to system call
and in fact you know you know we you
know we tweak biscuit in some places to
basically avoid recursive
function calls uh so that actually was
possible to do this you know
to do this kind of analysis and so this
kind of analysis not for free it's not
completely automatic
it takes a couple days of work you know
for in this case
you know cody to go through you know
look at all these loops
uh and uh and and annotate
uh you know there are a couple other go
specific issues that you have to deal
with slices
you know they might double in size if
you uh add an element to the slice
uh and so we we annotate the slices with
some maximum capacity
uh but it's all sort of doable so a
couple days work
and uh you know using this tool then you
can sort of get a number out that is
reasonable good
in terms of you know computing uh and
a maximum amount of memory that a
particular system call needs
and so this is basically how you know we
basically biscuit solves this particular
problem
oh sorry what else are people using this
tool for
like they're not they're not building a
kernel what are they using it for over
the static analysis packages
uh yeah the go compiler internally uses
it for all kinds of uh
optimizations you know to uh uh
and do static analysis on uh the gogo to
figure out
like the best way to comp to for the
best way to compile it
i see i see okay thank you uh
so this is one of the cool things about
it just as a package you know that the
compiler happens to use you know but we
could use it too
you'll see later on we also use it for a
couple other features uh
uh it's very convenient to have
um okay uh thank you
okay turns with the implementation uh
you know biscuit was basically
very similar to other uh kernels or like
you know in xv6 except you know more
uh high performance uh you know what
we adopted many of the optimizations or
cleverness that
the linux kernel has you know at least
for the system calls that we're trying
to implement
uh you know we use large pages for
kernel text you know to avoid you know
tob costs
uh we have per cpu nic transmit cues
so to avoid synchronization uh between
port
we have an rcu uh i'll talk a little bit
more about the directory cache
that is in basically lock free or read
lock free
directory cache at the end of the
semester we'll talk about rcu in more
detail but you know uh this could happen
too
uh you know
sort of the usual type of optimization
that actually you need to get
done to get high performance and the
main
lesson i think we learned is that you
know go was not standing in the way of
implementing these optimizations
uh so you know this optimization could
be
that were implemented in c and linux you
know we basically implemented the same
uh optimization but every implemented
bingo and so the language itself is not
a hurdle or a problem in fact it was
completely conducive to actually
implementing these optimizations
it was a lot of work to implement these
optimizations but you know those
irrespective of the language
okay so that brings me sort of to uh the
evaluation which is really what the
you know motivation of the whole paper
was which is like trying to get a
handle on uh the benefits and the costs
of high-level language so basically
the evaluation uh sort of split in two
parts first talking about the benefits
and then talking about the costs
so uh so three questions you know first
of all
you know there's a question like didn't
cheat you know
maybe we avoided all the expensive
high-level language features
uh that go offers um doesn't uh this is
the second question of course does the
high level simplify the basic code and
in order to prevent some of these
exploits that you know i mentioned
earlier on in the in the lecture
so first this back to the new high level
language uh features
we just wanted to see whether we were
sort of similar in terms of other big go
projects in terms of language features
so that you know we could say like well
the kernel seems to be doing
sort of roughly the same advantage of
the same features
in sort of similar ways so we use
actually the same static analysis tool
or package to basically analyze
a whole bunch of uh two big pieces of
ghost offer that are in github
you know there are millions of lines of
code one is you know the go runtime
itself and all its packages
and uh the system called moby and then
we just basically plot it for
sort of numerous high level language
features how many times they were used
per thousand lines
so this graph shows that so usually
around the
x-axis are the language features you
know basically allocations correspond to
calling
you know new and sort of this
corresponds to memory that it will be
dynamically allocated by the garbage
collector you know maps are like hash
tables
slices or dynamic arrays you know here's
the channels synchronization as you can
see we
use them very very literally but so does
the go runtime and mobi
clearly the feature that we liked most
was multi-function return
so being being able to return multiple
values
uh you know we use closures uh we didn't
use finalizer
uh use deferred a little bit you know
there's a bunch of you know go routines
that we do create
we use interfaces uh you know type
assertions to convert from
one type to another uh in a
type state manner and importing many
packages
so the kernel itself is built out of any
packages or not like for one big single
program
so if you look at this you know some
features you know uh biscuit uses less
than gold line and mobi and sometimes
you know
basically loses some features more or
roughly in there
not not in any sort of distinctly
different way
uh so the main conclusion from this is
you know biscuit uses the high level of
features that actually go offers and
doesn't sidestep them
to basically get good forms
okay um i have a question
how did you uh how how were you able to
count all of this
did you use the static analysis tool
yeah
yeah you basically use the static uh
package static analysis package and then
wrote a little program that uses a
static analysis packages go over every
statement in these programs and look at
what kind of type of statement it is
and then or you get the argument to see
how the arguments are being used and
that gives you a sense about how
that allows you to count these features
[Music]
okay so uh the the next thing is a
little bit subjective
uh the the high level and simplified
biscuit code
uh i think it generally did
uh and i also will argue one or two
examples explicitly but
uh not having the gcd allocation is
actually very nice and maybe i can make
the point like if you think about xv6 or
like you do an exit
on a point of exit there's a lot of data
structures that need to be freed or
returned to the kernel and
so that later process can use uh using
the garbage lecture is really easy you
know the garbage collector takes care of
all of it you know you don't really have
to do much
so if you allocate you know through your
address space you know the vmas that
corresponds up at address space will be
automatically freed by the garbage
collector too
so you know just that's just simple uh
as you mentioned earlier the
multi-return values were really nice
in terms of programming style uh
closures were nice maps were great you
know
you don't have to many places xp6 for
example
you know looks up something in a linear
fashion uh
but if you have hash tables or maps as a
first class object or abstraction in the
programming language you would never do
that
right right just use map and the runtime
will take care of you know doing
everything efficiently
so in effect i think you know
qualitatively you know it feels
you get simpler code but that's clearly
qualitatively you know just to give a
little bit more of a concrete example
where
really where sort of a high level
language a particular garbage collector
shines
is you know when there's a lot of
concurrency between uh when there's
concurrency threats and the threats have
to share
a particular shared data item and so for
example the
here's the sort of simplest case you
know where you can boil down this
question too let's say you allocate some
uh dynamically an object like a buffer
um your fork fret you know and that
process that buffer and there's another
thread that also process that buffer and
do something with this buffer
then when both frets are done you know
the buffer needs to be freed so that
they can be used for
later uh you know linear kernel
operations
and the question is like who should do
this who's in charge uh
and there's a little bit difficult uh to
coordinate
uh in uh c because you know you have to
have some way of deciding that actually
the buffer is actually not being used
if you use a garbage collector there's
nothing to decide you know basically
both threads run when they're done with
the
buffer uh no threat is pointing to that
buffer anymore the garbage collector you
know will trace you know starting from
the threat stacks
and we'll never you know and will not
account the buffer in any of the fret
stacks and therefore the garbage
collector will free
you know the memory at some point later
and so in
garbage collective language you just
don't have to think about this problem
at all
um so you know one way you could try to
solve this you know problem in occurring
language like c
so you maybe could put reference counts
on the objects you know the reference
counts of course have to be uh
protected you know by locks perhaps or
by some atomic operations
and then when the refs come to reach a
zero then you you can uh different
dereference it um and it turns out like
you know locks and
reference accounts actually slightly
expensive you know if you want a
high performance you know concurrency
and scale up your watch number course
then that actually can
be your bottleneck and we'll see that
later in a couple weeks we'll read a
paper that actually
talks about this very explicitly and so
people tend to
if you want to do a high performance you
and get good parallelism you people tend
to avoid them
uh and in fact in particular the
scenario that we try to avoid them is
like uh in read lock
you would like to make at least reading
sort of lock free so you don't have to
pay the cost
and so for example here's a code
fragment that would do that
here we have a get function that
basically you know reads the head of a
queue and returns the whatever is at the
head of the cube
and does it basically in a lock-free
manner you know it uses an atomic
load to actually read the head but it
doesn't actually take a lock out
then the writer you know does stick
locks out so this is like
block free but the writer is not block
free
and this is a very common style in the
linux kernel and so the writer actually
you know takes out the lock
you know whatever looks at the head
maybe
this is the pop function and it pops up
the head from the queue
and then you know in principle you could
reuse it and then unlocks
when you free the head now again in
[Music]
in see see there's a little bit
difficult you know when do you actually
free the head
uh because it could be the case that
some other concurrent threat that just
you know
just before you did this atomic store
you know this guy actually came through
and basically got a pointer to that
particular object so
once you're done with this atomic store
you can't actually free the pointer
because you know the
could be another fret actually has a
pointer to it and if you free it right
here
you could actually have use after free
buck and so the uh
and so you know we'll see uh in a couple
lectures
uh the linux kernel has a very clever
solution for this
which is called read copy update or rcu
and basically what it does is
it defers freeing of memory until it
really knows it's safe
and it has a very clever scheme to
actually decide how to when it's safe
but that scheme does come with all kinds
of it comes with restrictions and
programmers actually have to obey some
set of rules
uh that you must follow for sort of rcu
critical sections as they're called uh
for example you can't call
uh this you can't call you can't go to
sleep in an rcu
critical section or schedule and so it
turns out that you know
although you know the linux kernel uses
this extremely successful you know it's
a bit error prone and you know that
requires careful program to get it right
and
in the case of the garbage collector
language like you know go this is again
this is like a non-issue
because the carbs collector will
actually determine when actually
something's not in use anymore and then
only then free it
and so there's nothing really you know
there's no restrictions on the
programmer
uh it just taken care of by the garbage
collector
so that's sort of an example of you know
where sort of more maybe
quantitatively or more you know explicit
you can see sort of the advantage of a
garbage collected language
okay turns to the cvs you know i sort of
mentioned this already
we went through all these cvs and you
know sort of inspected them manually
and then tried to decide whether to
actually go with fix the problem
if we're living them you know we
couldn't figure out you know we looked
at the fix
you know the the patch that addresses
this if we
couldn't really figure out like what the
outcome and goal would like or how it
would manifest or how would
change we could see how we implemented
the fix but we couldn't decide whether
it would actually go with avoided the
problem or not
uh there were a number of logic blocks
in these cvs and so
presumably you know go you remain the
same logic bug as in c and you know
the the outcome would be the same but
then you know there were about 40
memory safety bugs you know use after
three or double freeze or out of bounds
and in you know eight of days you just
disappear because the garbage collector
takes care of them as i sure described
in the last couple slides
and in 32 cases you know we go with a
generated panic because your example
would go
outside of an array bound um and
of course panic is not good you know the
kernel crashes but it's probably better
than a security exploit
and so yeah so in 40 cases you know
basically the high level language helped
us
okay so that's the quality of the the
benefits
so now i want to talk a little bit about
the uh
the performance cost i love language
text
but before doing that let me ask if
there's any more questions
okay um you know i'm going to go through
them i'm not sure
we'll make it through all six uh because
i want to reserve a couple minutes at
least at the end you know to come back
to the
the starting point of the lecture
today's question
uh so the setup in terms of experiments
uh
you know the basically runs on raw
hardware
so these experiments are on little
physical machines not on top of qmu
there's a four core 2.8 gigahertz uh
intel processor 16 gigabyte rim but
hyper that's disabled we use three
applications
a web server a key value store and a
mail server benchmark
and all these applications stress uh the
kernel intensively
and so they run execute system calls and
the kernel must do a lot of work and you
can see that because
most of the time actually in this
application is spent in the kernel
so first question is like is linux even
or is biscuit even in the
neighborhood of you know production call
the uh
kernel or industrial quality kernel and
so what we did we compared the apps you
know through biscuit and linux
for linux we used 4.9 linux it's a
little bit out of date now because the
papers of course are
a couple of years old again but of
course when we linux we had to disable
all kinds of features that
uh biscuit uses or doesn't provide i
mean so like
page table isolation reptilian you know
all kinds of you know
long lists of features that interaction
disco doesn't provide norix36 provides
and we disable them linux to make the
comparison as fair as possible
and of course you know some features are
hard to disable and you know
we were not able to disable those but
you know we tried to get as close as
possible
and then you know we measured basically
the throughput and you know as you can
see you know the
biscuit is almost always slower
uh was always slower than linux uh
you know for mailbench you know it's
about to get whatever 10
on ngx gets a little bit more you know
the red is a little bit of 10 15 percent
but you should just use these numbers
very very grain salt right because
uh you know they're not identical uh and
it's not an apples to apples comparison
uh but they're like two sort of first
order you know they're roughly in the
same ballpark at least you know they're
not like 2x 3x 4x or 10x off
and so you know maybe it is worthwhile
to actually you know be able to do and
actually
you know to draw some conclusions out of
it
so um
so then we sort of looked at like you
know we looked basically profiled the
code and tried to
bucket you know the cycles uh that were
spent by the code and
particularly we're looking at like now
which cycles were actually in the
garbage collector
prologue of function calls uh
and the prologue actually in go does a
bunch of work you know to ensure
that the stack is large enough so you
don't run off to stack
uh write various cycles this is actually
uh
when in garbage collection mode you know
the
garbage collector turns on right
barriers
to basically track pointers between uh
different spaces
um and the safety cycles you know which
are safety cycles are
the cycles spent on
rebound checks and things like that and
no appointed checks
and so if you look at these applications
you know here are the numbers
so three percent of the execution time
was actually spent in sort of gc
cycles and i'll talk a little bit about
why that's low um but you know there is
the case that the card's collector was
running
while running these applications so it's
not the case that we measured the
applications you know we get so much
memory that you know just could run
without after half of running the
uh the garbage collector uh surprisingly
actually the prologue cycles turned out
to be the highest
uh and this is basically you know the
way they the scheme that we're
using that time for uh checking what the
kernel stack or the stack of the threat
needed
or go routine needed to be grown or not
and this is something that actually you
know the go
desires that point in a thought that is
probably easier to get lower
uh very little time actually barriers
and you know so two to three percent you
know in the
uh safety cycles uh and so in some sense
you know the
this is good news you know not uh you
know the tax is not
you know gigantic uh of course this
number could be much higher
you know because this is completely
dependent on how many
uh how big you know the heap is or light
and
how big the live number of live objects
is because the garbage collector will
have to trace all the live objects to
actually determine which objects are not
like
and so if you know there's a lot of live
objects you know the garbage collector
will have to trace more objects
and so it's completely sort of linear
with the number of live objects
so we did some other experiments let me
zoom ahead a little bit
where we basically i allocated a ton of
light data like a 2 million imb notes
think about this as 2 million eye notes
and then free the amount of sort of
head room or like change the amount of
headroom that the garbage collector has
you know for
free memory and then impact and then
measure the the cost
so this is the table here so we have
like 640 megabytes of light data
and then there's we run it with
different memory sizes and so
one says case there are 320 megabytes of
data so the ratio of life to phase two
and you see that in that case uh you
know go doesn't
do it a great imputation or search
overhead for garbage collector because
you know the guard selector needs to run
a lot you know because it doesn't have
much headroom
but you know if you basically if the
free memory is about
twice you know you could buy enough
memories the free members twice you know
that of the life memory
then the garbage collection on overhead
is not actually that crazy it's like in
the nine percent uh range
so basically to keep the gc overhead
like sort of a roughly one
around below ten percent you need about
you know three times the heap size
uh in terms of physical memory
uh any questions about this
um i had a question about the right
barriers
what are those do you is it like you
set some permissions okay
no it's not uh so if you i don't know if
you remember the lecture from a little
while ago the kind
appellant paper uh paper where we talked
about
the two and from spaces and oh
yeah garbage collector runs then uh you
have to check whether the pointers in
the from space right because it's in the
from space you have to copy it
uh and basically that the bright barrier
is very similar
that is the same sort of type idea where
you need to check every
uh pointer to see if actually it
actually uh points in
space that actually you need to guard
collect
and that's the right barrier
sorry so like the free memory
what is what is it exactly like how does
it work that the life is more than free
all right okay so you buy some amount of
memory
and live memory is actually memory that
was used by these v notes
and then there was another free under 20
megabyte that was just free
and so when this application allocated
more you know v notes
they first came out of the free memory
until the free memory is full accord and
then
concurrently the garbage selector was
running and
uh and so we run it in like three
configurations in one configuration
basically the amount of three members
twice
as the sort of the life memory
and so that means that the garbage
collector has a lot of sort of headroom
to do sort of concurrently
while running with the application and
if there's a lot of headroom
uh in this case we're in free memory
then you know the garbage collection
overheads are not that high
or they're around 10 instead of 34
okay i see i see thank you you think
about it like there's a little bit of
slack
you know sort of for the garbage
collector to do its work
right i thought that it's like total 320
and i was confused no no the total is
320 plus you know 640.
and my last line is 640 plus 1280.
okay thank you um
i'm going to skip this um
actually let me talk a little bit of
pauses you know this is a
the go garbage collector is a concurrent
garbage collector and with short pauses
uh it stops the world for a very short
period of time basically to enable right
barriers and then basically
the application keep on running while
the garbage selector doesn't
work and it's incremental as uh like the
one that we discussed a couple weeks ago
where
basically every call to neo does a
little bit of garbage selection work
and so every time that you do a little
bit of garbage collection work you know
there's some some delay
you know that's being cost correct and
so we measured
you know the uh we took one application
and looked at the sort of the maximum
pause time uh so the maximum time that
an application could be stopped you know
because the
guard's collector needs to do some work
and
it turned out to be you know the max
single pass you know 150 microseconds
that's in the case of the web server
that was using the tcp stack and
basically
uh a large part of the tcp connection
table needed to be marked
you know before you know continuing and
that took 150 microseconds
the maximum total pass time for a single
uh ngx or an http request is the sum
of the number of you know single passes
and the maximum pass time in total for a
single request
was 582 microseconds so basically when
the
request comes into the machine uh during
you know
there was a total delay of 582
microseconds to actually execute that
request
um and uh and it just happened very very
seldom you know only you know 0.3
percent of the requested times actually
had
a delay of more than 100 microseconds
um and so you know that's not good if
you're trying to achieve like
an sla or uh
where basically the longest retirement
request uh takes you know is
small uh but you know the if you look at
you know
google papers about like in the tailored
scale like you know how long the
longest request takes uh you know
they're talking about the new order of
you know tens of milliseconds or
milliseconds to 10 milliseconds
and so uh probably the programs that
uh these particular programs that
actually have a past time with maximum
price to pass number 582
microseconds is sort of within the
budget uh you know it's not ideal but
you know it's not not crazy
and so that basically says that they're
actually the
real what this basically says that they
know the go designers you know did
actually a terribly good job of actually
implementing their garbage collector
or impressively good job and this is one
of the things that we've noticed you
know while doing this project like every
time we upgraded the go run time
to the next runtime it came with a
better garbage collector and actually
these numbers got better and better
um okay one more sort of technical
detail that i want to
uh go over and uh so far
you know like the first comparison
between linux and biscuit you know it's
not really fair because biscuit and
linux implement slightly different
features so we did one more
experiment where we basically tried to
code up two kernel paths
completely identical both in uh linux
and
in uh like in c and in go and so we
looked at the
code path and sort of verified that
basically you know
it implements exactly the same thing and
we looked at the assembly instructions
to really see what what the differences
are they're going to be some differences
right because
goal is going to pay these safety checks
but look just in terms of
basic operation that at least the code
paths are sort of identical in terms of
functionality
and we did that for two code pass you
know this is difficult to do it was a
painstaking
that we did for two or cody did actually
for two and then we compared them
uh and so here's the results from one of
them this is a pipe ping-pong
you know sort of test you know your
ping-ponging a bite across the pipe
and we just looked at the code path
through the kernel to actually get that
byte from one then to the pipe to the
other end to the pipe
um and uh you know the third amount of
code in go is like this is one point
thousand lights code
and see it's one point eight thousand
lines of code
there's no allocation no gc so those
things are just
uh differ we also looked at like the run
time like where's the most time spent
and in both coast paths you know that
same top ten instructions showed up so
we sort of some confidence that the code
paths really are close
close as you can get to make them
similar
and then we looked at basically the
amount of operations you can do per
second
and as you see here you know basically
you know the go
is a little bit slower than the the c
implementation
and you know the ratio is about 1.5 15
slower and uh and that's sort of
you know if you look at the pro local
safety checks you know these are all the
instructions that the c code does not
have to execute
you know they turned out to be sort of
16 more uh
uh assembly instructions and so that
sort of roughly
sort of makes sense uh so you know the
main conclusion is you know go is slower
but pretty competitive you know not not
ridiculously slower
and that seems in line with the early
results of where we did this uh linux to
biscuit comparisons directly
okay so let me zoom a little bit further
uh let me skip this because i want to
talk a little bit about
uh this sort of the question that we
asked in the beginning you know whether
should one use a high level loan for a
new kernel
and uh maybe you're like i mean instead
of answering i have some thoughts about
this here on this slide you know there
were some conclusions that we draw and
you know it's not a crisp conclusion you
know there's some considerations
so maybe to take a step back it's just
like asking yourself the question like
what would you have preferred you know
would you prefer to write you know xv6
in the labs in c
or would you prefer to use a high level
limits for example like
go and particularly answering this
question
what kind of bugs would you have avoided
and you know maybe you had to have some
time
during this lecture to think about like
what bugs you had and i would love to
hear
you know what your experience
how you think uh switching to a
high-level lens would have changed your
experience
or if you have any thoughts on this
question at all
so let me boss you for a little bit so
you can
think about this and maybe chime in
i have had a couple of times when i did
the the thing where i create an object
in a function
and then i return a pointer to it and
then i do stuff with the pointer
and then i realize that the object is
gone yeah so this is a classic example
of a sort of use after free
case correct yeah
um the second time i realized it faster
than the first time
yeah that's definitely true we've seen
you a couple of times in those boxes
you get better at them any other
thoughts on this you know
all the experiences that people have had
think about your worst bugs or the bugs
that took the most time
would i let the language would have
helped
i think it definitely like like some of
the bugs were absolutely terrible to
deal with
but at the same time like in in this
context i
definitely appreciated having to work
with such a low-level language as c
because it helped me to really gain a
very
like a deep understanding of what's
actually going on inside the operating
system like
how it's working with memory like it it
it's definitely refreshing to
to like not have all of that abstracted
away and to actually
see exactly what's going on
that makes a lot of sense any other any
other people have opinions on this
um i think i also made
a lot of bugs in which i was
writing after the end of a string or
something like that
but then i wasn't getting any useful
feedback about it and then
very strange things happened that i
couldn't explain
um so yeah that better showed up in lab
one
where there was a bunch of strings
operations like when you're parsing
directories and things like that
it showed up in multiple apps okay okay
no i'm not surprised okay that's a great
example like you know the
it's very nice to actually have real
string objects
one thing on my end is that i i found
myself lacking whenever i needed
something like a map
and i just i cringed every time i needed
to do a for loop over
something and then find however i will
say
like coming from a high-level
programming background
this was my first real exposure to
something like c so going off of noah's
point it kind of helped me to understand
really what it means that like this code
that i'm writing is actually running on
the cpu and everything is from the
perspective of the cpu
any other
thoughts
oh i actually remember it was
specifically the difference between
cop safe string copy or just string
copy one of them was putting uh
was using the null terminator and that
was yeah
yep yeah a common c bug well so you know
first of all you know uh
thanks for the input uh of course we're
not going to change uh
xv6 to uh go or any high level limits
exactly for the reasons that you know i
think a number of you like no
uh meteor actually mentioned uh
go still hides too much and they're in
this particular class the whole purpose
is really trying to understand
everything
everything sort of between the cpu and
the system called interface
uh and so for example you go of course
you know heights threads
and you know in you know we don't want
to hide that we want to explain to you
actually how frets are implemented
and so uh we would not want to hide this
from you
so certainly future years you know of
actually six or uh this class will
keep on using c uh but like if you
implement a new kernel and
you know the the goal is not you know
educating you know students about
kernels
uh but you know the goal is to write
like a sort of a safe you know
high performance kernel you know there's
sort of you know some things you can
conclude from
the study that i've done that we've done
right
you know if memory or if performance is
really paramount you know you can't like
sacrifice 50
then you should probably you see if you
want to minimize memory use
you probably should see you see too if
safety is important or security is
important then probably the high level
language is the way to go
and probably in many cases performance
is merely important as opposed to
absolute you know
paramount and in many cases i think you
know high losing high level languages
are a perfectly reasonable thing to do
for a kernel
probably one thing i've learned or
probably you know
cody robin and i've learned from this
whole project is like whatever
programming language is a programming
language and you can use it to build
kernels you can build
user applications it's not really
standing anything in
really in the way
okay you know i think it's time to wrap
up
but you know if you uh have any more
questions you know free for you to hang
around
and ask them if you have to go somewhere
else
uh you know good luck with finishing the
map lab and
for those of you who have to are leaving
campus for thanksgiving
safe travels and well hope to see you
after thanksgiving in
monday's lecture after thanksgiving
thank you i was curious how did you
implement it like i said you are doing
that just on the hardware
so like when you start out how do you
start out
uh you know there's basically a little
shim code uh that sets up enough of the
hardware so that when biscuit you know
asks for
or when to go to a function the go
runtime ask for memory for the heap that
we can actually uh respond
uh that was one of the main things that
actually uh the go runtime actually
relies on
right i guess i was like you said that
you didn't
use a virtual machine for that so
we did of course you know we developed
okay motion development doesn't muck
[Laughter]
of course at the end we actually have to
get it running under our hardware that
also costs us a bunch of problems you
know because the boot loaders are
different you know there's a bunch of
boot code that you actually need to
write that you don't have to write if
you run it on tmu
uh and that kind of stuff but most of
the development is all done on tmu in
fact
you know if you want to hack a show
you're running biscuit on qmu
and it looks very simple to xv6 you know
the only thing it does like you know it
shows your prompt there's no window
system
nothing like that okay i see
so like what happens if you if you make
a mistake in the book
code uh it doesn't boot you know
basically nothing happens
you know it's completely nothing
how do you know ah
you will know because you know okay what
will happen is of course you don't see a
print statement like in xp6 work the
first thing we print is like you know
xv6 hello or something or
xc6 is booting uh you won't see anything
like that
and so you will see nothing and then
you know you have to track down and
guess you know what the problem might be
okay so you do it by looking
ah okay it's a little bit you can write
synchronously to the uart you know
you compute like you know stupid
characters and you see
put them in random places in the code
and hope that you see something
this is interesting thank you you know i
wanted to ask um
when you you so i know like you
implemented
the go some of the calls the go-run time
would make
um that you cannot make because you're
implementing the kernel itself
um is there any like did you just
implement just all of that in assembly
or did you say okay like some of this we
can still do and go like we can
bring go a bit closer and then do
assembly only what's necessary
or to just say like once the goal
runtime ends like
that's assembly uh that's where the 1500
lines of assembly came from
uh in biscuit you know that is basically
the code to sort of you know get
everything ready to be actually able to
run the go around time
now some of that we could have
implemented c but we didn't want to do
that because we didn't want to use any c
so we were in assembly
many of it actually requires assembly
because it's in the booting part
right but i guess some of the part
that's not the b so i'm i
i'm you know i know that some just you
cannot avoid
some boot code and assembly but could
you uh
could you have transformed some of the
assembly to go or did you go to the
absolute map
we did uh wrote a whole bunch of gold
that basically runs
uh very early on uh
and you know some of the gogos is quite
careful it doesn't do any memory
allocations
that makes sense we try to write as much
as possible you know i i
can like i have to look at the code
exactly you know to be able to answer
your uh
question specifically and you can look
at the git repo uh but you know that
uh yeah we tried to write everything and
go
and then one like kind of unrelated
small question i had
um what does go do with its go routines
that makes it possible to run like
hundred thousands of them
because you cannot just spin up a
hundred thousand p threads right
uh yeah it depends uh yeah okay so
i guess a lot longer and so the main
issue is that you know you
need to allocate a stack and uh
the go runtime actually allocates tax
incrementally and so grows them
dynamically
as you uh run your go go routine
uh this is where this prologue code is
for when you make a function call you'll
see
if there's enough space to actually make
the function call and if not it will
grow to stack dynamically for you
and often in frets implementations
uh allocating uh
threads a little bit more heavyweight
because uh
actually for example in linux you know
basically corresponds the corresponding
kernel thread is actually allocated too
and
they tend to be more heavyweight than
i see is the sketch is the scheduling of
all the go routines done completely in
user space
or does it help itself with some kernels
so
it's mostly done in user space
so the go runtime allocates a bunch of
kernel threats
uh you know they call them i think m
threads
and uh on top of that it implements the
go routines
oh so it's so it has like a couple
kernel threads that it shares to all go
routines based on which one's running
yes oh that makes a lot of sense yeah
is there uh like any c c plus plus
equivalent
like could you could you do something
like that to save
to save some memory yeah people have
done you know implemented like high
performance you know
c c libraries or uh threat libraries
that way you can create
like thousands of familiar threads or
millions of threads you know to
uh with similar style
okay uh you guys have a good break you
gotta head out youtube
see you next week oh two weeks
all right
oh go ahead um
okay sorry uh so i had a maybe basic
question about the shims
and i guess i think also maybe because
i'm just not familiar with
kind of specifically what like a runtime
is um and i guess like my confusion
comes from the fact that like
from a mental model of how like xv6 and
c
works is that c compiles c as a compiled
language
and so it goes directly to assembly or
machine code
and so it kind of just runs on the cpu
and so i guess
like there is no need for a shim for
like an xv6
os um but i guess my understanding is go
is also a compiled language so it also
goes to like assembly
so why is there a need for like a shin
in this case like why
why is is there maybe is there a shim
for like xp6 or you know what what is
different here and like
what why are there why are there things
that can't just be done onto cpu
yeah yeah yeah great question uh so i
think the answer to your question is
that the
go runtime provides all kinds of
features that like you know
you don't have correct in uh running
when you're running ce and xv6
so the go runtime provides frets go
runtime provides scheduler the
go runtime you know before it's uh hash
tables the go runtime provides a garbage
collector
that actually needs to run at runtime
right and there's no garbage collector
in xv6
and we implement the threads and uh
for example to support the garbage
lecture it needs a heap you know where
to allocate memory from and so it's like
ask the operating system underlying
operating system now please give me you
know some memories or i can use it as a
heap
and basically the shim layer implements
exactly
that kind of functionality that the go
runtime needs to do its job
at runtime
um yeah i just have
a f uh so it slightly makes sense um i
guess
a follow-up question is
maybe this is a dumb question but like
like can't we just compile the runtime
down
to machine code or runtime is compiled
to run
yeah okay so like you know the runtime
itself is also compiled but it's like
sort of part of the program that needs
to run always when you're running around
go code it has to be there like even
like c has a small runtime you know if
you think about like you know
we have like printf is part of the
shirley at the c runtime or like
streaming operations are part of the
tag right and they're compiled too but
you know there's a bunch of like small
number of functions that the c
runtime has but runtime is so small
compared to like the go runtime that you
know has to support many many more
features
because you know the programs the go
programs rely on them
i see i see and i guess like the last
question would maybe be is like
is it it kind of sounds like that in
this case the go
runtime or like actually the shim in
this case is almost
taking on some of the functionality of
normally like it's almost like it's like
a mini
it's almost kind of like it's like a
like a mini os layer like
in terms that it's just like another
layer that's performing some low level
system
functionality like reasonable yeah yeah
you can only think like maybe
you know one way to think about is
exorcism also has a very very minimal
shim
you know maybe like when it boots
correct the first thing it does actually
it allocates from stack so that you can
actually call
the c main function and you can think
about that that little fragment of code
which is all in a couple statements
it's the same layer for xv6 and once you
know you're through that couples
instructions you're actually in c code
and everything is fine
and you know the the shim layer for the
go runtime is slightly bigger because
there's a bunch of more features that
need to be set up before the go runtime
can actually happily execute
ah okay yeah that that's helpful that
makes sense
cool thank you you're welcome
happy thanksgiving yeah youtube oh i had
a question about the
ping pong program that i forgot to ask
so
i remember we also did a ping pong
program in one of the labs
and it was not a hundred those are a
thousand
lines of code why is
ah because i think uh are you referring
to lab one where you do the ping pong of
a bite across the pipe
yeah okay so that's the user side of the
benchmark
the kernel side correct is the other
side of it and basically you know the
what we did is implement the kernel pass
in an identical manner
okay so like you know you actually
executing the start of the system call
or you're saving variables in the stack
frame you know calling into
looking up the pipe you know and then uh
running maybe the scheduler to wake up
you know the receiver
uh and that whole code path you know on
the kernel
uh we try to implement it identically in
c and
go okay but the benchmark is basically
the same as your benchmark that you
implemented actually in lab one
the usual level side of it right right
okay that makes sense
so so does that mean that like
i mean i think that if you do that in
x56 it would be
significantly less than a thousand lines
of code if you like
take all the kernel code that is oh so
there's a thousand thousand lines for
assembly instructions correct
uh so you know you i i don't know i will
have to look at it but you know you're
gonna
you're gonna use the trap frame code
your statistical dispatch
going to the
[Music]
fd layer correct the file descriptors
then
uh a little bit of pipe code then
uh so copy in and copy out then the
scheduler
and then basically all and then bailing
out again or
returning yeah okay that makes sense
there is a you know i don't know on the
top of my head how much lines of code is
but you know there's
right yeah