all right anyone hear me
good all right today we got meltdown
um the reason why we're reading this
paper
is that you know security has kind of
been
a topic all along and comes up a lot in
the design of the kernels
that we talked about in the class and as
we know the
main strategy we've talked about for
what it means for a kernel to
provide security is isolation in the
sense that you know user programs can't
read data from the kernel and user
programs can't read
other users data from other user
programs
and the specific techniques that um
we've seen operating systems use in
order to get isolation are things like
the user supervisor mode and the
hardware and the page tables and
hardware
as well as uh just sort of well-designed
kernel software like the system calls
are all defensive about how they
use user-supplied pointers
but it's worth thinking about looking at
examples of
how this kind of stuff goes wrong i mean
in fact you know colonels try hard to
provide isolation security but
um there are problems that come up
and this paper is one of the most
interesting problems
that's come up with operating system
security in recent times
meltdown is came out it
was published at the beginning of 2018
so not too long ago
and a lot of people like me found it
surprising and actually pretty
disturbing
pretty disturbing attack on user kernel
isolation
it really undermined faith or sort of
this very basic assumption that the page
tables
that the hardware supplies just gets you
isolation and that's the end of the
story
this attack does not support that view
at all
further it was an example of one of a
number of recent examples of what's
called a microarchitectural attack
an attack that involves
[Music]
exploitation of hidden implementation
details
inside the cpu that are often not even
known how this how cpus work but people
guess
and they're able to make successful
attacks based on correct guesses
about hidden details of cpu
implementation
meltdown turns out to be fixable and uh
seems to be pretty completely fixed but
nevertheless people it
sort of set people up to fear that there
might be an open-ended supply of
similar micro-architectural attacks
so it's a pretty important recent
event worth understanding
let me start by uh just
laying out the basic core of the attack
and we'll talk about what's going on
here but this is a somewhat simplified
version
of the code in the paper for how the
attack works
the basic idea is that you're an
attacker and
for one reason or another you're able to
run software on
some computer that has some secrets that
you'd like to steal
you're not allowed to directly get at
the secrets but they're in memory maybe
kernel memory or another processes
memory
but you've been able to run a process
maybe because you
logged into a time sharing machine like
an athena machine or maybe because you
bought time on some hosting service um
and so what the attack allows you to do
is run a program in which
you declare a buffer in your own memory
so this buff
is uh just ordinary user memory that's
accessible
you have the virtual address in the
kernel
of something that you're interested in
stealing
and you issue what i'm writing out here
is sort of a
you know a mix of c and assembler but
what i mean in line three is that
you have the address of the the kernel
virtual address of the data you want to
steal and register 1 and r1
and on line 3 or just imagine that this
is instructions to dereference
register 1 and load its results into
register 2.
that's the instruction that we're going
to run and then there's an instruction
that
just gets the low bit of register 2. so
this attack this particular version of
this attack reads just
a single bit just one low bit of
one memory location from the kernel and
multiply that four thousand
four thousand and ninety six and since
it's either zero or one that means that
r2 will end up being zero four thousand
nine six and then we simply read
the contents of our buffer which is a
buffer and user memory
we simply read either buffer of zero or
buffer of 4096
and that's the basic attack um
so one question is why doesn't this just
directly work
like line three is reading this kernel
address
can we just read addresses from the
kernel
no no we all have faith that the answer
can't possibly be us
we can't possibly be able to just
directly read from the kernel if we're
in user space
and the machinery that we know the cpu
somehow is invoking to make this not
work out
is that when we use a kernel virtual
address
that implies a lookup in the page table
and there's permission bits in the page
table and we're just assuming that the
operating system
has not set the flag in the page table
entries for kernel virtual addresses has
not set that flag that allows
users to use those addresses that's the
pteu flag on
the risk 5 and that therefore this
instruction must fail
must cause a page fault right and indeed
if we ran this code this instruction
would cause a page fault
and if we tried to if we you know added
a
code after this to say print the value
in register 3
we get a page fault on line three and
we'd never get to the print statement
and we'd find we couldn't directly steal
data out of the kernel
nevertheless the sequence turned out to
be useful as the paper shows
one thing that
one thing that the paper assumes which
is no longer really true for the most
part
is that the kernel is mapped into
every user processes address space
that is every when a user when user
code's running
a full set of kernel ptes is present in
the page table
but they have the pteu bit clear so
user code will get a fault if it tries
to use a kernel
a virtual address so all those mappings
in in
at the time this paper was written all
those mappings were there when executing
in user space
they just couldn't be used by user code
or they cause a fault they were used by
user code
and the reason why people by operating
system designers
mapped both kernel and user addresses
when you run a user code is that made
system calls um quite a bit faster
because that meant that on a when a
system call happened you didn't have to
switch page tables and switching page
tables usually
usually takes time itself and also
typically causes
cpu caches to be flushed which makes
subsequent codes slower
so people got a boost by mapping both
user and kernel mappings always in user
space
but but this attack actually and this
attack relies on that habit
okay so i'm going to explain
what's going on here that makes this
code useful but before i do that
any any questions about
any questions about this this code
fragment
is actually wondering if you could
repeat what you just said about
kernel to user mapping it didn't really
register
okay let's see the
um you know how in xv6
when you're executing when the process
is executing in user space
if you look at the page table that page
table has mappings for the user
addresses
and for like the trampoline page and the
trap frame page and nothing else
so that's how xv6 works the page table
that this paper assumes we're different
from that
this in the time this paper was written
most operating systems
um would have a set complete
set of kernel mappings in the page table
while user code was running
um and then so all those page table
entries would be there
all the kernel page table entries would
be there when user code was running but
since the pteu bit
was clear on each of those page table
entries user code wouldn't actually be
able to use the kernel virtual address
but the mappings were there and the
reason for that is that when you do a
system call
you didn't have to switch page tables
because
you do a system call into the kernel and
boom you're using the same page table
but
now you can use all those kernel pdes
because you're in supervisor mode and
that saved a bunch of time
getting into and out of the kernel
during system calls so so everybody
everybody used that technique and indeed
that was almost certainly what intel had
in mind
for how you should write an operating
system
okay so that for the whole paper that
structure is
is assumed for the attack of course
getting rid of it is
was the most immediate solution to this
problem
but at the time that people was written
all those kernel mappings were present
in user space
other questions
so you need to know the address that you
want to
get yeah that's right it is
uh and
um so you know so that's a good point
you need to know the kernel virtual
address and that's actually
maybe no joke um
you might think that would make the
attack harder
um but first of all a point of
philosophy
in security you just have to assume that
the attacker has infinite time and
patience
and that if they're after some valuable
secret they are probably willing to
spend like a couple of months
trying to steal that secret um or longer
right because you know it's going to be
somebody's password that like protects
all kinds of valuable stuff maybe money
or
you know secret email so
that means for example the attacker
probably has time to try every
single kernel address right looking for
whatever precious data they're after
maybe a password
or the attacker may have time to like
study to look through the kernel code
and look through
typical compiled kernels and find
addresses and maybe put print statements
in their kernels to
examine the structure of data and kernel
memory until they understand
how the kernel works well enough to
be able to get an address here now
actually
because this game has been going on
other versions of this game
of the security game have been going on
for a long time colonels actually defend
themselves
um against attacks that involve
guessing kernel addresses and one of the
things
that was actually mentioned in this
paper is this called thing called
uh kernel address space
layout randomization so modern kernels
actually
load the kernel at a random address in
order to make it harder
to guess kernel of kernel virtual
addresses and they did this before this
long before this paper came out because
it was helpful in
defeating other attacks so so
this is the game but
we have to assume that the attacker in
the end the attacker will
probably win this game okay
so we'll just assume the attacker either
knows a juicy kernel virtual address to
look at or can guess one or is willing
to exhaustively try every address
and the paper suggests that that's a
plausible strategy
once you have meltdown
okay okay so what's going to happen
well so we're wondering how can this
code be
um possibly be useful to an attacker and
the answer has to do like if the way
cpus worked was just what you read
in the cpu manual this attack clearly is
nonsense
like it'll fault at instruction three
and that'll be the end of it but it
turns out cpus
work in far more complex ways are is in
the manual
and the way the reason the attack works
is because of
some cpu implementation details
and there's there's actually two main
things that the attack relies on one is
an implementation trick of cpus called
speculative execution
which i'll talk about first and and the
other
implementation trick the attack relies
on is the way cpus do caching um
okay so first speculative execution
um let me let me uh
i have a code example for that also um
and
for the moment i'm not talking about
security at all i'm the speculative
execution this stuff is
just a technique to improve the
performance of uh
cpus and some optimization trick that
cpus use
so imagine that um you know we're just
we have we're just running this code um
this is a somewhat contrived example but
it's sort of illustrates
uh what speculative execution is all
about um
supposing i have a uh address in some
say register zero and just because the
logic my program the address
is either valid or not valid maybe it
contains zero if under some
circumstances like we haven't
initialized
my data yet so there's this we'll assume
there's some a valid variable that's
sitting in memory somewhere
and so before using the address here
this address and register 0 here on line
4 we're going to test
we're going to load valid from memory
and we're only going to use the address
if valid is set to 1. and a valid is set
to zero we're just
not going to use the address at all and
if valid is set to one then we're going
to dereference the address
and you know load the data it points to
and to register two and add one to it
and it doesn't really matter
we're gonna do something with that data
we loaded in this case add one to it
and set the register three equal to the
the data plus one all right well
um in a simple cpu implementation
uh on line two here um you gotta load
the valve is a variable sitting in
memory in ram um
and you we have to issue some kind of
this is gonna be line two is gonna be
some sort of load instruction that reads
valid out of ram um all else being equal
if we actually have to load it from ram
that'll take hundreds of cycles on our
say two
gigahertz machine like any load that
actually has to go to ram will take
hundreds of cycles
the machine you know can execute an
instruction
up to an instruction every cycle so if
we actually had to wait a couple of
hundred
cycles here we'd be the machine would be
sitting there idling for hundreds
hundreds of cycles sort of wasting its
time
and because that's a significant
significant slowdown
right if if all everything went well
we'd be able to execute an instruction
every cycle instead of every couple
hundred cycles
all modern all serious modern cpus do
use something called branch prediction
so this if statement is a branch um if
we'd actually turned it into machine
instructions we'd see there was a branch
here
and it's a conditional branch branch
based on this
uh test of whether register one is equal
to one and what cpus do is they use
what's called branch branch prediction
that is for every branch
um more or less the cpu
essentially remembers a cache of
information about each of the branches
in your program or at least each
recently executed branch
and remember so did that branch was the
branch taken or not taken
and if the cpu doesn't have enough
information
to predict so that's prediction based on
the last time you executed the branch
even if the cpu doesn't have a
prediction it may still
just go ahead and execute the
instructions
um either that the branch takes you to
or the fall through instructions
assuming the branch wasn't taken that is
even before the cpu knows whether this
conditional is true
it'll choose one way or the other and
start executing down that path
even though it might be the wrong path
it doesn't know yet
and so in this case maybe before this
load completes and before
the value of valid is known the cpu may
start
executing instruction four and do the
load with whatever
value is sitting in r0 which may or may
not be a valid pointer
and once that load yields something
maybe even add one to it and set
register three equal to that value
and then maybe a long time later when
this load
at line two finally completes um
i mean now we know what the value of
valid is
the cpu will then this real you know
didn't know it kept track of the fact
that it
executed lines four and five without
really knowing whether that was proper
if valid is one then that's fine and it
just keeps going
if valid is zero then the cpu has enough
cleverness to cancel
the effects of its execution of line
four and
five and restart execution in the proper
place after the branch
at line seven and this execution of code
before you know whether you really
should be executing it
is called speculation
and again the point is performance if
the cpu guess is right
then it got a big head start executing
these instructions
and didn't have to wait for the member
for the expensive memory load
any questions about what this means
okay this machinery
the hardware the transistors in the cpu
for speculation
are extremely complex there's a
huge amount going on in the cpu to make
this work
none of which is published right it's
all
intel internal stuff not in the instruct
not in the machine manual
so surrounding meltdown and attacks like
it is a huge amount of speculation about
what's probably going on inside the cpu
in order to make such-and-such attack
work or not work
okay back to speculation though um
the uh um
uh one thing that's going on is that um
in order to undo speculative
failed specula mispredicted speculative
execution
the machine had keeps shadow versions of
registers essentially
you know it'll assign to registers 2 and
register 3 but
it'll it's assigning kind of a temporary
registers
if the speculation succeeds
then those registers those shadow
registers become the real registers
if it fails then those shadow registers
are discarded the cpu discards the
shadow registers
so these two assignments r2 and r3 would
just be as if they never happened
so in this code we need to think about
what happens if register 0
is a valid pointer and what happens if
it's not a valid pointer
right if we're speculatively executing
line four
and register two is a valid pointer then
it turns out the cpu will actually do
the load
and load it into at least the transient
version of register two so we'll
actually go out and
and uh try to fetch what r0 points do
and
that will certainly work if that if r0
if the data r0 is
pointed to is sitting in the cache and i
don't know if if the cpu will do the
load
if it misses in the cache and has to
load from ram it might
but maybe the more interesting question
for us for this attack is what happens
if register 0 is not a valid pointer
in that case if we're speculatively
executing here
the machine can't fault at this point
because we're speculatively executing
the machine
doesn't know it may know that r0 was an
invalid that
that this speculatively executed
instruction tried to use an invalid
pointer
an invalid address but it can't page
fault because it's not sure whether this
execution
is val is a correct speculative
execution or
misspeculation and so it's only
so so it can't actually raise a fault on
line four
until after valid the value of valid is
known and
after this branch this
specular predicted branch um is after we
know what after the machine knows what
the condition is
if the machine see you know if the
machines that line 4 sees oh register 0
is an invalid
address and then valid turns out to be 1
then and only then does the machine
actually generate the page fault
if r0 was an invalid address then valid
turns out to be zero
the machine does not generate a page
fault
so the pate the decision about whether
default is deferred possibly for
hundreds of
cycles until the value of valid is known
and the technical term for the point at
which we
know whether an instruction
was correctly speculatively executed
rather than being thrown away is called
retirement
so we say an instruction is speculative
and and
at some point it's retired and that's
when we know
it's either going to be thrown away or
was real and should be its effect should
be committed to the
visible state of the machine and the
rule is that
an instruction can only be retired if
first of all
it's finished executing you know loading
memory or adding one to something
and every instruction before it that was
executed before it has also retired
so you know this line four can't be
retired until the
load of valid completes and the
condition is
is evaluated only then can be retired so
if it's going to fall to me it's going
to fault
possibly hundreds of instructions after
it did the memory load
or attempted to do the memory load
and as a critical detail for this attack
there's an even more uh that if
let's see if the um if the address in r0
is
invalid and has no mapping in the page
table at all
then i actually don't know what happens
um
if the address in r0 has a page table
mapping
but there's no permission for it that is
the ptu flag
is not set then what intel machines
actually do
is load that data and assign it into the
transient register 2
and where it can be used by the
speculative execution of line 5.
so even if r0 wasn't was a address for
which we don't have permission because
it's a kernel address
we'll still see its value loaded into r3
and its value plus one
sorry we won't see it but it will be
loaded into r2
and that plus one and r3 and then
when this load is retired the machine
will realize aha
that was an invalid load because the
page table entry didn't allow it
and so we're going to raise a fault and
cancel
the execution of the subsequent
instructions and cancel the
effects of this instruction undo
the modification to r2 and r3 so in this
example
there's two speculations going on
one is we're speculating about where
this bran the machine's speculating
about where this branch went
and just saying oh it went one way or
the other i'm just going to give that a
shot speculatively
in addition there's speculative
execution after each load we're
essentially speculating about
whether the um the machine is
speculating
about whether that load uh completes
successfully
and in the case of a load intel machines
always just go on
you know if data could be provided
because it's in the cache and
at least the page table entry exists
permissions are not the machine will
speculatively continue to execute
and only on retirement of the load
will it actually generate the fault and
that will cause the speculation to be
cancelled
all right any questions about this stuff
i'm a little confused about um the the
second speculation which is uh loading
r0 into r2
so um does that mean that like
the value of r0 is loaded into r2 and
the flags are checked later
um yes yes
so what happens yes that's exactly right
so what actually happens
is that during the speculative phase um
whatever it is that our zero points do
if there's sort of an
if it points to anything if r0 points to
anything
then uh the the data at that memory
location will be loaded into r2
later when this load is retired
and it turn then the permissions will be
checked
and if we didn't have permission to do
that load
then all subsequent instructions effects
will be canceled like all these
modifications are registered will be
undone
um and default will be raised
with the state of the machines and
registers as they were just before
instruction
for okay that's interesting
yes yes i also have a question
is there no possible way to restrict the
cpu
from checking permissions before doing
uh speculative load
um you mean is there a way to cause the
machine
to do the check before the load
yes i guess more concretely like the
only reason this is a problem
or one of the ways is that we're just
loading a page that if we can be aware
that it has
permissions that are gonna like be bad
somehow
right we're actually accessing a page
that we don't we shouldn't be able to
access
the can the speculative execution be
cancelled given that we can read these
permissions
yes yes that's uh yeah um
well there's two answers one is that's
not the way the intel chips
cpus actually worked and the other
answer is yes
it would have been i i believe it would
have been easy for them
to have done and enforce the check even
for speculative loads so that
even in speculation register 2 would
never have been written
so so
and indeed it turns out that you may not
have noticed the paper mentioned that
the
meltdown seems not to work on amd
cpus even though emd cpu's
the instruction manual is the same as
for intel cpus essentially that is
they've on the same instruction said and
the instructions mean the same things
the attack doesn't work on amd cpus
and it's widely believed that the reason
is that amd cpus
even when speculatively executing
if you don't have permission to
read this address won't even
speculatively
load the value into r2
and that's why the attack didn't work on
amd cpus and
recent intel cpus apparently
have adopted that approach and they
actually
won't won't speculatively load
if they don't have permissions and as
far as i know there's no
particular sacrifice and performance i
think the information was all there
but for but just i don't know just
say maybe a few gates they decided only
to apply it on on retirement
because they still need to be very
interesting
yeah let me just warn you this there's a
lot of guesswork here
um and i believe what i'm saying is true
but
in intel and amd have not been very
revealing about what's going on
okay um there's a there's a uh
some terminology here that's it's
important the what you read
in the manual for the cpu that says oh
you know an ad structure takes two
registers and adds them and puts them in
a third
that's stuff um that aspect of the
design is called architectural
um it's sort of the advertised
uh behavior
the advertised behavior the machine um
and so the advertised behavior of the
machine is that if you load from an
address you don't permissions for you've
got a page fault period and you're not
allowed to load
and that's indistinction to what the
machine's actually doing which is called
micro
architectural
that is you know actually the machine
has speculative executions doing all
these crazy things
without telling you and the intent
of the cpu designers when they design
all these complex micro
architectural optimizations is that they
be transparent that yeah you know it's
doing all this stuff internally but
it looks the results you get from
programs are the same results you would
get from a simpler machine that
just did the straightforward thing that
was in the manual
right they're intended to be transparent
and so you know for example
at some level what intel was is doing
here is transparent yeah maybe they
don't check for permissions when you
when you do the memory load
but if there was a problem on retirement
it's going to undo
all these effects and so you'll never
see that memory you weren't supposed to
see so gosh that looks just like what
the manual said
you're not allowed to load stuff you
don't have permission for it
so this distinction is
a lot of what this attack is playing on
that it's knows all the attack knows a
lot about
what's going on inside
okay other questions about uh
speculative execution
okay i'm going to put that aside for a
moment and talk about another
piece of microarchitecture
and that's uh caches
and these again i mean everybody knows
caches are there but you know they're
supposed to be more or less
or less transparent so
and let me draw a picture of the caches
i think are relevant the cache structure
that i think is
most relevant to meltdown so first of
all you have the
you you have the core which is the
you know the part of the machine that
parses instructions and has registers
and
has an addition unit and a division unit
you know whatever the sort of execution
part
of the machine and then
whenever it needs to do a load or a
store
it talks to the the memory system
and the memory system has a bunch of
caches so in particular in the machines
we're talking about
there's a data cache
called a level one data cache
that is maybe
uh you know 64 kilobytes in size or
something not very big but it's
extremely fast
um if you if the data you need is in the
l1 cache that
it'll get back to you in a couple of
cycles and the structure of the l1 cache
it has a bunch of lines what are called
lines
each of which holds probably 64 bytes of
data the lines are indexed
it's a table really the cache the lines
are indexed by virtual address
um if a virtual address is in the cache
then
the cache holds the data for that
virtual dress
and in addition as it turns out
it's believed that a l1 cache entry
contains a copy of the permissions taken
from the page table entry that
corresponds to this virtual address
so there's a whole this is a
table when when the core is used a load
instruction
um the first thing that happens is that
the hardware looks in the l1 cache and
see if there's a
cache entry whose virtual address
matches the
requested
the address we're trying to load from it
and if so the we can just the
machine just returns this data from the
cache we're done very quickly
if the data is not in the l1 cache then
the next step
is that we um the rest of the memory
system is
is in is addressed with physical
addresses so we at this point we're
going to need a physical address if we
missed
the l1 cache this translation look aside
buffer is a cache of page table entries
so we're going to look up the virtual
address that the
program issued in the translation
leukocyte buffer
it may not be there in which case now
we've got a lot of work to do because
we've got to load the relevant page
table entry from memory
but let's assume we hit in the
translation look aside buffer we can now
get the needed physical address
typically there's another cache another
much bigger cache
that's physically indexed indexed with
the physical address
and so we might now that we have the
physical address we can look in this
cache
um and if we miss there then we have to
send the physical address after the ram
system
takes a long time but when we finally
get data back then we can populate the
level two cache
and populate the level one cache with
the stuff we got back from ram
and return the uh the data back to the
core
so this is caching
um uh just
uh by the by the hidden l1 cache
probably takes a few cycles the hidden
l2 cache probably takes a dozen or two
cycles
and a miss that requires you to go
around probably takes you a couple
hundred cycles
and these cycles are you know
less say half a nanosecond on a two
gigahertz machine
so it's extremely advantageous to have
caching i mean you would if you didn't
have caching you'd be sacrificing
a factor of a couple of hundred in
performance so these are just absolutely
critical to decent performance these
caches
now um
this cache is is the l1 cache
um well both it turns out both both
these caches can contain
if we're running in user space both
these caches and the
operating systems meltdown was aimed at
both of these caches can contain both
user data
and kernel data the l2 cache can contain
kernel data because um
it's physically addressed and there's
just no problem
um the l1 cache is a little bit trickier
it's virtually addressed when we change
page tables the contents of the l1 cache
are no longer valid because
we change page tables that means that
the meaning of virtual addresses change
so you'd have to flush the l1 cache if
you change page tables
although there's more complex tricks
that
can allow you to avoid that and so but
the fact that these operating systems
in the days of this paper didn't change
page tables when changing between user
space and kernel space because both were
mapped
meant that uh data we didn't have to
flush the l1 cache
and that meant that l1 cache would have
both user and kernel data in it and that
made system calls even faster right if
you call a system called a system called
returns there's still going to be
uh likely still to be useful user data
in the cache because
we never change the mean we never change
page tables or change the meanings of
these addresses
anyway so there's likely to be kernel
data even though you're running on user
space there's likely to be kernel data
in the l1 cache and it's these
permissions which are copied out of the
tlb
copied out of page table entries that
tells the machine
that oh even though the data is in the
cache you're not allowed to see it
and raise it raise the page fault
so this is a good time to mention that
even though the intent of micro
architectural optimizations is they be
completely transparent
that can't possibly be true because the
whole point
of these micro architectural
optimizations is almost
always to improve performance and so
they will you're
guaranteed to be at least visible
in terms of performance that is you
could tell if your machine has a cache
or not
because if it doesn't have a cache it'll
run a couple hundred times slower
right in addition you can tell whether
the data you're trying to fetch
if you're capable of measuring time
accurately enough and you do a load
you can tell if the load returned in a
couple cycles
the data must have been cached if the
load returned after
100 times that the data probably was had
to be loaded from ram
and so the differences are profound and
if you can measure time to
you know 10 a few nanoseconds or even
tens of nanoseconds
you can tell the difference so in the
performance level the micro architecture
is
absolutely not transparent and all the
things we talk about
like branch prediction caches or
whatever all that stuff is
at least indirectly visible through
timing
and so of course many people even though
the
microarchitectural design is
sort of in any detailed level secret to
intel it's just their private business
how they implement this
in fact it's all along been of extremely
intense
interest um to a lot of people because
it affects performance a lot
so compiler writers for example know a
lot about microarchitecture because
the most many many compiler
optimizations are implicitly exploiting
people's good guesses about what the
machine's actually doing inside
and indeed the cpu manufacturers publish
optimization guides that reveal some of
the micro architectural tricks
but they rarely go into much detail
certainly not enough detail to really
understand
sort of exactly why uh meltdown works
um so the microarchitecture stuff is
sort of sits somewhere between
supposed to be transparent and visible
and hidden and
sort of partially
you know certainly
a lot of people are interested and a lot
of people know all kinds of random
things about it
okay so the reason why this cache stuff
is interesting for meltdown first of all
any any questions about
about caching
okay let me talk then
um about the sort of main way that the
paper
uses caching the paper talks about this
technique called flush plus
flush and reload
um and
what flesh and reload is up to is that
it's answering the question
um did a particular piece of code
um use
the memory at a particular address and
it's not directly a security
exploit because it only works for memory
that you can get at
so if you're user code and you have some
memory that's your memory and you're
allowed to use it
you can and you call one of your own
functions or you know
then you you'll be able to tell you can
use flush and reload
to tell whether the function your
function that you just executed
used your memory you can't directly use
this attack
or it's not an attack you can't use this
technique to figure out if
some other process use that process as
private memory
although because processes sometimes
share memory uh
you may still be able to do it well
the right way to put it is you can only
find out about memory you're allowed to
access
okay so it's answering the question
did a particular function uh use this
memory so
step one
um is we're going to flush supposing we
were interested in address x
we want to flush the cache we want to
make sure the cache
doesn't contain the memory at location x
and it turns out that for our
convenience intel
supplies an instruction
called cl flush and you give it an
address
and it will get rid of it'll
ensure that that location is not
cached in any of the caches and so
that's super convenient
even if the machine didn't provide this
instruction though it turns out there's
ways of getting rid of stuff from the
cache like for example
if you know the cache holds 64 kilobytes
then it's likely to be the case that if
you load 64 kilobytes of
random memory you know just load
instructions
that um those will be loaded into the
cache
and after you've loaded 64 kilobytes of
new data into the cache
everything that used to be in it must be
gone because the cache can only hold 64
kilobytes or whatever it may be
so even without this nifty instruction
you can still
flush everything in the cache then step
two is
you know you're interested in whether
some particular piece of code
uses um the data x you just call that
code
whatever it is and it does what it does
maybe uses x maybe doesn't
um and now you want to tell if x is
actually in the cache because if it is
since you flushed it from the cache if
it's in the cache now it must be that
f causes it to be loaded unless
something else is going on
um so you need to you want to do a load
but you want to know how long the load
takes
so but you know we're only talking about
nanoseconds like 5 nanoseconds versus
100 nanoseconds here
how can we measure time that accurately
that's a
tough assignment however again the cpus
come to our a
they in fact provide an instruction
which gives you
cycle granularity time
and it's called rdtsc so we're just
gonna
execute the rdtsc instruction which
tells us essentially the number of
cycles that have elapsed
since the machine cycles that have
elapsed since the machine started
and since it's probably you know two
gigahertz machine that means that the
precision we have here is half a
nanosecond which is
pretty small and now we're going to load
we're just going to say junk
equals star x now we're going to load
the
data at location x and get the time
again
and look at the difference right b minus
a
if b minus a is you know 5 or 6 or 7 or
something
that means that the this load hit in the
cache and that means that
this function used the data if b minus a
is 150 then
that means that x wasn't in the cache
and you know that
may that probably means that f that may
mean that f didn't ever use dx now
that's not
quite that cut and dry because f might
have used x and then use something else
that conflicted with x in the cache and
caused x to be kicked out of the cache
again
but you know for simple situations
a very large value of b minus a means f
didn't use it and a small value of b
minus a means that f
did use that data
so this is not an attack yet because
again
we have to be able to access this memory
so this is our memory
any questions about flush plus reload
all right i think that's all the
preliminaries
uh let's go back to meltdown
so this is a more full version i showed
you a
sort of core meltdown at the beginning
this is a more
complete meltdown
and so we actually now have i added the
flush and reload part
again we're going to declare this buffer
and um
the idea is that uh depending on we're
going to be
just patching one bit from the kernel
and we're going to multiply that one bit
by 4096 so we're hoping to use flush
plus reload to see that either
buff of zero is in the cache or buff of
in the cache and the reason for the
large separation there
um is that apparently the pref
this hardware has a prefetcher in it so
if you load one thing from memory
it'll like load the next couple things
up from memory to the next couple cache
lines
and so we can't have the two different
cache lines
that we're going to apply flush and
reload to be to be particularly close
we need them to be far enough apart that
even prefix hardware prefetching won't
uh
cause confusion so we put them the whole
page apart
the flush part now that we just call the
cl flush instruction
to make sure that the relevant parts of
our buffer are not cached
now
um
we're exploiting this line seven is not
maybe
may or may not be necessary but what um
what's going on here is we're exploiting
the sort of the um
um we're going to be exploiting the gap
in time
uh between you know we
uh we're doing this loaded line
10 it's a load of a kernel address so
it's going to fault
but we're hoping to be able to execute
another couple of instructions
speculatively before the this
instruction is retired
and before it actually raises the fault
and cancels
these instructions right if the fault if
this load would be to retired say at
this point
that would be too early for us because
it's going to turn out we actually
need line 13 to be speculatively
executed
in order to complete the attack so we
want to make sure that this load isn't
retired
for as long as possible in order to
delay the fault and
delay the speculative cancellation
now we know instructions aren't retired
until all previous instructions have
retired
that's one of the rules so at line seven
i'm imagining that we're going to launch
some expensive instruction that doesn't
complete for a long time
you know maybe it loads something else
that's known to have to come from ram so
it'll take a few hundred cycles or
maybe it does a divide or a square root
or something who knows what
something that takes a long time and
won't be retired for a long time
and therefore will cause this load not
to be retired for a long time
giving these instructions time to
execute speculatively
okay all right now
we're assuming again we have a virtual
address in the kernel
um uh i'm going to execute line 10
line 10 won't raise a fault until that
we know it's going to raise the fall it
won't raise a fault until it retires but
we're intending we believe we've set
things up so we'll retire for a while
since it hasn't retired
and because on intel cpus the data's
returned
even if you weren't allowed to see it
the data's
returned for speculative execution even
if you didn't have permission
that means that we can speculatively
execute
the machine will speculatively execute
line 11 and get the low bit of
kernel data now multiplied by 4096.
line 13 is itself a load it's another
load
using an address basically the address
of buffer
plus the contents of r2
we know it's going to get cancelled
because we know this will fault right we
know the actual
right to r3 will be canceled but line 13
will cause
um some data from buffer to be loaded
into the cache
even if it doesn't end up affecting
register three so
r3 line 13 is going to cause
something to be loaded into the cache
and in this case depending on whether
the low bit is 0 1 line 13 will
cause the actual cache to contain either
buffer 0 or buffer 4096
then right and that you know that
even though r2 and r3 are cancelled the
change in the cache you know because
it's supposed to be hidden
microarchitectural state it will
actually be
the cache will be changed finally at
some point the fault will happen
um and we need to sort of recover after
the fault but
it it's just a page fault and it turns
out um
you can or user process can register a
page fault handler and get control back
after a page fault and
the paper mentions a couple of other
ways of being able to continue after the
fault
and so now all we have to do is figure
out whether it was buff of zero or
buffer 496
that was loaded into the cache and now
we can do the reload part of flush and
reload
you know read the accurate time
load buff is zero read the time again
load buff of one
read the time again and compare the two
differences in time
and whichever one of these took the
shorter amount of time
is likely to indicate whether the low
bit of the
kernel data was zero or one
and then if we report that repeat that
you know a couple of billion times
we can scan all of kernel memory um but
in this example
if b minus a is smaller than c minus b
doesn't that mean that buff of zero was
cashed
um let's see if i got this wrong b minus
a
yeah it means that buffer zero was cash
oh yeah yeah you're right yeah
now we're cooking
good catch
oh sorry do you need for before we had
an if before like my line nine
do we need it if now or is it is it
still
you know oh the if was to help me
illustrate
uh the legitimate reasons for
speculative execution keep computing
even though we don't know whether the
branch took or not but here the real
core of the speculation is that we don't
know if this load will fault
right and so we're the machine is
speculatively executing past the load
on the theory that it's probably you
know most leaders don't fault
right or even though they may take a
long time like a load could take
hundreds of cycles
um so we'd love to be able to so the
machine will speculatively execute past
the load
even though it doesn't you know not
knowing whether it's going to fault or
not and if the
load did fault it will then undo all
this speculative execution
there's a speculative execution comes up
any time you have
a long-running instruction that may or
may not succeed so like divide
so we know whether it's going to be
divided by 0 or not no so
instructions after divide are also
speculative
anyway the speculation the real critical
speculation starts here now in fact we
tried
you know in order to make the attack
likely to be more successful we
sort of ensured that speculation starts
here but this is the real speculation we
care about
other questions
for this example we've only read
one bit
yes is there some like really small
simple modification that we could make
to read like a full register
size of bits yeah run this 64 times one
for each bit
why is it not possible to just read 64
bits at a time well 60
60 well you need the buffer the size of
this buffer has to be
uh two to the um you know two to the
number of bits you're reading
times or something
so 64 bits is too big because we don't
have enough memory to uh
make a buffer that big right
we need this the way this is set up
but i rated it
yeah 64 bits too much you could
certainly read eight bits at a time
and have this buffer size be 256 times
4096.
um the paper actually argues in a
the paper observes
that since the most of the time is here
in the fleshless reload
um if you read a byte at a time
then figuring out what the bits of that
byte are takes
flush and reloads right one free once
for each possible value
if you load a bit at a time then each
bit
takes just one flush plus reload or
sort of two two probes or two flush plus
reloads
so if you read a bit at a time then you
end up only doing 16
flush plus reloads if you eat a bite at
a time you end up doing 256 flush plus
reloads
so the paper says that it's faster to do
it a bit at a time than a bite
of time which seems a little
counterintuitive but
seems to be true
other questions
so uh where would this user or where did
this program have to be
run from is there like any particular
location
on the machine like does it have to be
or like where would you ride it i guess
like where would this program be run
from uh can it be like a user
well yeah that depends on
what kind of access you have to the
machine and where the data is that you
want to steal
and that you know who knows right but
one example is supposing you're logged
into an athena dial-up
machine you know with a couple hundred
other users
and you want to steal somebody's
password
and you're patient you can use and
let's assume that athena's is now as a
couple years ago and athena was running
a version of linux that mapped the
kernel into every user's
every processes address space then you
can use meltdown
to get out you know bit by bit or
everything in the kernel including say
the i o buffers and the network
buffers and stuff and if somebody's
typing their password if you're lucky
or patient and somebody's typing your
password and you load all of kernel
memory you're going to see that password
in kernel memory
right and because in fact the kernel
probably maps
like xv6 maps all of physical memory
that means you can probably read all
physical memory that is
all of all other processes memory
using this technique on a time sharing
machine
so i can see what's everybody's in text
editor contents or whatever i like
now you have to
that's the way you could use it if
you're using a time sharing machine for
other situations
yeah it would be different
i mean time sharing is not that
pervasive anymore
um but the sort of killer scenario would
be some kind of cloud computing thing
where
you know you're using a cloud provider
like amazon and
you know which runs many customers on
the same machine and you know depending
on the details of how they set up their
virtual
machine monitor or container system or
whatever it may be
if you buy time from amazon
then you may be able to peer into the
memory of other customers
software running on the same amazon
machine maybe
so i think that's the really you know
that's how people would actually use
this probably
actually another time that it might be
useful is
your browser when you're browsing the
web your browser actually runs a lot of
code in it that
is not trusted that is supplied by the
random websites that you visit
um maybe in the form of plugins maybe in
the form of javascript that's
loaded into your browser and compiled by
the browser and executed
and it is possible that this attack
could be carried out
by a code that you
run in your browser when you browse the
web that you may not
even know is running there a little
different website something with steel
whatever stuff is sitting on your laptop
i don't know if the details of that
quite work out but
has anyone demonstrated an attack
through either javascript or like web
assembly
i don't know i don't know i i feel
certainly people were worried about web
assembly
i don't know whether the attack was
literally possible
for javascript i know that um
maybe the sticking point was the
accurate time
timing that you couldn't quite get this
nanosecond timing
so you couldn't quite execute flush plus
reload now you know whether somebody
with a bit more cleverness could figure
out a way to do it i don't know
webassembly is much closer to just
running
um machine code and
you know i don't know exactly how the
details worked out but you know boy was
it
something people rapidly thought about
okay it turns out the attack doesn't
always work
like and for reasons that i don't think
the authors never
explained or only speculated about and
you can see
i don't know if you can see this well
maybe you can't see this but if you turn
to the last page of their paper
you'll see the output it's actually you
know they've
mounted the attack on their own machines
and extracted a bunch of data from their
own
the kernel on their own machine and
if you look closely you'll see there's a
huge all these lines
are just x x x x x x x x x x x all these
lines
x x's with dots these are places where
they didn't manage to extract anything
where meltdown failed even though they
repeated it many times
um and you can tell they must have been
you know they were
the papers version of this attack was
retrying many many
times because for example section 6.2
that talks about performance
says that in some cases they the rate at
which they could extract data was only
10 bytes per second
which means they were sitting there
trying again and again and again and
after thousands of times they finally
managed to get some data that is that
flush plus reload indicated that the two
cache lines had different load times
so there's something unexplained going
on about why it's quite frequent
for meltdown to actually fail i get some
data they
actually got real data here but there
was also a bunch of data that they
didn't get
and um i don't know if people
as far as i know people are not really
sure what all the conditions are
about when it succeeds and when it
doesn't you know the most
straightforward possibility
is that if the kernel data is in the l1
cache
the meltdown succeeds and if the kernel
data is not in the l1 cache it doesn't
succeed
that's very easy to believe that that
could be what's going on
because if it's not in the l1 cache then
there's a whole bunch more machinery
involved in a speculative load
and it's easy to imagine that the cpu
for a speculative load that's maybe not
known if it's even needed
would not bother doing all the work
required to
load stuff from ram but
it's not quite that simple and you can
tell it's not quite that simple because
the paper says that sometimes when they
were tried many retried many times
it finally worked so there's some
more complex condition maybe a race
effectively a erase inside the cpu
under which it occasionally works even
for data that's not
not in the cache
the end of the papers actually also if
you didn't get that for worth reading
because it it does
explain a sort of more real world like
we wanted to find out this particular
thing you know this like
we know there's passwords stored in our
firefox's password manager
we wanted to get them out we want to
steal them using meltdown
you know what are all the how do you
find out what the address is for example
they sort of lay out a complete attack i
mean
a complete attack done by academics not
real attackers but nevertheless
i fill in many of the pragmatic details
the final thing i want to talk about is
is fixes
um which we've already touched on a
little bit
when this paper came out
it got a lot of attention and there was
actually another second paper by
overlapping set of people about a
different
attack that also used different
different kind of
speculation inside cpus called spectre
so the pair of the papers
came out at about the same time and was
very exciting and so people hustled
people realized that boy
this is extremely damaging because now
we're talking about is that you know
isolation has been broken
right you don't hardly it's so basic you
hardly even think about it anymore but
you know
this thing this is a technique for
breaking page table protections
which is you know how we enforce
isolation between user and kernel that's
like
deeply fundamental attack
or at any rate undermines a extremely
important piece of security
in a very general way right seems like
you'd read anything
and so people really really hustled to
uh deploy fixes for this
and the immediate fix that a lot of
operating systems
um installed within weeks of uh
um this paper coming out and sometimes
had already installed
this thing called kaiser and which is
now called
kpti in linux and it's there's
pretty straightforward idea the idea is
just like not to put
the kernel mappings in the user page
table
and instead as in xv6
switch page tables during system calls
so in user space you just have user
mappings
make a system call there's some kind of
trampoline arrangement like in
xv6 and you switch page tables to a page
table that has the kernel mappings
in order to execute the kernel and that
causes this attack
to not work because um
the in that because you switch page
tables
this the virtual address in r1
is not only no longer valid it's no
longer meaningful
because there's no translation for it
um and so the cpu doesn't know what to
do with it
like this virtual address won't be
cached it's not even in the
tlb so there's just no way for the
kernel to
decide what memory corresponds to this
virtual address
you know when this attack is executed in
user space because this virtual this
kernel virtual address no longer means
anything
um it's not it's not illegal it's just
meaningless
and so that would cause the attack not
to work
the downside of this kaiser fix
is that now system calls are more
expensive because switching page tables
now if you don't do anything
switching page tables causes the tlb to
be flushed because now all those
virtual addresses in the tlb are the
wrong virtual addresses they don't
correspond to this page table anymore
and it causes the l1 cache to be flushed
because it's virtually addressed
and so on uh on some machines the
switching page table tables made
system calls considerably slower
and but recent machines actually have
this trick called pcid
which you can look up but basically
makes it so you can avoid
flushing these caches on a page table
switch although it still takes some time
and if you poke around on the web
looking for people there was a lot of
worry at the time that this split
that this two-page table idea would be
unacceptably slow
and in fact that didn't really turn out
to be a serious problem
and if you poke around you'll see that
people's guesses about typical workloads
you know how much it impacts overall
performance of typical workloads which
after all don't spend all their time
entering an exiting kernel is like five
percent
so it wasn't such a bad deal
do any questions about this kaiser
fix
um so people adopted this pretty rapidly
in fact there had been colonels that had
already adopted it because it defended
against some other attacks
um there's also a reasonable hardware
fix that
i believe intel is actually made in
recent processors
and that amd had already made and that's
basically to um
because the uh in fact
the permission you know this is
the structure of the cache when when an
instruction loads something from the l1
cache like this kernel data we're trying
to attack
um the permissions where people believe
that the permissions are sitting right
there in the cache entry and so there's
no trouble with the cpu checking the
permissions at that point
and indeed amd cpus and perhaps modern
intel cpus will actually do the
permission check very early and
won't return this data they won't even
return it to the core
if the permission checks don't work out
so there's none of this
speculative instructions they're able to
see
forbidden data so i i don't know if you
know the answer to this question it's
probably just uh
speculative but um uh no pun intended um
but
why why do you think intel would do this
like this seems like
okay because to me it seems like it was
a discussion should we check permissions
on
transient instructions and they were
just like no why why bother
running just a simple check but why
bother
indeed stuff's transparent right i mean
the user is not going to be able to see
the data either way
doing the check early you know that's
like some gates
on a pretty critical path right the the
you know
the court or l1 data cache
path is extremely performance critical
you know and if you can shave a few
transistors
off the you know off the critical path
here between
issuing instruction getting the data
back you know that may
allow you to have a slightly faster
cycle time and run programs faster
and so it's got to be the case that well
i don't know got to be the case but
it's easy to imagine that it would have
cost them a few transistors
um to actually enforce the permissions
early
because after all they still need all of
the stuff at retirement
it's not like doing it early would save
them some work later on
they still have to defer the fault until
retirement
um so all that stuff's still there
i'm just guessing that didn't seem like
it would have any advantages and
would have been like a little bit of
extra work
um and to either way completely
invisible you know
theoretically invisible to the
architectural level
did any kernel decide to like revert
this
kaiser um fix now that p
like intel has fixed the cpu
to improve performance again i know it's
optional on a lot of kernels
i'm i'm not totally sure
what's going on with the intel fix i'm
fairly sure that they have this fix out
there but
exactly you know i i
i don't really know what's going on i
think the linux kernel you can just ask
you know which
hardware fixes have been implemented and
linux changes the
mitigation that it enables depending on
what actually the hardware tells it
so my dashboard also so you can you can
actually do that
like you can read enough info about the
processor
as the kernel to know whether what to do
but you can run on your
running your laptop there's a linux
command that is actually yeah uh on like
we just tells you exactly you know what
fixes have been implemented where things
are mitigated in hardware
because there's a wide range of these
you know special guesting attacks
are you saying that linux will actually
use the combined page table if the cpu
yes i'm pleased oh cool
yeah i think it was you know ninety-nine
percent i haven't checked it
recently right i believe that's the case
all right sorry so what were people
doing like like how did they find
find this what were they trying to do
what are they trying to do trying to
break into computers
now now well the the um
who knows what they're really trying to
do i mean the papers are you know
written by uh
academics maybe you know their
research is finding security problems
one thing that motivated them for a long
time is that they wanted to break uh
address-based randomization and they had
earlier papers you know the different
schemes trying to make uh break address
panelization so like one group of
you know one stream of researchers that
were in this area uh had that as a
background
uh i think the project zero people came
from a completely different angle
i see thank you this is people i think
robert said before people have been
working in this area for decades you
know trying to
find bugs that they can exploit and
understand
so i guess it's how this is a hard
question answer but like
how likely is it that there's another
like meltdown out there because it seems
like extremely
likely okay he's like the micro
the fundamental like thing with micro
architecture like exposing changes
that's right i i think part of what's
going on is that the
cpu manufacturers uh have you know for
decades and decades have been
um you know adding more and more and
more optimism there's many many many
sort of cool little tricks inside the
micro architecture for
making things go faster and
you know now and and people didn't worry
that much
or it just wasn't on the radar that this
could be
like a serious security problem and so
now
people are now very aware that this
stuff could be a serious security
problem
but we're now in a position where we're
living with you know 30 years of
clever ideas inside the cpus and so
indeed a bunch of i mean since this
paper came out and indeed before this
paper came out
a bunch of kind of a bunch of this style
of attacks have come to light exploiting
various different uh
microarchitectural
thingies and the cpus so i i i think
this is going to be a while before
this is all laid to rest yeah you look
to the security conferences in the last
you know two years basically every
year every conference has basically
session on like
exploiting speculative execution
properties
and see if they can make uh attacks work
maybe a larger question is whether you
know whether the situation is well you
know there's
you know 15 or 20 or 30 things that
sort of have to be worked out and then
we'll be done
or whether there's some
much higher level um
approach gone wrong you know that we all
i mean this is probably way too
pessimistic but you know people had a
lot of faith in isolation
as an idea that uh there's a totally
reasonable thing to
assume that isolation works and we'll
design stuff like cloud computing
and you know running javascript in the
browser and all this stuff under the
assumption
which is not actually true but was close
enough believed to be close enough to
true
that isolation will just you know cause
there not to be serious security
problems
and that's actually probably still
doable
but this whole bag of microarchitectural
attacks has
not made that story seem more convincing
that's for sure
um just to add on to that
uh i'm i'm not sure uh the office levels
expertise
with like cpu design but to what extent
can cpu design be
made straightforwardly without a micro
architecture
while still preserving its high
performance
oh oh performance i mean people believe
this
nicely security too but yeah well some
of this clearly can be fixed like this
meltdown thing i mean there is a fix
this you know to actually check the
permissions
um that probably doesn't sacrifice any
performance
for some of the other attacks that have
come up um
it's not clear that you could fix them
without sacrificing performance i mean
some of this very very deep like
the fact that we're sharing you know
there's a lot of sharing like in a time
sharing or cloud environment there's
just a lot of sharing
and um so for example
supposing there's a disk drive or a
network
on your cloud server right
gosh you might be able to get
information about the other people on
that cloud server
simply by watching how their traffic
interferes with your traffic disk
traffic or network traffic or memory
traffic
or something so there's some sort of you
know i don't know whether that's
practical maybe it's not although
you know for many many things in which
people said boy that attack just doesn't
seem to be practical
you know it's turned out to be practical
enough um
and i think and so a lot of this
microarchitectural stuff maybe could be
cleaned up without performance loss or
maybe can't be cleaned up to that
performance loss
you know but i i think it's i think it's
a much more serious problem than just
we're gonna
apply some fixes they'll all go away
like the place has been most acute is
cryptography
there's been many many years of people
looking into these kind of clever
um often cash timing based a ways of
sensing uh
bits out of keys and other people's
cryptographical you know
people running i'm running a
cryptographic encryption on the same
machine as you
can you guess anything about my key by
watching by doing cache timing
the answer is absolutely and it's not
like a microarchitectural bug
it's you know
it's just a consequence of sharing often
anyway i don't know how this is going to
play out but it's not it's not
straightforward
i mean the scariest part is when people
made progress on
um just measuring the
like em radiation from a cpu and
figuring out what instructions are run
and what data is in it
with machine learning with like some
accuracy you know not 100
not nearly but like a scary amount of
accuracy because anything over zero is
scary
yeah we all live in you know it's all
well there's a boundary between attacks
that are
or there's some threshold between
attacks that are like
possible but you know gosh just seems
like that would be too expensive or
awkward or painful
or whatever complex to carry out
and the taxi really could be carried out
of course we only should defend against
the second class because the first
class is often too expensive to defend
against but as
the value of stuff contained in
computers gets larger and
you know attackers get more clever get
more closer access
to shared environments the kind of
threshold by which attacks are
feasible enough to defend against
changes
all right i'm done with the lecture but
i'm happy to take more questions
thank you thank you
thanks oh i actually had a question
about the cash um so
the l on cash it's it's per cpu
right yes a nail too is it shared
well so this picture is different for
each cpu
for different models of cpu etc the
the habit today is um
looks it's uh is a little bit more
complex than this
typically you have multiple cores you
know
two or four or eight or 64 or something
each one has a l1 cache that's quite
close to the cpu but
small fast and small each core typically
also has a bigger l2 cache
that's you know and it's sort of
dedicated to that
cpu um
and then um
and and then there's often a shared
l3 cache often but not always
and another approach is to make the
summation of the l2 caches
sort of convenient for all the cpus to
use so that i have
super high speed access to my l2 cache
but i can get at other people's at a
slightly bigger penalty so the effective
cache size is larger
so you often see either three level
caches or
or uh these sort of joint two second
level caches
and typically the l2 and l3 are
physically addressed
l1 is virtual
so what's the point of having physically
addressed
is that the different processes
yeah it's easy the the um stuff in the
l1
in a virtually addressed cache um
if if the same data is used with
different virtual addresses you can't
you know the
virtual address cache doesn't really
help you find it um if it was cached
under a different address where these
l2 caches the data is independent is
usable no matter what virtual address
um you addressed it under you see
yeah where does the mmu sit
uh relative to all these caches in the
tlb oh
it's not it's distributed really because
the uh
i mean the most obvious um
i mean i think in real life
the tlb the most critical thing is the
tlb and i believe it's indexed in
parallel with the l1 cache typically
all right so if you hit in the cache the
l1 cache great
although there may be a
anyway and if you're missing the l1
cache then the now you have the physical
you were looking up in the tb the same
time now you're the physical cat
addressed the mmu though is not just a
single
box that sits somewhere it's actually
kind of
involved oh okay but isn't it hardware
so oh everything is here's hardware yeah
oh that was interesting
but but remember these you know these
chips have billions of transistors on
them
so yeah maybe it's hardware but we're
talking about
massively complex hardware that that's
designed using very sophisticated
software-like design techniques
so that it can do very very complex and
sophisticated things
so yeah it's hardware but yeah it's not
at all at all straightforward
so do table mapping like page table
mappings ever end up in the
caches at all or are they always just
routed through the tlb
because if you miss it the tlb you have
to go to memory
retrieve that right so there certainly
the l2 cache
will hold uh the from the point of view
tob misses tmp reloads or just
memory accesses so the tob needs to load
a bunch of page table junk
it's just a memory load and it could
stuff could easily be cached in the l2
but it has to skip to l1 because
l1 has virtual addresses which i don't
obviously don't think
the tlb would consult the l1 for its
okay
because it's uh virtually addressed yes
and then one thing about the spectre
attack um
um how would you i i so so the thing is
like i've heard about
meltdown inspector like at least a dozen
times and every time i looked it up i
would not understand it so this is the
first time i actually understand what's
going on
um but for spectre is there um like how
similar is it to meltdown it's not it's
not okay or
well my understanding of the spectre
attack is by training the branch
predictor
that you know the the other code that
you're
trying to attack stuff from let's
suppose it's um
another process and you share some
memory with it right you know because
you're
it's really the same program as you but
it's some other user
running the program right um you can
the branch the branch the tables that
the branch predictor uses
are shared uh between
different you know if i run out of cpu
for bidding that you run or maybe you
run on different hyper threads of the
same cpu everybody sees the same branch
you know
sees the same branch predictor so i can
train the branch predictor to predict
branches in a certain way
and then i let you run you're running
with my
branch predictor training right and so
that means i can essentially trick your
program into speculatively executing
instructions of my choice
right now this is only speculative so of
course they'll be undone but
they they will cause cash loads
um that to some extent i can control
because i control how you speculate
execute and then if we share memory i
can use
flesh and reload to sense what cache
lines your program loaded and this
speculative execution that
so in that case you you don't need to um
you don't need to like no like directly
address address
assist a piece of memory you just need
to make sure that
program will speculatively execute it
like in meltdown we did it ourselves
but especially just directed there
that's kind of cool because you can just
say oh you know just go and load that
secret
by training the branch predictor without
knowing where the secret is yeah
or like you got to know someone yeah you
you kind of have to know
you need an upgrade you know in great
depth oh yeah sorry yeah yeah
yeah but you don't have to load it
yourself yes that's not secret right
you're probably running a program that
i know what program you're running you
know yeah
okay that makes sense thank you
yeah i was just wondering it seems like
when you when a
research paper like this gets released
you know it's out there for like
people linux and windows and like intel
for them to try to go and
scramble to patch the bug but it's also
out there for like hackers can start to
like learn from the paper and be like oh
this is a method we could use
um and i'm i'm wondering like it
as a researcher is there a general
practice of like as we're working on the
paper we'll like sort of tip off the
yes the quote unquote good guys first so
that they can get a head start on
the authors informed every you know the
cpu manufacturers and the os
manufacturers before they publish the
paper
yeah there's a whole there's a whole
protocol and you know the paper even
these
these kind of papers won't even be
accepted anymore unless you know you
follow the protocol
yeah that doesn't mean the attackers
weren't already using it right because
yeah
probably know the attackers discovered
this 20 years ago but
thank you been following the protocol
it's not straightforward you know i
think in
this particular case i think you know
there was some intel was not too excited
about
the collaboration between the linux
community and intel was not completely
smooth i think
when this happened i think they worked
out some of the kinks
but
i think it was kind of scary because i i
read
on wikipedia that the ubuntu
fix was published after the paper was
published
which i found scary but
yeah thank you so much thank you
thank you thank you well see you next
week