all right
um the sort of underlying topic
for today is really getting multi-core
getting good multi-core performance
getting good performance on multi-core
hardware um
and that's actually like a very
interesting and
deep um fascinating topic
with many many different interesting
aspects
um today we're just going to bite off a
fairly small piece
and that's how to get good performance
for shared data in the kernel that's
read
much more often than it's written and
you know it turns out there's many kind
of specific cases
in which different ideas for getting
good multi-core performance are useful
and
what we're going to look at today is
linux's rcu which has been very
successful for
sort of read heavy data read heavy
kernel data
um the uh
general sort of uh background here is
that
if you have modern machines with four or
eight or 16 or 64
or however many uh cores running in
parallel and sharing memory
the kernel is really a parallel process
it's a parallel program and if you're
going to get good performance you need
to make sure that the kernel can run a
lot of its work
as much as possible in parallel on
different cores in order to get
that much more you know if you can run
the kernel
in parallel on eight cores all of them
do useful work you can get
eight times the performance um than if
the kernel could only run on a single
core
and at a high level
this should clearly be possible
if you have lots and lots of processes
running on your computer
well first of all the processes aren't
running and executing in the kernel
then we have very little to worry about
they're likely to run in parallel
without any kernel having to do anything
if the process is
if you have many applications running
and they're all making system calls
a lot of the time different system calls
made by different processes
just seem like they ought to be
independent and should be able to
proceed
in many cases though certainly not all
but should be able to proceed completely
without interference
like if two processes are forking um
or two processes are reading different
pipes or
you know reading or writing different
files um
there's no obvious reason why these
should interfere with each other
um you know why they shouldn't be able
to execute in parallel at n
times the total throughput but the
problem is the kernel has a lot of
shared resources um
in order to you know for other good
reasons the kernel shares a lot of
resources like memory
and cpus and a disk cache and an ino
cache
and all this other stuff that's actually
under the hood shared between different
processes
and that means that even if two
processors are doing
system calls two processes that have
totally never heard of each other and
aren't trying to interact make system
calls
if those system calls happen to allocate
memory or use the
disk cache or involve scheduling
decisions
they may well end up both using
data structures in the kernel and
therefore we need some story
for how they're both supposed to use the
same data without
getting underfoot without interfering
with each other and there's been
enormous effort over the years in making
kernels
and making all these cases and kernels
run fast
we've seen one of course that's oriented
towards correctness namely spin locks
spinlocks are straightforward as such
things
go and easy to reason about but you know
what a spin lock does is
prevent execution it prevents its job is
to prevent
parallelism in cases where there might
be a problem between two processes
so spinlocks are just directly a way to
decrease performance that's all they do
of course they make it easy to reason
about correctness but they
absolutely prevent parallel execution
and you know that's not always that
desirable
okay so again we're going to focus
on read heavy date on the case in which
you have data that's mostly read
and relatively rarely lit written and
the main example i'm going to use
is a linked list a singly linked list um
and so you can think of uh just the
standard link to style
this diagram there's some sort of maybe
global variable that's a pointer this
head
pointer um just a pointer and
uh there's a bunch of list elements um
and
each list element has a some data in it
we'll just say it's a string like
you know hello is the sort of
data in this element and each element
also has a next pointer
that points the next list element
and then finally there's a pointer that
points to
zero to mark the answer um very
straightforward
um and again we're going to assume that
most uses of this list that we're
interested in are just reads
you know the the kernel thread or
whatever it is that's using this list
it's just scanning a list looking for
something it's not trying to modify the
list
and occasional writers though you know
if all
if there were zero writers ever we
wouldn't need to have to worry about
this at all because it'd be a
completely static list never changes we
can read it freely
but we're going to imagine that every
once in a while somebody comes along and
wants to write the list so that may mean
that
some other thread wants to change the
data stored in the list element or maybe
delete an element or maybe insert a new
element somewhere
so even though it's we're aiming at
mostly
reads we do have to worry about rights
we need to make the read safe in the
face of rights
and of course in xv6 we just have a lock
protecting this list
and a reader now you know not only would
writers in xv6 not only would writers
have to acquire the lock
but readers would have to acquire the
lock too because we've got to rule out
the situation in which
while we're reading somebody's actually
modifying the list because that could
cause
sort of the reader to see a half updated
value or follow an invalid pointer or
something
so in xv6 we have locks um
but uh that has the defect that if the
common cases there's no writers
it it means that um every time somebody
comes along and reads
they in xv6 they grab an exclusive
like xp6 spin locks are exclusive even
if you have just two readers
only one of them can proceed at a time
so
what we'd like um or sort of one way to
improve this situation
would be to have a new kind of lock that
allows
multiple readers but only one writer
so i'm going to explore those next
actually both because they're
interesting
and because they're they help motivate
the need for rcu which we'll talk about
in a little while
um so there's this notion called read
write locks
and the interface is a little more
complicated than the spin locks we're
used to
we're going to imagine that there's one
set of call that you call if you just
want to read something
so we're going to imagine an r lock call
and you pass it a a lock
and then also an r unlock call
um and readers call these and then
there's a write
block call and a write unlock call also
and the semantics are
that you can either have
multiple readers acquire the block for
reading
so we do then would get parallelism or
you can have exactly one writer
have acquired the lock but you can never
have a mix you can never
be in this the locks rule out the possib
read
read write blocks rule out the
possibility of somebody having
locked the lock for writing and also
reading at the same time you either get
one writer
or lots of readers but nothing else um
so that's the uh question yes
uh this may be an implementation detail
but what kind of mechanisms does this
locking scheme put in place
to prevent uh someone writing
while they hold a read lock nothing
nothing it's just like xp6 locks
they're completely we're talking about
kernel code written by trusted
responsible developers and so just like
spinlocks in xv6
if the code that's using the lock is
incorrect it's incorrect
there's no okay and this is the way
you know typical kernels are written you
just have to assume that
people developing the kernel are
following their own rules
okay okay and again the reason why we
care is that
if we have a mostly a read mostly data
structure we'd love to have
multiple readers be able to use it at
the same time to get
genuine speed up from having
multiple cores
all right so um if there were no problem
here this would just be the answer we
wouldn't have need to read today's paper
but it turns out that if you dig into
the details of what actually happens
when you use read write locks especially
for
data that's actually read a lot there's
some problems
and in order to see what's going on we
actually have to look at the
implementation
linux indeed has a read write lock
implementation in it and this is um
a kind of simplified version of the
linux code the idea is that we have a
struct rw
lock which is like struck lock in xv6
and it has a count in it
if the count is zero that means that the
lock is not held by anybody
in any form if the count is negative one
that means that a writer has it locked
and if the count is greater than zero
that means that n
readers have it locked and we need to
keep track of them because
we can only let a writer in if the
number of readers descends to zero
okay so somebody asked about addings
no i'm not sure if there's a question in
the chat
interrupt me if there is um
the read lock function
um it has to sit in a loop because
if there's a writer we have to wait for
the writer
it looks
it grabs a copy of the current end value
if it's less than zero that means
there's a writer and we just need to
continue our loop and we're going to
spin
waiting for the writer to go away
otherwise we want to increment
that value but we only want to increment
it
if it's still greater than or equal to
zero so we can't
there's many things we can't do we can't
for example just add one with standard
n equals n plus one because if a writer
sneaks in
between when we check the value of n and
when we actually try to increment it
then we may actually go ahead and
increment it at the same time that some
writer is setting it to minus one
which is wrong so we need to increment
it only if it hasn't changed value
since we checked it and verified that
it's greater than or equal to zero
and um the way people do that is they
take advantage of
special atomic or interlocked
instructions which you
saw before for the um for our
implementation of
spinlocks and xv6 and the interlocked
instruction that
one that's particularly convenient to
use is something called compare and swap
the idea is that compare and swap takes
three arguments
the address of some location of memory
that we want to act on
the value that we think it holds and the
value that we'd like it to hold and the
semantics of compare and swap are that
the hardware
checks the hardware first sort of
you know basically sets an internal lock
that makes
only one compare and swap execute at a
time on a given locate memory location
then the hardware checks that the
current value of that location
is indeed still x and if it's still x
it sets it to this third argument which
is going to be x plus one
and then the instruction yields one
that's this value
if compare and swap observes that the
current value isn't x
um then it then it doesn't change the
value the memory location and it returns
zero
so this is basically an atomic if the
location is x set it to x plus one
and it has to be atomic because there's
really two things going on the hardware
is
checking the current value and setting
it to a new value
any questions about compare and swap
i have a question if there would be a
reader
and uh our lock needs to
continue would w unlock
reset the value back to x oh i'm
i'm uh well w unlock
if there's a writer w unlock which
i'm afraid i didn't show sets n to zero
because there can only be one writer
if there's what read unlock does
is use another compare and swap
to decrement in
okay because what happens if
um a writer locks
uh the lock between when x
is being computed and
so right here uh no
between the if and x
somehow okay okay it's i'm not sure i
understand exactly
what time you're asking but it's
absolutely a good question what happens
if w lock is called somewhere during
this sequence
and for me the most dangerous time for w
lock to be called
is after this check but before the
compare and swap
so let's imagine that read lock has
gotten as far as seeing that x that
x or l alright n is zero
okay so maybe we're right here right
here
and x is equal to zero
um and we've already checked it
so the check is finished and then right
at this time on another core
some other thread calls w lock
and it actually gets its compare and
swap in first
so on the other core that's trying to
grab the right lock
compare and swap is going to see if lron
is zero let's assume that n is zero
so that this test is true and the
compare and swap is
on that other core is gonna set n to
negative one so now the lock's locked
um but we still think that n is zero in
this code
uh even the lock's locked and now we're
gonna execute now back on the reading
core
we're going to execute compare and swap
but we're going to pass 0
here right this is the value we actually
we're going to pass in the value we
actually
looked at not the current value of n and
when we looked at it it was 0. so we're
going to pass
zero here and we're telling compare and
swap look only
add one to only set it to one if its
current value is zero
but it's not zero at this point it's
minus one and so this compare and swap
fails
does not modify n returns zero
and so that means we'll go back to the
top of this loop and try again of course
now
n is minus one
um this might be related to the previous
question a bit but
is it possible for an interrupt to occur
uh when that x plus 1 is being computed
in the cast
parameter or cas parameter you mean
before we actually execute cas but while
we're computing its arguments
right so like you compute or you pass in
the x
uh argument and that's okay but you
before you compute the x plus one or
while you're computing x plus one
an interrupt occurs um until x plus one
is wrong
so if an interrupt occurs while we're
computing x plus one that means we
haven't
cas is actually an instruction it's a
single machine instruction
so if we're computing s plus one that
means we haven't called cas yet
if the interrupt happens and all kinds
of things may happen
we're going to get the same if we
originally read zero here
right then interrupt or no interrupt
we're going to pass
one as this third argument because the
interrupt is not going to reach out and
change this is a local this x is a local
variable
for this code so the interrupt or
context which or anything is not going
to change
x and so that means we're going to pass
0 and 1 here and you know
if n is still zero then we'll set it to
one and that's that's what we want if
it's not still zero then
compare and swap won't change it right i
guess you would have problems if you
didn't set that local variable then
yeah if you used l arrow m here
yeah and l arrow n plus one you would
almost certainly be in big trouble
because then
n could change under foot at any time
that's why we
actually grab a copy and grab a copy
here in order to sort of
fix a specific value yeah yes
okay
um if two readers okay so i cover the
case of
whatever writer calls at the same
w lock is called the same time as our
lock
it's also interesting to wonder what if
our lock is called at the same time
um so supposing n starts at a zero we
know if two r locks
are called at the same time what we want
is for n to end up with value
two and for both our locks to return
that's what we want because we want two
readers to be able to execute in
parallel to use the data in parallel
um okay so
they're both going to see zero at this
point so
at this point both of them are going to
have x equal to zero they're both going
to call
compare and swap with zero and one
um only one of those two compare and
swaps hopefully
exactly one of those two comparison
swaps will succeed
whichever one you know parent swap it's
an atomic instruction
there only one of them happens at a time
on a given memory location
so whichever compare on top is first
we'll see
uh that at n is equal to zero and we'll
set it to one
the other course simultaneous call to r
lock
its compare swap will then execute
and it'll still pass zero and one here
but n will now be equal to one and so
the compare and top will fail
for the second core and return zero
the second core will go back to the top
of this loop at this point it'll read
one
um that's not less than zero so
we'll go on to the compare and swap and
now it'll pass one and two
and now the second read lock will
succeed
both of them will have the log so the
first one succeeded in the first stride
the second one actually go back
to the loop and try again
any questions
um oh sorry so it is somehow possible
that
so a bunch of reads come and
they they're they're reading their stuff
and then
a ride also comes and it also wants to
write
but then some other reads also come
after the right
but then somehow the reads like
outrun the right and the
right still has to wait somehow yes so
so with the sequences that a reader
managed to acquire the lock
one or more readers have the lock so now
n you know each of them
this is called a compare and swap you
know adds one to n for each reader
so now n is greater than zero because
there's multiple readers
if a writer tries to require the lock at
this point um
the writers compare and swap the compare
value is zero
so compare and swap will only change n
to minus one
if its current value is zero but we know
the current because there's
multiple readers the current value of n
is not zero and so the compare and swap
will fail
and return zero in the writer will
sit here in this loop basically waiting
until n is equal to 0
before its compare and swap will succeed
and return and
give the lock to the writer so this
certainly means the writer can be
starved
if there's a lot of readers and may
never be zero and so the right may never
succeed so that's a defect in this
locking scheme
thank you yeah i also have a question
about the
the two readers scenario that i just
mentioned
it appears that in the worst case
the reader that arrives second has to go
through another
iteration of the loop yes sounds
somewhat wasteful i wonder if this
generalizes to n
writers it certainly does they all have
to get lost
and start again you put your finger on
why people
don't like this scheme um if
there's a lot of simultaneous reader um
and so for
for the reason you just mentioned um
orlock even if there's no writers at all
if there's lots of readers or there's
readers on many cores
our lock can be very very expensive
and one thing you need to know about the
our lock scheme which i think we've
already mentioned in class is that
on a multi-core system every core
has an associated cache the we'll say
it's the l1 cache so each core has a bit
of cache memory
and whenever it reads or writes
something
it sits in the cache and so there may be
lots and lots of cores and there's some
kind of
interconnect network that allows the
course to talk to each other
because of course if lots of course have
some data
cached and one of the cores writes that
data the writing core has to tell the
other cores that they're not allowed to
cache the data anymore which is called
invalidation
so what actually happens if you have n
readers and people calling rlock at
about the same time on n
cores they're all going to read
n sorry this l arrow n value
and load this memory location into their
caches
they're all going to call compare and
swap
what the first one to actually call
compare and swap is going to modify the
data but in order for it to modify the
data it has to invalidate all these
other copies
and so the compare and swap instruction
that one has to send out an
invalidate message over this little
network to each of the other end cores
right and then it returns all the other
course the n minus one course they have
um their compare and swaps now actually
have to re-read
again requiring traffic over the network
re-read
this data this memory location compare
it with x and they'll have failed
because they all call x with zero
then the remaining n minus one readers
go back to the top of the loop and all
n minus one of them again read the data
and again one of them writes it
right so on each so there's going to be
n times through the loop once for each
core trying to acquire the lock each of
those trips through the loop
involves order n messages on the network
because at least
every copy of the cached lron has to be
invalidated
and that means that the total cost for n
cores to acquire a particular lock
even for reading is order n
and that means as you increase the
number of cores for a popular piece of
data
the uh cost for everybody to lock it
just
once goes up sorry it's order n squared
the total cost and time
or messages sent over this interconnect
is n squared
and this is a very bad deal right you
would hope that if you needed to do
something ten times
you know ten different cores needed to
do something especially
you know given that they're just reading
the list they're not modifying it
you'd hope that they could really run in
parallel that is the total wall clock
time for
16 cores to read something
should be the same as the total wall
clock time for one chord to read
something because that's what
that's what getting parallelism means is
that you can do things at the same time
but here the more cores i try to read
this the more expensive
the lock acquisition is and so um
what's going on is that this style of
locks
has converted read-only access to data
you know the list
is probably sitting in the cache already
because nobody's modifying the list
right so the actual access to the list
might only take a few dozen cycles but
if the date is popular getting the lock
can take hundreds or thousands of cycles
because of this n
squared effect and the fact that instead
of it being cached accesses
it's these accesses that have to go over
the bus
this interconnect in order to invalidate
and
do these cache coherence operations so
this these locks have turned
a very cheap read-only access to data
into an extremely expensive
read-write access to this data
and we'll probably completely destroy
any possible parallel
performance um if what you were doing
you know if
the actual data was fairly simple to
read the lock will dominate and destroy
parallel performance
so any questions about this performance
story
in a sense you know the bad performance
of read write
is the reason for the existence of rcu
because if this was efficient
then there'll be no need to do better
than that
right but it's terribly inefficient um
and
it it's there's two things going on one
is the details of this oh there needs to
be a total of n squared trips through
this loop if
we have n cores is sort of one way of
looking at it the other way of looking
at it is that
we're writing you know regardless of the
details of what's going on here
these locks have turned a read-only
access which could be cached and
extremely fast
into an access that one way or another
involves a right
one or more rights and rights are just
much more expensive than reads
if we're writing data that might be
shared
with other cores because a read
for data that's not modified can be
satisfied in a couple cycles out of your
own cache
a write any right to data that may be
cached by other cores
has to involve communication between
cores to invalidate other copies
so no matter how you slice it anything
that involves a right to share data is a
disaster for performance
if if you otherwise could have been read
only
so the details of this loop are sort of
less important than the fact that it
did a right to share data
so what we're looking for is a way to be
able to read data
without rights right we want to be able
to scan that list
um without doing any rights whatsoever
including
any rights that might be required to do
some kind of locking thing
they were looking for really really
read-only access to data
okay
so one possibility
that's not a possibility but it's sort
of a thought experiment is we just have
the readers not bother locking
right you know occasionally you get
lucky and it turns out that readers can
read stuff
and that only writers need to lock so
we'll just do a quick experiment to see
whether
we could have a lock just
have readers just read the list without
locking it
so suppose we have this list and it has
some you know strings
and uh
we're going to read it okay so nothing
goes wrong if there's no writer right
you just read the list it's not a
problem so we got to imagine there's a
writer
and there's probably three cases if you
read a list
while some other course modifying it
so one case is that the writer is just
changing the content
that is not adding or deleting anyone is
necessarily a writer is just changing
the string to be some other string
so one is the writer is changing the
content
two is the writer is inserting a new
list element
and the third case is if the writer is
deleting a
list element and i want to examine these
because
we need a story for each and rcu
actually kind of has a story for each so
the danger so i'm just talking about
what goes wrong if somebody's reading a
list while another course writing it
if the writer wants to it just changes
the string
then the danger is that the reader will
be actually reading the bytes of this
string or whatever
else is in the list element while the
writer
is modifying the same bytes and so if we
don't do anything special
the reader will see some mixture of the
old bytes
and the new bytes and that's probably a
disaster
that's one case we have to worry about
another possibility is that the writer
is inserting a new element
and of course what that means is that
you know supposing
for the writer wants to insert the new
element at the head the writer is going
to cook up
some new element going to change the
head pointer to point to it i'm going to
change
the uh new element to point at the old
first element
right and um
so the danger here if a reader reads
is reading the list while the writer is
inserting is that
maybe uh you know if we really blow it
the uh um
the writer may set the head pointer to
point to the new element
before the new element's initialized
that is while it maybe contains garbage
for the string
or some illegal pointer as the next
element
so that's the thing that could go wrong
if a writer's inserting
so let's
um and if the writer is deleting
then you know what it means to delete an
element is first
to change let's say we're deleting the
first element we change the head pointer
to point to the second element
and then call free on the first element
to return this to the free list
and the danger here you know if the
reader sees the new head pointer
that's fine they're just going to go on
to the second elements
first if the reader actually was looking
at the first element
and then the writer freed it then the
problem we have is now the reader is
looking at element
that's on the free list and could be
allocated for some other use and
overwritten
for some completely other use while the
reader's still looking at this element
so from the reader point of view now all
of a sudden the elements filled with
garbage
and said it was expecting so that's the
third case we have to uh
if we want to have lock we want to have
absolutely no blocks for beaters
we have to worry about these three
situations
and i'm not talking about writer versus
writer problems here because i'm
just assuming for this entire lecture
that writers still use locks
there's still some ordinary like xv6
style spin lock here
and writers acquire this lock before
doing anything
but readers don't require any luck
whatsoever
questions about these dangers
okay the point is we we can't just
simply
have readers read within locks but it
turns out we can
fix these specific problems and that
takes us to
rcu and rc has a couple of ideas in it
that uh
or rcu is by the way it's as much a kind
of
approach to concurrency um concurrency
control as it is a
particular algorithm right it's a way of
structuring
it's an approach to structuring readers
and writers so that
they can get along with the readers not
having to take logs
the general game with recopy update is
we're going to fix those three
situations in which readers might get
into trouble
if there's concurrent writers and we're
going to do it
by making the writers a little bit more
complicated
so the writer is going to end up
somewhat slower they still need to lock
plus follow some extra rules
but the reward will be the readers will
be dramatically faster
because they can operate without locks
and without ever writing memory
okay so the first big idea
in rcu
is that in that first
trouble situation we talked about before
where the writer is updating a list
element
the content of a list element
we're going to actually outlaw that
we're going to say writers are not
allowed
to modify the contents of
list elements instead if we have a
linked list like this with a couple of
elements
if a writer wanted to update the content
of element 2
instead of changing it in place which
wouldn't do it would actually
cook up it would call the allocator to
allocate a new
element
it would initialize the element
completely so whatever new content
you know we wanted to put here instead
of the old content
the writer would set the next pointer
on this new element so that this new
element is now completely correct
looking
and then in a single write to e1's next
pointer
the writer would switch e1 from pointing
to the
from pointing to the old version of e2
to pointing to the new version of e2 so
the game is instead of updating
things in place we're going to replace
them with new versions
of the same data and so um
so now a reader you know reader's gotten
as far as e1 and it's just looking at
e1's next pointer
the reader is going to either see the
old next pointer which points to e2 and
that's fine because
nobody was changing e2 or the reader is
going to see the new
next pointer and look at the new
list element and either way since the
writer initially initialized this
list element before setting anyone's
next point or either way the reader is
going to see
like a correct next pointer that points
to e3
so the point is the reader will never
see a string that's in the process of
being
a content that's in the process of being
modified
any questions about this particular idea
what about saying sorry
okay i can go ahead um will the
link between e2 and e3 be deleted or
will it be left
there in case that or either um somehow
reached e2
now we're just gonna leave it so well
i'll come to this this is a excellent
question um
and it's actually the main piece of
complexity in rcu
but for now we're just going to imagine
that e2 is left alone for the moment
the link from e to e to e3 we don't need
to worry about it anyway right because
that's a part of e2
and like in normal implementations we
just free that anyway
like with no rcu involved we don't ever
need to worry about that link
right well the danger is that's that
just before we changed
this next pointer that some reader had
followed the next pointer to e2
right so overall what we're worried
about here is that oh some some reader
on some chords actually right now
reading e2
so we'd better not free it right away
right
right so that's what i think that's all
we're saying is you better not free e2
right away
just leave it alone um
as a piece of jargon um
the right the swap of e1's
next pointer from the old e2 to the new
e2
um i in my head i call this a committing
right
there's a then part of the reason why
this works is that with a single
committing right which is
atomic like rights to pointers on the
machines we use are
atomic in the sense that either the
right to the point or happened or didn't
happen
from the perspective of readers because
they're atomic basically with that one
instruction
with the one atomic store we can it's an
ordinary store but
it's indivisible we switch e1 from
pointing to the old
the next pointer from pointing to the
old one to the new one and that right is
what sort of commits us to
now using the second version
this is a very basic technique a a very
important technique for rcu
and what it means is that rcu
is really mostly applicable to data
structures for which you can have
single committing rights so that means
there's some data structures which are
quite awkward in this scheme like a
doubly linked list
where every element is pointed to from
two different pointers
now we can't get rid of a list element
with a single committing write
because there's two pointers to it we
can't on most machines you can't
atomically change
two different memory locations at the
same time
so doubly linked lists are not so good
for rcu
a data structure that is good is a tree
and if you have a
tree of
a tree of nodes like this then we can do
you know suppose we want to change
we want to modify this value down here
what we can do
there's some head to the tree what we
can do is cook up
a new a new version of this part of the
tree here
and with the single committing right to
the head pointer
switch to the new version of the tree
and so the new version of the tree
which will you know the writer will
allocate
what um sort of create
um uh can actually
share for convenience can share
structure the unmodified part with the
old tree
and then with a single committing right
we're going to change the head pointer
to
the tree head pointer to point to the
new version
but for other data structures that don't
look like lister trees it's not so easy
to use rcu
okay so that's the first idea
any last questions
the second idea
one of the problems with uh one of the
potential problems
with uh
um the scheme i just
described and we're gonna cook up a new
e2
prime and what i said was oh well we'll
initialize the content for e2 prime and
we'll
you know set its next pointer correctly
and
after that we'll set e1's next pointer
to point to e2
as you may recall from discussions of
xv6
by default there's no after that on
these machines
the compiler and the hardware all
basically all compilers and
many microprocessors reorder memory
operations
so if you simply you know say
we allocate a new element
we just wrote this c code you know e
arrow next
equals you know e3
and then e1 arrow next
equals e this is not going to work well
this is not going to work reliably it's
going to work fine when you test it
but it won't work in real life all the
time occasionally it'll go wrong and
the reason is that the compiler
may end up reordering these rights or
the machine may end up reordering these
rights or
the reading code which reads these
various things
the compiler or the machine the
microprocessor may end up
reordering the reader's reads and of
course
if we set e1 arrow next to point to e2
before
we initialize the content of e2 so that
it's
string that holds or his next pointer
point off into space
then some reader's going to see this
point or follow it read garbage and
crash
so the second idea is that both readers
and writers have to use memory barriers
now even though we're not locking or
really because we're not locking
the writers and the readers have to use
a barrier and
for writers the place the barrier has to
go is before the committing right
so we need a barrier here
that tells the hardware and the compiler
look
all the writes before this barrier
please
finish them before doing any writes
after the barrier
so that e2 is fully initialized before
we set e1 to point to it
and on the read side
the reader needs to load e1 arrow next
into some you know temporary location or
register
so we'll just say register one equals
e1 arrow next
then the reader needs a barrier
and then the reader is going to look at
r1
arrow it's content and r1 arrow next
and what this barrier on the reader says
is
don't issue any of these loads
until after we've completed this load so
the reader is going to
look at e1r next and either get the old
e2 or the new e2
and then the barrier says that only then
are we going to start
looking at only after we've grabbed this
all these reads have to execute after
this read
and since the writer guaranteed to
initialize the content
before committing the pointer to eat the
new e2
that means these reads if this pointer
points to the new et2 that means these
reads are guaranteed to see the
initialized content
okay um so we saw a little bit of this
how can you i'm sorry yeah i was just
i was confused about a reader so how can
you
read one around
like anything before you read our one
i guess that's how how how are they
so yeah i guess like
if even if it reordered that how would
how'd it be able to read
r1x before it read he won
next uh
you uh i think you've stumped me um
yeah i mean what you're pointing out is
that before you even know what the
pointer is
uh you can't possibly actually issue the
reads the
um a a possibility
is that whatever this pointer points to
maybe is already cached on this core
due to some maybe you know this memory
was had been you know
a minute ago used for something else
something totally else and
we have an old version of this cached on
our core
um at the address at this address but
for some previous use of the memory if
this read was to use the old cached
value
i'm not sure this can happen i'm just
making this up for you but if this read
could use the old cache value then we'd
be in big trouble
and i don't know if the machine would
actually do that or whether
um
um another possibility is that the
compiler you know
the real answers i don't know i should
go off and think about uh what a
specific example would be
okay okay i see the cash version makes
sense
yes yeah i'm not actually completely
sure it could could happen
in real life um
that's a good question
okay um so that's the second idea
the third problem we have which is
something somebody raised before
is that the writer is going to swap the
e1 pointer to point to the new e2 but
there could be readers
um you know who started looking at who
followed this point or just before we
change the writer change it
who are still looking at e2
we need to free this list element
someday
but we better not free it while some
reader's still using it so we need to
somehow wait until the last reader has
finished using e2 before we can free it
now that's the sort of third and final
main problem that
rcu solves is how long should the writer
wait before it
frees e2
there's you could imagine a number of
ways of doing this
for example we could put a little
reference count in every list element
and have readers increment it and
operators wait
readers increment it when they start
using a list element decrement
it when they're done using the list
element and have the writer wait for the
reference count on this element to go to
zero we would regret that instantly
because
the whole point of rcu is to allow
reading
without writing um because we know that
if
lots of readers are uh changing this
reference account it's gonna be terribly
expensive
to do the rights involved in maintaining
a reference count so we absolutely don't
want reference counts
another possibility would be use a
garbage collected language
and in a garbage collected language you
don't ever free anything explicitly
instead
the garbage collector does the
bookkeeping required
to decide if any thread for example or
any data structure
has a still has a reference to this
element and the garbage collector once
it proves
this element can't possibly be ever used
again only then will the garbage
collector free this
so that's another quite possibly
reasonable scheme for deciding when to
free this list element
you know linux which uses rcu is not
written in a garbage collected language
so
and we're not even sure the garbage
collection would be would improve
performance um so we can't use a
standard garbage collector here and
instead
rcu uses another uh
sort of a trick that works well in the
kernel for
delaying freeze
and so that
idea is that the readers and writers
have to
each follow a rule that will allow
writers to delay
the free readers are not allowed to hold
a pointer to rcu protected data across a
context switch
so a reader is not allowed to hold a
pointer
to one of those list elements across a
context switch
so the readers
they cannot yield the cpu
in a rcu critical section
and then what the writers do is
they delay the free
until every core
has context switches at least once
so this is easy enough like this is
actually also a rule for spin locks in a
spin lock critical section you can't
yield the cpu
but nevertheless though you you have to
be a bit careful
this is a little more involved but it's
relatively
clear when each each core knows its
context switching
and so this is a pretty well defined
point for the writer to have to wait for
and just require some implementation
this also requires this may be a
significant delay it may be a
millisecond or a significant fraction of
a millisecond that the writer has to
wait
before it's allowed to free that list
element to be sure that no reader could
possibly still be using it
people have come up with a
bunch of techniques for actually
implementing this weight
the most the straightforward one the
paper talks about is that the writing
thread
simply arranges with the scheduler to
have the writing thread
be executed briefly on every one of the
cores in the system
and what that means is that that
every one of the cores must have done a
context switch during this process
and since readers can't hold stuff
across context switches that means that
the writer has now waited long enough
and so the way the actual writer code
looks like is
the writing code does whatever
modifications it's going to do to the
data and then it calls this
synchronize rcu call
which actually implements two
um and then the writer uh
frees whatever the old element was and
so that means that
you know the writer is doing whatever
it's doing you know at this point let's
say it's doing the
you know e1 arrow next
is equal to the new list element
and so you know uh
this synchronized rcu causes a force as
a context switch on
every core um so any core that could
have
read you know any core that could have
read the old
value must have read it at this point
i must have read it at this point in
time if after that point of time we've
done a context switch on every chord
that means that no core that read the
old value
could still have a pointer to that value
at this point in time
due to rule one and that means that
we're allowed to free the old value
any questions
you may object that this synchronized
rcu will take a
significant perhaps fraction of a
millisecond that's quite true
um it that uh so that's too bad
um one of the justifications is that
writing
you know for rcu protected data writing
is going to be relatively rare so the
fact that the rights take longer
may not will probably not affect overall
performance very much
for the situations in which the writer
really doesn't want to wait there's
another call
that that defers even the weight
called call rcu
and the idea is you pass it the um
in the usual use case you pass it a
pointer to the object you want to free
and then a callback function that just
calls free
on this pointer and the rcu system
basically stashes away
the call rcu stashes away
these two values on a list and then
immediately returns
and then does some bookkeeping typically
involving basically
looking at the counts of how many
context switches have occurred on each
core
the system sort of in the background
after caller c returns
does some bookkeeping to wait until all
cores a context switch and then calls
this callback function
with this argument and so this is a way
of avoiding the wait
because this call returns instantly
um on the other hand you're discouraged
from using it because
um now this list that um
if people if the colonel calls call rcu
a lot
then the list that holds these uh values
and get very long
and it means that there may be a lot of
memory that's not being freed
all the data all the uh this lit this
list goes very long
each list element of a is a has a
pointer in it that should be freed a
pointer to an object that should be
freed
and so under extreme circumstances you
can run a system if you're not careful
a lot of calls to rcu call rcu can run a
system out of memory because all the
memory ends up on this list of
deferred freeze
so people don't like to use this if they
don't have to
okay to uh
please ask questions if uh
if you have questions so this doesn't um
this prevents us free that's prevents us
from freeing something that
somebody's still using but it doesn't
prevent us
from modif like having the reader see
a half-baked version of something
because it's being modified right
idea one prevented that yeah
okay so the the the idea behind idea one
is that
instead of updating a list element in
place which would absolutely
cause the problem you mentioned when
writers are not allowed
to update rcu protected data in place
instead they
cook up a new data element
and sort of swap it into the data
structure with a single committing right
oh oh and the swapping will be atomic so
there's no problem over like
because that's a single pointer right
which is atomic whereas overwriting a
string is
completely not atomic that makes sense
other questions um does
condition one in um
idea three mean we need to be careful
about how much work we put
inside those protected sections since it
kind of hogs the
the core for that entire section
yes yes so so this is uh that's right so
um readers in the sort of rcu critical
section while they're looking at the
protected data they can't context switch
and so you're um
you know you want to keep those critical
sections short now
and then that's a consideration um the
the way it plays out though
is that the way rcu's been deployed is
typically that there'll be some piece of
code in linux
that was protected with ordinary locks
or read write logs
and somebody you know for some workloads
um
we'll see oh that lock is a terrible
performance problem and they're gonna
replace the locking critical section
with an rcu critical section although
sometimes it's more involved than that
and since locking critical sections were
already it was extremely important to
make them short
because while you hold a lock there may
be lots of other cores waiting for that
lock so there's a lot of pressure to
keep
ordinary lock critical sections short
because rcu critical sections are often
sort of revised lock critical things
that used to be locked critical sections
they tend to be short also and
you know that means that you know not
always but
usually um there's not a
not a direct worry about keeping the rcu
critical section short
um although it is a constraint the the
real constraint actually is you're not
allowed to hold pointers over con
pointers to rcu data over context
switches
um and that's actually that mean you
can't for example read the disk and
wait for the disk weed to complete while
while holding on a pointer
onto a pointer to rcu protected data
so it's not quite so much the or the
thing that usually comes up is not the
length of the critical section so much
as
the prohibition against yielding cpu
okay
let's see so just to kind of firm up but
i
all the stuff i just talked about here's
a
kind of what you would see in a simple
use of
rcu so this is code you might see for
reading a list
an rcu protected list and this is the
code you might see it on the right side
if
for code that just wants to the
particular case of replacing the first
list element so in the read side there
is actually this um
these read lock and read unlock calls
those do almost nothing almost nothing
um the only the only little thing they
do
is set a flag that says or rcu relock
sets a flag that says if a timer
interrupt happens
please don't context switch because i'm
in the middle of a
rcu critical section so that's all it
really does is set a flag that
prohibits timer interrupt context
switches the interrupt may still happen
but it won't context switch
and then read unlock unsets that flag
really it's a
you know counter of nested rcu critical
sections
so these two functions are extremely
fast and do almost nothing
and then this loop would sort of scan
down the uh
um our list this is the call
that um inserts the memory barrier so
what rc
this really boils down to just a couple
of instructions
it just reads
it grabs a copy of this pointer from
memory issues a memory barrier
and then returns that pointer
and then we can look at the content and
go on to the next list element
so the readers quite simple
the writer's a little more involved
writers still
you know the rcu doesn't help writers
avoid interfering with each other so
writers still have to have some way of
making sure only one writer modifies the
list at a time in this case
i'm just imagining we're going to use
ordinary spin locks so the writer
requires the lock
if we're replacing the first list
element
we need to save a copy at the beginning
because we're going to need to
eventually free it
so we save this copy of the oldest
element and now where this code plays
that trick i talked again about
allocating a complete new list element
to hold the sort of updated
uh content so we're going to allocate a
new list element we're going to
set its content we're going to set the
next pointer
to the next pointer in the old first
list element because we're replacing it
and then this rcu assign pointer
issues a memory barrier so that all
these
these writes happened
and then sets the pointer pointed to by
this first argument to be equal to that
so basically
this just issues a memory barrier and
then sets head equal to
e and now we can release the lock
we still have a pointer to the old first
list element
called synchronize rcu to make sure
every um
cpu that could have grabbed a uh
pointer to the old list element before
we did the committing right
has yielded the cpu and therefore given
up its
pointered rc protected data and now we
can free the old
list element
any questions
all right um
uh
there are rcu
one thing to note about this is that
while in the reader while we're allowed
to
look at this list element inside the
loop here
one thing we're not allowed to do is
return the list element
so for example we using rcu we couldn't
write a lookup a list lookup function
that returned either the list element
or a pointer into
data held in the list element like a
string that was embedded in the list
element
because then we'd be in then we would no
longer be in control you know
it has to be the case that we don't look
at rc protected data outside
um this rcu critical section or we don't
do a context which if
we just write a generic function that
returns a list element then for all we
know the caller
you know maybe we can persuade the
caller to follow some rules too but um
for all we know uh the caller may
context switch
or um or we'd run into trouble i that we
call rc read unlock before returning the
list element
which is illegal because now a timer
interrupt could force a switch
or we don't call rcub.unlock so the use
of rcu sort of
does put some additional constraints on
readers that
wouldn't have existed before a question
about that
yes so are you saying in particular that
if we had
some form of uh like read element
at index i method
that there is no way to structure this
so that it could return the value
held by the node at element i it could
return a copy
so what would work you know if erox is a
string we could return a copy of this
string
and that's fine what would be a
violation of the rcu rules is if we
returned a
pointer to this very string sitting
inside
you know a point
it would be a mistake to return a
pointer into somewhere into e
like if the string is stored inside the
list element we better not return this
pointer to that string
because then the uh
then we'll be we have to not context
switch while we're holding a pointer
into rcu protected data and the you know
the convention is
you know you just use that data within
this critical section
and so it would almost certainly be
breaking the convention or this setup
would have to be much more complicated
if we ended up returning pointers into
the protected data
thank you um
the so i just want to sort of return
briefly to the performance story
um it's
um it's hard to characterize sort of
what the performance is i mean in a
sense uh
the let's see the the overall
performance story is that if you use rcu
reads are extremely fast they just
proceed at you know whatever
they have sort of no overhead above the
ordinary overhead of looking at that
data so if your list is
a billion elements long yeah reading the
list will take a long time but it's not
because of synchronization it's just
because you're doing a lot of work
for readers so you can almost
view rcu as having zero overhead for
readers
and the
exceptions are minor rcu beadlock
you know just a tiny amount of work to
set this flag saying no contact switches
and rcu dereference issues a memory
barrier which
actually might slow you down by dozens a
few dozen cycles
but it much cheaper than uh
a lot the performance story for writers
is much sadder
you had to do all the stuff you always
had to do using locks in fact you have
to acquire and release locks
in the writer and you have this
potentially extremely expensive call
this or
time consuming called the synchronized
rcu in fact you can give a you know
internally synchronized rcu
gives up the cpu so you don't doesn't
spin necessarily
um but it may require a lot of elapsed
time waiting for every other core to
context switch
so depending on the mix of reason rights
um
and how much work was being done inside
the read critical section
the uh performance increase varies
tremendously from
um much much faster if these critical
sections were short
and there's few rights to perhaps even
slower
if rights are very common
and so when people apply rcu to kernel
stuff they actually
you absolutely have to do performance
tests against a bunch of workloads in
order to figure out whether
using rcu is a win for you because it's
so dependent on the workload
i have a maybe a tangential question but
we've seen that i guess when there's
multiple cores being used there's
some added complexity to our usual
implementations
and it's often the like these atomic
instructions
kind of come to the rescue and that's
assuming there's one
shared memory system but i wonder like
what happens if a machine is trying to
maintain like
multiple ram systems how does it
unify those
um the ordinary
um well
at a uh at the level we're talking about
the machine has one ram system
okay the you know the um
yeah it's um for all those sort of
ordinary computers you would buy that
have multiple
cores you can pretty much program them
as if they were just one ram system
shared among all the cores that's the
logical model the
hardware provides you at a physical
level it's not like that
often there's plenty of machines out
there that have
this physical arrangement we have a cpu
chip
so here's one cpu chip maybe with
lots of cores on it right and
you know you can get cpu chips with i
don't know how many cores these days 32
cores say let's say you want to build a
64 core machine you can only buy 32
core chips well you can make a board
i think it has two sockets for chips on
it so now we have two chips
the fastest way to get app memory is to
have the memory more or less as directly
attached to the cpu chip as possible
so what you would do is you'd have like
a very fat
set of wires here to right next to the
chip
um a bunch of ram so it has direct
access and of course this chip's going
to want its own ram
also all right so this is i'm just
drawing a picture of what you would see
if you opened up a
pc with two processor chips in it ram
but now we're faced with a problem what
happens if a software over on this chip
uses a memory location it's actually
stored in this ram
so in fact there's also a interconnect
between these two chips generally an
extremely fast interconnect like
gigabytes per second and the chips are
smart enough to know that certain
physical memory locations are in this
bank of ram
and other physical locations physical
memory addresses are in this bank of ram
and if software here
uses a physical address is over in this
one the chip is clever enough to send a
message
it's basically a little network send a
message over to this chip telling it
look i need to read some ram please do
it and
i'll go read its ram and send the result
back you know you can buy four chip
arrangements with the same thing with a
complex interconnect like this so
there's a huge amount of
engineering going on in order to map the
straightforward shared ram model
onto what's sort of feasible to build
with high performance
in real life and fit in two or three
dimensions
that answer your question yeah that
provides a lot of context thank you
okay
um
any questions on the actual technique um
all right so um as i'm sure you've
gotten the sense our
of rcu is not universally applicable
there's not you can't just
take every situation in which using
spinlocks and getting bad
parallel performance and convert it to
rcu and get better performance
because it the main reason is it
completely doesn't help rights
makes them slower now really only helps
performance if you
if the reads outnumber the rights
considerably
it has this restriction that you can't
hold pointers to protect the data across
sleep which just makes some kind of code
quite awkward
if you actually need to sleep you may
then need to re-look up
whatever it is you know to do another
rcu critical section after the sleep
completes
in order to look again for the um
for the data that you originally were
looking at assuming it still even exists
so it just makes code a bit more
complicated um
the data structures the the most
straightforward way to apply it is the
data structures that
have a structure that's amenable to
single committing rates for updates
so you can't modify things in place so
you have to replace stuff
and so you you know lists and trees but
not more complex data structures
the paper mentions some more complicated
ways like sequence locks
to be able to um update stuff in place
you know despite readers that aren't
using locks but they're good to
more complicated and the situations
under which they
actually improve performance are more
restricted
another subtle problem is that readers
can see stale data
uh without any obvious bound on how long
they can see the stale data for because
if some reader
gets a pointer to an rcu protected
object
just before a writer replaces it
the reader may still hold on to that
data for quite a long time at least on
the scale of
modern computer instructions
and a lot of the time this turns out not
to matter much
but the paper mentions some situations
which i actually don't really understand
in which people expect
rights to actually take effect after the
write completes
and therefore in which readers seeing
stale data is a bit of a surprise
you may also as a separate topic wonder
what happens if you have right heavy
data like rc is all about read heavy
data but that's just one of many
situations you might care about for
getting parallel
performance you also care about right
heavy data
actually in the extremes in some extreme
cases of rate iv data you can do quite
well there's no
technique i know of for write-heavy data
that's quite as
universally applicable as rcu um
but there are still ideas for for coping
with
data that's mostly written so the most
powerful idea is to restructure your
data
restructure the data structure so it's
not shared and sometimes you can do that
sometimes the sharing is just completely
gratuitous
and you can get rid of it once you
realize it's a problem
but it's also often the case that there
that while you do sometimes need to have
shared data that the common case doesn't
require
different cores to write the same data
even though they need to write
some of the data a lot and so you've
actually seen that in the labs
in the locking lab
in the k alloc part of the lab you
restructured the free list so that each
core has a dedicated free list
thus converting a right heavy data
structure the free list
into one that was sort of semi-private
per
core so most of the times cores just
have to
don't conflict with other cores because
they have their own private free list
and the only time you have to look at
other free lists is
if your free list runs out so there's
actually many examples of this
way of dealing with right heavy data
in the kernel i'm thinking of the
allocator analytics is like this
linux is scheduling lists um
there's a sort of separate set of
threads for each core that the scheduler
looks at most of the time
and cores only have to look at each
other's
scheduling lists if they run out of work
to do another example
statistics counters if you're counting
something
and the counts go change a lot but
they're rarely read
that is the counts are truly dominated
by rights and not reads
you can restructure your counter so that
each core
has a separate counter
and so beast core just modifies its own
counter when it needs to
change the count and if you want to read
something then
you have to go out and lock and read all
the per core counters
so that's a technique to make rights
very fast because the writers just
modify the local per core counter
but the reads are now very slow and
again you know but if
if your counters are right heavy that's
just the counters
often are um that could be a big win
shifting the work now to the reeds
um so the point is there are techniques
even though we didn't talk about that
much there are also
sometimes techniques that help for write
intensive workloads
um to wrap up the rcu the
stuff we read about in the paper is
actually a giant success story for linux
it's used all over linux to get at all
kinds of different data because it just
turns out that read and read mostly data
read intensive data is extremely common
like
cached file blocks for example they're
mostly red
so a technique that speeds up only reads
is
really very widely applicable
and artsy uses particularly magic
there's lots of other
interesting currency techniques uh
synchronization techniques rcu is magic
because it completely eliminates locking
and writing for the readers
so that's just like a big breakthrough
compared to things like rewrite locks
which were
the previous uh state of the art
and the key idea that really makes it
work is the um
sort of garbage collection like
deferring
a freeze for the what they call the
grace period
until all the readers are guaranteed to
be finished using the the data
so you can as well as a synchronization
technique it's actually fair to view it
as a
um very much so as a kind of uh
specialized garbage collection technique
and that is all i have to say so i'm
happy to take questions
oh sorry can you explain the uh the
stale
data for readers so i don't understand
why how that can happen because you
you read in your critical section
and um you just get whatever
data is there at that point and then you
just
um leave yeah it actually usually is not
a problem
um but the reason why it ever
might come up well ordinarily
you know if you have code that says x
equals one
and then you you know print
done gosh it's pretty surprising
if after this point someone reading the
data
sees that value before you set it to one
right that's a maybe a bit of a surprise
right
well there's a sense in which rcu allows
that to happen
right if this is really you know what
we're really talking about
is um you know list
replace whatever you know find the
element that is one in it and change it
to two
with our you know using rcu right
after that finishes and we print oh yeah
we're done
if there's some reader that was looking
at the list
right they may have you know just gotten
to the list element that held one that
we replaced with two and then a good
deal longer you know
and then they do the actual read of
the list element you know they look at
whatever the content is in the list
element after we've done this
you know they're reading the list
element only at this point later in time
and they see the old value
so if you're not prepared for this so
this is like a little bit odd now
um i mean
they may even do a memory barrier right
i mean it's not a memory barrier issue
it's just like
and indeed most of the time it doesn't
matter
i see so this is when this replace
is very close
so like the read somehow like starts
before
their plays but it just
takes a while and yes yeah if the reader
is slower than the writer or something
now you know be
i think this mostly doesn't matter
because
after all the reader and the writer were
acting concurrently
and you know if two things happen
concurrently
usually you you would never have
imagined that you could have been
guaranteed much about the exact order
if the two operations were invoked
concurrently
the the paper claims i mean the paper
has an example in which they said it
matters
it turned out to cause a real problem
although i don't really understand
why that was i see this makes sense
and my other question was it's called
rcu because of
idea one is that right read copy update
yes i believe it's because of idea one
that is that
instead of modifying things in place you
make a copy and you sort of
that's the real thing right this makes
sense thank you so much
yes so at the beginning of lecture or
towards the beginning we talked about
the of and
squared runtime for uh the cache
coherence protocols
um for for updating the read write locks
um
isn't this also a problem with spinlocks
where
yeah okay so so like what's the
reason why we didn't discuss that that
aspect
why we didn't yeah or like is there a
reason that
that still exists or like what do
spinlocks do to address that
nothing oh okay the knocks are hideously
expensive
if they're uh or standard spin locks
like xv6 has are
extremely fast if the lock is not
particularly contended
and terribly slow if lots of cords try
to get this unlock at the same time
gotcha okay yeah this is one of the
things that makes life interesting and
you know there's
i mean there's there's locks that are
have better scaling but worse
um that they have better high load
performance but worse low load
performance
but i'm not aware of a lock that is
anyway
it's hard it's hard to get this stuff
right it's hard to
get good performance in these machines
other questions
uh this might be unrelated but
can there ever be like lockings between
multiple assists different systems
um for like not just contained to one
system maybe like
multiple servers perhaps there are
absolutely distributed systems in which
there's a sort of locking
um in which the sort of universe of lock
spans multiple machines
when places comes up is in distributed
databases where the
data you know you have met you display
your data over multiple servers but if
you want to have a transaction
that you know uses data that's you know
different pieces of the data on
different servers
you're going to need to collect locks
that were uh
you need to basically collect locks from
multiple servers
um another place that comes up
although well there's been a number of
systems that are essentially try
to mimic shared memory across
independent machines
with machines you know if i use some
memory that's in your machine then
you know there's some infrastructure
stuff that causes my machine to talk to
your machine and ask for the memory
and um uh
you know then the game is usually to run
existing parallel programs
on a cluster of workstations instead of
on a
big multi-core machine hoping it's going
to be cheaper
and you know something needs to be done
about spin locks there or whatever
locking you're going to use and so
people have invented various ways to
make the locking work out well in that
case too
using techniques that are not you know
often not quite the same as this
although the pressure to avoid the
the pressure to avoid costs is even
higher in that case
anything else
thank you you're welcome