all right actually
it's time to start all right um
okay as franz was saying for you feel
free to interrupt with questions and uh
feel free to leave your camera on so
that we can
see each other as people this is going
to be another lecture about logging
this time a case study of the current
logging synthesis system
in linux's ext3 file system which is
extremely widely used
and we'll try to dip into some of the
kind of real world design
problems that a high performance file
system
has to deal with when it adds logging to
the file system
i'm just going to i'm going to spend a
few minutes basically reviewing
why we're talking about logging the
reason
uh that we feel logging is pretty
important
is that it's been a tremendously
successful and important idea
it's almost like logging is kind of a
magic way to add
crash recovery to any almost any
existing
storage system it's sort of a
in many ways pretty orthogonal to
whatever it is you're actually trying to
store
and so you see logging applied in a huge
number of
different storage situations certainly
databases and file systems but also many
very specialized systems
that need to store things and recover
after crashes
you also see logging used a lot in
distributed systems as a way of
organizing
the recovery from failure because among
other things logging is kind of a
structured way of saying well
here's all the things that happened just
before the crash and if we can
understand them then maybe we can
recover from the crash more easily
plus there's a huge amount of
interesting stuff to chew on
when you try to build high performance
logging systems and as i mentioned a few
minutes ago just as a
point of terminology when we talk about
log
it's talking about this exactly the same
thing as today's reader
reading was talking about when it said
use the word journal they're just
synonyms and furthermore the
today's reading talked about adding a
journal to ext2
the modern name for the resulting file
system is ext3
um which is how i'm going to refer to it
okay so i want to spend
the the way i'm going to kind of talk
about
ext3 is by
contrasting it to some extent with xv6
and explaining ways in which ext3
fixes some performance problems um
that xv6 logging has and along the way
changes a few of the semantics of
what happens during crashes
all right so this is sort of xv6
log review if you remember um
we have a disc the file system disks for
xv6
there's you know you can think of it as
having two parts it's got a
file system tree on it with a root
directory and under the root directory
maybe there's other directories and
in those this might be directory one and
directory two
we can think of this as the file system
it's just a data structure it's a tree
structured data structure
maybe it has files sitting in the
directories
and each file has a bun block numbers of
a bunch of blocks in it
and there's some other data that's not
really tree structured like there's the
bitmap
uh that indicates for every block
whether that block is
you know free or allocated um
and the inodes and the directory
contents and the bitmap blocks
we're going to refer to as metadata in
contrast to blocks that hold
file content which we'll call file
content blocks
okay so in addition to the file system
xp6 has a log it's near the beginning of
the disk and
the x86 log is relatively simple it has
this header block
and then some number of blocks that
contain
updated versions of blocks from the file
system both
data blocks and metadata blocks
and in this initial header block there's
the
block numbers where
these blocks in the log ought to be
written to like maybe the first one
should go to block 17 and then 29
who knows whatever it might be and then
in the computer
we have some user process that's maybe
calling write or
create or some other system call that
modifies the file system
um and
uh there's a block cache in the computer
and initially the rights just go to the
block cache
those are just copies of blocks from the
disk
so initially write updates file blocks
or inodes or whatever
those rates go there and then at the end
of an operation
these blocks are copied to the log and
when we've copied all the blocks of the
log then
we write the block numbers to the header
block to indicate that
this transaction's worth of updates is
complete
and in the code for the file system
you'll see
[Music]
that every system call that modifies the
file system
somewhere has a begin op which says i'm
about to start a
group of updates to the file system
please don't do
any of them until i'm finished so we
have a and then
there's a bunch of block reads and
writes and then in
end op which tells the file system
logging system
i've completely done all the writes i'm
going to do so
um between the begin op and the end op
the writes
only go to the cache and when the
system call makes this end up call then
the file system copies the
modified blocks from the cache into the
log and
after it's written all these modified
blocks into the log
only then does the file system write the
block numbers
in a single disk right to the header
block
and that's called the commit point this
is the point before the file system
wrote these blocked numbers to the
header block
if a crash had happened then none of
these rights
would have been applied after the crash
and reboot
after the file system writes these block
numbers of the header block
after that disk rate is complete then
it's guaranteed that even if there's a
crash at this point
the recovery software will look at the
log see that there's block numbers in
the header block
and write all these blocks that are
mentioned in the header block
to their home locations in the file
system
and so what's going on here is this is a
technique to allow
all of the writes that happen in the
system call between the begin up and the
end op
to be atomic with respect to crashes
that is either all of them happen
because the file system got as far as
rating the header block before the crash
or none of them happen because a crash
happened before
the file system wrote the header block
and so it's important that after a crash
and restart there's some recovery
software that runs that reads the log
looks at the header block and decides is
the header block actually have block
numbers in it or not
if it does it writes possibly rewrites
all these blocks to their home locations
if the header blocks doesn't have any
block numbers in it then the recovery
software does nothing
any questions about this quick review
okay um there's a couple of super
important points
to remember about xv6 and indeed most
logging systems
one is that xv6 all logging systems
essentially
obey what's called the right ahead rule
that is
whenever you have a bunch of rights done
by some operation and those rights all
need to be atomic
it the system has to write
all of these updated all the updated
data to the log
before it is allowed to apply any of
those updates
to the home locations in the file system
that is that we're required to sort of
pre-declare
all the updates that we want to have be
atomic
pre-declare them in a log before we can
apply any of them to the file system
that's called the write ahead rule and
this is really the foundation of
how logging allows crash recovery so the
writer head rule allows this
collection of updates to appear atomic
with respect to crashes
um there's another rule i haven't talked
about
which is that we can't free
or reuse the log you know we xv6
uses the log over and over again once
for every system call we cannot allow to
reuse the log
until all of the writes that are in the
log have actually been written to their
home locations on the disk
so there's also what i'll call a freeing
rule
which says we can't overwrite or reuse
the log until uh the
you know the part of the log that holds
a particular transaction
you know set of rights that need to be
atomic we can't reuse that part of the
log until all the rights
that are in that part of the log all of
them have been
reflected into the
uh actual home locations in the file
system so the deal in xv6 is
in what endop does actually triggers a
whole lot of work
first and the file system you know as i
mentioned writes all the blocks to the
log rates the header log
writes the header block and then the
file system
writes all these blocks to their home
locations this is assuming no crash
which is the ordinary case
so then the file system writes a second
time you know
all these blocks to the home locations
on the disk and then after the
all the home locations have been updated
only then does the file system go
xv6 file system erase
these block numbers from the header
block to indicate that
oh we're done with this transaction and
we can reuse the log
and it's critical to erase the block
numbers
before writing anything new to the log
because we wouldn't want to be in a
position where there were some
block numbers from a previous
transaction in the header
but blocks from a new transaction
with presumably different block numbers
sitting in the log
because then a crash would might apply
these contents
um to the stale block numbers left over
in the header block so we have to erase
the header block first
so this is freeing rule that says before
we're allowed to
erase a transaction from the log we have
to write all this block to the file
system
okay so the net effect of this is to
make
file system updates which can be
complicated and require many rights
the net effects is to make each system
call essentially be atomic
all its rights are none of them with
respect to crashes
okay so um
so the sort of bridge to linux's logging
scheme
is the question of what's wrong with xe6
logging you know why doesn't linux just
use
exactly the same scheme that xv6 does
and the answer is basically that it's
slow the xv6 game is
quite slow every system call before a
system call like write or create
can return in xv6 um all of this stuff i
just talked about has to complete
so before your file creation system call
can return to user space
um the it has to finish all the stuff
that endop does which means
write every block to the log write the
header block write all those blocks to
the locations here and then erase the
header block and then you can return
and during that time um not only does
each system call take a long
time but nothing else can happen in the
file system
while any system call is committing
um and then writing its blocks to their
home location so the
system calls really occur one at a time
and each system called recur
requires many disk rights um
and the technical term for every system
call has to wait for all of its disk
rates to complete is called synchronous
um there's
probably spelled differently from that
anyway xv6 is system calls are
synchronous with respect to disk right
so they're very very slow
they were horribly slow with mechanical
hard drives because
each write you know basically would take
10 milliseconds
we're talking about many writes for
system calls so xv6 could only do
a few file system modifying system calls
per second
and i want to if we ran a solid state
drive to be faster but still
like not nearly as efficient as it could
be
another more detailed thing to notice
about this is that every block is
written
twice in the xv6 scheme it's written
once to the log and then a second time
to the disk and so this is also
something that
there's good reasons for that but it's
ext3 partially fixes
okay so on to linux is under the
today's reading and it's sort of
i'm going to talk about the uh
this ext3 file system which is
what the today's reading had turned into
a few years later after a bit more
development
and was widely used
okay so um
exc3 um
it's actually a modification a
previous logless file system and so they
really did uh
play this game of taking an existing
storage system and sort of layering
logging on top of it in a way that left
the
underlying ext2 file system
almost unmodified although not quite um
and so in a sense the logging was a very
kind of
easy you know at least in principle easy
upgrade for them
exe3 keeps
data structures that are similar to
xv6s in memory there's a block cache
it's a right back cache
so there's a bunch of cache blocks some
of them are clean in the sense that they
haven't been modified since
you know identical to what's on the disk
some of them dirty the sense that
they've been written to
since they were read from the disk um
and some of them were pinned and that
they're not allowed to be
written back to the disk uh because of
the right-back rule
i mean because of the freeing rule the
right-ahead rule
esd2 also cause maintains
some transaction information
it can maintain information actually
about multiple transactions that are
concurrently in different stages of
execution
so there might be a number of different
transactions that the
exc3 system is keeping track of
each one each transaction has a sequence
number
um a set of block numbers that the
transaction system is the logging system
is remembering are
blocks modified by that transaction so
these are
set of block numbers and this really
refers to
cache blocks because any modifications
at least initially you happen only in
the cache
and then a set of what are called
handles
which are information about system calls
that are still currently executing
and as part of this transaction and
reading and writing
cached blocks and on the disk
on the disk just like xv6 there's the
usual file system tree
with inodes and directory blocks and
files and whatnot
and there's bitmap blocks
indicating you know whether each block
is
data block is allocated or free and so
these are what i'll be calling the home
locations of file system blocks
and then on a sort of designated part of
the disk
um there's the log
and so so far this is pretty similar to
xv6 the main difference is the
ext3's ability to keep track of multiple
uh
transactions at the same time in sort of
different stages of their execution
now i want to look more closely at
what's inside
the log in ext3 it's a bit different
from
what's in the xv6 log
this is really the log format
um at the beginning of the log there's
something called the super block
and the super block this is the log
super block different from the file
system super block
the log super block contains the offset
and sequence number of the
first valid transaction in the log
so it's going to have an offset this is
just a byte number or block number in
the log and then this
sequence number remember i said that
every transaction has its own sequence
number
and then the rest of the log the log is
just a bunch of sequential
blocks on disks of a known size
every transaction the rest of the log
consists of transactions each
transaction
consists of a descriptor block
which contains block numbers just as in
much like the header block in the uh
xv6 and then the set of for you know for
each of these block numbers the actual
co
updated content block
corresponding that block number and then
finally for a transaction that's
actually finished and committed
there'll be a commit block
and this is a separate block in the log
and because there can be more than one
transaction of the log
that a commit block may be followed by
the next transactions descriptor block
and then some data blocks and then maybe
the next transmission transactions
commit block
so we have multiple the log file can be
quite long and contain
many transactions in it
um so this we can think of this offset
and sequence numbers basically between
them
uh pointing to the very the first
the beginning of the earliest lowest
numbered
valid transaction in the log
a uh a little detail here
that will become important in a little
while is that
these the descriptor blocks and the
commit blocks
in order to be able to help distinguish
them from d from data blocks
if when they're in scanning log after a
crash and recovery the description of
the commit blocks
start with a magic number which is just
some 32-bit number that
is unlikely to occur in data
and that helps the log software
distinguish
descriptor and commit blocks from data
blocks
okay um with this in mind with this
structure in mind i'm going to talk
about the
high level the ways that exe3 gets good
performance and there's really three
main
questions is it possible for at least in
this system
to have a descriptor block before they
commit block let's say two transactions
going on at the same time
there can be multiple transactions in
the log
um does the transaction need to finish
before the next one can start
yeah we'll talk in a moment about that
but it's it
is the case yes that um
there's there's only one open
transaction at a time
um and this is really um
not quite the right picture for that
because the current open transaction
the the current open transaction is is
the transaction into which system calls
are performing their rights
and so the current open transaction
really only exists in memory
um and because current system calls are
sort of updating
they're just updating block the cached
file system blocks in memory
when the exc3 system decides to finish
the current open transaction um
you know after it decides to finish it
it'll do two things one is it'll start a
new open transaction which will be the
next transaction
and it will then write the the just
finished transaction it'll start writing
the just finished transaction to disk
which may actually take quite a while
so um so so
you know the full story is that there's
a bunch of older transactions on disk
that all of which are closed
plus um one open transaction that really
only exists in memory
and at least initially these
transactions that are on disk
uh may only exist in the form of the log
records
and haven't initially at least been
written to their home locations and then
after a while in the background
the starting with oldest transaction the
logging system will you know write these
uh updated blocks in a log to their home
locations and then once that's been done
for each
complete transaction then the login
system can free and reuse
this space in the log and so this is
really a circular log when you
get to the end of the log the logging
system
starts using the blocks at the beginning
and you know has to free
them free these blocks by writing them
to their home locations before it can
reuse them
okay okay so there's three ways that uh
the system gets
exe3 gets good performance uh
one is that it's um has asynchronous
system calls that is
system calls uh return before they've
written the disk
the system called just updates cached
blocks in memory and then returns
never never has to write the disk never
has to wait for disk rights
although it may wait for disk reads
the next big idea for performance is
batching
we can batch many system calls into a
single transaction
and the final big idea for performance
is concurrency
and these are all the things these are
basically the things that ext3 does
that xv6 doesn't do
okay so i'm going to talk about each one
of these three performance techniques
oh sorry i wanted to ask about batching
yes xv6 allow for there to be multiple
system calls that do start off end up
um like at kind of the same time
so then they will commit together
yeah that's true xv6 is a limited amount
of batching
thank you yeah
okay so first um uh
asynchronous system calls
um
this just means the system calls return
but they modify blocks in the cache and
then return and
don't particularly don't trigger disk
rights
so this has the obvious advantage of the
system calls return quickly
it also allows for io concurrency that
is
the application can make some file
system system calls that imply
that the file system ought to do a bunch
of disk operations disk rights
um but the application can then return
to computing
uh in parallel with the file system
doing whatever the rights are that are
required by those system calls
so this is called i o concurrency and
without asynchronous system calls it's
hard to get i o concur
concurrency to get overlap between
disk operations and application
computing if the applications always
have to wait for the
disk rights to complete um
and the other thing that's nice about
asynchronous system calls is that
they allow they make it easier to do
large amounts of batching
so they're sort of help batching
the downside of asynchronous system
calls is that
it means that just because the system
calls return
doesn't mean that the work that
you that the system calls ought to have
done
has actually been completed so for
example if you write a program that
creates a file and writes some data data
to it and then closes the file and then
prints done on the console to the user
and then you pull out the power plug on
your computer
after you restart the computer your data
may not be there even though all the
system calls returned
and even though the programs are just
said look you know i called those system
calls and they returned
um and this means that um
in a world with asynchronous system
calls applications have to be written
more carefully if they
if they care about their behavior with
respect
to crashes this is actually kind of a
big deal in
in xv6 if a write returned
the data was on the disk and would be
there after a crash
in est3 if a right returns this
you don't know anything about what will
happen after a crash may or may not be
there
um so it is possible despite
asynchronous system calls to write
careful programs like databases need to
be careful
text editors need to be careful if i
write out a file you know i do not want
if there's a power failure while i'm
writing out a file in my text editor i
don't want to
after be starting to see garbage or a
partial file and i want to see either
the old file or the new file
and so the file system also provides
some techniques for careful applications
to um get predictable
behavior despite crashes and the main
tool for that is called
it's a system call called
fsync which you know all unix systems
have and what this basically says is
that
uh you pass it a file descriptor and it
tells the file system look actually do
all of the rights you know i may have
called write a bunch of things and
called fsync
i now want you to actually do the rights
and don't return from this system call
until the rights are on disk and will
are guaranteed to be still there if
there's a crash
so if you look at the source code for
databases or text editors or a number of
other
programs that really care about their
data you'll see sort of carefully placed
calls to fsync
in order to sort of overcome this
um fight back against these asynchronous
system calls
most programs though like your compiler
you know it's no big deal if
the output of the compiler goes away if
there's a crash and therefore many many
programs
don't call f-sync are very happy to get
the good performance of asynchronous
system calls
and are not worried about their crash
behavior
okay so this is this uh also called like
flush sometimes
because i think that that words i've
heard that word before
a lot yeah yeah you could a reasonable
way to explain what
fsync does is that it flushes all
previous writes to this file to the disk
and only returns that so flash is a
reasonable word for this
flashing rights to disk
okay so that's the signal the system
calls the next
technique that axt3 uses is batching
and
the game here is that there's at any one
time there's always
one open
transaction in the x3 ext3
a transaction in exc3 can actually hold
the rights of many
different sys many distinct system calls
um
so the ydx c3 does is says well i'm
going to start a new transaction now and
then
for the next couple of seconds all
system calls that execute
are um their rights are part of that one
big transaction
i think by default ext3 only creates a
new transaction every five seconds
so each transaction may have up to five
seconds worth of system calls in it
all as a huge batch and then at the end
of the five seconds
ext3 will commit this single big
transaction they may have hundreds of
updated blocks in it commit this
transaction to disk as
a single transaction and so the reason
why this is a win
first of all it spreads some fixed
transaction costs
amortizes some fixed transaction costs
across many system calls so for example
you have to write the descriptor block
and the commit block um
and you have to seek on a mechanical
drive at least you have to seek and let
the drive rotate to the place where the
log is and those are significant costs
and they only have to be done once per
batch instead of once per system call
so it lowers the impact of those those
costs
the other big deal is that another big
deal is that it allows
right absorption that is
it's often the case that you have a
whole
sequence of system calls that end up
modifying the very same blocks over and
over again
so for example if i create a whole bunch
of files
um i need to allocate a bunch of inodes
and that means
all i knows are small maybe 64 bytes so
many many inodes fit in the block
so creating a bunch of files in a row is
going to dirty
many inodes in a few blocks
because there's many i knows for block
similarly if i'm
writing um a bunch of data to a file i
may need to allocate a lot of data
blocks
i may flip many of the uh
bits in the block free map and if i
allocate blocks that are next to each
other
their bits are going to be in the same
block and so i may flip many bits
in just one block so many system calls
again
um may end up writing the same blocks
over and over again and
if in the system with batching those
many many writes are the same blocks
just happen
very quickly to the cached um just
the cache copies of the blocks because
we're not writing the disk and then we
write
the the um those small number of blocks
of the disk
only once at the end of the transaction
and the single block right into the
onto the right hand to the log reflects
many many system calls worth of
modifications to the same block so this
rate absorption can be
reduce the amount of just the total
number of times we have to write the
block
dramatically compared to a synchronous
system like
xv6 um
and the final big win is disk scheduling
um in general
even if we um suppose we have to write
a thousand blocks to the disk it turns
out to be much more efficient
certainly in mechanical drives but even
in solid-state drives
to write a thousands blocks all at once
just in
sequential locations as you would do to
a log
um it's much faster to do that than to
write a thousand blocks
one at a time to different locations um
or even a thousand blocks
you know even right the same block a
thousand times in a log
um so by handing the disk
large batches of writes to do
this can be much more efficient there's
also
not only do we get an efficiency from
writing a large number of blocks
sequentially in the log
but even when we go to write the home
locations for this
for a batch of uh the rights resulting
from a batch of operations in a single
big transaction
even then if we can hand a very large
number of rights to the drive
even if they're to different locations
because they're to the home locations of
you know referred to by many different
system calls if we allow the disk
to schedule um a large number of
distinct writes
it can pick an order to do them in
that's particularly efficient
and on a mechanical drive this would um
involve sorting them and
sorting them by track number on the
drive and doing uh
you know just a little seek from one to
the next and they can do this sort
if you give it all of the blocks at the
same time
and but even on a solid state drive it
turns out there's
smaller winds to be gone from giving the
disc lots of work to do
anyway so this you can only really get
this kind of disk scheduling
if you have very large batches of rates
to give to the drive
so there's another win from batch
all right and
a final big win from
that est3 gets is concurrency it's
really got
two kinds of concurrency that it
benefits from
compared to xv6
one is that it can allow many system
calls to execute at the same time so
we can have into many individual system
calls
in parallel because
at least
until exe3 decides to close out and
commit the
current transaction the system calls
don't have to wait for each other they
can all modify blocks that are part of
the current transaction and all these
many many system calls
can execute in parallel and
contribute blocks to the current
transaction that's particularly
important on a multi-core machine
where we don't want to have the
different course be waiting for a lock
you know in xv6 we often it's often the
case that you're not allowed
a system call can't proceed because um
the current transaction is busy doing
something else
most of the time in est3 many system
calls
can modify the current transaction the
other way that
exe3 gets concurrency is that there can
be multiple transactions
older transactions in different stages
of execution
so it's true a system calls only the one
open transaction
can receive system calls but the other
transactions that are writing things to
disk and go on in parallel
so many older transactions
and the different sort of stages in a
transaction's life that can go on in
parallel
first there's the one open transaction
there can be some number of transactions
that are recent
and the file system is committing them
but
they're still writing their blocks to
the disk so we have
some number of transactions that are
currently committing to the log
and we don't have to wait for these to
finish that is we can continue with
system calls in the
new open transaction while the previous
transaction is still writing to the log
and hasn't
actually finished committing yet of
course this stage ends when the
transaction writes its commit block to
the disk the log
there can be transactions that are
even older transactions that are writing
their blocks from the cache to the home
locations
of the modified blocks and finally
this doesn't take much work but there
can be the oldest transactions are being
freed this doesn't really take work
itself the work is really writing the
transactions
to their home the blocks of their home
locations but anyway there's
typically multiple transactions in
existence in these different stages
and so in particular our new system call
is going to execute without waiting for
older transactions to either
finish committing to the log or finish
writing their blocks to their home
locations
in contrast to xv6 where new system
calls had to wait for this to complete
for
all for for the one previous transaction
i have a quick question um so how does
it work when
there's an operation or when something
is writing to a cache block
and the block is also being written to
the disk
okay so there's um uh so that is indeed
a problem
uh then and the the uh
the um there's a potential difficulty
here because
a transaction you know the stuff that a
transaction writes to the log should
only include
updates made by system calls that were
in that transaction it
shouldn't include any any block updates
made by system calls that came after
that transaction
because if you did you'd risk
sort of committing having in the log
updates
that only represent partial system calls
whereas we want to make sure that the
transaction only contains all of any
given system calls
updates so we can't afford to have a
transaction
include updates made by anything that
happened after the transaction
started to close and the way esd3 deals
with that
is that at least notionally it makes a
copy of when it
decides to wrap up the current open
transaction it makes a copy of
all the blocks for that transaction as
of the time it closed out this
transaction
so it sort of makes copies of all the
blocks and then it's though
that copy of the blocks that the
transaction
commits into its log and any newer
transactions
have their own copy of that block that
they modify it's a
different copy from the moment
committing to the log
and in order to make this efficient the
system actually uses a kind of copy on
right scheme to
avoid making the copies until it
actually notices that a newer
transaction is
needs to write that block cool that
makes sense
um good and so the
the reason why concurrency helps
performance again is that um
it can help us uh if we can run system
calls in parallel we can get multi-core
parallelism and if we can run
applications and system calls at the
same time we're rating the disk then we
can get
i o concurrency that is overlap between
cpu
and cpu execution and disk io
and all these sort of help use the
hardware resources the machine more
efficiently more intensively
all right any questions about
concurrency
all right i want to um just give you a
taste of what
the actual file system code if you look
at the linux source
for the file system um
sort of at a somewhat abstract level
this is the way
each system call looks um so you might
have a
unlink system call
and this is you know can be pretty
familiar from
xv6 we need to every system call needs
to say
here's the beginning of the sequence of
writes you know i'm about to do a
sequence of writes and they need to be
atomic with respect to crashes so every
system call
well in any transaction system there has
to be a clear sort of begin
and you know everything between these
two points
needs to be atomic and there's a start
call that system call code makes um
and it turns out that exe3 has to be
aware
of the different system calls that are
active for reasons i'll explain in a
in a minute or two um so every system
call when it calls start it actually
gets what's called a handle
um that's a sort of unique identifier of
this particular system call
um and the rights that it makes are the
loggings the file system sort of keeps
track oh yeah that write was done by
this particular system call
and then the system call needs to read
and write blocks and so it makes a
to get hold of a block or really a
buffer
a block cache buffer makes a get
call and it tells the handle and then
the block number it needs to read or
write
and it may do a bunch of these right if
you need to modify many blocks
and then when modify so that it will
modify the blocks in the cache
and when it's done this this particular
system call is done
it makes a stop call and passes the
handle
to the stop call
so um the
a lot of what this is about is informing
the logging system you know once a
system once a system called starts
a transaction is not allowed to commit
until all the system calls that started
in that transaction have finished
so um and
because there can be multiple
transactions
the system has to be able to associ one
of the reasons for the handles is so the
system
the file system can remember for each
system called which transaction it was
part of
so it knows oh and this just call
finishes
that's one of the system calls a
particular transaction was waiting for
before it could actually commit
we pass the handle to the get system
call so that
every system every transaction has a
bunch of blocks that are
associated with it that were the blocks
modified as part of that transaction
so what we're seeing here among as well
as getting a pointer to the block
is we're telling the logging system look
this block number
is part of the transaction that this
handle refers to
the stop call doesn't actually cause a
commit it just tells the logging system
look
you know you have one fewer system calls
that are active
in this transaction and so a transaction
can only commit
if all of the system calls that started
in this transaction
have called stops so the transaction has
to do some bookkeeping has to remember
all the handles that started so that it
can sort of check them off
as those system calls finish
so with this structure in mind i'm just
going to lay out the complete
sequence of what it takes to commit a
transaction
so you know at some point when all the
you know every five seconds the
file system is going to think to itself
oh you know now would be a good time to
commit the current open transaction
and so here's what happens when the
here's what's involved in the file
system
committing a transaction so these are
like steps
so first we have to block any new system
calls
right we we need to have um our
transaction
uh reflect um only entire system calls
so we don't
want to let anything new start um
when we're trying to commit this
transaction we want to only include
system calls that have already started
so we need to block new system calls
there's actually another reason i'll
talk about
why we need to block new system calls
this is actually a little bit of a
performance defect there's going to be a
period of time here
when system calls have to wait and are
not allowed to execute so that's too bad
the second step is that there were a
bunch of system calls that already
started that are part of this
transaction
um then we need to wait for them to
finish
so we need to wait for the outstanding
system calls
that are in this transaction
because of course we want the
transaction to reflect all of their
rights
so we need to wait for them to finish
the next thing that happens is
you know once all the system calls for
this transaction are finished
and have done their rights into the
cache it turns out then it's okay to
start a new transaction and let these
blocked system calls continue
so now we're going to open a new
transaction
for these for any subsequent system
calls
but now this i'm continuing the story
with our original transaction which is
now closed so remember the log
next in ext3 contains descriptors and
data blocks and commit blocks
so now we know the full set
of blocks modified
by all the system calls that were in
this transaction because they all called
get with
a handle that told us about what
transaction they were part of
so we know the full set of modified
blocks for this transaction
so now we can write a descriptor block
um that has all the block numbers
for all the blocks dirtied in this
transaction
we're also going to write the actual
modified blocks
from the disk cache
into the log and in fact as somebody
somebody asks a question about oh what
happens if the next transaction
modifies this block what we're actually
writing in this stage is the
sort of saved copies of
this transaction's blocks as of the time
when it finished
so i'm going to write the actual
blocks to the log
and now we're going to wait for these
rights to finish
so these need to finish um
before we can proceed once the
descriptor and the data blocks are
guaranteed to be on the disk then we can
write the commit record
to the log
and once that write is finished we have
to wait for it to finish
so we're waiting for the waiting for the
commit rate to finish at this point
once the commit rate is finished uh this
transaction
um with the sort of technical term is
that this transaction has reached its
commit point
that is it's guaranteed the rights in
this traction are guaranteed to survive
a crash at this point
if the crash had occurred before this
before writing the commit block
the rights in the transaction would not
appear after a crash and reboot
and running the recovery software if a
crash occurs now after the
this commit point after the commit block
is written to the disk
um then they're guaranteed to those
rights
all the rights in the transaction are
guaranteed to appear after crash
reboot and recovery okay and now
then only now um in the background
that all of this kind of happened in the
background no process was really waiting
for this stuff
now we can write the transactions blocks
to their home locations in the file
system
um and
uh as i'll talk about in a few minutes
after all of these rights have completed
um for all the blocks that are part of
this transaction
then only then can we reuse
that part of the log
so in a very busy system if the head of
the law catches up with the tail
there may actually we may not be able to
start a new transaction until
all of these rights have finished for
the oldest transaction because
uh we may need log space and we you know
won't we
need to reuse the oldest transactions
log space we have to write for it to
write all the cat its cash blocks their
home locations
this usually you people try to make the
log big enough that this
happens pretty rarely so that this stuff
can go on in the background
any questions about these steps
oh sorry where are those run
right for doing this um
file system stuff
can you see that again oh so you said
that no process is
waiting for those things to um
to get done so where where are they
scheduled where are they run
oh um there's there's a background
thread
there's a background thread in the
kernel dedicated
i see thank you
got a question actually about reusing
part of the
lock so let's let's say eventually we
start using
a particular section of log
and the load the that particular as i
think just as mentioned
that particular lock of particular part
of the log actually
in my new transaction actually
[Music]
ends up using the whole log part that
was just freed up
and there's nothing else there's no more
space for the lock
with the lock then like with the system
just wait
until the another portion of luck is
freed up
or to put it to something else to uh
yes it'll wait um uh
let me though let me just draw a picture
to
help me make sure i'm answering the
right question here um you know we can
think of the log
as just this linear part of the disk
and at any given time you know maybe
maybe the oldest valid transaction is
you know t7
and then there's t8 in this region
and we have t9 and we you know we want
to start
you know we want to put t10 here um
the um
let's see one you know we'd like to
start a new transaction and put it here
um the
[Music]
we may have to wait for t7
to um write all its blocks to their home
locations so that we can free it
and that may mean that the transaction
stuff in transaction 10 may have to
pause waiting for
this space in the log to free up is that
what you're talking about
yeah so let's say that so it could be
the case at the beginning
the i can put in blocks for transaction
in the actual free space right now but
eventually
if the luck grows big enough it's just
going to run out of free space and at
that point it's just going to wait for
transaction 7
to yes be recorded okay yes yes
certainly if there's enough activity
going on and the log wraps around
quickly enough
you may end up having to wait for a new
new
system calls we may not be even be able
to start the system calls because we
before we can free up space in the log
for the blocks that they're going to
modify
and you know if you care about the
diesels of this it turns out there's
some potential deadlocks here
um that require
that that mean that um ext3 ends up
system calls have to pre-declare how
many blocks they're going to need
so that the logging system knows
sort of how much can reason about
whether
there's enough space for this
transaction because we don't want to
allow a transaction to start
that we wouldn't actually be able to
commit into the log
okay let's um let's say it's
the new log or the new transaction
you're trying to put
goes to like eight transaction eight
so you would have to wait for seven and
eight right so how does that
work you mean okay so
it's transaction seven and transaction
eight in transaction 9 at least
in this diagram have all completed or
the all the system calls have finished
and these transactions are committed in
the log
because these are the old transactions
so
in this picture at least we're just
starting transaction 10.
and so new system calls are going to be
writing into transaction 10.
right but you said that um transaction
10 is not
big enough to fill that space so you
need to um
free transaction 7 right yes you need to
wait for that to like
commit to disk yes
but what happens if you if it's if 10 is
like
bigger than like seven like it goes to
eight transactions then we have to wait
for two
yeah we have we may have to wait for
however big transaction 10 is
you know we need we need enough space on
the disk to fit it
and not enough space in the log to fit
it and so indeed if transaction 10 and
it turns out being big it may
need to force multiple transat multiple
of the oldest transactions
um to write to their home locations and
and free themselves i guess how how does
code for that work
like does it like just run through how
big it is and like say hey there's a
transaction here and a transaction here
and it's like i have to wait for
both of them the file system knows
knows how big all the transactions in
the log are
and it remembers and remember i mean
actually the file system remembers quite
a bit about each of these older
transactions it knows
for each one whether it's written you
know
for ever the file system keeps track of
for every block and
all these each of these older
transactions whether it has written that
block to the home location
so that it can know oh i've written it
can know whether or not
and recognize the point at which it's
finished writing all the transaction
sevens blocks or transactions ease
blocks so there's quite a lot of
bookkeeping going on here
for this file system to understand in
detail the state of every
old transaction
okay um
okay so uh indeed there's there's on the
topic of how to reuse log space there's
one little detail here that
um needs to be said if you remember at
the beginning of the let me
let me write a new diagram um there's
actually a
super block the log super block at the
beginning of the log
and so at any given time you might have
the log super block
and then um some set of transactions
you know maybe it was transaction four
which is a the newest transaction and
then
transaction one and
the older transactions and so what this
means is that of course the log is
wrapped around
um um
and you know the uh
the rule for whether we could reuse a
part of the log just
now i've mentioned this before i just
want to say it again is that we can
reuse the log
say we can reuse this part of the log
that transaction 2 is in
if t2 has committed and
all of t2's blocks have been written to
their home locations in the file system
so that there could never be any need
after a crash to replay
these blocks right
and if all transactions prior to
transaction 2
have also been freed so if those
conditions are all true
then we can free and reuse the part of
the log that t2 sits in
um so we can only use t2 and
after t2 is after t1 has finished all
committing and writing its box to the
log to the home locations also
um and then this super block for the
convenience of the recovery software
after a crash
if we decide that we can if the file
system decides it
can free and reuse a particular part of
the log
um it rewrites the superblock to
the super block as a pointer to the the
first
transaction of the log and so as part of
freeing
part of the log the file system modifies
a super block to point to the new
the beginning of the of the now oldest
transaction in the log and then if
there's a crash
other recovery software reads the
superblock finds the beginning of the
log
okay so if there's a crash um
of course a crash um
causes everything in ram to evaporate
so all that bookkeeping that the file
system is keeping about what blocks have
been written
to their home locations that's all lost
if there's a crash or power failure
however so the one of the assumptions is
there's nothing useful in ram
the only stuff that's can be preserved
across the crash is whatever's on the
disk
but we are absolutely in all these
discussions about logging
assuming that the disk is completely
intact that nothing went wrong with the
disk
um so so maybe the right model for you
to think in terms of is that there was a
power failure that everything was
humming along and then the power failed
and the system just stopped at some
point
um and the disc is after power's
restored the disc just has whatever it
had on it
at the point of the power failure so
we're absolutely
not considering situations in which the
disc
was somehow corrupted or destroyed by
the crash
and so the crash of course may interrupt
um
you know whatever transactions we're in
the middle of committing or not yet
committing yet or
whatever the crash may interrupt um
either the commit of a transaction or
the writing of a
transaction's blocks into their home
locations
um so what that means is that the on
disk log
when the power is restored and recovery
software's run it's going to have
a bunch of complete transact older
complete transactions
and maybe t1 and t2
um actually let me think of a new
example for uh
for recovery uh let's say we have the
again the super block
um and
maybe at the time of the crash the um
oldest transaction um
it was t6 and then there's t7 then we
wrapped around
still before the crash to t8
and there was a t5
um but t8 as
let us imagine has started has
overwritten the first part of t5 because
t5 was
you know we know that t5 was freed
before the crash but
you know the recovery software doesn't
necessarily know that um
and let's say the uh super block points
to t6 as being the
start of the oldest valid transaction
you know so
t5 is it's free um
we're going to reboot with an attack
disk the recovery software reads the
super block and so then it knows the
where the beginning of the log is then
the recover software is going to scan
forward in the log to try to find the
end of the log
but we need to have a way for it to
actually figure out oh you know that's
the end of the log
the way it does that is
we know that every transaction
consists of a descriptor block that
indicates how many data blocks there are
on the transaction
so the descriptor block says oh yeah
there's 17 data blocks and we expect 17
data blocks and finally a commit record
and then another descriptor record and
then the number of data blocks implied
by the descriptor block
and then another commit block and so the
log software's going to scan forward
maybe t6 and t7 are fine then it's going
to look at t8 t8's got some descriptor
block
and then the recovery software is going
to look forward to
where the end of transaction h should be
and look for a
commit block and so you know there's a
couple of
things that may have happened here it
could be that
transaction a did commit and that the
recovery software finds the commit block
it'll then look for another
you know it doesn't know that
transaction is the last transaction
needs to figure that out so it's going
to look at the very next block
to see if this is a valid descriptor
block
now we know that this block was really
just a random block in the middle of
transaction five and not a descriptor
block at all
and the question is how can the recovery
software reliably distinguish between oh
this is a
just some data block in the middle of an
old transaction or
it's the maybe the descriptor block for
transaction nine
and he guesses for a reliable method to
do that
is that the magic number or yeah or is
there just a reserved
bit there is indeed every uh
descriptor and commit block starts with
some um
magic number just just a 32-bit value
that the recovery software is looking
for
i don't actually know what it is um so
um definitely the game is that we come
to the end of transaction eight if the
very next block
starts with the magic number um then the
recovery software is gonna
assume that oh this is a valid
descriptor block
um sorry quick question
um would it be unreliable to try to
like uh interpret it as a
descriptor block try to read the number
of like data blocks that it specifies
then like see if there's a commit block
at the expected location after that
number of blocks
um if well certainly if this block does
look like a descriptor block
then it will skip forward and try to
read the corresponding commit block
and if that commit block doesn't look
like a commit block with the right magic
number it will
not believe in this transaction
the the the thing that's uh the one
little
remaining detail here is that this block
that we're looking at here and we're
wondering or the
uh recovery software is wondering if
it's a descriptor block
this could be just a block right in the
middle of transaction
five containing any arbitrary bit
pattern
it could be just like the data block
from a file that just happens to begin
with the magic number
so you know as a final detail the
logging system needs to be able to
distinguish between a valid descriptor
block that starts with this magic number
and just some data block that starts
with the magic number
and you can imagine various ways of
doing that in fact
what ext3 does is whenever it's going to
write a block to the log that's not a
descriptor block or a commit block
if that block starts with the magic
number it replaces that with 0
and sets a bit corresponding to that
block
in that transaction's descriptor block
then that bit means
this particular data block started with
the magic number and we replaced it with
xero
and then if the recovery software ever
needs to replay that block
so let's say transaction 8 had one of
these blocks that originally started
with the magic number it's going to set
the bit
this magic flag corresponding to that
block and the descriptor block
and replace magic number with 0. if
recovery has to replay this block it'll
see that flag
and before replaying this block to its
own location we'll replace the zero
with the magic number and therefore
no block other than a descriptor or
commit block can possibly start with the
magic number
in this logging system so we never have
this ambiguity if the block after a
commit block
starts with a magic number then it must
be a descriptor block
okay um all right so recovery we were
doing recovery it
starts at the block that the
superblock says is the beginning of the
oldest transaction it scans
forward and it'll scan forward until
you know it look at a descriptor is
there a corresponding commit block
and it'll stop as soon as it sees oh
the block following a commit block
wasn't a descriptor block at all
or yeah the block following a commit
block is a descriptor block but
the what should have been the
corresponding commit block
is not in fact a valid commit block it
doesn't have the magic number so at that
point it'll stop
um and recovery software will declare
the log to have ended
at the point where the the last valid
commit block
and it will ignore there may be a
partial transaction after this
that started to commit but didn't finish
but the recovery software ignores that
partial transaction you know because it
doesn't have all the rights
so it can't restore it atomically and
then the recovery software will go
through
go back to the beginning of the log and
replay each block
rewrite each block to its home location
all through the log
to the last up to the last valid commit
block
and then i can sort of restart the rest
of the
operating system start the rest of the
operating system and uh
ordinary programs can run of course
before recovery finishes you can't
you know you can't run any programs
because the file system
isn't valid
any questions about recovery
i i have a quick question um i think you
mentioned this before but what
parts of this logging transaction scheme
is missing
in xv6 um the the main thing
that's missing in xv6 is the ability to
have multiple transactions
in the log so in xv6 there's only ever
at most one transaction in the log and
so
you can't um you don't get this
concurrency in xv6 where
while i'm executing system calls from
transaction
7 you know that are going to go into
transaction 7
in parallel with that ext3 can be
committing
transaction 6 to the disk that's not
available that
concurrency is not possible in ext
in xv6 because
the the log holds just the one
transaction so we have to completely do
all the work for one transaction before
we're allowed to start anything
with the with the next transaction and
so it's correct and simple but
um you don't get a lot of parallelism
out of xv6
okay thank you are you saying that it
can still have multiple transaction
blocks but it just can't execute them
asynchronously
would that be correct xv6
and x36 it um yeah it it
it it only has the once it decides to
i mean the the picture's a little bit
confused because xv6 can allow
more than one system call into a single
transaction so xv6 actually does have
some of this concurrency in it and some
of this batching
but once that c6 decides to start
committing a transaction
it has to completely finish with that
transaction commit it to disk
you know write the header block write
the blocks to the home locations
and then erase the transaction from the
log
it has to do all that stuff before it
can execute any new system calls
because there's nowhere to you know
there's nowhere to put the modifications
for the new system calls until the
previous transaction is completely
finished
so xv6 sort of you know alternates
between they can run a few system calls
and then commit a transaction and then
run a few more system calls but they
can't
sort of overlap those two exe3cam
thank you yeah
okay so that was a relatively
straightforward part of
ext3 design
it turns out there's also a bunch of
tricky details
a few of which i want to talk about so i
mentioned before
that you know there's an open
transaction but when exc3 decides that
it wants to close
the open transaction it has to wait for
all system calls in that transaction to
finish
before any trans any new transactions
are allowed to start
so the maybe a picture for that is that
you know we had
uh our original old transaction t1
and there were you know multiple system
calls that um
executing in transaction one if we want
to close transaction one we have to stop
accepting new system calls because we
want to wait for the existing ones to
finish
before we can commit but until these all
these system calls finished
no new system calls are allowed to start
in the xt3
so if there's some transaction two here
nothing is allowed to happen in
transaction two
no nothing's allowed to system calls are
allowed to start until these system
calls
have finished and only then can
transaction two start
accepting system calls so um
there's a period of time here in which
uh new system calls are all blocked and
so you know that reduces performance
because
we could have been executing system
calls but we're not allowed to
and the question is how come ext3
doesn't allow new system calls to start
in transaction two
until all system calls and transaction
one have finished
and you know it's a good question
because it limits performance so
let me give you an example if we if ext3
didn't do this
then the following bad situation could
arise
so let's suppose transaction one just
has one system call in it
and it's a create a system called to
create a file maybe a file called
x and the idea is that before this
create is finished
uh the file system decides it wants to
start a new transaction
open up a new transaction and it's going
to accept any system calls after the
create in the
in this new transaction transaction t2
so we're going to say t2 starts
before t1 finishes and we start
executing system calls now in
transaction 2.
and maybe transaction t2 calls unlink on
some other file well
then unlink will free the inode
associated with y
right and so maybe it may be at some
time i'm having time
go this way in my diagram
maybe at this point in time transaction
marks the inode is free marks the ion
for y is free
create of course has to allocate an
inode for x maybe it allocates an i node
at this point in time
well because the creed is allocating
after the unlink freed
it might reuse the same inode so maybe
x is going to get the same inode that y
hat say
maybe i node 17. all right
and then um you know which is okay
because unlink free design notes so
it doesn't look like a problem yet um
you know the point is we're trying to
close transaction one so then when the
create finishes we close transaction one
and we're going to write let's say
transaction one actually commits we
write all of its modifications to disk
fantastic however supposing
after the unlink takes a while it hasn't
finished yet
supposing after this commit finishes
there's a crash
right
when the recovery software runs it's
going to see that transaction 1
committed
and that transaction 2 didn't so the
recovery software is going to just
completely ignore transaction 2.
so that means the unlink never took
place its rights the recovery software
won't do won't perform the unlinked
rights to the disk
therefore won't free the inode uh won't
won't delete y after the crash and
recovery y will still exist
it'll still be using inode 17 however
the creates transaction
did complete and therefore x is going to
be using
inode 17 as well and so now we
mistakenly
have two files that happen to be using
the same inode
right which means they'll share content
or write to one will mysteriously
show up in the other file
which is completely the wrong thing
right the whole point was when we wanted
to unlink y
and use a free dinode in x not a i know
that was already in use
so something's gone terribly wrong here
um
and you know the one way of thinking
about it is that
that unlink in transit in what should
have been transaction two wrote a block
modified a block and essentially that
modified block was used by an earlier
transaction so a later transaction
modified a block
and that modified block was seen by an
earlier transaction
and and indeed information based
on this modification from transaction
two was incorporated into transaction
one
but that means that we've lost atomicity
here
because the whole you know the goal of
this was that all the modifications for
the unlink should occur or none of them
not not just some of them but what's
essentially happened here is
because transaction one committed the
free of this inode
it means that some of transaction two's
modified modifications actually occurred
but others did not so we've broken
atomicity by
including a later transactions right
in an earlier transaction you can
actually imagine
multiple different ways of dealing with
this right
you know maybe create could notice that
17 had been freed by a
you know a future transaction and not
use that inode
in fact uh exc3 takes a sort of
pretty simple approach to this it
doesn't allow any system call to start
until all system calls from the previous
transaction have finished
so there's no possibility of a
transaction
of a system call from transaction one
seeing a modify
seeing an update from a system call in a
future transaction
essentially all the unlink is pushed is
blocked and not allowed to start until
t1 commits any questions about this
so i have a question about um
what exactly happens when you close
an open transaction does it like
snapshot
uh like the current state of like the
cash
yes that's exactly right so when we
close this transaction
at least in principle the system makes a
copy of
all the blocks that were modified by
system calls in this transaction
the logging system makes a copy of them
in the cache sort of private copy
just for this transact just so this
transaction can commit them
and then future transactions execute
sort of on the real
cached blocks this transaction commits
from its private copy
of the blocks it modified and then when
it's done committing those
this private copy of those blocks to
disk you can throw those copies away
yes
okay um there's
it turns out this is one of about half a
dozen or a dozen
sort of similar little quirks that um
exc3 has to deal with because in order
to support concurrency
there's a whole bunch of kind of similar
little ordering
niggles that have to be that sort of
special cases that ext3 has to get right
which we don't have time to talk about
but uh the take-home points that i want
people to remember about
logging and about ext3 first just the
general point
that what logs are all about is making
multi-step
disk updates atomic all or nothing with
respect to crashes like
you know that's the main thing to
remember about logging um
the logging the correctness of logging
depends on this right ahead rule
that's another critical thing to
remember you'll hear write ahead
log and write ahead rule a lot in the
kind of crash recovery
business and the writer head rule says
that you have to commit
all changes to the log before you're
allowed to make
any of the modifications to the home
locations
in the file system and recovery
absolutely relies on this rule
um a lot of the point at least for file
systems a lot of the point of logging
is is simply fast recovery that the log
may have a couple hundred blocks in it
you can replay a couple hundred blocks
in way under a second
um and then boom your file system even a
very large one is
now fit for use and a final point for
more detailed point about ext3 is that
it uses batching and concurrency to get
considerably better performance than xv6
does although
at the case of considerable considerably
higher complexity
to support concurrency than xv6 had
and that's all for today i'm happy to
take questions
oh hi i had another question it's
um about so you said that um
things that there's a file like a file
system thread that does
all this stuff there must be only one of
this threads because otherwise
it could it could do basically what he
just talked about
right um
it may indeed be that there's just one i
actually don't know how many there are
one is certainly a particularly
attractive number
because you know a lot of the rationale
for why the logging is correct is that
you know the older transactions are you
know
committed before newer transactions
i i don't think it's a logical necessity
that
um there'd be only one thread though you
could imagine
uh old transactions committing
in an overlapped way uh you know
essentially using multiple
threads um one for each transaction
oh okay i see yeah
okay i see another question um
in when you're talking about crashes and
you have that diagram of
t8 rewriting t5
um that was being freed um
so what happens if uh t8 hasn't actually
committed
at the point of the crash um because
there could be
maybe t5 if it's being freed as
something needs to rewrite it then there
could be a commit block from t5 that
exists
um in maybe a location where t8 would
have predicted it to
exist and then couldn't that
inaccurately represent that t8 was actu
had actually been committed
okay so let me try to draw out the
scenario
yeah so we have this ancient transaction
t5
right and um you know maybe a t6
who cares and then we're we wrapped
around a t8
and you know t8 started somewhere now
it's because t5 is
free t8 is starting to eat up
uh t5 that is
the end of t8 is overrun the beginning
of t5 is that
okay and the the worry is okay of course
if ta did commit then it'll end up in a
commit block and
it'll all look pretty reasonable if
there's a crash in recovery
and the scenario you're worried about is
the t8 did not commit
right and maybe let's see
right before writing the block okay so
the juicy
yeah yeah exactly so t8 has gone t8 just
happens to be gonna put its commit block
in exactly the same place where t5 put
its commit block
but it didn't quite get the writing the
commit block it's all good except
this we have a totally correct t8 but
it's t5's commit block
yeah and you're wondering gosh looks
just like a commit block
okay the answer is that the uh
descriptor blocks and commit blocks as
well as everything else have the
sequence number
of the transactions so this descriptor
block has an eight in it
and but t5s commit descriptor
doesn't matter but t5's commit block has
a five in it
okay yeah and so yeah it's looking for
eight as well as the magic number
good question uh
wait but in this case wouldn't you also
have the descriptor block of t5
so you don't really need the numbers
well in this particular case so yeah t5
used to have a descriptor block here
with a five in it however t8 is so large
that
t8 overwrote this descriptor block with
it one of its own data blocks
so that t5 descriptor block's now gone
and been replaced by a
t8 data block so yeah it used to be
evidence for a transaction five but now
it's
now it's gone
so do we know the size of transaction
eight before we started
um
um sorry this is a complex question
the uh it's probably the case that he ex
that
um okay when t8 was opened
as the active transaction that system
calls were writing into
at that point in time the system didn't
know how big t8 was going to be
when the system starts committing t8
it does know it doesn't it does know how
t8 how big t8
is the system doesn't start committing
t8 until after t8 is closed and all of
its system calls are finished
and at that point the system knows i
mean it saw all the writes that were
done
you know all the rights vt have
completed all the system calls are
completed so the system knows how big it
is
um and one reason why that must be
is that the descriptor block holds the
complete list of blocks in that
transaction and so with the time the
descriptor block was written which is
first the logging system knew how many
blocks that were going
we're going to be in t8
yeah okay i see i see thank you
uh why don't we just uh kind of like
have the commit
information in the descriptor block and
avoid this kind of problem
because i know i know it's not great
that we have to go back and like write
back to a location
like not in sequence but wouldn't that
help
okay so the proposal is that instead of
having a commit block
um we basically have the descriptor
block act as a commit block
and xv6 actually is very much like this
um and that you know you could do it
um and and in fact i think you can do it
without
at least an ext3 without sacrificing
efficiency however you have to play the
same you have to
structure this in the same way that xv6
does namely
um you you
um if there's a you know there have to
be something in the descriptor block
that indicates
this is a committed transaction and
we're not allowed to
set whatever that flag is until after
all of the data blocks have been written
so the routine would have to be we don't
write the commit block first
instead we write all the data blocks for
transaction eight first
and then we go back and write the commit
block with the block numbers
um or the descriptor block whatever it
is now and
some kind of magic this is really a
committed
transaction so we could write all the
data box and then go back and write the
commit block
the descriptor commit block whatever
i don't know any um
i don't know any reason why this
couldn't be made to work
it i i don't think it
it doesn't i don't think it really
eliminates any of the
problems we've discussed because we
still have this problem
you know the original problem was gosh
how do we distinguish
you know this commit plot this stale
commit block from transaction five from
a true commit
block for transaction eight we're gonna
have the same problem here
you know this it could be that what's
sitting here you know just happens to be
the descriptor block
from transaction five and so you know
maybe we've gone ahead and written all
the data blocks for transaction eight
and then there was a crash
the recovery software still needs to be
able to tell the difference between
to be able to look at this descriptor
block and say wait a minute
you know there's something wrong here
even though this looks like a valid
descriptor block it's not really
and so we'd still have to have the magic
number and
the transaction number the sequence
number
um oh yeah that makes sense yeah i was
just thinking like we'd
have we kind of have like the commit
part in the description block but
obviously like when we start ta we write
the descriptive block saying it's
uncommitted then we write the data
blocks then we say
it's a committed right now the thing
that
could be saved here is the expense of
waiting for these rights
and then writing a commit block right
that weight
is quite expensive we're not allowed to
start the right of the commit block
until the data blocks
are on the disk and i i don't think
we have to have the same weight before
we in here in this sort of new
single block scheme we have to have the
same rate weight
before we're allowed to write this new
descriptor block so it saves a block
but it doesn't save i don't think it
would save much time
um the trick i
the trick that later versions of the
linux file system play that
sort of does do what i think you're
hoping for um
you know the this is looking into the
you know ext4 does the following
for better efficiency of writing the
commit blocks um
it exe4 will
write out the all the data blocks and
the commit block at the same time
um that is it doesn't wait for the data
block rates to finish before it writes
the commit block
so it doesn't have this long pause but
then
there's this terrible issue of what
happens if the disc you know the disc is
free to do writes out of order
what if the disc writes the commit block
first before it actually
performs the rights for the data blocks
and then there's a crash then we have a
commit block
without having the discover having
written the data blocks and the way ext4
solves that
is it has a checksum
in the commit block over a checksum over
all the data blocks
and so if there's a crash happens after
the commit block was written but before
the data blocks were written the
checksum won't work out
the recovery software look at this
checksum and then it will compute the
checksum over the data blocks that are
actually in the log if they're not the
same it knows that something went wrong
and so by doing this ext4 basically
saves
on a mechanical drive saves an entire
rotation
that would happen if it had to wait for
the data blocks
before it commits
okay thanks sure
oh that's cool
i love this stuff but this
this is very cool oh i wanted to ask
also about the
data blocks just the content blocks
so i think i got confused but where in
the steps that we were talking about
uh on your one of your previous boards
where
would that be done where would which be
done
so like uh not the metadata blocks but
um the actual file content yeah all
right
okay this is a there's sort of multiple
answers to this
in the uh
ext3 has multiple modes
um for what happens to the data blocks i
think
there's three two of which i remember um
there's journaled data
and ordered data in the
and you when you configure an exc3 file
system you
tell linux which you want
if you ask for journal data
then file content just goes right into
the log there's nothing special going on
if you
write data to a file you know and that
causes the inode to be updated
then the log is going to contain your
data and the updated inode
you know everything everything that's
modified goes in the log
so that's journal data but of course
it's quite slow or slower than you might
hope because
um you know
now you if you write a whole bunch of
data it has to be written once to the
log and then a second time to the home
location so
the journal data scheme is sort of
straightforward but
slow then there's this other ordered
data scheme
that people it's actually the most
popular mode um
that avoid that doesn't write the data
to the log
in the order data scheme only metadata
like inodes and directory blocks are
written to the log
and file content block is just written
directly
to the home locations in the file system
and so it's a lot faster because you
don't have to write the file content
twice
it does lead to more complexity though
because
if you you can't just write the file
data anytime you want
because then there's a risk that
if you don't worry about the order in
which you write the inodes versus the
file data
there's the risk that you might out do a
write that causes a new block to be
allocated for a file
and have the updated inode be
written into the log and committed and
then have a crash happen before you
get around to writing the actual file
content to the disk
and then after recovery what you would
see is
the inode with the new newly allocated
data block
but the old contents of that data block
from whatever
file previously used that data block um
and so if you're running a system that
has multiple users like an athena
system then it could be that one user
will end up having a file that contains
contents from another user's deleted
file
if we're not careful about the order in
which we uh write the data
versus the inodes
aexd3 ordered data mode solves this
by not committing a mod the modified
inode until
after the file content has been written
to disk
so if you're an application and you
write to a file that and that right
causes a new block to
be allocated uh the file system will
write the new file content to the newly
allocated block
and once that write is finished only
then will it commit
the transaction that
causes the inode to be updated to have
the new block number and that means that
um
a crash if there's a crash that's going
to be happened between when you wrote
the data
after you wrote the data and before you
wrote the inode and therefore won't
reveal
somebody else's old deleted data block
to the new user of a file
okay i see okay i see but you could
still have the data but
not the inode yeah you might
if there's a crash after you after you
wrote the data block before you wrote
the inode then
you'll have updated the data block but
it doesn't matter because not only did
you not write the inode you also didn't
write the updated uh block
free bitmap lock and so that block will
still be free and can be allocated for
something else so you
don't even lose a block all right and if
it was an old blog then
it's still okay right say it again
if it was just just the same the same
block could just
write some new data to it but same block
same size
um same same location
but we already wrote like it's not that
we created a new block but
in the old block we just wrote some
extra data but it was a little bit so we
didn't
need to create a new one yeah we wrote
data we ended up writing to a
data to a block that was not in use by
any file
so it's not visible right okay i see
thank you