uh
good afternoon uh quick sound check can
people hear me yes
thanks okay so uh i guess uh today
you know so far it's the last lecture or
so 81 this semester and
we don't really have a formal uh
topic uh you know there's a q a lecture
uh so feel free
to ask questions uh about anything uh
this is i guess last uh your last chance
at least this semester for this class
um by default my plan was to uh
go over a couple topics uh based on the
questions uh over email
one i was gonna talk a little bit about
the network lab the solutions
uh the it's possible also a little bit
of
time about the ml lab and again talking
about those solutions
and then there were a lot of questions
about the follow-on classes
and the fact that i think i'll cover
that first
uh but before diving in uh in any of
these three topics uh let me remind you
uh there's a subject evaluation
uh outgoing ongoing and uh we repeat
as a staff of so81 we appreciate if you
uh
you know give your feedback on so 81 and
hopefully it's positive and you know we
get a chance to teach you again
uh next year and maybe this is also
a good time to you know uh actually
thank you for attending
today's lecture even though there's not
a sort of very formal program but i also
uh
appreciate the fact that with the staff
and generally appreciate the fact that
uh you know you're you've been very
engaged and uh
you know particularly with the papers
that are not directly to the labs you
know
it's clear that many of you dove into
the papers and try to really understand
them and
ask great great questions uh over email
so
we very much appreciate the engagement
any questions before i
go over this set of topics
okay let me uh start them with the
question that probably came up most in
email
what next um there's a quite a number of
classes
uh that uh you know systems oriented
focused
and i'm sure i missed a number of
classes
uh that i should have listed here uh you
know immediately sort of straightly
related to operating systems you know
clearly you know if you haven't taken o3
yet you know it's a great class to take
and particularly
read read or learn how to read papers
uh 6828 was the
the original and the only os class uh
that
we offered uh you know these this year
uh where this is the second year where
this year is the year first year that
we're offering both uh so soa one is
the undergrad os and sa2a the
of h28 as the grad level os class
um and you know the basically 808
assumes you have taken oath one
or undergrad os and you know goes off in
doing projects and
building interesting os artifacts and
reading more papers from the literature
more of the modern research literature
then maybe you're more you know the the
os sort of you know does a lot of
interfacing with the hardware
a little bit more of the hardware side
of systems you know the computer
architecture class a23 which i
believe is offered to the coming spring
and of course the 611
you know sort of the you know building
something uh
hardware devices uh on the
sort of performance sites and the
compiler sites 6172 and 6035
are good places i think the number of
you are taking 6172
in parallel with s081 so but if you
haven't taken for example the compile
class or v5 or the dynamic
you know compiler class you know both of
them are also great classes
uh systems is a broad topic uh so like
there's
uh networking and there's a whole branch
of classes and a whole stream of classes
around networking
there's a whole stream of class around
databases
which are all good and
important and uh aspects that you've
seen
in so 81 will show up in much more
prominent ways
uh in those classes um so for example
networking clearly is a great topic of
829 and so you'll see a lot more about
networking there
than you've seen in so 81 uh 6830 you
know we talked about file systems you
know
clearly another important class of uh
storage systems uh
and probably in some ways more important
for many applications is databases and
so
630 is a great topic class to learn a
lot more about databases
in terms of like classes that are sort
of uh you know sometimes called whatever
the pdos classes
um there's a number of them uh
eight through four the distributed
systems class uh we'll be offering that
uh
uh coming semester spring semester and
a a section of the number of the
staff involved this semester in nassau
will be involved in a24
uh there's a 858 which is the computer
security class
we won't be offering that coming this
spring
but you know we hope to offer it the
next academic year
and there's uh 826 which is the
principles of computer systems so if a
number of people ask about verification
and system software
uh this is the class to take if you're
interested in that topic
uh more broadly speaking a lot of people
wondering like
what is actually going on in research if
you're interested you know the
almost all the papers in the systems
literature are publicly available even
the ones at the recent
conferences so example the oci
conference happened a couple weeks ago
and you can just look at them and see
what kind of topics are covered and
read the papers that you find
interesting all the talks are published
one of the advantages of i guess you
know the covert period is that all these
companies are virtual
and so all the conferences are recorded
and you can just watch them and
see what's going on if you're interested
in the sort of two parts you know just
the research part
then of course you know there's what's
going on in practice and you know if
you're interested in
keeping track of what's happening with
linux and how that's
uh how it's evolving uh lwn.net actually
publishes a
at a very regular page and a very very
interesting articles about like sort of
big changes
or topics that are around the linux
kernel
uh finally you know uh if you're just
excited about like
doing the labs you know just keep keep
hacking i think you
you can use easily to cook up projects
uh either by doing
extensions of labs or just trying things
out on your own and
it's a great way to really learn and
appreciate how things work you probably
have gotten a good sense of that during
the labs
we're sort of big fans of learning by
doing and
you you can a lot of that you can do it
on your own
any questions about
what next after actually one
okay well let's talk about the uh
net lap uh and then that was julia like
i said
yesterday um
and so uh there's a couple things so
maybe i'll start it uh
we'll dive in sort of slowly and start a
little bit at the top
um and let me talk a little bit in
generic uh terms about
the lab
uh there's a couple things i first i
want to talk a little bit about just
sort of structural things uh that sort
of influenced
the design of the lab or you know the
coding of the lab
and those are four different things
aspects one is i just want to talk a
little bit about hardware
uh you know this is one of the labs
where we uh
there's a lot of interaction between the
software and hardware in fact the
hardware determines for a great part
like how the
the structure of the software um known a
little bit about software structure
uh and just come sort of back to this
general topic that we covered in uh sort
of
like somewhere in the middle of the term
about you know the organization of
drivers relative to the rest of the
operating system kernel
then talk a little bit more specific
about hardware structures you know the
rings uh and you know the descriptors
are the two primary sort of hardware
structures that the
driver deals with or it must deal with
and then
uh i'll talk a little bit talk about the
code and particularly the solutions
uh and sort of focusing on a little bit
about the role of m-buffs
uh you know walking a lot of questions
uh over email about
you know why not a lock in receive lock
would receive
uh in the receive function uh why the
loop in the receive handler
and uh you know what exactly you know do
the
flags mean in the command command
field of the structure of the descriptor
and so
we'll get to those issues if we as we
look at the top as we look at the code
the just before we drive in like it may
be worthwhile so reminding ourselves
here what the
challenges are although they're probably
fresh in your head
but like from a high level like what are
the sort of core talent challenges that
you know you have to deal with in this
lab
if you'll jump in now to add any ones
that i might have missed and you
struggled with so first of all you know
there's the hardware specification
uh this is a you know it's a
pdf is a pretty serious document uh
and this network card uh the 1000 um
even though it's a reasonable simple
network card is still a very
sophisticated uh piece of hardware
uh that offers a lot of different
features and ways you can
program and as you're just getting on
top of actually what the
you know the card does and how do you
program it
uh you know just internalizing all that
uh is is difficult
and uh poses a challenge um
the second i think you know major
challenge is the
concurrency side of things
and there's sort of two parts of the
concurrency that makes this a lot
uh challenging one is just the
concurrency between the hardware and the
software
right like the network card is just
doing things like sending packets
receiving packets at the same time
you know the os kernel is running and
the driver is running and so there has
to be some coordination plan
you know between the hardware and
software you know to actually make sure
that everything works out
and uh and a large part of the driver uh
is you know dealing with that you know
coordination
uh there's also the software chakra
convert
coordination you know the driver
multiple threats or multiple kernel
threats might be ending or
handler run inside of the driver uh
and we've got to make sure that they
don't step on each other's toes
nothing else happens and this comes a
lot to like you know the
locking uh topic
even the even in this driver you know
things are reasonable uh
straightforward in terms of the
concurrency for
the software concurrency but
nevertheless you know it's something
that requires attention and a little bit
of thinking
and then finally i guess the as you
that's probably on the top of your list
or many of your list is you know just
debugging
this is a little bit hard a little bit
sometimes more challenging of pure
software debugging because
you can't set you know break points
inside of the network card
you know you can program the registers
and then this will give the card a kick
and say like you know please do your
work
uh and then if the card doesn't do
anything or you don't see your packet
coming out on the other side
you know in the log you know of
the packet trace then you know you
basically have to scratch your head and
sort of start thinking about like what
what you what might have gone wrong or
what it might you have missed in the
hardware specification and so you have
to go circle back and forth and
there's no sort of easy way uh or you
can just can't not single step
you know through the the network card
does that make sense in terms of
challenges you know does that line up
with your own experience or am i missing
some of the
missing one of the core challenges that
you dealt with
okay oh uh
let's talk to them uh let's start with
the hardware side of things
uh and uh and the reason i want to start
there because
uh you know it's easy to keep or lose
track of the fact that you know actually
we're dealing with hardware here
uh you know even though you know it's
sort of virtualized where it is
emulated by qmu and you're just running
it on your
on athena or on your laptop uh the
actual thing that's implemented by qmu
is hardware and so it's usually
reminding you again
you've seen this picture before uh you
know the way to think about it is that
you know qmu
emulates a complete board of
devices and the processor
and um
um and so you know if we don't know i'll
talk a little bit before about it like
the process actually is
like almost like a small piece of the
whole
uh board you know it's the thing that
sits under the fan here uh
but then you know there's a range of
devices you know that are
you know connected or can be connected
to this board and then interact you know
with the
code running on the processor you know
here you know for this particular
you know what it's really interesting
sort of is the actual
event jack you know where you can plug
in your ethernet cable and then that is
actually the thing that the network card
you know sends its package over
um now pbu doesn't emulate exactly this
board
so things are slightly differently but
again you know at least conceptually
this is like a picture you should have
in your
in your head right and so when you know
the process really
you know writing you know registers you
know of the device driver
that cost some stuff to happen that
actually in the end some packet comes
out of this cable
that's connected to the ethernet
connector
um you know in a slightly more
uh you know
uh in a slightly more in a in a
schematic diagram you know this is the
same picture basically in here you know
we're seeing
here's our processor uh board that has
four
cores on it uh it has one of the l1 and
l2 caches and then it has like a link
you know going to memory
so here's the memory and the ram random
access memory and as we'll see
in a second you know that plays actually
a big role and then here
like intersection the link you know to
the or here actually it's linked to the
gigabit
uh even a controller now
uh it's a little bit messy you know so
to think about the
this level of detail uh what exactly is
going on and so like for the rest of the
lecture you're a little bit more
simpler uh sp picture
uh and the picture guys you really you
should you're in your head
and you probably developed uh while
doing the lab is as follows
basically have our risk four processors
for the course so here's our risk five
and you know there is this five uh
courses execute the instructions
uh that you know you're you're writing
and you can just think about them
they're sort of
all connected to a boss and there's a
little bit of a simplification but like
it makes it easier to
explain things and so like on the boss
you know there's the random access
memory
where all the data you know the kernel
actually uses is
historic you know the kernel taxes
itself is stored you know we've looked
at there's a
great amount of detail in the beginning
of the semester and then in this you
know for this particular lab the thing
that's interesting is that on the bus
uh is actually uh the network cart
you know the e15 that you want thousand
and you know the the ram is generally
more connected to the risk fly processor
directly with some private bus
uh and network the devices intentionally
tend to be on a slower
type of bus and in particular the bus
that uh in the lab you know there's a
pci a
pcie bus that actually connects
the processor part you know with the
network card
now to get the network card to do
something the network card you know has
a controller inside of it
and you know these controllers has
registers
and you can one of the cool aspects of
you know these
registers they're called like memory
mapped
io registers and so you could just write
them with you know whatever star
you know ox and whatever the value is
you know for in the physical memory
space what the value is for that
particular reticent
you know it's like we might have our
head our tail register
and you know we can the driver can you
know write those by executing you know a
load or restore instruction
you know to the address you know that
corresponds you know in the physical
address space
to the location of that register and the
hardware will ensure
when we do load the store you know that
that store will either go you know we'll
go to the uh
if it is now to one of the controllers
it will go to the control registers
if it goes to you know one address is in
ram we can all go to the ram
and so you can just manipulate or
program uh the
network card by loading you know reading
and writing
these controller editors and basically
the bits in these controller registers
have special meaning as you have seen
um now for this particular card you know
the
network card needs to send of course
packets across the network
and you know and it needs to get the
packet somewhere
and so uh the packets actually live you
know
are allocated as we'll see in a second
you know they just live somewhere in
memory
and and what we do is and in fact in
addition to these packets you know there
are sort of two
ring structures that also leave in
memory
and uh
and we can you know program uh and we
can tell the cart you know the card also
knows where these ring structures are
you know it has an
address for where the you know tx ring
is you know it has an address for where
the
rx ring is and you know the hardware
card
you know looks at those addresses to
actually see which packets need to be
sent
and so here we might have a queue of you
know packets that need to be transmitted
or a few packets that needs to be
received
and uh you know the e1000 you know
uh dmas you know if for example like you
know there's
it's gonna work on uh like the first
factor two cents you know it will dma
basically you know those
packets you know the data associated
with the packets
you know straight from ram to the
network
without actually having the processor
involved at all so this is what i call
dma direct memory access
okay does this make sense
in terms of a more abstract picture uh
for the
organization of the risk 5
ram and the e1000 any questions about
this
so one thing in the talking about sort
of this hardware hardware and hardware
software concurrency
clearly you know the e1000 and
you know the processor are both
manipulating these
transmission and reception cues or
uh rings and so there has to be some
protocol
sort of given taken give and take
protocol where
you know at some point particular parts
of the ring are
operated through are owned or operated
by the
net network card and that are parts that
are maybe under control of the software
or the os or the kernel
and you know we'll see in a second how
that is arranged but you know we got a
little bit careful and again that the
car
doesn't triple over uh or trip over
the operating system or the other way
around
a quick question so is there um a
separate
like transmit ring and and receiver in
the ram
and then in uh also in the e100
or e1000 uh driver yeah well the one
weight thing okay so there's two things
going on and we'll look at the code in a
second
uh the the the transmission ring
and the receiver ring basically live in
ram and both
the e1000 and the risc-5 manipulate
you know the ring that actually stored
in ram
um and those those are the the rings
that you saw in the hardware
documentation
it happens to be the case that xv6 also
has a you know the driver maintains a
a sort of a ring of m buffs separately
of the transmit ring and the rx
range so like there's something like tx
in boss
and that's you know that is a data
structure that only the operating system
really knows about you know
the the network card doesn't really know
about it network card only knows about
uh the the tx ring and rx rim
because those are the values that were
programmed into the registers
saying like here's where you can find
here's the address where you can find
the transmitter
the receiver okay
yeah that makes sense that makes sense
yeah
okay so that's sort of the hardware
picture in a more schematic
version uh actually let's talk a little
bit about the software structure
and it's a bit confusing actually in
this uh in in this lab
so software structure
um so you know let's just
draw you know the thing that we most
care about of course is here now the
driver
so here's our driver uh
the e1000 driver
and you know it basically has only two
functions it has the
transmit function
and it has the receive function
and the receive function runs in
response to interrupts
so an interrupt happens
then you know xv6 you know we'll use the
with the usual
interrupt mechanism you know a trap will
happen the trap will look you know to
see if there's an interrupt from the
network card if there's an interrupt in
the network card it will call the
receive function
and as you remember you know we used to
you know in one of the previous lectures
about device drivers
you know it's often helpful to think of
the device drivers are split in two
parts
you know the the bottom half which runs
in the context of an interrupt handler
the typical name for you used in the top
half
which generally runs in the context of
uh
a you know kernel process or like a
usual of a process so for example if
you're thinking about
you know things that sit on top of here
uh there's a
the network stack you know the code that
actually implements you know ip
uh udp et cetera sits sort of above this
and then you know there's you know our
usual
you know sort of line of you know kernel
space blow user space what
up and this is a very os view of the
world
where like use space is not particularly
that big or important
and uh you know example our t whatever
net test
you can use a lot of program correct
that runs user space
and it makes system calls the system
goals go to the
uh the network stack uh and example
i give you the calls to write
system call with a file descriptor the
kernel knows
you know for that file descriptor if you
do it right then you know the right
should go to the network stack
the network stack builds up the packets
and then it calls transmit
and then transmit you know whatever
manipulates the uh
transmission queue the tx cue or ring
and you know that actually gets packets
you know off the network you know at
some point their response might come
with that
come back you know that will generate an
interrupt and then the receive function
will run and inspect you know the
uh receive ring right
so there's a couple things that you know
you want to
i want to point out you know in terms of
concurrency uh
so first of all like you know the
interrupt handler basically can run
at any instant in time right uh you know
we might be in user space and if the
interrupt comes in
you know the interrupt mechanism will
cost you know the
current the user program to switch to
the kernel mode you know the trap
functionality uh code that we've seen
before runs and
it will all receive so we might be in
the middle of some usual
process and boom you know we get an
interrupt and suddenly we're in the
receive function and even in the kernel
like if we're
not holding locks you know watch turn
the interrupts off but if we were not
holding locks you know we could get an
interrupt
and the kernel may change the program
counter basically to the
interrupt handler and run the receive
function
so this code sort of runs you know the
things that in the bottom half you know
can basically
run instantly almost any time
and the code that in the top half it
really operates on behalf
of usual level processes or kernel
threads that actually make
calls into the uh the top half and
you know easily it could have been the
case correctly in fact this is the case
even in that test you know we might
actually have
um net text actually a forks you know a
whole bunch of processes
so we have actually many instances in
one of the tests we have many many
instances of net tests running
and they all jump into you know the
network stack and they all
you know then called transmit right so
that is the case so we're looking at
this from the perspective concurrency
uh multiple zenders uh can be actually
in the context that can be in the top
half
and so it's pretty clear that you know
we need some locking scheme
or discipline to at least you know make
sure that the
different senders don't uh trip over
each other
okay then on the bottom half there's
only one
interrupt handler correct if there's
never the case that receive is going to
be called by
multiple there are multiple receives
running at the same time
in parallel in different course you know
the interrupt handler uh
when an interrupt happens uh the process
is alerted
um and if future interrupts happen
they're actually
blocked until the current interrupt
actually is dealt with
and so in fact uh
the when the receive function runs uh
there's actually only one
interruption running uh at the time that
calls receive
and so there's no real immediately
concurrency
uh in receive itself although uh of
course the
the transmit you know threats can run in
currently with the interrupt handler for
example we might have one core running
in the interrupt handler
and we may have another core again it
actually is about to transmit
is this any questions about this
it's sort of important to have
to understand it's a bit of review but
you know that's important too
okay so i guess i have a general
question
how do we know what is supposed to be
classified as a bottom
half and a top half ah so yeah uh i
think the way to think about it is that
anything that runs in the context of an
interrupt handler that's the bottom half
and in this case it's basically just
receive
and anything that runs in the context of
a regular process
or fret or kernel fret you know that's
the top half
okay um so if you look at this picture
uh
a little bit more since we're you know
actually let me make a
high level statement here a lot of
people ask you know
why no lock and receive and
uh where is a lock needed and
so the first glance uh
it might not be necessary that lock is
necessary correct because there's only
one
instance of receive running so there's
not multiple instances of procedure
running at the same time
and so these receives since there's only
one receive you know it doesn't share
data structures with any other receive
because there's only
one of them right now of course it could
be the case that the receive and the
transmitter
share data structures but as we see in a
second that actually is not the case
basically the mission part of the driver
is completely separate from the
reception part of the driver or the
receiving packets and so as a result
this machine doesn't really
doesn't need actual blocks you know it's
really not sharing data data structures
with any other concurrent activity
the weird part is that you know some of
you if i found out if you do use a lock
uh you actually get a panic and so let
me
say a little bit about that because the
reason
you know that panic happens is a little
bit because there's a this
the software structure actually in the
e1 in the xv6 kernel slightly
uh uh slightly more complicated
than you might think and and the reason
is that basically the
receive uh interrupt hand election does
quite a bit of work
or can do quite a bit of work so let me
talk a little bit about it
and the particular case that actually
where does quite a bit of work is for
example arp
requests
okay so arp is one of those packet types
that uh robert talked about a little
while ago
uh but basically what happens like like
an interrupt comes in
so an arp request you know for
the discover but the ethernet address is
where uh an
ip address you know comes in you know uh
that will call
you know e1000 receive
and you know we'll call whatever net rx
so that will go
call into the network stack on the
previous
picture so that receive calls calls into
this code over here
um that receive you know calls oops
receive calls uh net
rx arf
and it uh and you know it looks you can
see how there's an art packet
and basically it sends back you know the
ethernet address runner for this
particular
uh for uh for for xc6
and and the way he does that of course
you know to send the packet
it will call you know e1000
transmit
right and you know we know that we'll
actually need to acquire a lock
all of you did that you know whatever
there's the e1000
lock
and the reason that actually has to
acquire your lock is because there might
be multiple
senders and you know the sender should
not trip over uh
over and trip over each other um
so that's sort of the picture so what we
basically in terms of this previous
picture what we're seeing here is that
the bottom half
may end up you know calling code in the
top half
and then come back into the driver
through the top half
and a number of you know you run into
trouble with that because
you know the uh you know it's not 100
clear that you didn't need
uh locks in the receiving thing uh
part and so quite a number you ran into
this particular bug where
you know you actually acquired
the you know e1000 lock
in receive and that worked all fine
correctly except that once in a while
you got to panic
and why do you get the panic hopefully
with this picture that's pretty clear
but
i mean isn't it going to be the same
lock that e1000 transmit is going to try
to acquire
down the stock yeah exactly correct so
the the e1500 here at this point now
owns the walk
holds it calls netrx calls net rxr email
files to transmit then it calls the car
again
and as you might remember from previous
laps if require
uh is called and is already held uh
that's a deadlock
right and so you know the xv6 girdle
panics
got a question let's let's assume we had
a slightly different implementation of
locks such as those spendings are not
occurring
like they would let's assume like if i
wanted to acquire a lot that i already
held nothing happened
yeah so uh these are these were called
recursive logs
or re-entering locks is another wave
name for them
and so if you have the recursive locks
or re-entrant blocks then you know you
could just
freely do this and it would be no
problem and
i think one of you over email uh
mentioned to me that actually
they implemented recursive logs to
exactly deal with this particular
problem
and so they did they required the locks
in the uh e1000 received function
uh and uh you know after the panic
basically fixed you know acquiring lease
in
xv6 direction support uh recursive locks
and i'll review solution uh the simple
solution is a fine solution
uh the solution that we intended and the
the staff solution has is that basically
it just doesn't require locks in
retrieve
at all because it's actually turned out
not to be necessary
sorry can you say again why there could
be two
threads in receive
there's only one thread they receive the
interrupt handler runs
there's only one receive function ever
running at the time on any core
that actually calls into the top half
of the you know the top half of the
operating system
and that goes back out into the bottom
half
sorry not in the bottom that calls back
into e transmit and transmit
definitely needs to acquire a lock so
you want to receive e1500 receive
uh while holding the lock calls e1000
transmit
which tries to acquire the same lock
that the interrupt handler already
holds if you have if you're locked in
the receive handler i see
so so it is the case and
like one interrupt can go off and then
while it's still running another
interrupt could go off as well
no no no no no no no the the bigger
question maybe they'll go back to this
picture
so interrupt happens that calls the
receive function
there's only one receive function
running that receive function calls
you know rx net receive that calls rx
network c
arc and then that arp function calls
transmit
and if you were using the same lock in
transmit and receive
you know you would get a deadlock
okay i see thank you
and that's sort of okay and so basically
there's two solutions to this
you know one is to use recursive blocks
other solution was no locks in
receive or you know
have two locks
all three of them are totally reasonable
solutions
any questions about this would there be
a reason to have a lock
around uh receive at all no in this
particular case there's no
reason to have walk at all
what would be okay could we think of a
situation where you would want
a receive lock would it be like if you
had two network cards
or something yeah or uh
you'd like if you remember in the uart
code
uh okay so the the main
a common reason why you might want to
have a locking shared is because the
bottom half and the top half share data
structures
so for example the receive and the
transmit might uh manipulate the same
shared data structures
at that point you need a key you need a
lock and so for example you remember
from the console driver
they shared a queue and so the receive
handler needed to get a cue and needed
to get the lock to actually get access
to that view
does that answer your question
yeah thanks and so this brings me up
with a second sort of point that i
wanted to make
uh that the uh let me actually draw a
new picture because it gets a little bit
crowded
um so we think about the bottom half
again in the top half
so here's the bottom there's a little
bit abstract but you know this may be
helpful
um in much typically in much softer
uh driver shopper the bottom half
basically doesn't really
call in to the top half at all
so for example if you go back and you
look at the console code
this sequence of the sequence cannot
happen there and
the reason doesn't happen is because the
bottom half typically there's very
little work
you know the only thing it does maybe is
you know grab the packet and stick the
packet on the queue
and then at some point later you know
the the
top half you know there's a separate
thread that they're in the top half that
basically looks at that queue and then
grabs packets out of the queue and then
keeps on doing whatever needs to be done
now for
simplicity uh in this for simplicity and
you know to reduce the amount of code
that's not the structure that this
particular driver follows you know this
driver once in a while may actually call
up in you know
and call up actually sometimes this
structure is followed by the driver but
you know once a while it can actually go
into the top half
and come back out into the bottom half
any questions about this
okay so that's sort of i guess software
concurrency
uh and we'll come back to it more later
if we look at the code in a little bit
more detail
uh we'll talk a little bit about the
rings
and so basically you know the way to
think about it you know there's a
ring uh there's two rings you know one
for receiving and one for sending
the tx rx both live in
uh ram and you know they're manipulated
uh by you know code running on the uh
risk five course
and by you know the network card itself
and so there has to be some protocol
between the network card and uh
the risk five course uh about you know
who gets to look at what
and so the way and this is a very common
organization in hardware devices
uh the way that typically is done you
know there are sort of like let's look
at the transmit queue
there's basically a queue of some fixed
size structures descriptors
as we'll look at in a second these are
the descriptors
and the organization or the coordination
that is actually
uh that's happening between the
the driver and the network card is in
consumer
producer
coordination and uh basically you know
one way to think about it you know there
is a
uh if this is the transmit queue you
know there's maybe there's a head
pointer
there's a tail pointer
and you know this the tail pointer is
controlled by the software
and so the software looks at the tail
pointer and if it wants to sit in
a minute and send another packet you
know it sticks it you know in
uh the ring at the location of t plus
one and then moves up you know the tail
point in that direction
and the head pointer is basically
controlled by the hardware
so tail by software head by
hardware and then basically the you know
the hardware basically looks at the head
and then this is the first packet that
is going to be sent
you know and there's a little bit of
information in the descriptor or enough
information in the descriptor
for the network card to look at it and
say like ah this is the bytes that i
need to
move on to the uh move on to the cable
and once it is done you know it moves
the head pointer in that direction you
know once it consumed
you know one of the packets out of the
transmission tube
and one way to think about it is that
all the
descriptors between here
you know between the tail and so all the
things that are actually
being filled in so like the tails moved
up maybe to here
you know all the packets that are all
the descriptor entries that are actually
filled in
the way you think about them is they're
sort of owned by the hardware they're
owned by the network card
the network card is allowed to read them
you know do things with them uh but the
software in the software is not allowed
to you know do anything
with that curriculum if given the
software would be scribbling
over these descriptors uh
while they really sort of owned by the
hardware desk by their network card
that would change the data that the
network card sees
and so that'd be pretty undesirable uh
and so the protocol basically is that
like once you know the software moves
the tail point or one up
then you know that point you know what
it just moved into the network queue in
the transmission queue
is now owned by the hardware and it will
stick in you know
it will be uh owned by the hardware
until you know it has been sent
and basically until the head pointer
moves past you know to that particular
structure
does that make sense
good and for the transmission basically
it's the same story you know there's a
you know there's a head pointer you know
you know that's basically
that's controlled by the hardware and
there's a tail pointer
that is controlled by sort of is the
software pointer
and the basically the packets in between
are the packets that actually uh uh
are have been received you know by the
hardware
and um uh
and you know by inspecting the tail
pointer and the software can see if
there's actually a new packet you know
that is ready to be
uh consumed and if it's ready to be
consumed the heart will indicate that
by setting that dd bit in the status
field and so when the
dd bit is set you know the hardened
software sheets are good you know this
packet you know the hardware is done
with it
and so it can take it out and move the
tail pointer one up
and so there's sort of this give and
take between
the driver and our hardware to actually
coordinate
that they don't trip over each other
any question about the
rings
um is this like is this like a universal
way to kind of uh implement like hues or
any kind of communication between two
things that have shared memory
yeah there's a pretty uh certainly also
in the software you see this but
many hardware devices play this sort of
trick
where uh there's a sort of producer
consumer style
coordination between the heart rate and
soccer
so yeah it's a very common structure
maybe one or two questions uh that we
can ask about it
like why is there actually even a queue
now why is there a ring
okay the reason there's a ring correct
because the queue wraps
queue wraps around to make it fix size
but
you know why why not uh you know have a
cure one entry
one entry
almost like the uart if you remember the
uart uh
driver and controller there's basically
only one register
you know to send the byte and there's
another registered receiver byte
and so why have you know why go for this
complicated
scheme if you could have yourself a
single register and then you could
basically say you know
hardware this register is now ready send
it and then you just wait until
the it's done
to allow for when there are bursts of
packets yeah yeah exactly
you know the network interface or the
network uh card or cable is pretty high
performance in fact it's very high
performance correct on gigabits
per second and so uh
it can be hard for the core or the
processor to actually keep up with it so
you would like to give it a whole bunch
of packets you know the networks or the
network cards can
chunk along and all send them out at
high speed and similarly you know in
reception you might get a burst of
packets coming in
and you want to place them in the queue
and then you know the operating system
can start them processing the queue
right and so this is a common
this is the reason that these cues are
common
to handle bursts
what happens if the cues fall like on
reception
i think the the document mentioned that
it does some form of a
drop tale scheme yeah
the the the the yeah basically the packs
get dropped
so any future incoming packets if the
queue is full the the packets
uh there's no room anymore in the wrong
the network card can't do anything with
that correctly and so the only
option it actually has is to basically
delete the packet
or not add it to the ring and therefore
disappears
and so one reason of packet loss
sometimes is that
an operating system is overloaded you
know with packet can't keep up
and the ring fills and then you know the
packets get dropped
now higher level software of course may
like a tcp connection might
retransmit those packets but this is one
reason why packets can get dropped
so even if the hardware sort of works
all perfectly fine
you know because of this burstiness you
know it can't happen that pacco section
might get dropped
so you had a really really big burst
um the head and um tail pointers they're
all software abstractions right
of the queue ah okay so these are
actually turns out that those are uh
these control registers right so there's
a controller register for the
hardware head pointer as a control
register for the
basically you know detail pointer
there's no really distinction between
hardware software
basically the driver knows about the
tail pointer and it knows about the
hardware knows about the tail pointer
and the head pointer and these are basic
controller registers
right okay yeah and we'll see in the
code in seconds how that shows up
make sure if you go back to our uh maybe
let's see if we have this picture still
here you know here's the that
earlier picture that we looked at and
you know here's
controller register that holds the head
and here the control register and holds
the tail
and of course there's one for both
reception and one for
sending
okay
let's go back here okay so
let's talk a little bit about the
descriptors and so the
descriptors are defined by the hardware
and so the hardware says like here's how
a descriptor should look like and your
driver
you know these are the bits you can fill
in and if you fill in that bit
that tells me the following all right
and so here's the
uh two um descriptors that are important
you know here's the uh
receive descriptor rx and here's the tx
one of the tx descriptors so let's look
a little bit
uh yeah let's look a little bit
um probably the most important part is
this
address and that is the address that the
software filled in to say
like where they should where the car to
dump you know the packet you know where
in ram
should the driver
or where should the network card put the
data that it receives
into ram so it's the address or the
reception buffer if you will
um
and then you know probably the most
important part in
is the status field as you've seen
so when the driver basically still
continues to look sort of at the tail
and sees if there's a new packet has
been received
and the way it tells whether there's a
new package received is is that the dd
bit
correct is set uh by the hardware
uh and you know the shaded areas are
the fields of the packet descriptor of
the the
uh receive descriptor that actually the
hardware fills in
and the white you know the non-shaded
ones are the fields that are actually
shaded in
are filled in by the software again here
we see this clear distinction about
some things are owned by software some
things are owned by
uh by the hardware
okay and this there's a similar you know
descriptor very similar descriptor that
looks uh
that's the hardwood scripter for the
transmission it has
an address and that address of course is
the address
where the data is in memory that needs
to be sent
and then it has a bunch of you know it
has a command field
and here's how the software tells the
driver tells the network card
this is what you should do with this
particular packet or you know this is
what you should know about this
particular packet
and so one thing yeah we i think we fill
in two pack
two things we call the aeop that says
you know the
end of packet and that basically tells
the driver this is the last descriptor
of a particular packet and now it can
you know send off
you know whatever data that's in these
descriptors
um and i think we set the
uh response in a requested
uh command bit uh or rs i think it is
uh basically tells the network card when
you're done
transmitting this thing you know set the
said a bit that it actually has been
transmitted we'll see in a second how
that
how that shows up any questions
so one one thing to keep in mind you
know with these structures these are
defined by the hardware right like so
the hardware the software has no control
over their structure
you know they're just literally defined
by the hardware or by the network card
okay let's look at a little bit of code
uh
and see uh what the solution looks like
and we'll look at a couple of
issues that we haven't looked at yet you
know the mbofs of the issues of
doing transmission and the issues during
receiving
and this should be presumably all well
familiar with to you given the fact that
you
just finished the lab
okay so here just to go go to the top
uh here's the transmit ring uh
and that's basically the ring of
descriptors you know that we
drew off in the last you know couple
slides
there's a separate you know we talked
briefly about this there's a separate
uh basically ring of emboss but that in
that ring is completely
you know a software or driver only
abstraction
uh the hardware uh this is defined by
the this structure or the
is defined by the hardware right then if
you look at
oops
uh you look at the definitions quick
here's the struct you know tx desk
and that corresponds you know to the c
version of exactly the structure that
actually was defined by the hardware you
know the 64-bit
address you know the length field the
cso byte the command byte the status
byte the ccs byte and then you know to
a word for special and there's a similar
ring that you know is literally defined
by the hardware
or similar descriptor and receive
descriptors as defined by hardware and
those we just have c
decorations corresponding to these
hardware structures
all right let's look at transmit
uh so mirrors that's the sort of staff
solution for transmit
uh you know acquires a lock and the
reason we as we said before that it
needed lock is because multiple
functions or multiple threads kernel
threats might call
transmits at the same time and then
it looks at the tail you know to see if
there's any uh
if there's room to actually send a new
uh packet because you know the
network hardware got behind and all the
descriptors actually are being
in use and so the way it checks uh
where actually the descriptor is in uh
in use is by
uh checking whether the dd bit uh
is not set
uh and if it is set then
if it's not set then it returns uh
immediately not sending the packet at
all and in the other case
gonna actually keeps on going and
actually will send the end buff
so if there's still an m buff in this
position in the txm nbox that means
uh this is an m buffer a while back you
know we free that m buff because we're
going to actually stick in a new m buff
into this descriptor and we just need to
remember which you know mbot we stuck in
that descriptor
and so the way we do that is by keeping
that in the txm buffs
and then we fill in the descriptor and
so the first thing we're filling is the
head and we fill in
we put in the address the start
of the first header in the end buff
then put the length set the status to
zero
put the command field in place by
sending both the rs
and the eop bit as well i discussed the
second
and um and then basically
we synchronize to make actually sure
that there's no reordering of
you know that all these instructions are
performed
before the next instruction and what the
next instruction does it actually
updates the tail pointer
and so the adapter updates the tail
pointer and the steel pointer correct is
a control register in the network card
and so basically when we update the tail
pointer
the network card knows ah something
changed
and it's going to read you know the data
at that
uh descriptor um and it's going to
basically read that these fields where
we just filled in
so we're going to make absolutely sure
that all these
you know writes all these stores are
materialized in memory
before the network card actually reads
them and so this is why the sync
synchronizes there
and then we release about a lock and
that's basically all we have to do you
know transmitter packet
can you explain the sync synchronize
again like
what yeah i'm having to do this
it's mostly a memory ordering
technicality correct like compilers are
free to reorder instructions
uh the uh the rights might actually sit
in the
l1 cache or the l12 cache and
basically the synchronize is sort of a
memory fence uh that you know tells the
hardware and the compiler
please don't move any instructions
across this barrier and make sure that
all the data that you know
all the stores before this barrier are
actually actually
materialized in ram and the reason that
it's important
is because the you know go back to our
picture for a little while ago
all the way back here
actually both you know the risk five
cores that render the driver code you
know basically put values
here in round correct but you know those
values are reversing the l1 cache and
the l2 cache
and the memory flash nothing sure is
that they actually show up in the ram
this is important because as soon as we
update the tail pointer the e1000 is
going to look in ram for these two
descriptors
and we've got to make sure that all the
you know fields are indeed set
otherwise it would read state of values
does that make sense no thank you
um so why do mbos exist
why have this sort of separate structure
of you know why have these two
sort of corresponding structures
so i guess part of it is it's all
nice and well if the driver needs to
talk to
the hardware about where things are but
at the end of the day we do need to
store the packet to hand off to the
network stack somehow
yeah exactly you know so one way to
think about it is that the you know the
m buffers are completely an os
extraction
nothing to do with really the network
card at all and it's there because like
you know
if um at some point you know the
maybe receive a packet you know we hand
it off to the network stack and the
network stack now
sticks on some queue so that when later
a user process calls read you internet
actually can read it and in the meantime
we need to have some structure that sort
of holds that data
that we actually received and that's
exactly what those inbox structures are
sorry can you talk about the
like how how do you use the linked list
structure in your code because i was
trying to
to understand it and to track it down
and
it seems like there is some push
tail or push head but i don't ever
call it in my code oh it might be
it might be in the net dot c file
well the network c file is a file that
we gave you to you okay
and where you're thinking um
if you look for something like
um pull pull pop i think pop
um
yeah so this is this is the only place
where
it looks like it does things with the
linked list
structure of m buff
and if you don't ever call this function
or
the push tail you basically just treat
the m buff
as an array of
like however many characters
so so why is mbuff there
because here
when you receive a udp packet so the udp
packet comes in from the network card
it goes into the network stack then the
udp packet
the m-buff for that udp that holds that
uh udv packet
is actually stuck in the queue right
here
on the socket for the receiver
and so this is the reason that you can
have cues with m buffs
and the reason it's stuck in the queue
they are correct is because you know who
knows you know the user process that's
going to read
you know from this particular socket you
know might be doing something else
and at some point later you know it's
going to call the read system call and
then the read system call is going to
remove
you know that the inbox from that socket
and so the point of each socket can have
a list
of end buffs for reset for reception
i see thank you
okay let's go back to the driver so
another
transmit
so then receive is you know almost
similar
not that much different uh you know
basically
you read the tail pointer from the
network card
you see if there actually is a packet
and
if there's a packet then the dd field
would be set if the dd field is not set
then we know there's no packet and so
we're done
if it is set then we're going to read it
and read the length you know and when we
and then we call and netrx you know do
the up call into the higher level stack
and when we're done you know we're
basically free up you know that entry uh
so that the driver can use it to
actually receive more packets in it
and the real crucial operation there is
correct and we bump up basically the
tail you know to tell the driver
okay you know we're done with it you can
use it again you know it's yours again
that slot
and so maybe the most interesting
question is and the number of
question you have you asked us you know
why is the wild there
why is this in a loop don't you get an
interrupt and then you know you grab the
one pack and then you'll be done or like
a number of people that actually
forgot the while loop first you know
notice that basically at some point you
don't receive
packets anymore during net tests
is it because you would like to transmit
as many packets that are ready as
possible with only one interrupt so that
you can um
kind of amortize the cost of the
interrupt
yeah this is this is absolutely part of
it you know you get through the
let's first talk about you know what the
the root cause you have is right
right the uh if the number you know the
burst of packets comes in
and the network card will generate you
know the interrupt
but more packets are coming in and so it
will just you know put them in the
three descriptors right that it actually
can use uh i can't generate more
interrupts because it's already
generated in the rut
and at some point you know the uh you
know whatever the processor you know
maybe
like we were the core was just in a
section of code that turned off
interrupts because it was doing
something atomic
so at the end of it you know there's a
releasing from lock that actually turns
interrupts or not
at that point in time then basically the
uh receive
handler is the interrupt handler is
going to run right but between that
period when like that first packet comes
in and before the receive handler runs
there's a whole bunch of other packets
might have come
it could have come could have come in
uh and so if we don't run in the while
loop we'll leave those packets
uh we'll we'll grab the first one and
we'll grab the other
and the later ones are just stick there
in the queue right they're just sitting
there in that ring
now if a subsequent interrupt would come
in we'll grab the next one
uh but like the tests you know what they
do they
run their udb packets you know so they
send off a whole bunch
like one of the tests since like 10 uh
ping requests in parallel
you know the 10 responses come in
parallel back you know correct
uh the first one receives generates an
interrupt
the other nine go into the queue uh
the higher level software you know
reached the first one
uh and then you know returns just like
it's done and at that point
nothing happens anymore because the
receiver is waiting for more receive
packets
they happen to be there they're sitting
in the ring uh except you know you know
the receive didn't do them in a while
loop and so it didn't pick them up
does that make sense
so for example if the test programs
would have sent one
request waited for response one request
waited for response
then you would never notice that you
need to do the while loop
uh it is because like there's a burst of
responses might come back
and that only generate together one
interrupt
any questions about that how about this
i have a question
uh so for example if instead of a
while one uh we would have a for loop
that just goes through the whole cue
that would also
be wrong for the same reason um
no as long as we skip all the ones that
have the dd not set
okay should we should only well we
should only look at packets that
actually
uh we should only look at the tail
pointer
but you know in principle you could just
scan the whole cue and i guess we'll
look at the dd packets
and let it see if the dd bit is set and
that might work i don't know i
haven't tried that okay but isn't the
device able to put more m buffs in the
receive
um after we read stale
yes yeah yeah yeah
okay and we have to
it's very dangerous like this proposal
of like sort of looking around and you
know seeing
the db be the set because you know you
know really what we should do we should
not look at
uh buffers that really are controlled by
the driver or by the hardware
and only look at buffers that are
actually available to us to the software
and which is indicated by the dd bit and
basically by looking at the tail pointer
because basically anything owned between
the tail and the head is owned by the
hardware
going back to the um mbuff like the
reason we need the mbuff
why do we need uh the other information
in the buffer
like the uh care array um
i think it's called the backing store
i think it's in net.h
so we need we need the buff field
correct because that actually contains
the data
i thought the head contained a pointer
to the data yeah yeah yeah okay but the
buff actually is the actual you know
allocate space you know to hold packets
correct
and then head you know points into buff
to basically the start of the packet
okay okay and this is the m-buffs this
is uh
okay so a little bit more context here
mbox is a structure that you see in a
lot of network stacks so you look in the
linux kernel and you'll see a structure
similar like this and it's typically
called mbuffs
and so we have to um we could have
simplified this structure quite a bit if
we wanted to
uh and maybe in subsequent years we
should uh but this is sort of the
standard way
in which packets are represented in
operating system kernels
okay any further questions about this
um so i have a choice now
uh there's a couple more things that i
could say about the network driver
but then i won't have any time to talk
about nmap uh i could also talk a little
bit about map
and then and stop here uh in terms of
talking to network driver
any preferences
no preferences
let me talk a little bit about map
because there was a question that came
up a couple times
and that might be worth addressing
uh uh it's almost more a question about
you know why map exists than
uh you know actually how to implement it
uh so there's no real objections which
it sounds different
let me talk a little bit more about map
so this is your last chance to ask any
questions about the network driver
until the end of class
okay um let's
talk about inbox map
[Music]
uh
okay
okay so the the question really relates
to sort of the file system api
and so yeah the file system has a
reasonable broad
api you have supporting directories
symbolic links
hard links etc etc but presumably the
main the main part of it is the
the file api correct and the file api
you know is hopefully well familiar to
you by now
and you can open a file
with you know some permissions and once
you have opened the file
you know you can read you know from the
file
yeah into a buffer create some data
um and you can write you know to the
file
you know whatever file script or above
you know laying
so let's say we uh and then we can close
you know the file script now let's say
we want to write an application
and you can think about the you know
maybe
as the file as uh you know the file's
normally in
an array of bytes uh but like maybe this
application has you know sort of
it's an array of trucks that are stored
in it and so
uh and let's say the application wants
to update this truck so you know we have
to file
correct here's our file and sort of
divide it in
you know structs you know whatever zero
to you know here's the file length
and you know we uh maybe like in the
middle
you know let's have a structure maybe 16
bytes or something and you know we want
to like update one of these
but maybe we want to update the first
one
and so in the way we could do that
correctly if we read and we open the
file
we read you know the first you know
whatever 16 bytes
that correspond to this you know we you
know let's say
update you know the first you know field
or struct
in the third byte of that struct you
know to be one
and then we call right to basically
write it back
and then we close the file so if this
when is the write happens where does it
actually write
so we have set the this memory above to
one we're going to will this
first byte change to one
if we call right
so remember the file script has an
offshore associated with it correct
and you know reads read pushes that
offset you know forward
in this case if we're at red 16 bytes no
the offset goes from
0 to 16. and so where does wright write
as you notice there's no offset argument
in the right
system call so where does it write
len you know we'll write len bytes and
which offset
in the file presumably at land exactly
at 16 right
yes it will right here so which so this
byte will change
to one correct
not the actual thing that we were
actually trying to modify
does that make sense so the way you
would written this application it turns
out there's one
system call that we didn't really talk
much about at all but every operating
system unit operating system has a call
to call
a system call called lseq
and l6 allows you basically to change
the offset
to some position and so in this
particular case we wanted to
have the effect that we're going to
write this struct and not that one
then we would have set like you know lc
you know zero you know basically
resetting the offset to actually
uh the zero and so then this right we're
actually so here now offset is zero
and then this right actually you know
would write actually at the first
16 bytes does that make sense
so this is slightly inconvenient
correctly if you think about this you
know like you look at this interface you
know there's actually quite a bit of
stuff going on
you know you gotta open you gotta read
it you know you're gonna seek it and
then
going to write it and so one reason that
map is popular
is you can sort of avoid uh you know
these complications because if you would
write this
using map you know we do fd is open
and we open the file as before
and then uh you know we just call map
it's going to be like whatever our
struct let's say our structure's h
uh you know blah blah blah you know
whatever
some link for the file uh
you know read
write permissions uh
you know map shared
and then file descriptor comma zero
and then uh so now so basically with
this dot correct we're in mapping you
know the file f
at the location h you know in memory uh
now we can just like say h you know
whatever first byte
is zero or one as we did before and then
you know at some point you know we can
unmap
you know the unmapped uh
h right and so if we think about this
okay so we look in memory
we're looking at this from the
perspective of the file you know what
this does correct because literally did
is basically got a pointer
you know to this h and you can just
update here you know that thing to one
and be done with it right and so if we
sort of
need to manipulate you know file
structure you know data structures that
sit inside of a file
uh this map interface is much more
convenient
than you know this previous interface
where you know we have to read
you know we manipulated the memory you
know we you know seek back
and then we actually write the
information uh and in this particular
case you know we really can think about
the file as being an array of bytes you
know that we can
write willy-nilly without actually
having to navigate or jump around
do people see what the advantage of the
nmap interface is
any questions about this
do any big storage systems uh use uh
this like i don't know like databases do
they use this a lot
or not really they use this a lot yeah
i think a lot of applications will use
map because for
these kinds of things like a database
it's much more convenient
than this this interface this interface
is great correct if you need to read
from standard input
and there's a stream of bytes coming in
you just read you read you read and then
you produce some output on some other
uh stream that interface
that interface is very suitable for here
you don't have to update offset you know
you read you can
offset immediately update you read again
you read a little bit further et cetera
et cetera
so it's really good for sort of the
stream-oriented uh inputs
uh well this is really good you know if
the file has for the data structure
uh and you just want to sort of
update bits and pieces of the file and
you know
arbitrary locations
okay um
let's see um so i'm going to start i'm
i'm
about to run out of time um so let me
stop here hopefully this one one sort of
tidbit about mmap
you know as uh useful to uh to know uh
and uh tells you why you know that sort
of
is a popular scheme
uh let's see uh so i i think for that
actually you know we were
basically we come to the the end of this
lecture and i guess the end of
uh
the end of success 6s081
and so again you know if you have not
filled out the
uh feedback survey you know uh please uh
do so you know we really appreciate if
you fill out the subject evaluation
and again i want to thank you for
you know your attention again it is a
strange semester uh
i wish i could have met you all in
person and
talk to you in person either class or
before class or after class
uh and unfortunately that
hasn't happened uh but i hope you you
got quite a bit of out of uh son one and
uh certainly with the staff thank you
for the engagement
you guys have been wonderful this
semester so with that
thank you and if you have any questions
please hang on hang around
but i'm sure some of you have deadlines
i want to say on behalf of the
tas as well we've really enjoyed um all
the time we spent with you guys in
office hours and doing check-offs and
this is the first semester where we've
done check-offs and i think david and i
both
found it a really enjoyable process and
you know hopefully we were able to
help you guys out and have some good
conversations as well so
thanks for making it a great semester
and adjusting on the fly with us with
all of the uh
remote learning problems we've you know
run into and had to deal with it's been
an absolute pleasure to eating this
course
any further questions or you know again
feel free to hang around
oh um i had a question
so it's it's oh yeah thank you so much
for the class i
really like the class it's the best
class this semester um
i wanted to ask about the interrupts
the receive interrupts how does the how
does the hardware knows
when when the software has finished
handling the previous interrupt to not
issue another one
because there's multiple steps
one is you know if you're looking
uh
you want thousands at the bottom we
re-enable interrupts or we tell the card
you know we're ready to receive for the
interrupts
so that's how we think that will tell
the car to generate interrupts
of course at this point interrupts
actually not really turned on and we
just tells the card you can generate
interrupts again
uh the interrupts get turned on correct
like you know by
you know these functions you know
interrupt enable
and at that point if you turn on the
internet or able if this interrupt if
this
this field was set plus you know at the
point where you turn on interrupt enable
and actually interrupt
might happen again right i forgot about
this register thank you so much
yeah it's like one instruction
easy to miss
any other questions
all right thank you all thank you okay
thank you thank you
thank you so much