all right
good morning or good afternoon everyone
um
let's get started can can people hear me
yep thank you all right today
what i'd like to do is um give you a
chance to ask
questions about xv6 and about the recent
labs
and in order to kind of give us
something to talk about
i'm going to do as much as i can of the
copy on write fork lab here just to give
us
sort of something to chew on and you
should feel free to ask any questions
you like
you can ask about why my solution is
different from your solution or
why xv6 works the way it does or why
the bugs we encounter um
show up in the way they do so
just to remind you although i'm sure
this is
sure i don't need to remind you you know
the point of copy and write fork is to
avoid
copying costs for pages and a fork that
are never modified
i put in a few lines of code to measure
the reduction
in the number of bytes that mem copy had
to copy
during user tests for my copy and write
solution and found that
it actually reduced the amount of
copying by 90 percent
and this is for user tests which is kind
of a weird program but nevertheless
and i think a lot of it is reductions in
copying of the instruction pages because
the instruction pages for
are never modified so there's never any
point in having copies of them
and i think that's where a lot of the
win was from copy and write fork also
reduces ram use
the sort of maximum amount of ram you
ever need to use and it reduces the
amount of time you spend in fork
and so fork returns more quickly you
know on the other hand of course the
total cost may be larger because if
programs end up modifying all the copy
and write pages
you end up having to do all the copies
plus take all the page faults
which can be a little bit expensive but
nevertheless
people have found that in general it's a
net benefit i mean as you know the main
challenges
are one challenge is how to avoid
freeing memory and now we're sharing
pages among processes
we have to not de-allocate them have to
not free them until the last
process is finished using them so we
need more book keeping
and the other interesting challenge is
that there's
in copy out in particular the xv6
modifies user memory without actually
going to the mmu paging hardware
and so we have to mimic some page faults
there
i'm going to go through the lab starting
at the beginning the copy and write lab
before i start i just want to uh just
sort of mention the strategy that
i think of myself as following when i do
labs and i do a lot of labs you know
from one year to an x i don't remember
the details of how to do the labs
and in addition the labs change all
right so
um when i'm doing the labs i always take
small steps i make find
you know some sort of next subset of the
problem to solve
maybe five or ten lines of code i
program that up
and i run it and try to get it to
working before i go on to the next
proceeding to the next step and this is
you know as opposed to for example
thinking through and writing a complete
solution
before starting to test and debug it i
always
test and debug a little bit at a time a
lot of the reason for that is that
um even though you may um you may have
sort of thought through a lot of the
things a lot of the challenges and a lot
of the design
for what you're going to have to do to
solve a lab i find at least there's
often
surprises and so if i
implement everything first i may find
then that i wasted a lot of time because
i didn't fully understand the problem
until i actually got into debugging it
and the way i choose the next step at
each point is usually driven by
whatever panic or crash or test failure
i see next sort of
tells me what to what i need to fix next
and while i'm doing this lab i'll i'll
make a few mistakes that i actually made
the last time i did the lab
so that we can do have a little practice
debugging together
and again feel free to break in at any
time and
ask questions about anything
i'm starting here with a fresh copy of
the copy and write lab
source the same as all of you did so
i'll just fire this up
and
run the copy and write test and you know
maybe i'll get lucky and all the tests
will pass and i won't have to do
anything
ah too bad one of the tests failed okay
so not too surprising
um and
you know a good step at this point is to
go have a look at the tests
and figure out what it's trying to do
and the sad truth is some of the tests
are
complicated and hard to understand and
don't necessarily test anything
specific they just sort of try different
things to see if something will break
but luckily with this simple test um
it's pretty clear what it's doing um
yeah yeah do you mean to share your
screen you cannot see anything
oh gosh i'm i'm sorry about that
thank you thank you for letting me know
all right is that better yes
good uh brilliant all right okay
well that's bug number one um
okay so um i'll just uh
here i am in my copy and write test i
ran
copy and write test and it fails
i look at the test this simple test on
the screen at right is
what actually failed and this test
luckily enough it actually tells us what
it's doing and allocates
what it knows to be more than half the
available memory
in xv6 and then forks
and so of course the reason this fails
is that fork
makes a copy then ordinary xv6
actually literally makes a copy and so
if we have to copy more than half of
memory there's just not enough space for
that
okay so of course this is this is what
copy and write's all about
um and we know that the basic game is
that instead of copying
the process's memory we want to just
copy its page table
and not the memory so the child has just
has a
carbon copy of the parent's page table
instead of memory
referring to all the same physical pages
the place where
fork does its copying is in vm.c in
uvm copy
and so we can just modify this code
um to instead of allocating a page of
memory
uh here and copying onto it
we're gonna eliminate those three lines
and instead
just copy page table entries so
i'm actually just going to hack this
copy of
map pages since we didn't actually
allocate memory here i'm going to get
rid of this free
i'm going to fix this mac pages to
instead of
mapping mem at
address i i'm going to map the pa
which is the physical address we pulled
out of the parents page table
so is that clear so this will just have
the effect of
mapping all of the parents pages into
the child's address space
isn't pa already a un-64
uh probably or is it
is it bad if you were to cast it if it's
already that type the cast does
absolutely nothing other than shut the
compiler up
since it's already since addresses are
64 bits and uh 64 is 64 bit
that cast doesn't change the bits it
just
makes the type checker less upset
but let's see i actually don't know what
any of these types are
all right one thing is we don't need
this mem variable
oh well okay so you're right about pa
gosh i wonder if we're done now let's
run the cow test and see what happens
definitely not done okay so
what we got here is this user trap
with s cos of two anybody remember what
s cause two is
i'll just tell you construction failure
it's an illegal instruction so
why would we get getting an illegal
instruction now
is this what we expected
did we overwrite uh the like
portion where we have instructions
yes something is damaging the
instructions of the
user program
of course the fault we're not surprised
we get a fault here
but we were hoping for right for stored
faults
to drive the copying process and copy on
write
we're not getting the store fault
um any other
hypotheses for this this is not really
fair because like
this is my bug not your bug but
nevertheless
does it have to do with the flags yes
it does
okay so i'll just leave that to the side
it'll actually come up again
another question is we're hoping for
store page faults
which will drive the copying process
why didn't we get a stored page fault
all right why would we get a store page
fault
under what circumstances does the risk 5
generate
a store page fault
we would get it if the right flag is not
set but
now we can just write to everything
normally yeah i've left the right flag
set all right so that's bug one which
i did actually make last time i did this
lab so
i've left the right flag set in the
parent and i've done i haven't done
anything to the right flags
this flags variable here is um
it's just the way we pulled it out of
the parent's page table it's all its
pages are writable and so that means
that it's going to be right up on the
child too we won't get store page faults
so i'll just be
sharing a page read write which is not
what we wanted
so how am i going to turn off the how am
i going to write protect
these pages
any proposals which i type
how about you can do flags
um and equals um
the the wave sign
underscore w
yeah yeah so we gotta get it we need the
tilde there i call that wave sign at
tilde
we need to the waves the it's clear we
need to clear this bit in the flags but
we want to leave all the other flags set
okay so that's gonna will this clear the
flag and the parent of the child
child just the child so how do i clear
do i also need to clear the flag and the
parent
yes because uh like we want the child to
be independent for the parents so if we
write something we don't want like the
child to also
get the modification from the parents
that's absolutely right we need to write
protect the page and the parent as well
because we don't want the child to see
the parents
modifications we're trying to mimic them
having completely separate copies
so what can i do to clear the flag in
the
parents page table
you can do something like star pte and
equals
not pte right yeah so i have the parents
paid a pointer the parents page table
entry right here in pte
um and so i can clear the pte flag here
too so that's pretty convenient
um and my belief is that's enough to
make
both copies of the page or both mappings
of the page
uh read-only so hopefully now we'll
start getting um
right faults is it all possible to
do to clear the ptew bit before you say
flags equals pte flags
of pg and that way like the original
flag is just
the correct thing oh i see put a way up
here
yeah oh yeah i know i'll give that a
shot
well seems to work yeah that makes sense
okay so now i get my right fault um
which is what we're hoping for and
hopefully what this right fold means is
that one of the other processes tried to
modify the page and
the risk 5 generated a page fault from
that and
we're going to want to react to that by
uh making a copy of the page and mapping
it read write
um before we do that just to make sure
that
what we're seeing you know this this
it's this f here
this s cause that is sort of making me
imagine that we're
seeing what we want to see namely a
storeflow let's actually go and look and
see where that happened we know what's
in process id3
uh process id 1 is init process id 2 is
the
shell and so maybe process id3 is going
to be cow
test we can look in
we can look in cowtest.asm
and look for 9da
and see if it makes sense as a
instruction that could generate a store
page fault
boy this doesn't look so good
um i can't even remember what a uipc
does but i don't believe it
performs a store any guesses what's
going on
it'd be nice if the page falls we're
seeing actually made sense
um i'll tell you uh it turns out this
page fault occurred in the shell
after the shell fork but before it exec
cow test and so we're really looking at
a wrong asm file
it turns out the right asm file is the
shell asm file so
we'll look for 9da there
oh yes and in the shell 9da is a store
instruction
and it's at the beginning of this parse
command function that actually
parses the cow test command that we
typed and figures out
what to do with it mainly call exec and
it's doing a store under the stack
it's the preamble that stores the
these saved registers um
and not surprisingly that this should be
the first page fault we get because
it's on the stack you know the very
first thing most functions do after fork
returns is they modify their variables
in the stack and boom
unsurprisingly that causes a store page
fault so
any questions about why we're faulting
i have a quick question how did you
figure out it was in the shell rather
than in cow test
because i looked at 90a and cow test
and that is not a store instruction i
thought
gosh what could possibly be going on
now look at processing three so is pin
three to shell or is that
pit three is pid two is the shell that
printed that prompt
pid three is the next process that's
created
and so initially the shell
to make pid 3 but after the fork it's
still
running the shell right it's a child of
the shell running
a copy of the shell it's going to call
exec
to run cow test but it hasn't done it
yet
it hasn't been able to get that far
without taking a store page fault
when it writes a stack
so can you clarify does that mean that
there's like an error
with the shell relate to process id 2
because it doesn't
have the proper data in order for the
child to have the right data or is it an
error with process id
3 it's a page fault
that occurs in process id 3.
right but the bug that we're seeing
right here like there's no bug
this is you know i'm implementing copy
on right fork
and what we just did in vm.c
was right protect every single page in
the parent and the child
right that's what this line is doing so
the next time either the parent or the
child does a store
from user code it's going to be a store
into a right protected page
because every page is right protected
and so it will cause a page fault
oh so this is the proper page fault that
we want this is right and i was just
all i was doing is checking that
that what's going on is exactly what we
think is going on
as opposed to some other bug gosh it
makes sense
okay all right so we took a page fault
here in this store which is presumably
the first store the shell does after the
fork
okay so now we have to handle these uh
now you want to do something useful
in this page faults so first the page
fault
handlers and the cr and trap.c
in user fault
um i think it
pretty much doesn't matter where we
insert code to uh
i mean that there's all these different
cases here that
uservec is userback right yeah oh user
trap the user trap is dealing with
we're just going to throw in another
else
we only interested in right faults we're
happy to read these shared pages because
all the data's there it's just rights we
want to catch so
now it turns out as you as i'm sure you
know that
we're going to need to use the code i'm
about to write from two different places
so i'm going to just wrap it up in uh
the code that sort of makes the copy of
this page
in a function i'm going to call cow
fault
it needs to know the current page table
and it needs to know the virtual address
that we faulted on
that's st val sometimes it can fail
because say it runs out of memory um
maybe chao
chao equal fails so we need to prepare
for return value and
pretty much no matter what the failure
is uh
we're going to kill this process all
right
and if we didn't kill it we'll have cow
fault return minus one if there's a
failure
return zero if there's no failure if
there's no failure then
we're going to rely on cow fault having
made this virtual address writable
so that when user trap returns the
process can actually continue
successfully
um so that you put
or like is there a reason why you put
this line above
the else if which dev deventer um
i don't think so uh whether it's correct
uh depends on what deventer does we'll
just take a look the the risk is that
deventer might um
see a device interrupt for some reason
even though we are in a page fault
so we could just got to check that
deventer
looks at s cause and if
s causes f it's gonna return zero
so we just want to make sure that if
uh yeah if devent or return 0 then
it's going to go on to our code so
that's fine
okay okay now we need to write
actually there's one thing i want to
observe here and that's that
if there's a failure we kill the process
so
this is unfortunate it would be
fantastic if instead
you know most of the time processes
allocate memory or whatever by calling
system calls the system calls can return
some error value negative one or
something if there's a failure
and the process can then do something
appropriate
if it knows how in order to deal with
that failure here though because there's
no system call
there's not any obvious way to tell the
process that
something went wrong which is
irritating you can imagine solutions to
this for example
in some more sophisticated operating
system we could have
something like the alarm user
fault handler that you implemented that
we could call up into to say look you
know
we can't continue your process because
we can't fix this page fault
but we want to tell you something went
wrong
but we're not going to do that now it's
much simpler to just kill the process
okay so we have to implement page this
cow fault program
takes a
uh a page table the current process page
that was argument and the virtual
address
that the fault occurred on
okay so the first question we always
have to worry about when dealing with
virtual addresses that the user program
produced like this one
is what if it's a completely crazy
address
like way up above the top of the process
or what if it's an address like
in the um trap frame or in the
trampoline page or in the
page the stack guard page um
so can anybody sort of outline a
strategy for uh
defending ourselves against the user
process intentionally faulting
on crazy addresses
isn't there like a max virtual address
yes yes there is and that will actually
come up
um but the uh
top of the user address space is below
um max va
and the um
like the stack guard page which we
shouldn't be allowing right you
certainly shouldn't be treating as a
copy and right thing
all right i will uh um
i'll show a solution here we're just
going to call walk for now
and one thing that can go wrong is walk
doesn't find a page table entry
so for most illegal pages that a
process might refer to there's no pte
and there's only a few exceptions to
that so if we
detect the illegal if we tucked the
detect then
pde not found return value from walk and
return minus one
we've handled almost every case the only
cases i'm aware of
where walk would return a page table
entry but we
don't want to allow rights to it are for
the
trampoline trap frame and stack guard
pages
and those all have pteu clear
so the way i'm going to detect crazy
addresses illegal addresses is by
checking that ptu
is set and also
just for chuckles look at ptev
and if either of those is clear then we
know this is like
um not an okay address
and we'll just return minus one now
which will kill the process
so i believe you've taken care of all
the uh
illegal addresses the user process could
use
try to use all right how can we
find out we want to do a copy now we
want to make the this process a
copy of the page how do we find the page
to copy from i have a question here
please um wouldn't the strategy
of using the pteu to judge if the
page is if there
if it's a legit page for copy and write
wouldn't the strategy
not be very good for the long term
process maybe you add some other
part to the address space which is which
is supposed to be
a writable which are only supposed to be
readable
but that doesn't get taken care of here
as in you'll have to come back here
again
you're absolutely right if we were to
add
any other interesting paging feature
you know like maybe lazy page allocation
for example
we'd have to revisit these decisions and
come up with some other strategy for
deciding
is this a copy and write page is this a
lazy
allocation page is this a paged out to
disk page
is this a memory map file um
and and we need more sophisticated you
know with the
in the end i think most serious
operating systems actually keep their
own
data structure nothing to do with
you know not a page table but sort of
mimicking a page table that describes
the process's address space and
sort of describes what each page means
and what its state is
and we'd have to consult that table
but for this lab since we don't have
those other features and we're not sure
what they would be
i'm just going to do something
straightforward and indeed we would have
to come back and fix it
if we made xv6 more sophisticated
um wouldn't that panic if va is
more than max va because of the walk
um gosh media would
now we'll look at that yeah maybe if the
process
uh yeah i think you're right well that's
too bad
okay so we're certainly uh you're right
all right well i was i was wrong about
this
wait can you just return a negative one
if you just check the maps va
i think the observation is that if if
the user tries to
intentionally program tries to write a
very large address
of course you know i can't expect to
survive that
um but what we would do here
is call walk with a very large address
and i'm looking at here the
implementation of walk
in and it's going to panic
i think we can just use the same
approach as walk address does i have
this same bug
you can just return minus one like other
people were saying if va is
greater than max va before walk
what i'm upset about is that the tests
don't seem to test this
because i didn't put this in my solution
okay um
okay okay so um
how do we find out we need to we want to
copy the page
how do i get a pointer to the page to
the
pointer to something i can copy
the pta 2pa yeah so
it's just in the pde um
and where am i going to copy to
what should i copy to
a nearly allocated page yeah so i just
call
k lock of course chao lock is
likely to fail so um i gotta catch that
uh we're actually gonna see this
so i'm gonna put in a print statement so
we know
okay
i actually made this error and i wanted
to reproduce it so that we would have to
track it down but you're too clever for
me
all right i want to copy 2
pa2 from p1
okay so how can i what do i need to do
in order to map this page
this new page pa2 into the
address space
what should i type there's like two
broad ways there's either
unmapping and then mapping with the
built-ins that exist
or you could manipulate the bits
yeah be well i am way too lazy to figure
out
how to use m on map and map so i'm going
to
just cook up a new page table entry
right here
um i have a question so actually i ran
into
this issue in almost every lab in which
i somehow needed to remap things
and uh because it
occurred so often i implemented
a map that which could remap basically
um and i was wondering is that a bad
design choice is it like dangerous
that's totally reasonable you know the
functions on xv6
are are you know specialized
to xv6 as it exists
um and so they
you know they make assumptions about how
the other code works they have panics in
them that are
intended to catch other code using them
in unexpected ways but
if you change the way xv6 works and you
need to do different things then
it's totally reasonable to modify you
know oh you need to
be able to remap this without a panic
well old xv6 never needs to do that
but your code does so you should feel
free to modify
anything you need to
okay so okay so the deal is
here we had a write protected page that
was probably shared with another process
what do we have to do to that other
process at this point
um
what do we need to do to the other
process
we can just not do anything and then
when it page folds we allocate a new
page
and remove the original one
that's absolutely right so you could
imagine doing something but it would be
quite complex to do it correctly
and so we just do nothing and if the
other
process never writes this page well it's
not a problem if it does write a page
then
it'll go through all this it'll make a
copy and
it'll proceed safely as well so doing
nothing is
totally reasonable um okay so now we're
going to return the return
value zero says there was no error and
hopefully the um
process will but we should
should free the physical page right or
are we not there yet
um we can do it or not um
[Music]
um i guess if we're going steps we
shouldn't yeah
so if i did this what would happen
well we would definitely crash right all
right so let's not do this
or i don't know if we would crash but
um we would then be if we if we freed a
page
it would be presumably pa1 because
people don't have free pa 2.
because we're using ph2 if we free pa1
that means the other
process has got a problem it is now
mapped into its address space and
presumably using
you know executing instructions in or i
don't know what a page that we just
freed and might be reusing for some
other purpose and
writing something else over so i'm
reluctant to free it
although it's
oh yeah so sadly among many other things
xv6 walk is never called from outside of
vm.c
in ordinary xv6 but now we're doing it
all right where were we
okay remember the very first page what
we got was an s cause 2.
why are we getting s cos 2 page faults
that's an illegal instruction
like this is the next problem we have to
solve this problem now what's gone wrong
or what are what are some plausible
guesses for what might have gone wrong
so the sequence we when i type cow test
what we think happens is that the shell
forks it's copy and right fork
we have the child running
the shell's instructions um
probably taking store faults but for
handling those store faults correctly
and then the child execs the child copy
of the shell execs cow test
what bad thing might that do to the
parent shell
well when you call exec the
implementation of exec
uh frees up all the processes current
pages
and then allocates new pages to load
the file into that you're executing
what's going to happen in the child the
child shell that calls exact when it
frees all of its pages
what's that going to do to the parent
shell it's going to end up
accidentally oh sorry is it going to
accidentally free the
um shells um page 2
page pages yes we're going to free every
single one of the shelves pages
except the one or two that the that were
written
so this includes the shells instruction
pages
and then we're going to reallocate them
they're going to be instantly
reallocated by exec to hold other stuff
loaded from the file that we're running
cow test so it's going to totally change
everything in the shell underfoot
and unsurprisingly it's going to
instantly crash
so we have to not free those pages
somehow um
does everyone see that a good question
um what does the scpc here point to
which assembly file would you find that
instruction
well
you said it's shale right it's people
well last
time was for some other fault somewhere
else it was shell
what it is here i actually don't know i
never
uh i did not unfortunately take the time
to track this down
um um so one problem with any answer
even if i could give you an answer
so so the the answer is either the shell
or cow test
for process id3 that again is the
it's probably cow test i have to say i
don't completely know what's going on
here
looking at the asm files unlikely to be
helpful
because the whole problem that we
believe has happened is that
the page holding the instructions was
freed and reused
and so they were therefore not executing
the instructions in the asm file anymore
or executing some garbage that makes
sense yeah
um so we could look at the address 2004
but it it wouldn't really tell us what
had happened
we might we probably could find this out
using the debugger
we could uh break in gdb and then look
at the instructions it's
actually at whatever virtual address a
thousand four
points to a quick follow-up question
um about that fall uh so
my understanding is that we're getting
like an invalid instruction fault
because
um like we're changing the instruction
pages
instruction physical memory underfoot
and like the memories just being written
to something else
um is it possible that
like in some lucky case that they are
being rewritten
but when we look at it again it's being
being rewritten to valid instruction
pages so we actually just start
executing like random instructions and
we don't actually get an invalid
instruction fault we get some other
fault
yes absolutely
yeah yeah i mean really we're now like
anything could happen
um i would not have been able to guess
if i had not done this lab
i wouldn't be able to guess what would
go wrong at this point
and indeed i think i have seen other
strange things
happen at this point because maybe the
data maybe the first
page that has garbage in it actually has
data in it and a
shell trips over some complete garbage
data like a stack
instead of instructions
okay so we don't want to free the page
right away we you know we only want to
free the page when it's really not being
used anymore
so can anybody uh propose
a sort of criterion for when
we should or shouldn't free the pa for
each page of memory
we could keep track of like how many
times
or like basically whenever in k alec
whenever you
you should increment and decrement some
type of variable
and keep an array of like all the
different addresses
yes yeah exactly so one way to think
about this is that we want to only free
a page
when there's zero page tables that refer
to it
but there could be many if if a program
forks and that forks again and then
forks again boy
we can now have like three or four
different processes that all refer
due to copy and write fork to this one
page
um so that this you know this count of
how many times how many page tables
refer to a page and go up
due to fork and they can go back down
when a process
exits or calls exec um you know it's
clears all these references out of its
page table entry or if a process
actually
does a write and causes a right fault
that's also a situation in which
we have one fewer reference from a one
fewer page tables referring to a page
so we want to keep a count and we want
to count be counting
the number of page table entries that
refer to a page
so we're going to need to think about
how to maintain this count and when to
increment it
exactly where on the code to increment
it and decrement it
okay so the there's as
you may be aware there's multiple ways
to
maintain this count the way i do it
is i make an array um
called ref count it's just gonna have a
for every page
account um we need to know how many
entries are in ref count
in xc6 it's so simple um
that it just has it just uses a fixed
amount of memory
physical memory right we only need to
keep a count per page of physical memory
um we know that from inspecting
k in it that xv6 uses only fizz top
amount of physical memory we only need
to keep a count per page
not per byte so we're going to divide
fizz top by 4096
and that's how many array elements we
need
in a more serious operating system where
we don't know how much memory is
available
until we inspect the hardware we might
have to we would have to allocate this
array
dynamically any questions about where to
put the counts
all right actually yes i'm wondering is
there a reason that you're using 4096
specifically and not the
page size macro uh yeah the reason is
that i can remember 4096
and i don't remember the name of the
page size macro but i'm happy to use it
if you like
um it actually if
if xv6 was intended to be portable and
to be able to run on
all kinds of different machines with
different page sizes we'd have to be
much more careful about this but
there's 500 ways in which xv6 is totally
not portable um
so
i don't worry about it state size is
determined in hardware
and i guess where
and the hardware that risk five
manual says how big a pages
yeah because the um it's the mmu
that takes a virtual address and uses it
to index into the page table
oh right right because the address
translation happens in hardware so the
hardware has to know how big the
pages are okay it's it's configurable
but
you know there's a couple of different
strategies you can tell the hardware to
use but
we tell it to use 4096 byte pages
okay sorry quick question uh so where
are
i guess this is a c question so in where
are like global
um variables like ref count stored
like what like already associated with
specific
process or this is the kernel
um what's going on is that the
file the executable file
um that the compiler and the
loader or linker produces
has it just sort of just
indicates how much date how the total
size of all the global variables in the
program
and so we don't see the code for this
but when
qmu loads the kernel
well what's really going on is that when
you compile
the program called the linker figures
out based on uh
looks at all the global variables and
their sizes and assigns an address in
memory
you know to each global variable
and that's where it lives in memory
[Music]
i mean um
and
we just arranged that the you know so
the xv6
kernel uses you know i don't know 10 000
bytes of
various global variables and wherever
the
boot process loads it into memory say at
address a million
it just
uses those addresses
for the global variables i see is this
is this similar to how like there's only
one
copy of like the instructions for a
program on disk and there's only like
one copy of
the kind of global variables for that
program on those
well
um a program has this well
not really sure how to answer this i
mean
the uh when you declare a global
variable like index
when you compile the compiler and the
linker just decide
based on who knows what or it's
configurable but they decide
the address for that variable they they
decide all right boy x is going to go at
address 1000.
and then the code that reads a write x
you know if we have code that says
you know ref count of zero equals one
you know what that compiled into was
just setting the memory
at address a thousand or wherever we
linker decided to put ref count
we just does a store to set the memory
to address a thousand one
um yeah
it's it's not it's actually almost
exactly the same that happens when you
run an ordinary user program
you know the linker and the compiler
decide where memory global variables are
and
they just read and write there and
and it just works i'm sorry that's not
much of an explanation
all right so we just define this global
array of counts one
per physical page and
we need to modify these counts in
various places certainly when we first
allocate a page
we're going to say that it has one
reference because we return the rest of
the page to whoever the call whoever
called k
lock and at the moment only that
program has a reference to this page so
i'm just going to
set the ref count for this page
to be 1. so first of all i'm just going
to calculate the page number which is
the
address of the page divided by 4096
that's the page number
and then i'm going to set the reference
count
for the page we just allocated to one
any questions about this code
um just because i know that i'm going to
have bugs with reference counting
i'm actually going to do a little bit of
a sanity check here and
um just the you know the reference count
really should be zero if the pages we
just allocated a page that was free
boy it better have a reference count of
zero
all right any questions about this code
all right so in general we want to
increment the reference count when
we add when copy and write fork
adds a page table entry that points to
an existing page
and we want to actually we want to
decrement
the reference count as it turns out in
many places
for example when a process exits we need
to decrement the reference count of all
its pages
when you call exec and that
frees all the current memory because
it's going to replace it we want to
decrement all those reference accounts
when a
copy and write page fault happens and we
make a copy
we want to decrement a reference count
on the old page it turns out these are
all the same places
that currently free a page because the
current xv6
thinks there's only ever one reference
to each page
so in most of the places we care about
where we want to decrement there's
currently
called the k free so what i'm going to
do is
modify k free to be have somewhat
different semantics and to
have kfree be
sort of a function that decrements the
reference count and
frees the page only if the reference
account has dropped to zero
i mean that will just automatically fix
all the places that call kfree
all right so um we need to actually do
the check
um before we fill the page with junk
um so this makes the cafe a little bit
more complicated because
even though there's a critical section
with locks and k3 already
we can't use it because it happens after
the point at which we filled the page
with garbage
so we need to lock
because we could be freeing the same
page at the same time from multiple
different cores
again i'm going to find the
page number by dividing the
physical address by 4096
i want to panic again just a sanity
check
gosh you know if we're freeing a page it
better have more than zero ref counts
um we need to return if the
page has more than one ref reference
count to it
well actually let's
decrement the reference count we want to
return after we release locks and so we
have to remember a variable we're going
to
remember whether the page has more
references and then release locks and
then return
so i'm going to make a temporary
variable which has the
um
and release
then say if uh there's still references
this page let's just return and not free
it
and only if the reference count dropped
to zero do we free it
any questions can you explain again why
you have to acquire the k-member
during this process why you have to
acquire it at all uh yeah uh when you're
doing the page number calculations and
it's this line
um really is this line and the next line
that are the problem the issue is that
on this page we now is
likely has more than one reference to it
and so if two processes with a reference
to the same
with a page table entry pointed at the
same page if they both exit at the same
time on different cores
they're both going to call k free for
the same page at the same time
yeah could could you just create a new
lock
for the reference count variable and use
that as well
yes
yes yeah basically everybody you know
all code that manipulates these counts
needs to use the same lock but
i don't think it matters what lock it is
okay so this takes care of decrement
most of the decrements we care about
every time a page is free we're really
going to you know
only free it if the reference count is
fallen to zero we also need to
increment the reference count where do
we need to increment the reference count
well because i know we're going to need
to do it and write the function that
anybody can call um
um again i want to panic if something is
weird so if the address is wacky
i certainly don't want to
go beyond the end of the array
or we if we don't want to increment the
reference count of a page whose
reference counts currently zero
that's also an error
i'm just putting these in there because
i know from experience with my code
that this is exactly the kind of place
i'm going to have a bug in
all right where should i call incorrect
from
you have view vm copy when you yeah
yeah yeah i think uvm's copy is the only
place that uh
makes another reference to a page
all right gosh what am i going to put
this well it almost doesn't really
matter
um all right we're making another
reference to pa
so we want to say ink ref pa
and we're likely to run into trouble
from the compiler if we don't put a
definition for it in
traps.h whatever
okay
all right let's see
well that was pretty quick um
all right what's k free ref up kfree is
unhappy
um okay well
here's the time we don't know it's very
early in the boot process which is maybe
a hinted
as to what's going wrong if anybody has
any
guesses i'd be happy to hear them
meanwhile i'll just fire up the debugger
to try to get back trees
it is during knit because you're trying
to put
things into the linked list and you
haven't allocated yet
so you um in when you're
trying to load everything into the link
list
you haven't called klog before that
yeah that's exactly right so
let's just see that in action here okay
i got the panic i type where
and it's in uh there's kfree being
called and panicked and it's been called
from free range right at the beginning
when we're initializing
uh the free list indeed uh so there's
something to be fixed in
free range um the problem is i'm calling
key for k
free as as you said i'm calling k free
but of course all the reference counts
are zero and k
free panic so the reference count is
zero uh so i'll just
um i'll just
uh hack this to be
how about that
oh okay we managed to boot now um
but i wonder if we're done let's see
okay so let's let's run the cow test
again
ah at least we passed this simple test
so we passed
the simple tests which is great um
and we passed one time through the three
tests
but we didn't we didn't make it through
the second time to the
three test and the three tests
triggered uh the print statement that i
added to drop
trap which said cow chaolak failed
which only would print it if we're out
of memory
so we're out of memory um
why are we out of memory
so we've updated reference counts every
time we've
allocated but we haven't
decremented counts whenever we've tried
to free right
so where should i add a uh
well with your current approach i think
uh
pa1 that reference count needs to get
decremented so we would need to k
free it yeah exactly so the i think
somebody actually possibly you brought
this up
um 45 minutes ago
let's see let's free pa1
not pa2 okay and so now what
k free means now is don't is not free
this page
it's what k free means is decrement the
ref count on this page
and free it if it's zero and so if we're
in a simple situation where there was
just one fork
and so there were two references to the
page um
and we've taken a right fault and made a
copy where now all k free
is going to do is decrement the account
to be one and now the other process
could use the page we're not actually
going to free it
okay so hopefully now
we'll uh
not run out of memory in countest
i love it okay we made it through the
three tests
without running out of memory
all right but we're not done
sadly we have this interesting error
[Music]
in the file test let's take a look at
the file
test
all right so here's the file test and it
says right on the comment for the test
that it's
investigating copy out so good hint of
where our problem is going to be the
thing that actually
failed is i mean you have to use your
imagination a little bit but
the error message seems to be this one
printed from two different processes
at the same time
and indeed this is a loop this test is a
loop um
that for four iterations just forks and
so it's going to produce
four concurrent processes those error
messages
will be interleaved um so we need to
know why that read failed if we want to
understand what the bug is
um we need to know why the read failed
so the first step is maybe to figure out
what the read actually returned all we
know
is that it
returns something other than size of i
but i don't know what it returns so i'm
going to capture the
return value
and i'm going to print the return value
so at least now
oh i have a question sorry um it seems
like
three of the threads failed but
one of them didn't and it's like it's
running why is it not failing
why did the third fret not fail the
fourth
why did the four like if you if you do
cow test and then echo
that other one is still going to be
running and you're going to see
more output
yeah three field and one didn't um
uh let's just finish investigating why
any of them failed
and then i can make a guess although i
don't really know why
one of them didn't fail okay so
what's happening here is that read is
returning minus one
so why is read returning minus -1
you might hypothesize that you know we
were passing this buffer into read
you might imagine that the you know read
and read is needs to do something namely
called copy out to copy file data into
this
into this buff buffer that we passed to
read and maybe something's going wrong
with that and its relationship to copy
and write fork
so let's take a look at read
and see why it's failing try to track
down
why we just um all right so let's
capture the what read all cis read does
this this
calls it calls file read after fetching
a bunch of arguments
um so we'll fix this
to uh take us one step closer to
understanding why things are going wrong
and we're expecting cc to be
minus one
that's interesting we never saw cc minus
equals minus one in fact the failure
occurred
uh if failure starts occurring here
before we get
any corresponding cc print
print statements and it's not minus one
at all it's four which is a non-failure
value
um so what that means is that something
before the call to file read
must have caused must have triggered
this return
so one of these functions here has
caused read to return minus one
please feel free to guess while i'm
typing
was a complete surprise to me by the way
when i
tracked it down oh i think the file is
character
yeah the file descriptor i saw what i
expected was that file read was failing
due to something in copy out not doing
the right thing with copy on right
pages but that is not at all where the
failure is
okay so if we want to find out like it's
either arghfd or argent or arg adder
that's failing
let's start with argh d i'm just going
to stick print statements in here to
help me
figure out which one of these failure
cases is actually triggering triggering
it's only two places it returns minus
one
and this one there's something wrong
with the fd itself
all right so we're going to get these
print statements on cases where r give d
returns minus one
what does this mean fd
all right so the that we expect these fd
printouts to
to occur just before the error so what
we saw is fd9
it was fd9 this causes the error
so fd9 failed one of these three tests
well we know it's not less than
zero i happen to know it's not greater
than equal to
no file for number of open files and so
that means that the o
file array for nine
files nine must have been zero that is
in this process
there is no file descriptor 9.
so somehow copy on write
test um this code
and the copy on write test is passing an
invalid file descriptor to read
so this file descriptor is in it comes
from fds
fds comes from a call to pipe
how could i usually pipe if it doesn't
fail it leaves the file descriptor in
the array so how could this go wrong
oh we all know the answer has to be blah
blah blah
copy out
so what's the missing piece
i mean i i guess like one thing that
helped me
track this down is i realized at least
first of all
um fd should not be nine in every
iteration
nine is kind of the value that you would
expect um
kind of at on the last iteration that's
kind of like the highest call
to pipe yeah yeah they all got a nine
you're right
so something they're kind of touching
each other's memory
strange yeah that's exactly right so
you know the fds pipe the way pipe
returns the file descriptors is that it
calls
copy out to copy the file descriptor
number that is allocated into the
caller's address space well
we're using copy and write fork here so
if we're not careful
so at least initially all the there's
just one page and it's shared among all
the processes
so the first process that calls pipe
if something goes wrong the pipe system
call might conceivably
write the shared page and
that value that file descriptor will
then be seen by all the processes
instead of just the process that
actually allocated the descriptor
so everybody see this as a kind of at
least hypothetical risk
so so let's look at what try to imagine
well so first
let's look at um sysfile
to see uh
how pipe
uh copies out the uh
file descriptors it allocates and indeed
down here are these two calls to uh
copy out to copy the two elements of
that pipe array
so pipe is using copy out to copy the
file descriptor numbers into the array
in user space
so what does copy app do
well it looks up the virtual address to
find a physical address
and then
[Music]
it writes copies over that physical
address and that's it so one thing it is
not doing is checking for write
permission doesn't look at ptew
and so this page or this virtual address
refers to a copy on right
shared page copy out just has no idea it
just
goes ahead and writes it and so i mean
indeed
when pipe calls copy out it's going to
be writing a shared page so that all of
the forked processes see this
modification
not just the process the called pipe
any questions about why this is
happening
okay
all right so as you all know we need to
modify copy out
to since copy out is you know looking up
a virtual address and
translating into a physical address but
it is not using the mmu
so the mmu doesn't catch the right fault
because the mmu's
not involved walk adder looks at the
page table itself instead of
basically getting the mmu to look at the
page table for it
um okay so we need to modify
copy out we don't want to call walk at
or walk out or just produces a physical
address
we actually want the page table entry
because we want to look at the
permission bits
to see if it's a copy and rate a write
protected page
so we're going to call walk instead
[Music]
we need to check all the usual errors
so maybe there's no mapping at all
maybe it's not a valid mapping
or maybe it's a mapping that the user
code is not allowed to use and in all
those cases
it's an error but this time we can
actually return an error which we'll
call just read to return -1 instead of
killing the process
that's nice
next we need to know how to check
whether it's a copy on right page
any any ideas for how we can
uh check whether we should apply copy
whether we should do a copy
at this point
what's different about between copy and
write pages and just sort of ordinary
unshared pages
would the reference count to be large
ah that's a good point if the reference
count was um
greater than one that certainly be a
very strong hint
that's a copy of one right page but if
the reference count is one
does that mean it's not a copy and write
page turns out if you fork and the child
takes a copy on right fault
and makes a copy that reduces the
reference count to one
but the page is still rate protected in
the parent
and actually probably we could get away
with modifying in that case
so i think we actually could check the
reference count and only treat it as a
copy and write page if the reference
account is greater than zero but what
i'm going to do is a different
an even easier shortcut and say
if the page is right protected the only
way a page can be right protected
and have the pteu bit set
in this version of xv6 is if it's a copy
on right page
so this saves me a little bit of typing
compared to checking the reference count
we already wrote the code to deal with
this in trap.c
um so i'm just going to call that code
from here
now we still have to deal with the uh
possible error return if it's a
crazy address oh actually we don't
all right
all right so if the page is not writable
we're just going to call
copy and write fault and copy and right
fold you know does the copy
and it makes the page writable so
i think we're um we're almost done at
this point
um however if copy if cow fault
did make a
and we gotta get rid of this if cow fall
did
make a copy it's gonna have modified the
physical address in the page table entry
so we have to pull that physical address
out of the page table entry again in
case it was changed
i'm just going to do that since we have
the
page table entry right here
and i think this is more or less enough
so any any questions about the
modification to
copy out
all right i got to uh make a global
declaration for cow fault
ah beautiful
all right that's looking great um
anybody happen to know if we're done
we may or may not be we also have to
pass user tests
oh all right let me get rid of this
these print statements
i think the exec out test intentionally
allocates a lot of memory
all right any questions while we uh
wait for the verdict from user tests
aha okay user test was unhappy i think
this is a familiar
piece of damage which somebody has
brought up already it's the
um uh
it's the panic and walk if the user
process the user test actually
i think does intentionally we'll take a
look at user tests
and it's the copy out test
and it even says in the comment it
passes ridiculous pointers to system
calls
all right so what we're faced with is
copy out
we pass in a ridiculous pointer it
simply calls walk with that ridiculous
pointer
and walk panics if you give it a
ridiculous pointer
so as somebody mentioned
we need to not call walk with
ridiculous pointers what is it max va
or something all right
now of course we're totally entitled to
return an error if a user process
passes us how to balance a pointer
all right i'm i'm just hoping it passes
now
i'm not aware of any other problems
okay questions
i guess my question is more broad
like we saw when uh we were doing that
with small steps
we were getting random bugs
at point at our step and if we're doing
the lab
from scratch then wouldn't it be
confusing to get all of those
weird bugs and
how would how do you how do you know
whether it's a bug with something you
wrote or
a bug because you didn't write the rest
of it i'm afraid i cannot answer your
question
um the the sad truth about bugs
particularly bugs caused by doing funny
things to page tables
inside the kernel is that every bug
you know every bug is different and how
you
you know what turns out to be the
winning strategy for tracking a bug down
it just depends totally on the nature of
the bug
um you know my usual uh you know and
i have some i have a sort of a
collection of strategies that
are sometimes helpful and sometimes not
like i'm a huge believer in putting
print statements into the code in order
to gather information
or to verify hypotheses um
i'll often spend time just looking at
the code just for the purpose of
generating
sort of brainstorming with myself to
just try to generate you know
things that could possibly be going
wrong at this point
and then put print statements in her
panics or something to try to
uh rule in or rule out various guesses
at what the problem might be another
possibility is that
you know you've you've made some you
know your code worked or didn't show
this error or something
you know half an hour ago and you made
some changes and now you have some bug
so another possibility is to if you can
you know back up to a version of the
code that didn't have the bug and sort
of add your changes bit by bit
until the bug shows up none of these are
i don't know any strategy that always
works or even works more than a fraction
of the time
but the truth is part of what you're
learning in this class as well as
learning about operating systems
you know you're getting experience
writing and debugging code
sorry not to be more helpful
other questions
all right we're at that
end of class time um
i'm happy to talk more but
we're done with the formal part of this
class
all right and just see you all on
wednesday
oh sorry i actually have another
question when we were
seeing our first um
uh right fault we also saw
after that for the shell illegal
instruction fault
and then something for the unit process
what was that um
um well
um i don't have a theory
the init process sh i don't think would
share pages with anything
i i just don't know i'm sorry we could
uh
um i would have to back up but this
happened very early when i was doing the
lab right
we just had a copy of the page table
nothing else yeah
i think it was a uh like s-cos f
for the shell and i think s-cos c
for the init process
maybe all right all right let me let's
see
if you really let's see let's see
we can
let's reconstruct um
uh the lab from scratch so i'm gonna
clone
ugh
okay at this point we had just made uh
just made changes to uvm copyright
um and so we were
what are we not doing here we're not
allocating and we're not doing a
move
but we are um
uh we're gonna pass pa
to map pages and well i think the very
was the very first time i ran anything i
think this was the state of play
it was after we did the flags also okay
all right so let's clear
and
does that look good
all right we got a c well let's see
c is instruction page fault oh this so
okay so uh s calls to
you know is you know we think uh shared
and process id two ah man
you're right is process id one
i just don't have a theory for why
process id one
might run into trouble let's let's let's
look at what an it does
isn't it
okay it execs the shell
i don't know um
you know okay oh here's an idea process
id2
is taking a fault and it's exited so you
do report later
like right yeah and so that means that
this weight in a nit
has returned yeah right and so it's
going to go back around the loop and
call fork again and so you know after a
for
we're now sharing and you know depending
on all this damage code
um okay i see
okay yeah that's very confusing oh yeah
these errors are just
like complete bananas because we
violated all sorts of
intuitions about how things should work
okay