all right
i'd like to get started um can anyone
hear me
yep loud and clear good all right so
today my plan is for first i want to
spend a few minutes um
re-emphasizing some points from the
lecture last week on thread switching
because
they turned out to be important points
and then i wanted to spend most of the
lecture talking about
something called coordination which is
the larger term for
xv6 sleep and wake-up mechanism and in
particularly
i'm going to talk about the lost wake-up
problem all right
so um one one point i want to just
mention again is that uh
is the fact that xv6 whenever um
anything calls switch to switch from one
thread to another
usually from a kernel thread to the
scheduler thread
it's always preceded by an acquire
of this processes lock
so a process requires this lock called
switch
which always switches into the scheduler
and it's the schedule that releases the
lock
um and in fact almost always the
sequence looks more like this
where the a process it wants to go to
sleep for some reason it's yielding the
cpu or waiting for something
um it acquires a lock on itself it sets
its state
um and there's a number of different
states what we see
we saw last week was set at stake to
runnable
instead of running um and then call
switch
or sked which itself calls switch
um and that you know this switch
basically switches
threads um over into the scheduler
thread
which so as previous call to switch over
in the
scheduler thread returns um
and then the sweat scheduler thread
calls release on um
the lock of the process that's just
yielded the cpu
um the reason for this
just to repeat um is that uh
the acquisition of this lock on the
process prevents
the scheduler on a different core from
from looking right at this point in time
and seeing that oh this thread is
runnable
and trying to run it because every other
core may be running a scheduler loop
which is continually looping over the uh
process table
looking for runnable threads so any one
of them may
see that this thread's runnable if we
hadn't acquired the process lock
so the fact that we acquire the process
lock means that the other schedulers
before they
even look at a process of state must
acquire its lock so we know after
this acquisition no other thread is
going to look at the lock
we can't give up the lock here though we
can't give up the lock
before calling switch that is this
thread acquires a lock but it can't give
it up
because if we did then right after we
gave it up some other
core scheduler would probably start
running this process even though
the thread is currently running on this
core i mean having two
cores run the same thread using the same
stack
is would cause a pretty instant crash
and therefore the process acquires the
lock and doesn't release it on call
switch and a different thread namely the
scheduler thread
actually releases the lock at a point
after this thread
has completely stopped using its own
stack so at this point it's okay
for another course scheduler
to start running this thread because the
thread is now no longer running
and has given up given up the processor
okay so that's an important point and
it'll come up in a few minutes it's one
of the many constraints on the design of
the
sleep wake up coordination scheme
any questions about this holding of the
p arrow lock across switch
yeah if yes when we have multiple
cores the only reason they're able to
have the same
view of the lock is because there's a
single shared physical
memory system right that is correct
so what is there like implementations
where there's
weird file systems that can't guarantee
this atmosphere so we can lock
if you buy two computers then they don't
share memory
right so that's one way to do if you buy
two separate computers
then they won't share memory and we
wouldn't have any of these problems
it's just that the way processor chips
look these days
there's always multiple cores on a
single processor chip and so the
hardware just
is built to have multiple cores sharing
the same memory system
i see thanks yeah
okay so that's one point
another point um which i don't think
i've mentioned yet has to do
with uh the fact that in
xv6 a process is not allowed to hold
any other lock when it calls switch
process is required to hold p arrow lock
when it calls switch
but is forbidden to hold any other lock
so this is another important constraint
on the design of
many things including how sleep is going
to work so
let me lay out the reasoning for this so
it's no other locks
when you call switch
um a scenario sort of illustrating why
this is this rule has to be enforced and
this is a rule that
you know if you're extending you know if
you're a programmer developing the xv6
kernel you have to follow this rule
along with
many other rules so the justification
for this rule
supposing we have process one or you
know the kernel thread for process one
and it requires some lock
not its price of stock but just
something like maybe it's using the disk
or using the ur
to console and acquire some lock
and supposing it did then give up the
cpu by calling switch or yield or sked
or something
while still holding this lock
so now p1 holds a lock this lock's held
but it's not running
and imagine also for a moment that we're
on a machine with just a single core
so there's only one core the process one
called switch
which transfers the scheduler the
scheduler sees a hot process two's
kernel thread is waiting to run
and so the scheduler switches to process
starts running process to two switches
to process two
and supposing process two for whatever
reason maybe it also wants to use the
disk or
use the uart or something and it calls
acquire
on the same lock
so we have a second acquire of this lock
it's the same the same lock
of course the lock's already held so
this acquirer can't get it these are
spin locks
so what this actually causes to happen
is that process two
inside acquire will just sit in a loop
spinning waiting for the lock to be
released
and acquire won't return and since
acquirer doesn't return
process 2 can't doesn't have a chance
even though it may be willing to yield
the cpu when it's done
later on it doesn't get a chance to
because acquire doesn't
return until the lock's released but the
only way the lock could be released
is if process one resumes execution and
presumably later
if it's correctly it doesn't have
terrible bugs in it
it was going to call was intending to
release this lock
right but it hasn't happened yet because
it called switch
and process 2 is spinning waiting for
the lock so this is a deadlock
right and
it will just cause the system to freeze
and while i've described this in the
context of a machine with a single cpu a
single core
you can construct scenarios that using
multiple locks
would cause the same kind of deadlock on
a machine with multiple cores
and so as a result we have a general
prohibition in xv6
that you're not allowed to hold spin
locks
across the switch any questions about
this rule
there's a question in the chat robert oh
uh wouldn't you have a timer interrupt
switch to p1 which resolves the deadlock
okay so um yet it does turn out so we're
running
both all this stuff's running in the
kernel right it's you know acquire
release switch you know it's only it's
all kernel code so we're now running in
user space but indeed
a timer interrupt could occur and um
expisius is actually and allows timer
interrupts
to happen in while running kernel code
uh system call code and in fact if you
look at the
um kernel trap code or whatever it is in
trap.c
you'll see that if the timer interrupt
happens while
xp6 is executing the kernel it will call
yield
so if a timer interrupt could happen
while we're running acquire here
then actually we would be saved because
call yield yield would switch back here
and hopefully p1 would then resume and
eventually release the lock
however for reasons that were
explained in a previous lecture a choir
turns off interrupts
before it starts to wait for the lock
because we absolutely for other reasons
cannot afford
to have an interrupt happen while we're
holding a lock because that would cause
a different kind of deadlock
if the interrupt handler
needed to use needed to acquire the lock
that
this acquirer had possibly um
just acquired so if you look at the code
for acquiring xv6
you'll see the first thing it does is
turn off interrupts and then spins
and you may wonder geez why doesn't it
spin and then turn off interrupts and
the reason is
that would allow a short period of time
to occur in which the lock is held
but interrupts weren't disabled and
again
a device interrupted that time might
cause a deadlock
so unfortunately this other requirement
that we leave interrupts off while we're
spinning waiting for a lock
prevents the timer interrupt from going
off and therefore
prevents process two from yielding back
to process one
it's a good question um
okay so another question can i repeat
how deadlocks are avoided
um
oh deadlocks are avoided in xv6 by
prohibiting this
xv6 code is not allowed to acquire any
lock
other than p arrow lock and then call
switch
and if you look at the code for switch
there's actually some checks and switch
that are equivalent to checking that
no locks are held other than p arrow
lock
so the problem with this is this code if
it occurred in the xv6 kernel would be
illegal
and would could easily cause a deadlock
so it's forbidden
does that answer the question okay
um other questions
okay um okay so keep this rule and the
previous need to hold p arrow lock
across switch in mind
because they'll come up again in our
discussion of how sleep
and wake-up work
all right new topic um
coordination
which really means sleep
the um
uh we've heard a lot about locks and
locks are fantastic
for situations where different threads
really want to not be aware
and not have to worry about or think
about what other threads are up to we
hold locks and share data that means we
just like never have to worry about the
possibility that some other lock is
is or maybe not who knows using that
data because the lock
sort of causes things to happen one at a
time but
when you're writing threaded code there
are also situations where you explicitly
want to wait for some specific event
where you want
different threads to interact
so for example supposing we have pipes
and we got a reader and a writer
right if i'm reading a pipe and there's
nothing currently to read in the pipe
i want to be able to wait for any other
process to write data to the pipes i
want to wait for this sort of
pipe is not empty event
similarly if i'm reading the disk or
writing the disk
if i'm reading the disk then i want to
be able to tell the disk controller look
please read a particular block on the
disk
it may take a long time milliseconds
long long time before the disk
finally finishes the read especially if
it has to seek and rotate
and the process is doing the read needs
to be able to wait for that specific
event
we want to wait for the disk read to
complete
similarly you may have noticed when
you're programming that
a unix program can make the weight
system call
and what weight does is it causes the
calling process to wait until
any of its children exit so here we have
the parent shot
process intentionally waiting for some
event sort of caused by another process
so these are all situations where a
process needs to wait for a
specific event either typically io or
another process
sort of declaring that something
specific has happened
and coordination is the sort of tool
that helps us
solve these kind of problems or
implement these kind of requirements
and coordination is totally fundamental
just just like with locks
coordination is another fundamental tool
for writing threaded programs and it
comes up
all the time all right so
how could we have a process
or a thread wait for this this kind of
event
so one possibility there's an extremely
straightforward one
is just a busy weight to loop
so you could imagine and we'll discard
this is a bad idea in a moment but
let's say we want to read from a pipe we
just write a loop in the pipe read
function
that says you know while
you know the pipe buffer is empty
we're gonna do absolutely nothing
all right and we're going to let's just
sit in this loop going round and round
in this loop
until maybe some other thread on another
core writes into the buffer and makes it
not empty and then this loop will finish
and then we'll you know return the data
or whatever it is we're supposed
to do with the data um
so you can imagine writing code like
this and actually there is a little bit
of
there may be you know small amounts of
code like this like if you
know that the thing you're waiting for
is extremely like
likely to happen and a tenth of a
microsecond let's say
this may be the best way to wait for it
so
typically this is done with some kinds
of device hardware
where you ask the device hardware to do
something you know it will always
complete that task in a tiny amount of
time
just sitting in a short loop can be the
right answer
but if this might take a long time
milliseconds or you just don't know how
long right
maybe it's going to be 10 minutes before
whatever process is writing the pipe
actually writes anything then we don't
want to spin there and waste cpu time
which could be used to you know find
more digits of pi
or something else useful we want to give
up the cpu instead
and only we want some way to give up the
cpu like switch
but actually regain the cpu when the
event we care about
has actually occurred and it's that that
coordination is all about techniques to
give up the cpu
until the condition the event that we're
waiting for has actually occurred
and again uh sleep and wake up there's
actu there's a number of different
coordination primitives that people have
invented over the years
and xv6 in common with many flavors of
unix
uses something called sleep and wake up
okay
um all right with this background i'd
like to
switch to looking at the
code in xv6
all right so i've just shared my screen
let me know if the screen share did not
work
okay i have in preparation for this
lecture
rewritten some of the code in the uart
driver
that's the serial driver that xv6 uses
to read and write
characters from the console and so i
have this function uart right which
when a program like the shell prints its
prompt or produces any other output
that you know makes a write system call
and in my slightly modified version of
xv6
that right system call ends up with a
call to uart right
in the uart driver which actually writes
the characters in this loop
um one by one to the uart hardware
and this is written in a sort of classic
device driver style
you'll see code like this in many device
drivers
okay so one of the things that's going
on here is that the uart hardware
can only accept one character for
transmission at a time
and so the way this code has to look you
know typically you have lots of
characters you
want to write you can write a character
to the uart hardware
and it needs to wait for the uart
hardware to say yes i finish
sending that character i'm ready for a
new one and then the driver can write a
new one
a new character the next character to
output because
this hardware can operate very slowly
like maybe only a thousand characters
per second
the amount of time we have to wait
between characters can be very long like
a millisecond is a long long time
on modern computer it's you know a
billion cycles a million cycles maybe
um which a huge amount of work could be
done so we'd really prefer not to
just spin waiting for the uart to finish
sending each character
we'd like to have a better way and so in
fact xv6 has a better way
like like most operating systems the
uart hardware
will raise and interrupt after it's
finished sending each character
and so we have not just this right
routine wheels the uart driver has an
interrupt routine
which i think trap.c calls when the uart
hardware
raises an interrupt to say that it's
finished and the interrupt routine
checks the uart it reads one of the
memory map registers in the uart
hardware
to look for the flag that says i'm done
transmitting which is this
lsr tx idle flag and if that flag's set
then the interrupt routine actually sets
this
flag in memory and makes this wake-up
call
which will cause the you are right
whatever threat is in your right to
return from its sleep here and
attempt to send a new character so the
game is that
if a thread needs to wait for something
and here we go we need to wait for the
uart hardware to be willing to accept a
new character it'll call sleep
waiting for a specific condition usually
and when the condition is fulfilled
code that realizes the condition is
fulfilled we'll call wake up
so these sleeps and wakeups are paired
and
sleep we'll look at the implementation
by and by but sleep does a number of
things
and then calls switch in order to give
up the cpu
one thing to notice is that the wake up
and the sleep have to be linked together
somehow
that is when we call wake up we really
only want to wake up
threads that are waiting for the
specific event that we realize has
happened
and so uh sleep and wake up take this
argument
um which is called the sleep channel so
wake up supplies
the very same value here that
we're passing to sleep sleep and wake up
actually don't really look
don't care what the these they just take
64-bit values here they don't care what
they are really
the only thing that's going on is that
when if we sleep on a particular
sleep channel this particular weight
channel
we want the wake up to pass the very
same value here in order to show that it
indicate which sleepers it wants to wake
up
any questions about this interface okay
so there's a question just to clarify
the process has not woken up
every for every character that's written
um okay let's see
in this driver that i've specially
hacked for demonstration purposes
um there's an interrupt per character
so the the uh the way you are right
works is that
for each character that is in this while
for each character in the buffer of
characters we're supposed to write
we wait here in this loop
until the uart is ready to accept one
more character we write one more
character
we set this done flag to zero
and go back and wait typically in sleep
until the done flag is one
um and then after the you are finished
ascending this character
it'll interrupt and the interrupt
routine will set done to one and do the
wake up so in fact there is a
wake up a sleep and a wake up and an
iteration of the loop for every single
character
and more the uart is actually capable of
sending
um some number like 4 or 16 or something
characters at a time so a more efficient
driver would
would uh hand 16 characters to the uart
per iteration of this loop and there'd
be an interrupt every 16 characters
and higher speed devices you know
typically like ethernet drivers
typically accept many more bytes than
that per interrupt
all right okay so this is just a
illustration of what the interface looks
like
um uh sleep and wake up are nice because
or one reason they're nice is they're
relatively flexible um sleep and wake up
don't really care what it is you're up
to
um you know you can
you don't have to tell sleep what you're
waiting for you don't have to tell wake
up what event happened
you just need to have these matching
sleep channel
64-bit values however
there's one uh interesting property of
the sleep interface
we have to pass it a lock here there's
the second argument
this lock argument and
there's a big story behind why sleep
takes this second argument and
i'm gonna explain what's going on but
the high level
uh picture is that um
it's not doesn't seem to be possible to
to design a sleep
that is completely ignorant of
what it is you're trying to wait for
you it's it's hard to write a sort of
general purpose sleep that
simply sleeps waiting for some specific
event
and this is danger which we'll see in a
moment called lost loss wakeups
that just about every coordination
mechanism has to grapple with somehow
and deal with somehow
and in the sleep interface this fact
that we have to pass a lock
is sort of a little bit of ugly
implementation
leaking through into the interface in a
way i'll explain in just a moment
yeah i'll explain oh there's a question
why do we need the done flag
and the sleep channel i will hold on to
that question
i'll explain that in 5 or 10 minutes
okay so before explaining why it is what
it is that sleep is doing with this lock
i actually want to talk a bit about what
the implications would be
if we had a simpler sleep
that didn't have didn't take that extra
lock argument
so
all right so
and the topic here is lost wake ups
that's the problem i'm going to describe
now
um so uh
suppose that the interface was just
sleep on this arbitrary
channel value with no second argument
um uh you can't make this work so i'm
actually going to call this broken sleep
and you could imagine if we didn't know
better that
a sleep like this could simply set
the state of the
process to this special sleeping value
which says i don't want to run anymore
i'm waiting for a specific event
and then if you look at the xv6's
implementation of sleep you'll see it
does this
among other things we need to record
this special
sleep channel value so that a future
call to wake up can
realize that we're actually waiting for
the thing that the um
wake up is waking us up for so you could
imagine a sleep
and it would be broken that really just
did this i guess you'd have to take
acquire this process is lock also
and then of course money wake up
wake up um
and this really is pretty much how wake
up works we want to wake up all the
threads that are waiting on
that are called sleep with this
particular channel value so we're just
going to say
you know for each p in
the process table
if the state
if it's sleeping
and it's sleeping on the channel that
we're waking up
then set the state to
runnable
and actually modulo locks this is pretty
much what wake up does
okay so uh some alternate universe boy
it would be nice if uh sleep and wake up
were this simple
um let me demonstrate though
um well
uh
let me demonstrate um
well before i go back to the actual xv6
code
let me just outline how you would use
this sleep in wake up
in the uar driver and this is sort of a
repeat of what we've already seen but
using this
slightly simpler interface you would
have
and indeed the driver does this you'd
have this done flag
and then you are right
you know would say for each
character in the buffer
and then it would check this done flag
just say while not done
i'm gonna sleep
and then pass that uh channel whatever
it was
tx chan or something it doesn't really
matter
okay and then we're going to send c
to the uart and set done equals
zero right and then the interrupt
routine
just sets the done flag is equal to true
and calls wake up
so this is how we could use
this simplified broken sleep all right
so this is really broken sleep
what this is missing though is locking
so actually both the both of these
routines here both the right routine and
the interrupt routine absolutely have
to lock and one reason
is that uh this done flag anytime we
have shared data
we really need to put a lock around the
shared data and the other reason is that
actually i didn't put it in here but
both the interrupt routine and
the right routine need to access the
hardware the uart hardware itself
and typically it's an error unless
you're very very clever
it's an error to have two threads
concurrently
try to read and write the memory mapped
hardware registers
so we need to lock around in both of
these subroutines in order to
avoid both
racing access is done and racing
accesses to the hard
hardware and so the question is where
should we put the locks in
it's it's easy in the interrupt routine
we're going to lock our lock
at the beginning whatever the lock i
think is called urtx lock or something
and we're going to unlock at the end
right so the interrupt routine just
takes the lock and releases it the
puzzle is where to put the locks
in the uart routine
one possibility is that you are right
could hold the lock for the entire
sequence of
trying to send a character each
character
so we could acquire the lock here
and unlock here
so lock and unlock sort of at the
beginning and very end processing each
character
so why why does this definitely not work
well one reason is that the only way we
can get out of this loop
is that the interrupt routine sets done
to one
but if we hold this lock for this entire
sequence
the init the interrupt routine also
needs to lock um and so it will sit here
spinning waiting for the lock
because um we hold the lock and aren't
going to release it
until done is set but done can only be
set when the interrupt routine
is actually able to get the lock so we
cannot just simply hold the lock
across the entire sequence of sending
each character
all right so another possibility you
know the sort of
nasty problem here is that we the you
are right was holding a lock
at the time when it expected the
interrupt routine to execute
which is right here the only time when
we really need the interrupt routine to
execute is
is at this point here otherwise it's
okay to hold the lock
so another possibility would be to yeah
acquire the lock at the beginning
because we need to protect our access to
just
this shared variable done but release it
before the call to sleep that gives the
interrupt routine a chance to execute
and set done to one
and then we'll just reacquire it after
sleep returns
so that when we go back up to the top
and check done again we have the lock
again
all right so let me actually modify my
driver to do this
we'll see see what the consequences are
all right um so the sleep we're talking
about
where we wanna you can see this code
actually does
acquire the lock at the very very
beginning and release it at the end
and the interrupt routine also acquires
and releases and the proposal is
that we do two things one is
um we're gonna what we're exploring is
why my broken sleep idea
that only takes a single argument
why that doesn't work so the idea is
that in order to make the locking work
out right we're going to call broken
sleep all right but we're going to
release
the lock here and reacquire it
after sleep returns
and then literally all this broken sleep
does is exactly what i wrote on my
little white board namely it sets the
state to sleeping it sets the channel to
this tx chan argument then i call switch
all right let's see what happens
oh wow look at that um it actually
managed to
init is printing out its init starting
message and it actually managed to write
a few characters and now it seems to
have hung
and it turns out that if i type a
character i'm going to type a period
by typing period
output restarts uh
maybe make some more output i run ls
oops
ls also emitted a few characters and
then stopped but if i type something and
take
i'm going to type x it'll restart
ls and it'll keep going so
um what do we think is going on here
somebody want to propose a theory
the problem definitely has to do with
the code that i just changed
so what's happening
all right so what's going on here is
that
my new code releases the lock
releases this lock at this point and
then right here
um the interrupt happens because as soon
as you release a lock
first of all the interrupts are
re-enabled so on this cpu interrupts
could happen this is a multi-core
machine so actually interrupts can be
taken
on any core
so almost certainly what's going on at
this point that i've marked in the code
is that
on some other core the the uart
interrupt
is executing and it's sitting in a choir
waiting for this lock on some other core
um and so as soon as i release it that
other core is going to acquire the lock
it's going to see that the uart has
completed sending the character
and it's going to set this transmit done
flag to 1
which is great and then it's going to
call wake up
on tx chan which is also fine
except because the writing thread is
still executing
between the release and the broken sleep
the writing thread
hasn't gone to sleep yet so the wake up
that the interrupt routine calls doesn't
actually wake up any
anything up because nothing's yet gone
to sleep on that channel
and and then um the writing thread will
proceed to call its broken sleep which
will
you know set the state to sleeping and
set the sleep channel
but the interrupt has already happened
and the wake up has already been called
so this sleep nothing will ever wake it
up
because the wake up already happened
this is called the the lost wake up
problem
any questions about why or how this
arises
yeah uh is it always going to be the
case
that once something gets a lot once us
a wake up gets lost that on the next
time everything that's been buffered is
just going to get dumped
well it completely depends on the
details of
of what's going on in in this case it's
actually
just a it's sort of accidental
that me typing something
caused the output to resume so me typing
input calls the output to get
fixed and the reason for that is that
the uart has only one kind of interrupt
it makes it
it calls the same interrupt routine
whether for both input
to signal input and the signal completed
output um so when i type
something which is input the this uart
interrupt routine gets called
and the uart is thinking that it's
calling it just a signal that input has
arrived but in fact the interrupt
routine
in xv6 you know looks for
you know notices that the um you know
the way this code happens to be written
is that it if the uart is ready to
transmit another character it always
calls wake up
um even though it's a while ago maybe r
had already called wake up
so it's sort of accidental that me
typing characters uh
caused this to get restarted and so
sometimes
you know if there are lost wake ups
they sort of fix themselves in this way
if you're lucky and sometimes they don't
like if the uart had had separate
receive and transmit interrupt routines
then
there would have been no getting out of
this
does that answer your question yes thank
you
okay so yes please go ahead
what purpose does the tx done bit serve
or the tx done bit um or you mean the
cis flag
tx done it is simply a way for the
interrupt routine
to communicate to you are right
that um the previously transmitted
character is finished
and it's okay for you all right to
proceed to transmitting the next
character
so it's a little piece of it's just like
a little communication flag from the
interrupt routine
uh to you all right
so does that make sense because if it
it could like it would sleep and then it
would know that
when it wakes up it's probably the uart
interrupt that woke it up so
probably the tx done bit like
would have been said but if we didn't
have it so
i guess i'm saying that actually wakes
up it
should know that it's from uart
interrupt
okay so is another way of phrasing your
question how come there's this while
loop here
instead of just okay i think i answered
my question uh i think the answer to my
question is because you are
interested two purposes okay yeah
so yeah yeah in general did your the
answer your question sort of a specific
instance of the more general answer
that um
it's it just turns out to be
not practical to make sleeps and
wake-ups
be precise guaranteed precise that is
that
if sleep returns then for sure whatever
you're waiting for has happened
so one example of this is that
supposing we have two processes that are
both trying to write the uart
at the same time they're both in you are
right and they can because
after one writes a character it'll sleep
um
and releasing that's turns out releasing
the lock and then the other one can
enter that loop and try to wait until
the uart's not busy
and they both may both end up sleeping
and when an interrupt happens and the ur
can accept one more character they'll
both be woken up
um but only one should actually write
the character
and that this while loop and in fact
you'll see
a while loop around every sleep in xv6 i
believe
and it's because this problem of you may
be woken up but really somebody else
sort of
took the thing you were waiting for so
you have to sleep again this happens
pervasively
okay thank you yes
i've got a question yes um so it looks
like
uh we only saw one last wake up because
as soon as we pressed like a character
the rest of the output
the entire wrist output came out
shouldn't we have seen like multiple
loss wake ups where
like why didn't it happen again oh it
did it did here let me let me run this
i'm going to run read me i'm going to
cat read me right which is a couple
thousand bytes
so oops uh sorry i had already typed
something
um oh gosh we've got one character i'm
going to type a period
ah we got a few more characters and then
it hung up again
i'm going to take another period another
couple characters
right each time i type a period that
causes a interrupt for the res
for the input which then wakes up the
process and i could do a few more
characters of rights and then hangs
again
you know gets another lost wake up is
that uh
yeah okay i just missed that yep that
makes sense all right yeah so i'm typing
period here i get a
couple characters per lost wake up
because you know the loss wake up
requires this coincidence that the
interrupt had already happened and was
waiting to acquire the lock and
just we get that coincidence a lot of
the time but not all the time
all right okay so our goal then
is to get rid of this loss wake up
problem by somehow eliminating this
window here
between the release of the urtx lock
which we have to release
right because the interrupt needs that
lock so we know we have to release the
lock
but somehow we want to eliminate this
window between when we release the lock
and when the process actually marks
itself as sleeping
so that the interrupts wake up we'll see
that the process is sleeping and
actually wake it up
and therefore not lose the wake up
so we've got to somehow close that
window
and to do that we've got to make sleeps
interface a little bit more complicated
um so go back to the um
original working sleep and a call to the
working sleep
and the the way that um people solve
this problem
is that sleep requires even though sleep
doesn't really know what you're waiting
for
it requires that you be waiting for
something and furthermore
that there be a lock that protects
whatever it is you're waiting for
so it requires that there be a sleep
condition
which it doesn't really know about the
sleep condition is that tx done is equal
to one so sleep doesn't know what the
sleep condition is but it does
it is requires that there be a lock that
protects the sleep condition namely
namely this ur
tx lock and that the lock be locked
when you check the condition that you
hold the lock until you call sleep
and that you pass the lock to sleep and
what sleep promises essentially at an
interface level is that it's going to
atomically
put the process to sleep and release the
lock as a sort of
at least isn't indivisible pair of
actions at least with respect to wake up
um so
wake up will never see this situation in
which yeah you've released the lock
but no the process is not asleep all
right so sleep makes the release of the
lock and the putting the
process to sleep atomic
and the rules for this is that there has
to be this it has to be a condition
there has to be a lock protecting the
condition the lock has to be held when
you call sleep you have to pass the lock
to sleep and
furthermore the lock has to be held
when you call wake up this condition
lock
needs to be held when you call wake up
so these are rules
that the programmer had better follow if
they want to write correct code using
sleep and wake up
all right so let's look at
uh the sleep and wake up um to try to
spot how they actually
use this extra little piece of
information and these rules
to avoid lost wake-ups so first i want
to look at wake up
wake up's not very surprising it just
runs through the entire process table
it locks every process and remember that
after it's locked the process and you
can't really look at a process of state
without locking it
it locks each process if the process is
sleeping
and the channel that it's sleeping for
is the same channel that was passed to
wake up
then wake up marks the changes the
processes state to runnable
and then releases the processes lock
so no surprises here we'll ignore my
broken sleep and instead look at sleep
itself so here's the implementation of
sleep
with now this new lock argument
um so we know sleep has to reduce has to
release
that condition lock that its second
argument we know it has to release it
because the
you know the interrupt routine has to be
able to acquire it so we know there's
going to be release of that lock
somewhere inside sleep and indeed
here's the release of that lock of
course we're worried
after we release the lock that at this
very point
wake up might be called and might wake
up this process
so in order to might try to wake up this
process but of course we haven't marked
it sleeping yet
right so we cannot afford to have wake
up
execute um oops
to have wake up execute right after this
release
even though we're releasing so in order
to cause that not to happen before
releasing the condition lock
sleep acquires the lock of the process
that's going to sleep
if you recall
wake up must be called with the
condition lock held
and it acquires the if it's about to
wake up a process it first
must wait to acquire that process is
lock
so for the entire amount of time between
when you are
right between before you are right
checked
the condition um and we when we call
sched here
this thread holds one or another of the
condition lock and p arrow lock at all
times
just to go back to you are that's i want
to emphasize this
um uart right acquires
the condition lock here and holds the
condition lock all the way through to
where it calls sleep
and so it requires the condition lock
checks the condition with the lock held
calls sleep with the condition lock held
so wake up
can't do anything now because can not
even allow to call wake up
until we until the caller owns the
condition lock so wake up is definitely
not executing now
um we still hold the lock when we call
sleep
uh sleep releases the condition lock but
first acquires the processes lock
and if you remember oops
wake up wake up is called with the
condition lock
um after we release it i'm sorry
after we release the condition lock wake
up can be called but wake up
won't look at the process until it has
the process lock which we hold so okay
so wake up is still not executing
um
acquire the process lock release the
condition lock while holding the process
lock mark the
process as sleeping on this particular
channel
and then call sched which calls switch
right we still the process lock so wake
up still isn't doing anything
and if you remember the we're now
switching away from this
thread to the scheduler thread and the
scheduler routine after it's called the
switch returns
releases um the recently running
processes lock
so at this point after we're in the
scheduler
wakeup can finally acquire prlock for
this process
notice that it's sleeping and
on this channel and set its state to
wake up so we're guaranteed the
effect of the rule that you have to hold
the condition lock when calling sleep
the fact that sleep knows about that
lock and releases it only after
requiring process
pr lock and wake up needing to hold both
locks
in order to think about this process
means that we can no longer
lose a wake up and so we fix this loss
wake-up problem
i realize that a little bit involved any
questions about what's going on here
all right well feel free to uh ask
questions at any time
um all right so we saw one
we saw this one looked at this one case
in which we're
using sleep and wake up in a way that
avoids loss wake ups
um there's a bunch of others in xv6
this particular one the thing that we're
waiting for the condition that we're
waiting for
is that an interrupt has occurred that
is signaled that hardware's ready
to sort of do the next thing
there's also times when uh
kernel code calls sleep in order to wait
for a diff some other thread to do
something
which is not actually in the end
conceptually different but
may feel a little bit different so in
the pipe code for example
if you look at pipe read
you know there's a bunch of junk here
which you have to ignore but
um the reed system call on a pipe ends
up calling pipe read
there's a lock that protects the pipe
and this is
going to end up being
the condition lock pipe read needs to
wait until there's actually
data buffered in the pipe um and that
condition
is you know that there's data ready is n
read
or n write is greater than n re that is
more bytes have been written than red
while that's not true
pipe reed sits in sleep waiting for that
condition
and passes in this pipe lock
the condition lock that protects the
condition into sleep
in order to protect against loss
wake-ups and the reason why you might
get a loss wake up is that
on a different core um
we go a little farther up in the file on
a different core there's probably some
other thread
just now calling pipe right and it's
going to add
bytes to the pipe buffer and finally
called wake up
on the channel that pipe read is
waiting for and you know the we want to
avoid the risk that between
the reader checking uh that there's
and noticing there's no bytes to read
and calling sleep
we do not want a a pipe right on another
core to slip in there
and add bites and wake us up before
we've even gone to sleep
right that would be a lost wake up and
this lock basically this lock and the
fact that
sleep is careful about releasing it
prevent a writer from slipping in
between the check of the condition and
the sleep
because the writer has to acquire the
slot too
and um for those of you who are
the people asked about wrapping sleep
and while loops
both pipe read and pipe right are
examples of a
sleep wrapped in a while so for example
the
this is the loop that pipe read waits
for data to appear waits for the
pipe buffer to be non-empty and the
sleep is wrapped in a loop
and again the reason is that there could
be perfectly well be multiple
processes reading the very same pipe and
so if a writer writes
one byte to the pipe so there's only one
byte there
the writer is going to call wake up
that's going to wake up
all the multiple processes that were
reading that pipe
but there's only one bite in the pipe
and so one of those processes is going
to wake up first
right it's going to come out of its
sleep first
actually this reminds me there's another
crucial thing i forgot to mention about
sleep um
and that's that the last thing sleep
does let's look at uh
here's here's the uh sorry here's the
end of sleep
the last thing sleep does is acquires
the condition lock
so you you must call sleep with the
condition lock held and sleep reacquires
it before it returns
um okay so what that means is that
if there are a bunch of readers there's
one byte written just written to a pipe
and a bunch of readers they're all woken
up
one of them will succeed one of the
sleeps of one of the threads will
succeed in acquiring this lock
the others will be waiting and sleep
spinning waiting for the lock
that one lucky process uh sleep will
return
it'll come back to this check and now
pro and write is one larger than n read
so there's data to read it'll fall out
of the loop it'll read the one byte
and now there's nothing in the buffer
release the lock
and return and now the next thread that
was woken up
its sleep will be able to reacquire the
condition lock its sleeve will return
it will return recheck the loop
condition but now
n read is equal to n right and so that
thread and any other thread waiting will
go back to sleep
this is again just to reinforce why
almost every maybe every call to sleep
has to be wrapped in a loop that
rechecks the condition
questions about the way sleep pipes use
sleep
all right um the sleep in wake up
interfacing rules are
a little bit complex because you have to
sort of reveal a bit to sleep about
what you're waiting for you have to tell
the lock and follow some rules
which is sometimes annoying on the other
hand sleep and wake up
pretty flexible partially because they
don't actually have to understand the
condition itself
there just has to be a condition and be
a lock
there are other schemes that are
somewhat higher level
there's other coordination schemes like
the semaphores you read about in
the reading for today in which the
interface is slightly less complex like
the semaphores you don't have to tell
the semaphore about a lock
and the color the semaphore doesn't have
to worry about lost wake ups
internally the implementation of the
semaphore again as you saw
in the uh reading for today the internal
implementation of semaphores worries
about
uh lost wake up so because the interface
is specialized
to these up down counters
the need to deal with loss wake-ups
doesn't leak through into the interface
so the semaphores are somewhat simpler
although they're less general
if you don't if you're not if you don't
have a count and you're not waiting for
a count
then semaphores are not
necessarily going to be super helpful
for you so it's that
that causes me to claim that sleep and
wake up are a little more general
all right so with sleep and wake up
under our belts um i want to talk about
one more
kind of challenge that xv6 faces that's
actually related to sleep and wake up
and that's how to shut down threads
every threading system you know the
threads eventually need to exit and we
need to
clean up their state free their stack on
xv6
when a process exits we need to free its
user memory and free its page table and
free its trap frame
and mark the process the slot in the
process table as
reusable so these are sort of typical
cleanup requirements there's a bunch of
stuff that has to be freed
when threads exit
or are um or are killed so but there's
two big problems that arise here
with uh thread exit or killing threads
one is that
we can't just reach out we can't usually
just reach out and
unilaterally destroy another thread
the problem is that that other thread
may actually be currently executing on
another core and using its stack
and maybe about to save its registers in
its struct context or whatever
the other thread if it's in the kernel
maybe holding locks it may be in the
middle of some
complicated update to a kernel data
structure
and if we simply somehow shoot down the
thread and stop it dead in its tracks
then it may have gotten halfway through
a delicate update
to some kernel data but we shot it down
before it completed
um and so uh
you know we can't afford any of those
things to happen um
another problem is that even if a thread
calls exit and is sort of
decided for it's not killed but decided
for itself that it wants to
quit it has resources that it uses while
it executes
like it's stack for example and it's
slot in the process table
and while it's still executing it it may
not be able to free up
the resources that it's still using so
we need a way for threads to
for those last few resources that are
critical to execution to somehow be
freed even though the thread needs them
even just to execute any code at all
okay so keep these two problems in mind
xv6 actually has two
two things that are related to shutting
down threads or processes
one is exit and the other is kill so
let's look at exit first
i'm going to look at the code for exit
and proc.c
this is what the exit system call
calls um
uh and you know what exit has to do in
the end we know
sort of from the outside from the
interface that it's got to free up the
process memory and page table it's got
to close its open files
and we also know that there's this wait
call that the parent may be waking
making and that exit has to eventually
cause the parent to be woken up
as well and so we're going to look for
all these things in the
an exit code so you can see um some of
this stuff like
exit specifically closes the open files
and this might actually be quite complex
because the files are
you know file system files closing them
actually involves things like reference
counting
and we haven't gotten there yet but
we'll see that
this takes a fair amount of work but a
process goes ahead and closes when you
call exit
closes its own files
and it also does something similar it uh
has a
record of the current working directory
which is what's changed when you call it
cd and it needs to
sort of release that reference into the
file system
then there's some other horrible stuff
that happens that's
related to the fact that if a process
exits but it has children of its own
those children are inherited by the init
process
because as it turns out we'll see in a
few minutes that
every process that exits there has to be
a corresponding weight
from a parent that actually finishes up
some of the steps in exiting and so if i
exit
my children they need to be waited for i
was their parent i'm not going to wait
for them because i've exited
and so there's a stretch of code here
and exit that is
re-parenting the exiting processes
children so that they're parents of init
which is
process id one
and then finally a process wakes up its
own parent
which might be waiting and sleeping and
wait
um and
uh sets its state to the zombie state
um it turns out we haven't we'll see in
a moment but the process hasn't
completely finished releasing
all of its resources um so it's not
quite ready to be reused
like we want to end up in a position
where the process can be
and all its state can be reused by a
fork
by some other fork that's unrelated
right but we're not quite there yet
and we'll see why in a moment we set the
state to zombie um
and then and we're not done yet right we
haven't freed the process
um we just jump into the scheduler
without having completely finished um
freeing all resources
okay so the story here continues
you know at this point a zombie process
won't be run
the scheduler only runs runnable
processes so this
process isn't quite free because that
would be state equals unused
but it's definitely not going to run
again because it's in state zombie so
resistance to scheduler
scheduler now runs something else
we know from the sort of description of
exit and weight
in unix that if a process exits
then if its parent calls weight
the weight that weight is going to
return to signal to the parent that
one of its children is exited so we can
look for the implementation of weight
also here this is a big loop this
implementation of weight but
really what's going on is that when a
process calls weight
it uh scans the process table
looking for processes whose parent
is the current process
and in particular looking for processes
whose parent is the current process
and are in state zombie that is they
they've gotten that far
in uh in exit or almost finished exiting
um so now we found this called a weight
to the wait system calls found a child
process
that has exited
and i don't know if you remember
exit can return this 32-bit
exit status to the parents so the next
bunch of code collects that
and then it's the parent that calls free
proc
which does the final steps in freeing a
processes resources
so we'll look at free proc and this is
the final shutdown of stuff
that would be quite awkward if the if
the exiting process
itself freed while it was executing
so it frees its trap frame it frees the
user page table
and if we freed kernel stacks
the processes exiting processes kernel
stack would be freed here
also but because of the
stat guard kernel stack stack guard
pages we don't actually ever
turns out we don't free do another free
the
kernel stacks um but all the stuff that
would be sort of potentially a pain to
free in the
exit while the exiting process is
running is freed by the parent
um one thing to notice here is that
weight
um weight is not just for the
convenience of parents that want to know
when their pro
when their children have exited weight
is actually a critical piece of the exit
process
and you really in unix it's just a
requirement
that there be a weight that corresponds
to every
exiting process and that's really the
reason why um
when a process exits its children are
sort of given away to init
um they're turned into in its children
um what init does is just
calls weight in a loop um because every
process has to be waited for
so that the its parent can call free
proc and finish
freeing up its resources and then when
it's completely done
it sets if when the parent's done
freeing all the exited processes
resources it
sets that child state unused now
fork and you know some future called a
fork
can reuse that process slot
any questions
oh i have a question about sleep um
so in sleep where we
are um yeah so
when we are oh sorry not sleep um
exit i won't say exit yeah
yeah so why are we
why are we grabbing original parent
before
we repaired is that necessary
this is grim code
that's wrestling with the possibility
that
a process and its parent may
exit at the same time
um and there's some
um you know even though ordinarily
there's like nothing interesting going
on process exits
it's apparent waits for it everything's
fine
but it could be that a parent that a
process exits and its parent process
excess at the same time and so
while we're trying to like wake up our
parent to tell we've exited
that parent is itself exiting
and a lot of this code here um
which i feel i kind of understood a year
ago but don't any longer understand
is about taking care of this rare case
of concurrent exits of a parent and
child
and if it weren't for that it would all
be extremely straightforward apparent
the process would have a parent
and it would just wake up its parent at
this point
and we wouldn't if
it weren't for concurrent exits of
parent and child the child could just
wake up its parent
period okay i see thank you sorry sorry
to not really be explaining here
um i have a quick question um so why are
we setting the
process state to zombie after we wake up
the
parent wouldn't we want to do that
before oh
yeah um it turns out because
we've acquired the the the exiting
process has
acquired its own process lock the parent
can't look at this process
um and we've acquired the our own lock
here and then we're going to call sched
the parent is parent's weight acquires
pr
acquires the child's lock which is pr
lock
and so that means that between this
acquire and
when after we call sched and the
scheduler thread releases
this pr lock the parent can't look at
this process
in this block of code okay
and so the order of this stuff doesn't
matter and indeed
um if we didn't have the log up it's
possible some other or
well in in most situations
no order would work if we didn't hold
the lock
um anyway yeah because we hold a lock
the
order sort of doesn't matter because the
parent can't look that makes sense
okay um
okay so the trick here is or the trick i
wanted to emphasize was that
um to a great extent
actually the child doesn't in the end
the child doesn't free all its resources
because it can't because it's still
using it while it executes and instead
some other thread namely the parent does
the freeing of the delicate resources
that are
required for execution
so that's sort of a trick to allow us to
greatly simplify exit
okay a last thing i want to look at is
kill
so the you know the kill system call
one process in unix can call that make
the kill system call and
pass it the process id of a different
process and the goal is that
that should cause that other process the
target process to stop
executing and if we're not careful you
know this
risks especially if that other process
is executing in the kernel
um this risk this problem i mentioned a
few minutes ago where
gosh that you know the kernel thread of
the process we're trying to kill might
might be in the middle of updating
something you know updating the file
system creating a file for example
and we can't just like kill it dead on
the spot because
that would leave some delicate
multi-step operation only
halfway completed so we know that kill
can't really just stop the target
process
and indeed on xv6 and of the unix's as
well
kill does almost absolutely nothing
it scans the process table looking for
the target process id
and just sets this flag
in that processes process structure
and also if it was sleeping causes it to
be runnable so it'll wake up from the
sleep but all it does is set this flag
doesn't stop the other process from
executing
or anything like it
so kill itself is very gentle um
and the game is that the target process
at
points in the kernel code where it would
be safe to stop executing
the other process checks its own killed
flag
and if it's set the other process sort
of voluntarily
exits you know calls this exit function
and you can see some of those points in
trap.c
in fact you can see all the points
so if we're in user trap in a system
call
before actually executing the system
call if the process has already been
killed
or if kill has been called for this
process
then the process calls exit and goes
away
and this is a point in the kernel where
it's not holding any locks it's not in
the middle of doing anything
and so it's completely safe for the
process to just
quit and call exit
and there's a similar check at the end
of user trap
so after a system call
the process also checks if it's being
killed and indeed this code here um
executes even if there's an if the
process is
interrupted by an interrupt so for
example if a timer interrupt goes off
then um this code will execute and we'll
see that the process
has been killed and then the process
will exit
and so what that means is that the sort
of what kill means
kill the meaning of kill or the effect
of kill is not exactly
stop the other process right now it's
much more like
well you know if the proc other process
is in user space
then the next time it makes a system
call
it will exit or the next time a timer
interrupt goes off
while executing user code in the target
process
if it's interrupted by a timer interrupt
or some other interrupt
then it will also exit so there might be
a significant delay between
when one process calls kill and when the
other process
actually exits and that's just the way
it is
um there is a sort of intermediate
question though of
if the process is not in user zone user
space but is in the middle of a system
call
and it's killed do we need to do
anything special
the reason why this may come up is
suppose the process is
reading from the console right you know
reading for the next character you type
well you might not type another
character until tomorrow
and it would be nice if when you killed
the process it
actually went away before tomorrow
and for that reason in a number of
points in xv6
in which a process is uh is sleeping
xv6 actually arranges that if it's
killed while sleeping in the kernel
it will actually exit so let me show you
the machinery for that
the first thing to look at is in kill
itself
you can see that if the target process
is sleeping
then kill will set its state to runnable
and that will mean that even if it had
called
sleep the scheduler will now run it and
it will simply return from sleep
um and so let's look at a place where
that actually matters in the pipe code
if a process is in sleep waiting to read
a pipe
um and it's killed kill we'll set it to
runnable it'll return from sleep
we'll go back to the top of this loop
it'll probably
if there was no data in the pipe before
there'll probably still be no data in
the pipe
and now this pipe read at least checks
whether the process
has been killed and if it has been
killed instead of sleeping again
the pipe read will return return and
error it doesn't really matter
but what we're returning to is
this syscall since we're in a system
call
um where pipe really returns to in the
end is returns from the system call
and then user trap checks piero kill
again and will now exit so for
sleeps that we know it's okay
to just bail out of when a process is
killed
those loops check the killed flag but
there are also sleeps
where it would not be okay for a process
to quit if it's killed in that sleep
so for example if a process is in the
middle of updating the file system on
disk to create a new file
that is a bad time even if it's sleeping
waiting for the disk that's a bad time
for a process to just decide to quit
because it's been killed we want to
finish the complete file system
operation
and only then have the process exit and
so you can see this
we haven't looked at this but um i'll
show you in the disk driver
an example of a sleep loop that doesn't
check killed
well look at that so here we are this is
the sleep
in which a process waits for the disc to
finish reading a disc block
and it absolutely doesn't check killed
because it wants to finish maybe in the
middle of like creating a file which
involves multiple disk reads and writes
i want to finish the entire file system
operation the entire system call
and only then check pro killed and exit
questions about anything
um i have a question about why is skill
allowed in the way it is why wouldn't
the process
kill all the other processes so that it
can run
by itself well
uh you know you do that at mit on athena
time sharing machine they'll probably
kick you out of school
um right but why is it out loud
i guess it's allowed in xv6 because xv6
is a toy operating system
that um
it just like anything that has to do
with
like permissions it just doesn't exist
in xv6
in linux or a real operating system
every process has
a user id that corresponds to the more
or less to the human root user who's
executing the process
and some system calls use the user id
of the process to kind of check what is
the process allowed to do this
and so in linux you would see a
an extra check here that said that
the calling process has to have the same
user id
as the process is trying to kill
otherwise it's not allowed
and that at least in a time sharing
context
where we have multiple users and we
don't want them to kill each other's
processes
that's more or less sufficient to keep
people from to make it hard for people
to
kill other people's processes
okay see thank you yeah
um does the init process ever exit
uh let me check
yes if fork fails it'll exit
however the real answer to the question
is no the intent
is that init never exit it just sit in
this loop
and what it's doing is calling weight
over and over again
if an it exits i think that's a fatal
error and the system will crash
and there's code somewhere in the kernel
that says maybe an exit
let's just check exit uh
um yeah yeah here we are next at the
beginning of exit
if it looks like the current process is
the inet process
it's a panic because
the system would eventually grind to a
halt if there were a no init because
then
then there'd be nothing collect nothing
to call weight
on these exiting processes and nothing
to complete the freeing of the processes
and gradually we'd run out of processes
and then
that would be some other error but yeah
we have to have an init
so the real answer is that no and it
really can't be allowed to exit
better not exit
okay um
any other questions
um i guess another question uh so
i guess we haven't really talked about
it much in this class yet but like what
happens
or what needs to happen to like shut
down the os
you gotta unplug it okay
okay um yeah this is like very
complex and it depends on what you're
running if if you're
if the operating if the machine is
currently doing nothing
um well
part of the answer to the question is
that the file system ends up being
because the file system is permanent you
know the file system is carried over
from reboot to reboot um
we we need to leave the file system in
good shape so
if we were in the middle of some update
to the file system like creating a file
then we and we want to shut the system
down or the power fails or something we
absolutely need a strategy
to make sure that that even though we
were in the middle of some complex
update to the file system that we don't
leave it in
the file system in a state we you know
don't expose any broken invariants
in the on disk file system structures
because the file system's really just a
data structure that lives on disk
so there's only like a a lot of
sort of machinery involved in like
making sure that if you shut down or the
power fails or who knows what that
the disk can that we can recover the
file system on disk
um for the rest though if it's not for
that
then whether you have to do anything
special to shut down
depends on what processes you're running
if you're running some important server
you know a database server that
a lot of other computers depend on and
use over the network
who knows you know the answer may be
that you just cannot be allowed to shut
down because
you're providing a service that's
critical to a bunch of other computers
if your computer's not doing much of
anything
then you can just turn it off and it
will stop executing
and there's not much to do i mean really
maybe the answer to your question is
if you want to shut down the computer
make sure the file system is good in
good shape
and then stop executing instructions and
that's fine
that makes sense yeah thank you
anything else
oh sorry i have another question so what
is the semaphore
interface we're talking about p and v
so just to just those two functions um
yeah oh yeah xb6 doesn't have semaphores
really but
you know the book's sum before so i
think it's just p and v there's just two
those are two methods you know you have
a semaphore object there's two methods
p and v okay i see you thank you
sure
anything else