all right
hello everyone welcome back from um
thanksgiving um can anyone hear me
yep you're good good all right today i
want to talk about
uh networking and how it relates to
operating systems
um and a lot of this is
geared towards the lab the last lab
in which you'll actually build some uh
network interface driver some of us just
care for general understanding of how
the network software
typically is set up in operating systems
and then we're going to talk about the
today's paper on live look which
illustrates a interesting danger
in network and stack design so first let
me set the general scheme
scene by uh drawing a few network
pictures
um the network of course connects up
different hosts
at uh there's kind of
two ways um in which you can view the
connections is occurring
one is that in the in for nearby hosts
they're often connected
to what you what's essentially um the
same network
so there may be a single ethernet
and maybe this is a switch or a cable
and you might have a bunch of hosts
connected to this this ethernet
where hosts are maybe laptops
or servers or as it'll turn out routers
and
the way network software's designed is
to kind of try to ignore as much as
possible the details of exactly what
this network is that directly attac
attaches hosts it might be a single
cable which is probably the case
at the time today's paper was written
this might be an ethernet switch
this might be some sort of wi-fi
wireless lan and these
these things aren't wires at all but
rather radio links
but for the most part these these
differences in
sort of exactly what the local
connectivity is are kind of
totally papered over at a pretty low
level
in the networking stack
and so on each of these hosts there may
be different applications maybe there's
a
web browser here and you know http
server over here and they need to talk
to each other across this
this network now there's a limit to how
big you can build a single local area
network so
for which the abbreviation is usually
lan
local area network um and
the way to think about it maybe is that
a local area network is can be as large
as
the network in which it makes sense for
all the hosts to be able to see
all of each other's packets that is
sometimes hosts need to want to
broadcast to
all of the local hosts you know that
works fine with a dozen or
20 or 50 or maybe even 100 hosts but you
can't really
easily build single networks where all
the hosts can more or less directly talk
to each other
with more than say a few hundred hosts
and so to deal with that the way the
larger internet is constructed
is that there's a number of these
individual lands
maybe one at mit you know maybe one at
harvard
maybe one far away at
stanford and
there's some sort of connectivity
between them which you can think of as
routers so there might be a router
that's plugged into the mit local area
network and
also has perhaps a longer link to
the um to the harvard network
and in fact there's a network of routers
which is essentially the backbone of the
internet
um including long distance router to
router links
so there might be a longer link across
the country and maybe this router is
plugged into the
some local area network at stanford and
then we have hosts we have the sort of
more elaborate task in which we want to
host at mit to be able to talk through a
sequence of routers
to a host to stanford and this is called
routing
so we need to have a way for hosts at
mit to
to address to names individual hosts at
stanford
and we need some way to so that routers
near mit can look at a packet sent by
mit and say oh
that's a packet for emp for harvard or
packet for stanford or a packet that
you know needs to go somewhere in japan
or who knows what
so from the point of view of network
protocols
this local
this local communication is taken care
of by
ethernet protocols and this long
distance
communication is sort of layered on top
of that and taken care of by
ip or internet protocols that know how
to
route over long distances to distant
hosts
okay this is what a network looks like
in a nutshell
i would now want to talk about the
what's
inside the packets that move across an
ethernet or move across
the larger internet with an eye to
eventually
talking about the software that act that
in
hosts that has to process hosts and
routers that has to process those
packets
so let me start with the lowest level
and talk about what's inside
an ethernet packet so when two hosts
that are quite nearby attached to the
same cable or same wi-fi network or same
ethernet
want to talk to each other um the
sort of lowest level protocol
which allows two hosts on the scene land
to talk to each other is the ethernet
protocol
and you can think of one host
host one
sending a frame over the over the
ethernet to host two
what's called an ethernet frame which is
the ethernet work for a packet
and it's a series of bytes that are sent
over the ethernet from one host to
another and what the ethernet protocol
does is have
just enough information in it to
allow the two hosts to realize who's
talking to each other and
cause the host to be able to recognize
packets that are addressed to them
and so when an ethernet header looks so
the way that ethernet deals with this is
that every ethernet packet
has at the beginning
a header that has three fields
followed by some ethernet payload
and what's in the header is two
ethernet addresses we'll call them the
destination address
and the source address and also the type
of the packet
each of these addresses is a just a
48-bit number
that uniquely identifies a particular
network interface card really
and this type field is going to indicate
to the recipient
host what it's supposed to do with that
packet and what that really means is
what higher level protocol
should examine and process the payload
of that ethernet pack
so these these are bits that go um are
typically said to go over the wire
these 48 plus 48 plus 16 bits of header
and then however much payload and not
really visible to the software but
there's going to be something at the
beginning of the packet that's
recognized at a very low level by the
hardware that signifies the start of a
packet
and the receiving hose needs to know
when the packet ends and so there's
going to be another
sort of special bit pattern at the end
that signifies the end of the packet
these two begin and end flags are never
seen by the software
but the rest the rest of this ethernet
frame
is delivered by the network interface
card the nick at h2
to the software
if you've looked at the final lab for
the course
you'll see that the software we give you
includes a bunch of new files including
kernel slash net.h which contains a
whole bunch of
definitions of
packet headers for different network
protocols
and so this is just text taken directly
from this net.h file we give you
and it includes a description of the the
layout of the ethernet header um and
this this
software we give you actually uses
literally uses this struct definition
in order to parse incoming ethernet
packets that
is to pick apart the head to get the
destination and type and also it uses
this structure to format packets
so the host is really in charge of sort
of setting up and parsing this header
that's used by ethernet
any questions about uh ethernet packets
uh yeah i had a question please is is
the
bit pattern you mentioned that the
hardware uses to determine the start and
end of a packet similar to
the eop in the lab
which is uh end of packet no
no the eop is a is a separate
mechanism between the driver and the nic
to help them communicate
this is you know there's some electrical
scheme there's some slow level
electrical or optical
signaling scheme to transmit bits over
ethernet cables
and these flags have to do with um
they're
typically electrical
patterns that would not be legal inside
a packet
and so you know one scheme is to instead
of just sending
0 1 bits over the wire you can send you
could send
uh sequences of two signals so there's
four different
symbols possible with sequences of two
different
um you know electrical voltage levels or
something
and have two of the four possible
symbols indicate zero or one bits
in the body of the packet and have the
remaining two
indicate beginning and end and that was
in fact a scheme that was used years ago
much like that was used years ago on
ethernet i don't actually know how it
works now
okay uh something to know about these
addresses is that what these are 48-bit
addresses
the reason for the 48 bits is that they
wanted to make sure that there was
enough bits
to be able to give a unique uh address
to
every different nic ever manufactured so
there's a vast number of possible
addresses
the internal structure of these 48-bit
addresses is that the first
half the first 24 bits is a manufacturer
number
and this there's every manufacturer of
network interface cards of nyx
has its own manufacturer number so
that's the first 24 bits
and the second 24 bits is just any
number
can be any unique number assigned by the
manufacturer so manufacturers typically
assign them in just
ascending order so if you buy you know
half a dozen network interface cards
the network enterprise card each network
interface card has programmed into its
own
address and if you look at the address
you'll see that the high bits are the
same for these
six cards you bought from the same
manufacturer but the low
below 24 bits are probably six
sequential numbers
so these addresses are unique
but what they're not helpful in is
locating the destination hosts so if you
know the host you're talking about is on
the same local area network as you
you can use a ethernet address and
it's on the same local area network so
it will be listening for packets with
its own address
but if the host you're trying to talk to
is in the other side of the country you
have to use a different scheme and
that's what's ip is all about
which i'll talk about in a bit
okay so this is what these packets look
like
you can actually look at ethernet
packets
in action using the tcp dump program and
you're encouraged to do this you'll
probably need to do this as part of the
lab
and this is actually uh
the output of tcp dump from the lab
and what tcp dump is telling us here was
telling us a whole bunch of things this
first part is the time at which the
packet
arrived um if you like you can try this
on your laptops if you install tcpdump
um and the rest of the first line is
a sort of human readable
interpretation of what kind of packet
that is and then these next three lines
or the this part here is a hex
dump of the of the received packet
and you can see we can actually follow
along with the
ethernet header there's these first
48 bits or six bytes is a broadcast
address all
f's and all f's ethernet addresses
broadcast all the hosts
on the local network the next 48 bits
is the sending host's ethernet address
which
um you know we can't necessarily tell
anything about
although uh the high bits i mean in fact
this was generated by
xv6 running under qmu so no real nick
was involved
so it's not actually a manufacturer
number up here it's just something that
qmu makes up and then the next 16 bits
the next
two bytes is the type it's the ethernet
type of the packet in this case it's
0806 which is a protocol called arp
which i'll talk about in a moment
and the rest of this stuff is is the
payload
of an art packet which i'll also talk
about
any questions about what we're um what
we're looking at here
this is well worth trying out on your
own computer if you care about networks
okay so um the next protocol that's of
relevance to the lab and communication
over an ethernet
is called arp so at the ethernet level
every host has a 48-bit ethernet address
but for communicating over the internet
it turns out you need to use a
32-bit internet address and the reason
why
internet addresses are different is that
internet addresses have internal
structure
in the in a 32-bit in a host's 32-bit
internet address
the high bits are full of all kinds of
hints
about where in the entire internet this
packet needs to go
and so you can think of an internet
address as having in the high bits a
network number
it's actually a little more complex than
that but it's essentially a network
number every network and the internet
has a distinct number and routers look
at these the high bits in the internet
address
to decide which router on the internet
this packet needs to be forwarded to
um and then the low bits in a 32-bit
ethernet internet
internet address ip address are the
number of that
of the host we want to talk to on
its local network um but when a packet
finally arrives
um at a when the internet packet arrives
at a
ethernet we need some way to give in a
32-bit ip address
figure out the 48-bit ethernet address
of that host
and the way the internet chooses to do
that is to have a
dynamic resolution protocol a kind of
request response protocol called art
for address resolution protocol and the
way to think about it is that
when a ip packet arrives at a router or
it
needs to be sent by a host to a host
that's known to be on the same lan
local area network the sender first
broadcasts on that lan an art packet
that's a request that says whoever has
whoever owns this ip address
please respond with your 48-bit ethernet
address
and assuming that host exists and is
turned on
it'll respond with an arp response
packet
and this is the format of the packet of
an art packet
the way it actually shows up is inside
an ethernet packet
and so you what you would actually see
in the network is
first the ethernet header which has the
48-bit source field and a 48-bit
destination field
maybe it's destination source type so
this is the ethernet header
and then from the ethernet point of view
the rest is payload but actually it's an
art that in the
ethernet payload is an art packet which
has
these fields um boom boom boom right
after the ethernet
uh header and the way the receiving host
knows is in our packet
is by looking at this type field and if
it's 0806
that's the agreed on ethernet protocol
number for arp
and then the receiving host software
would know to hand this packet to its
arp protocol processing code
what's in these packets and there's a
bunch of junk here that basically
amounts to saying
i have a internet address i want to turn
it into an ethernet address
please respond if you own this internet
address
and then these fields
hold the internet and ethernet
addresses um of whatever host is sending
this art packet and that's enough to
figure out the car
for who's to build dynamically tables
that tell them the correspondence
between ethernet and ip addresses
again we can use tcp dump in order to
see these packets go by and you're
highly likely to see them if you run tcp
done here's
um again a tcp dump output taken
from the lab and it turns out that
in the lab you're gonna your xv6 will
end up
talking simulated true but talking
ethernet protocol and sending ip packets
through
ethernet through a simulated ethernet
protocol with whatever host you're
running qm you want
and so when you want you'll actually be
able to see these
arp exchanges between xv6 and your host
and so what we're seeing here is
my host wants knows the ip address
of my xv6 and wants to wants to figure
out its ethernet address
on the lan the qmu simulates and
this second packet is my xv6
and you can see the code for the
generates is my xv6 has seen this
request
realize that it's the owner of the ip
address in the request
and is sending back the response tcp dub
has nicely parsed out
the fields in the art packet and printed
them here and i think
this is the sender's ip address
and this is the request sorry
this is the sender's ip address this is
the
ip address that the sender is interested
in and those would
presumably go in here and here
and this is the response
with the ethernet address
of the owner of this ip address and this
ethernet address would probably
end up being in this field and if we're
clever enough we can pick apart these
packets and see some of these fields
as we know this part
is the ethernet header destination
ethernet address source ethernet address
and packet type
0806 working backwards
this is the tip field which is the ip
address that the sender
wants to find the ethernet address for
and
if you pick this apart there's one byte
for each of the four fields of the ip
address
sorry it's really looking for 10 0 215
this is 10 hex zero hex two hex 15 hex
and then there's the targets
ethernet address which is not known and
then the sender's ip address 1022
and the senders ethernet address and a
bunch of other junk here saying that
we're interested in ethernet and
ip address formats
and here's the course this is a request
this is a response
any questions about arp um
yeah question um
why is it necessary for the sender to
include its
ip address if it if the its ethernet
address is already
um included in the packet like to
respond to it wouldn't
it wouldn't the the receiver only need
the ethernet address
yeah i don't know why that all this
stuff's in there um i think you if you
wanted to you could strip this down
quite a bit
um you know like the scent
well okay maybe the answer is that this
protocol was designed to be usable on
networks other than ethernet and so it
was designed to be fairly self-contained
so that it didn't depend on anything
didn't in on anything else and therefore
the arp header has a copy of the
ethernet addresses
now in fact if you know you're sending
arp over ethernet the ethernet packet
also has all the ethernet addresses as
you can see here
um so it's redundant if you
running rp over ethernet but maybe if
you were running arp over something else
um you'd need these fields because maybe
something else packet format doesn't
have the
doesn't already include these addresses
i see okay thank you
yeah oh sorry what is that part
on the right versus are you oh this okay
this this is not interesting yet but
this is
a ascii interpretation of these bytes
so well it's a the dot here corresponds
to
you know a heck a byte that has no ascii
equivalent
and this i guess somewhere in here 52 or
probably 52 is probably r and 55 is
probably you
and ascii so this would be more
interesting when we start sending
packets that have actual ascii text in
them rather than
binary fields okay i see thank you
yes okay and i'm showing you this
because you'll see these packets in the
lab
okay um
actually there's something i wanted to
uh
well there's a
something i want to make sure that you
all caught in this discussion and
that's the habit in um
formatting packets of nesting protocols
and nesting headers so
so what we just saw was a packet that
had an ethernet header
and ethernet payload the first part of
the ethernet payload was
you know an r petter and as it happens
arp has no remaining payload
but there are other what we'll see in a
moment is much more complicated
structures in which we have an ethernet
packet
that contains an ip packet and inside
the ip packet
is a udp packet and so you know udp is
another protocol that you can run over
ip
so there's a udp header it also
you know you don't necessarily have to
understand these acronyms yet but
this udp header a udp packet also has a
header and a payload um and there's
times when you
carry another protocol inside udp so for
example the domain name
system has yet another format of packet
defined that fits inside udp so what you
see is that
hosts that are sending packets will
build up a packet the dns software will
say i want to send a packet over udp
the udp software will prepend a udp
header we need to send that over ip the
ip
software will prepend an ip header the
ethernet software will prepare an
ethernet header and gradually build up
packets in
in that software when it's sending and
similarly when a system receives packets
it first gets the whole packet inspects
the first header
and knows it's ethernet because it
receives it from an ethernet nic
you know check some validity strips off
this header to look at the next header
and there'll be a type this you know
always a either a type field or
in this case a protocol field that tells
the software
what to expect after the ethernet header
so there's a tight field that indicates
ip versus arp and so this the software
will
will look at each header validate it
strip it off revealing the next header
you know
check that head or interpret it figure
out what it means strip it off revealing
the next and sort of hand it on to the
next layer of software
um i'll talk a bit more about this but
this is a sort of universal way of
looking at
these nested packet headers
all right so the ethernet packet the
ethernet header
is enough to get a packet to a host on
the
local area network and when especially
when
and if you want to send an ip packet
locally
you can use arp but ip is used much more
generally ip's the
sort of layer of the protocol that helps
you deliver a packet anywhere in the
internet
based on ip addresses
and so this is the format of an ip
packet again
taken you can find it in net.h and the
source we give you
um and over ethernet at least the way
you'd see this
is um in an ethernet packet with
destination source and type of uh
ethernet type equals 0800
and then the ip header and then ip
payload um
when you send a packet to a distant
network you know on the other side of
the world
the ip header gets passed along you know
the
this ethernet header gets stripped off
after you leave
the local ethernet maybe a new one gets
put on at
for each hop that your packet is routed
but the ip header stays basically the
same
uh the whole way from the ultimate the
original source host
you know your computer all the way to
the destination so this
header has sort of global significance
whereas the ethernet header
is really only used for each um
for a single local area network so there
has to be enough information here to
carry a packet all the way to
the far side of the internet and the
critical fields
for our purposes is really three very
interesting fields in this packet
format the
destination field which is the 32-bit ip
address
of the host that we want to send the
pack to and in particular when it's high
bits it's going to have
network numbers in it that will help
routers and then when the packet's
delivered this p
protocol field will tell the destination
host
what to do with the packet not what to
do with it next after it
strips off the ip header
and if you've ever seen a mit ip address
uh you'll see well there's a couple
different ones but for example if you
see an
uh internet address starting with 18
this things have actually changed in the
last couple years but
this for a long time was the network
number of
mit and so most hosts at mit would have
ip addresses whose high
byte was 18 and routers all over the
world would have some table
they'd look up 18 and say ha i know how
to route this packet one step closer to
mit
so let me let me show you again tcp dump
output again actually taken from the lab
that includes
an ip header okay so
we can parse this packet because it was
sent over the
ethernet it starts with an ethernet
header
um it actually one
thing that's kind of wrong with these
tcp dump with these packets that are
generated and
now that i'm seeing it i'm not sure what
the problem is um
they should not start with all these
ethernet headers shouldn't start with
all
fs because that's the broadcast address
that causes the packet to go to every
host
and you would not see that for a packet
sent between two individual hosts as
this one is
on a real network so there's something
funny going on with my
solution to the network lab or with qmu
anyway we have the
ethernet destination address ethernet
source
address and the ethernet type and 0800
is means that the remaining bytes or
ip packet the ip packet
header length i think is 20 bytes
um let's see if we can find the end
so this must be the end of the ip header
and working backwards because these are
the fields we really care about
the destination ip field is
as101022
which is i think the in qmu's funny
simulated network is the address of the
real computer i'm
running qmu on and then before that is
this
ip source address which is 100 215
which is the sender which is qmu's
address for the
for xv6 basically running inside qmu and
then
this stuff before it is all this other
stuff there's a 16-bit checksum
which your software is supposed to check
to realize that a packet's been
corrupted and should be discarded that's
this
checksum there's a one byte
all right mess something up here
oh this is this is 16 sorry this is 16
bit check sum
this 11 is the protocol number which is
particularly important
11 hex is 16 plus 1 or 17.
so that means that this is a udp packet
based on the protocol field
and then all this other stuff we don't
really care about it has things like the
length of the packet
any questions about ip headers
all right again the critical stuff is
the
ip header has the ip address the source
of destination
and this protocol field is going to tell
the
destination hosts networking stack that
this package should be processed by its
udp software
which i'll talk about right now
okay the um this this ip header
is enough to get a packet to any host on
the internet
um but we want to do better than that
every host you know is running lots and
lots of different programs that need to
use the network
they need to send and receive packets on
the network and so we need
a way that's not in the eye that's it's
not included in the ip field
in order to decide which application um
needs to which application on the target
host
this packet ought to be handed off to
and there's a couple of protocols that
do that job one of them is tcp
which is quite complex another is udp
tcp is actually what's used mostly for
things like the web
tcp is a very complex protocol that not
only
helps your packet be delivered to the
right application but also has
a lot of things like sequence numbers in
order to
detect lost packets and re-transmit them
make sure packets are data is delivered
in order and without gaps if
in case anything goes wrong udp is a
much simpler protocol
that just delivers a sort of best effort
delivery of a packet to a particular
application but
without any error correction or
well basically without anything else for
us the
critical fields are these two port
numbers
and the game here is that when your
application
wants to send or receive packets it uses
the what's called the sockets api
on unix at any rate and this is a set of
system calls
whereby a process can say look i'm
interested in packets
addressed to a particular port and it'll
say
what port number it's interested sorry
packets with this particular
i want to receive packets with a
particular destination port
and the operating so you make a system
call it
sets this up and the operating system
will return a file descriptor
and every time a packet arrives with the
port that the application asks for
that packet will appear on the file
descriptor and the application can read
it
and the these ports there's really two
kinds of
ports some are well known port numbers
like
i think port 53 is the official
well-known universally agreed port
number for
a dns name server so if you want to send
a request to a dns name server
you're going to send it in a udp packet
addressed to deport 53
and there's a bunch of other sort of
well-known ports for
commonly available services with
universally agreed on numbers and then
the remaining
remainder of the 16-bit port number
space
is used for the sort of anonymous client
and support so if
um i want to send a packet to a dns
server
its d port will be 53 all right but its
s port will be
a more or less randomly chosen number
for my end
so that when the that'll be associated
with my applications
socket so that when the dns server sends
a reply it'll be addressed
that the dns server will copy the
request
source port into the destination port
field of the reply
send it back to my machine and my
machine will use this port number to
figure out which application should get
the reply
okay so the main function here is to
have these two port numbers
in order to hand out be able to hand off
packets to individual applications
on this machine
so feel free to ask questions
i have tcp dump output for
udp also again taken from the lab um
so again we have an ethernet header
and a 20 by
ip header which probably ends here the
11 is
ip protocol 17 which is udp so the
receiving host will know to
process it with its udp software
the next eight bytes
are the udp header which is shown right
here
and so who knows what these port numbers
are
i mean now this this is unfortunately a
package is generated by the lab software
without any
um any special numbers in it so these
are just the port numbers that happen to
choose
this must be the length of the packets
1b is
20 something and this my you know this
our software for udp and xv6 is so lame
that it uh
doesn't fill in the checksum field but
this is the header
and then after the udp header is the
payload of the udp packet
and in this case the application is
sending ascii text
and that ascii text is right here
so this is a masking text placed inside
a udp packet place inside an
ip packet the police inside an ethernet
packet and
sent over a simulated ethernet
oh sorry i just had a question so when
when you
when you said when you send a package to
someone you don't know their
ethernet i like address so do you just
send it to your router then and then the
router
figures it out from there if um if
for for most for packets sent somewhere
else on the internet
um let's see
your host if you send a packet to a
particular ip address
your host software will look at the
destination address to figure out
if the target host is on the same local
area network as you are
and if it is it'll use arp
to translate the ip address into an
ethernet address and then send the
packet
over the ethernet to the target host so
that's what happens is sort of in the
special case in which the target host is
on the same network
in the more general case where you're
sending the packet to somewhere else on
the internet
you know across the country you'll send
the packet to
a router on the same local area network
that router will look at the destination
ip
address to pick the next router to
decide
which router it's attached to it should
forward the packet to in the packet will
go hop by hop through routers getting
closer and closer to the target
does that answer your question okay i
see yes thank you so much
someone asked if there's a limit to the
length of a packet and the answer is yes
there's a couple of different limits
every network every underlying network
technology like ethernet
but there are other things that are like
ethernet
has its own maximum packet length
so when today's paper was written the
maximum packet length was
on ethernet it was 1500 bytes i think
modern ethernets
allow packets up to around 9000 or 10
000 bytes
but that's about the highest maximum
packet size i've heard of and the reason
there's a couple of reasons why you
wouldn't want sort of
infinitely long single packets one of
them is that
the packets are you're sending these
packets over wires they could be quite
long and subject to noise and
interference
and so you do get corruption of bits
when you're sending packets
uh basically every networking technology
is some kind of
checksum or error correcting code that
goes along with every packet
but uh checksums and error correcting
codes are only capable of reliably
detecting errors
over a certain number of bits which and
so as you increase the number of bits
the probability of an uncaught error
goes up and up
and so that limits the for a reasonable
size checks on like
16 or 32 bits that limits the maximum
size of a packet
and the other limitation is that if you
send huge packets
that means that all the routers and hose
and volt have to
have huge packet buffers to be prepared
to receive
huge packets and
that starts to get unwieldy and
expensive
because it's difficult to have variable
length buffers it's most convenient to
have just
a single length of buffer and that works
best if the maximum packet length isn't
too enormous anyway so for ethernet for
so ethernet has a 1500 or
9000 byte limit in addition you know for
all these ip protocols have length
fields which are uh
16 bits so even if you are willing to
have ethernet have a larger packet size
ip itself has a kind of baked in
a maximum pack a size of 64 kilobytes
okay
okay good so much for udp
and hopefully when you finish the lab
you'll see output very much like this
in particular the message from xv6 and
a message a reply back from the host
that you're running
running qmu on
in fact actually at the end of the lab
you'll use
you'll run software which we provide
which will actually send a dns query to
google's dns servers
and get the response back and our
software will print the response but
your software will have done the sort of
ethernet level
device driver interactions
all right so that's the story for packet
headers
and protocols on the wire so
corresponding to these packet formats
is this what's called the stack of
network software that runs on the host
so
if you think about what's sitting inside
the host um
and then from now on i'm talking and
mostly talk about sort of
typical software arrangements there's
all kinds of different ways people
structure network software
um and um somewhat
quite different from what i'm going to
talk about but i'm going to talk about
kind of the
what i think of this at least is the
sort of standard approach so
you know let's assume we're running
linux or maybe xv6 um
and we have a bunch of applications
maybe a web browser
maybe a dns server
who knows what a bunch of applications
they'll have used the sockets api to
open up file descriptors
in the sockets layer so this is going to
be this
inside the kernel
a layer software called the sockets
layer that
remember has tables that remembers the
correspondence between file descriptors
which the applications read or write and
um
udp port numbers or tcp port numbers
which is
for the um the sort of end points of
conversations that these file
descriptors refer to so the socket layer
has these
tables of file descriptors and port
numbers and it also typically has a
queue of packets that have arrived and
are waiting
to be read by each socket or file
descriptor
and the software we provide you has a
very primitive sockets layer
underneath that are going to be um
the udp and tcp protocol
layers
udp has almost nothing going on it
basically looks at incoming packets
extracts the destination port number and
hands the packet off to the socket layer
to
so the payload is enqueued on the
correct file descriptor's incoming queue
tcp actually is much more complex it
keeps state for each tcp connection and
it
remembers all kinds of sequence numbers
and packets that haven't been
acknowledged and need to be
transmitted so there's a huge amount of
state in what's called a
protocol control block in tcp
and virtually no state in the udp layer
these are often called transport layers
udp and tcp
and we provide you with a simple udp
layer but not
a tcp layer underneath tcp and ip is a
ip layer
which is often fairly simple
and kind of in parallel with the ip
layer i'm not sure whether i should draw
it on the same level or underneath
it is the r player
under them both we can think of as an
ether layer but it's really
there's not typically a separate
ethernet layer typically there's a
one or more nic drivers
at the lowest layer and these talk to
the actual nik network interface
hardware
which itself has a connection off to the
local area network or
whatever kind of network you're attached
and sort of at this level what happens
is the packet arrives
off the network the nic you know pulls
it off the network
um hands it off to the driver and the
driver
essentially pushes the network to pack
it up the networking stack
um and at each layer in the stack the
you know that layers header
you know the ip layer we'll look the ip
header
verify the header strip it off hand it
to udp udp will figure out
what file descriptor to cue the data on
and add it to that queue
now so packets come in and are parsed
and headers are stripped in the way up
and when a application sends a packet
the reverse thing happens as the packet
moves down through the layers
more and more headers are added on until
you get to the bottom layer and then the
packet's handed to the nic for
transmission
um and so of course the software
the way people think about and design
network software in the kernel is
typically
driven by the nesting of the protocols
inside the packets
any questions about this structure
there's actually one important thing
that i kind of left out here that sits
on the side
there's buffers there's packet buffers
all through this so when a packet
arrives it's copied into a
packet buffer and the packet buffers are
sort of
sent up and down the stack and there's
often quite a few packet buffers
there's often cues between these layers
there's certainly a queue here
a packet's waiting to be processed by
applications
and this will be a linked list of
buffers
and so there's a buffer allocator that's
this
buffer scheme and a buffer allocator
that's used throughout the stack
um and in the software we give you uh
these
the buffer scheme is called m-buffs so
it's kind of a
m-buff
scheme that's not a layer but it's used
all throughout these layers
okay this is the layering diagram of
sort of typical network stack
for this paper it's actually important
to understand how the control flow works
which is
maybe a little bit different from what's
in that diagram um
one thing to know about network stacks
is that there's typically
multiple independent actors that process
packets and take input
think about those packets and produce
output and for various reasons
these different actors are decoupled so
they can run concurrently and have
packet cues connecting them so that's
extremely important from the point of
view of this paper
so within the kernel so again we have a
network interface card and then we have
the kernel
um the uh a classic arrangement here
is for uh the nick to somehow get
packets
um well for the nic when it receives a
packet
to generate and interrupt and there's so
there's this
interrupt routine that gets triggered
whenever there's an interrupt and this
job of the interrupt routine
is to get the packet from the nic
and because we don't want to dedicate
cpu time to
completing the processing of the packet
now the interrupt routine typically just
appends the packet to a queue of packets
um for later processing and then returns
so it sort of does the minimum work
um required to get the packet from the
nic and put it in a queue
and the reason why we want to transfer
or in the sort of
traditional network stack we want to
quickly move the packet out of the nic
and into this software cube is that
nicks typically have a very limited
amount of memory for queuing packets
whereas in the main memory the ram and
the computer we might have gigabytes of
memory we have so far more space here
so the neck so if there's a burst of
packets the neck may actually
run out of space to cue them so we copy
them this cue here to
avoid the nick running out of space and
then
separately perhaps in a separate thread
there's um
what i'll call the ip processing thread
and sometimes it's not a thread
sometimes it's a sort of different kind
of entity
but it's basic job is to to read
packets off these incoming queues and
there may be multiple nics
uh you know appending packets to these
queues so our ip thread runs it
looks at packets that are queued here
and decides what to do
with them one possibility is to send
them up through udp
into the sockets layer to be queued
waiting for some application
and typically this will just be a
function calls here within the
context of this thread
another possibility and this is the
possibility the paper cares most about
is that
this host is actually a router and its
packets are coming in one nic
and routed out one or more other nics
because
it's very common to build routers out of
ordinary
operating systems like linux like if you
buy a wi-fi box now or a cable
modem router or something it's extremely
likely to be running
linux internally and to use the standard
linux stack which
has a complete router implementation
it's highly likely to be using the
standard linux stack in order to do its
routing
so if the ip thread looks at the
destination ip address and decides oh i
should send this out
i should forward this packet out you
know out another
network interface
it'll add the packet to a queue of
outgoing packets
for this outgoing interface and there's
almost certainly so this is a receive
interrupt
or rx for receive um there's usually
some sort of transmit
interrupt scheme
for the outgoing nick
that and the nick will interrupt
whenever it's finished sending one
packet and is ready to be handed
more packets so these outgoing
interrupts
may also be important um and
the point here is that there's a bunch
of concurrent entities
um that are sort of separately scheduled
in various different ways
these interrupts are triggered by the
knicks asking for interrupts when
packets arrive or when packets have been
sent
this thread may be a
kernel thread like we have in xv6 and on
a unit processor
as was the case with today's paper you
know this thread can't run at the same
time as interrupt
interrupts have absolute priority on a
multi-core machine
uh there may be more parallelism and
then if it's important that applications
to be able to read the packets
uh the applications are yet another sort
of independently scheduled entities
um uh that we'd like uh to get their
chance at um
executing on the cpu
so these are all the players in the
in this in the scheduling game
essentially
uh one thing that comes up a lot
is uh buffering so there's
three cues here by buffering i mean
these structures in which one
independent entity appends
input packets and some other entity
pulls packets off the front of the queue
these queues are pervasive in networking
systems
one reason for them is to allow
temporary to cope with temporary bursts
you know this ip thread maybe can only
process packets at however many per
second
but the nick may be able to deliver
packets much more quickly
and so there may be a little sort of
temporary burst of packets we'd like to
have somewhere to put them
um waiting for the ip thread to get
around to processing them and so that
that's one use of cues on the output
side
uh another use of queues is we like to
um especially if packets are bursty we'd
like to be able to
stack up a bunch of packets here ready
for the nick to send to keep the nic
to output nick busy because
depending on the speeds of things it may
be quite important to be able to hunt to
utilize a hundred percent
of the network here
and the other reason for or maybe the
same reason stated differently for
having queues is is to be able to
structure software
into independent parts that are
scheduled separately
like we wouldn't necessarily want to
have our ip thread or the application
know about the other things that have to
go on like interrupt processing
so the ip thread is sort of the
traditional
networking system you know doesn't
necessarily know
when interrupts happen or when
applications run
although we'll see in this paper that
there may be advantages to having a
little bit of knowledge there
questions about this sort of scheduling
control diagram
oh i have a good question so can the
same neck
not be used uh for both transmitting and
receiving
okay okay okay so my laptop really only
has one interface and it
connected to wi-fi when it receives a
packet this so on my laptop this nic is
actually a wi-fi
radio interface packets arrive and go
out on the same deck
the two nick situation is certainly used
for routers
so your home wi-fi i don't know maybe
you have i have wi-fi and cable
and there's a router box that has
two nicks one is the it's connection to
my cable modem which these are the rest
of the internet and the other one is my
the wi-fi interface
so the little box that the cable modem
cable company sent me is a router
with two network interfaces
and there's actually a lot of servers
have multiple interfaces also
especially ones that are web servers
that you know you want to talk to the
outside world
out one winter face and to your private
sensitive database
machine or something on a totally
separate network
on a with another network interface
so this arrangement's pretty common the
criteria for having multiple nics is
just uh
wanting to talk to different networks
then yeah
okay yeah if you want to talk to
different networks then you would have
multiple links yes
all right i want to as an aside talk a
little bit more about um
nick's what nicks do with packets when
they arrive and this is
of a special relevance to the lab
um you uh
you know though what a nick looks like
internally
um you know it's got a a cable leading
or a radio leading to the
from the outside world um you know and
it looks at electrons as they come in
and sort of turns them into packets um
and then there's the host uh and there's
the host has some sort of driver
software in it
and one way or another you know we need
to get a
a packet that's decoded in the nick into
memory
where the ip software in the host
can parse that packet and so there's a
lot of different schemes been designed
over the years
the paper scheme is that the nic has a
lot of
internal memory and as packets arrive
the only thing
the only immediate thing that happens is
the nic puts you know lays down the
packets in its own buffer memory
and that's it and interrupts the uh
host the host and so that the nic has an
internal queue
of packets and a bunch of memory and
then in the interrupt
well in the host driver the host driver
has a loop in it the host driver
will talk to the neck and say you know
many packets buffered and if it does now
the host has a
loop that will just copy you know by
byte or word by word
copy this packet into the um memory of
the host and append it to a queue
inside the host so that's how the papers
nick works the driver
is responsible for doing the copy from
nick memory to host memory
that made a lot of sense 30 years ago
today though it turns out that loops in
the cpu that
copy uh that you know talk to external
hardware or hardware
sitting on buses are very very slow this
sort of there's a
you know in the grand scheme of
microprocessor design
this distance here between the cpu
and an external device even if it's on
the same
computer this is a very long distance
and this each
conversation today takes a long time for
each back and forth chit chat and
so you don't want to have a lot of bite
by by
interaction um so people don't design
high speed interfaces like this anymore
so a much more modern arrangement
looks like this and so now i'm going to
talk about an arrangement which
shows up in the e1000 nick
which you'll use in the lab
or simulation of which uh the way the
e1000 nick works
and so has his wire and it's looking at
the electrons but
as the packets arrive the nick
writes them the nick
doesn't really have significant internal
buffering although it has a little bit
it actually copies the packets directly
into host memory where they'll be
sitting there in host memory
waiting for the driver to pick them up
sort of already copied
um but that means that nick has to know
where in memory it should put each
packet
so the way the e1000
nick works is that the host software
formats up what's called rings dma rings
of packet pointers so dma ring is just
an array
of pointers
to packet buffers
so the post host driver when it's
initialized in the card will allocate
however many say 16
1500 byte packet buffers will create a
array of 15 pointers or 16 pointers and
make these pointers point to there and
then it'll tell the nick in
configuration time
look uh here's the
ring so this is called a dma ring
because uh after you've gone off the end
you start back at the beginning
uh the driver software will tell them
look here's here's a pointer the address
in my ram of the ring
the dma ring that you're supposed to use
to deposit
incoming packets so when a packet
arrives the nick will actually remember
which ring entry is the next one
well it has a little
pointer here that allows it to remember
the next entry that it should dma a
packet into when a packet arrives
the nick will fetch the pointer out of
this fetch this buffer point or out of
the host ram
copy the pack and bytes into this buffer
and then advance its internal
index here to point to the next ring
slot which we'll use for the next packet
and there's a similar so this will be
the rx ring
for receive there's a similar ring that
the driver sets up
in which the driver puts packets
that it wants the nic to send so that
nick also has a pointer to the
tx ring and so you'll learn your job in
the lab is basically to write the
driver software that handle these rings
any questions about this arrangement
yeah uh how does the e1000
compare with you know production level
mix that may be used in high performance
environments
like that well when the u1000 came out
it was the
absolute best nick available
and it was the neck that was used in
serious production environments but that
was however many years ago
modern knicks um are quite a bit clever
the what hasn't changed that much is
this dma ring
structure you still find that nicks
they use dma to deliver packets and the
way they find the place to deliver the
packet is by these
rings of buffer pointers the
main there's a couple things that are
that modern knicks are
more clever about um one is that modern
knicks you can set them up with many
many
cues the e1000 i think just has a single
receive queue
but you can tell a modern nick look you
know i i want you to split my packets up
into 32 different
incoming queues and here's how to decide
for each packet you know look at this
field and use that to
choose which ring to dma the packet into
um and there's a whole bunch of clever
ways that people use that capability
like
if you have multiple virtual machines
you're amazon and you're running many
guest virtual machines you may use that
capability to
sort of direct each packet to the queue
corresponding to the virtual machine
that that packet should be read by
and another way in which modern licks
are more clever is that they'll do some
of the
tcp processing on the nic like maybe
typically check some calculations the
most
thing anyway yeah so
modern x would like the e1000 but more
okay thanks
sorry go ahead oh yeah i just wanted to
ask so in our scheme in the lab
um there there is no cue between the ip
layer and the driver right
yeah yeah the lab network stack is
stripped down to the absolute minimum
this okay far
simpler and structured than a real
network stack
but this is worse in terms of
oh i don't know okay i never run it in
real life i'm sure
i mean they've certainly we paid zero
attention to performance
when writing the lab network stack so it
would be surprising
mostly it's not a question of
performance there's limitations it
doesn't do
95 of what you need a network stack to
do like
uh handle multiple nics or
have tcp right right
okay i see thank you okay
um uh sorry uh so
uh were there any like hardware changes
to
um like the overall system that were
needed to
to enable like nyx to have direct memory
access
like in the previous picture um was
everything mediated through the cpu or
or could nix also like reach it that
memory directly
in the picture i showed before now the
neck doesn't reach in the memory at all
um the the okay
um i actually don't know i mean
the the maybe the most important
question is how virtual memory whether
and how
virtual memory translation works when
nick
wants to use an address that refers to
host memory and
i don't actually know how that works i
don't know how that works
i suspect there's a translation
you know the nick is really sitting on a
bus that's connected with
you know through some fairly intelligent
silicon to the
to the dram system and i believe in
modern machines you can set up
translation tables so that the nic
could use virtual addresses or addresses
that are translated
by this hardware that sits between it
and ran and that could be very valuable
for some situations
the other thing
another thing that i'm aware of is that
if the nick is going to write some
memory or read some memory and the
memory is
cached on the cpu
you you know you want the nick to read
if if the software just you know wrote
a packet buffer but the cpu hasn't
the cpu is merely cached uh the right
because after all
uh most memory is right back um
that means that the real latest version
of that memory is sitting on the cpu
cache not in ram and in that case
we'd like the nick to be reading the cpu
cache not the ram if it does dma
and certainly on intel machines and
probably on others
there's some fairly elaborate machinery
so that if the nic
reads some memory but the latest copy of
that memories in the cpu cache this it's
the cpu cache that will produce the data
and not ram and that's
yeah that's that's actually a facility
you can that some clever
software uses to get high performance
that is to
have the effect of having them this
happens for writes also that the nic
will essentially directly write cache
lines in the cache where it's
the cpu can get at the data very quickly
yeah so they're simple but the real life
it's
pretty involved other questions about
about anything
okay um i'd like to switch gears now to
today's paper
and i'm just gonna like because we've
already talked about the
sort of a lot of the background of this
paper i'm just gonna go directly
to the first graph in the paper
um and essentially drive
the discussion off of the paper's graphs
um and so what we're looking at here is
the performance graph for a router
um on the x-axis there's a router with
two nicks so it's job is to package them
in one nick and it's supposed to just
send them out the other nick the x-axis
is the arrival rate
which packets arrive at the input nic
and the y-axis is the output rate at
which packets are observed
to leave the output nick
and the line we care about is the
is the um
filled circles which goes up and then
down
so even without knowing
anything about what's going on here we
can look at this graph and we can ask
ourselves gosh
why does it go up why does it go down
you know what's special about this point
that's an
inflection you know what is it that
governs how fast it goes up or how fast
it goes
down right so even with zero knowledge
we
kind of have a good clue about what
questions to ask so why does it go up
why do these thoughts go about
it's not a very deep question
they go up sorry go ahead oh because
when they're
like until it gets like saturated you
can
process more input packages and produce
more output packages
absolutely like until something starts
to go wrong
um for every packet that comes in the
router just forwards it out
so you know until things go wrong if
packets arrive at 2000 packets per
second well it just copies every input
packet to the output and that means that
the output rate is just equal to the
input rate so this is just y equals x
you know because every input packet gets
sent out so it's y equals x for a while
and so why does it stop going up
isn't this the the one thing they
mentioned in the paper about
uh the there being
interrupts that can't be processed
at the necessary rate that's the answer
to the question
why does it go down
my question is why does it stop going up
what is it that could this line in a
well-designed system supposing that they
hadn't messed up the design
right you and i would design a system
that didn't have problems
right would r in our system with a line
just keep going up
um i guess not because at some point the
rate at which packets come
will um if
if you can process packets fast enough
then
at some point um the
the bottleneck will be the rate at which
packets arrive
that's right the the system we're
talking about has has some
as sort of limits it's not the cpu is
not infinitely fast the cpu executes
however many instructions per second and
no more so
each of these packets has to be
processed the ip software has to look at
the header and check the checksum
and look up the destination addresses
and table whatever it takes
hundreds of thousands of cpu cycles per
packet
and so we can never never expect these
lines to go up indefinitely they must
stop somewhere
right and we can sort of tell what we
can make some guesses
on this system it goes up to 5000 and no
more
and what that basically suggests to us
is that it takes about 200 microseconds
on this computer to
process each packet right that's what
this
point the fact that the inflection point
is here means suggests
that the total cost of processing a
packet is around 200 microseconds of cpu
time
yeah that it's a guess but it's likely
to be close to correct
and so there's just no way we could get
you know maybe we could make the
software a little more efficient maybe
we could reduce that to 150 microseconds
per packet or something and
so maybe we could move the inflection
point up a bit but we're certainly faced
with
some point at which well that's just how
many packets
this system can process um
now um that's not necessarily what's
going on here it happens to be what's
going on here but it didn't it's not
written in stone um in fact the
there's other bottlenecks that could be
the limit other than
uh cpu time which are worth considering
the most obvious is the speed of the
network the network they were using ran
at only 10 megabits per second that's
just how fast the
low level networking hardware
sent bits and so it can never transmit
more than 10 000
10 million bits per second um
and so that may also constitute a limit
and so we're thinking about whether
maybe that's actually what's determining
this 5000.
um
i don't act the paper doesn't quite say
enough to know
whether it's whether it's cpu or the nic
that's the limiting factor here
um but the fact is with the with their
10 megabit network
if you send small packets it can
the 10 megabits translates into
something like 10 or 15
000 packets per second so that's the
limit that the
networking cable puts on the input
rate and so this is well under uh
the 10 or 15 000 packets per second that
the network is capable of so almost
certainly the limit has to do with
cpu or memory or something and not the
not the network itself okay
um what we love to see
in a well-designed router is that um
that it can actually have you know if it
takes 200 microseconds to forward a
packet
to process a packet what we'd like to
see is that the thing the router can
actually forward 5000 packets per second
no matter what even if the load is high
so what we'd
like to have seen is this line here
where the
output rate matches the input rate until
you get up to the capacity of the system
you know 5000 packs per second and then
it just continues to
forward 5000 packets per second and
presumably drops
discards the rest
so this is what we'd like to design but
what actually happened is much worse
than that
as you increase the rate beyond 5000 uh
the
number of packets that it manages the
forward goes down towards zero
so why does this line go down i think
somebody mentioned this before
well the the the
reason that the authors figured out is
that
as you increase the input rate each of
these input packets generates an
interrupt
and the interrupts take time actually on
their system the interrupts are quite
expensive because they involved
uh copying a packet off of the network
interface card and in domain memory
which
took a long time because the cpu was
doing it so each
so you know we know if packets arriving
at ten thousand per second we certainly
can't forward ten thousand
um that means the best we can hope for
is to forward five thousand
and simply discard the other five
thousand but in fact
the extra five thousand packets each a
very expensive interrupt
so for each additional packet over 5000
per second
we're generating more and more expensive
interrupts which have priority like
interrupts boy whatever you're doing
it stops the machine takes the interrupt
because the machine is essentially
giving priority these interrupts
that means every additional packet per
second is taking cpu time away
from the forwarding code
until finally 100 of the cpu time is
used up in the input interrupt routine
and no cpu time is used uh in the thread
that
forwards packets
is everyone happy with this explanation
and this going down um
is called interrupt live lock
the fact that this line goes down
instead of steering flags is what people
mean
by interrupt live lock um and
it's it's actually a phenomenon that
occurs
um in many systems
i mean the sort of thing that's driving
it is that there's two separate tasks
like the input interrupt task and the
forwarding task
and because of a scheduling problem
essentially priority is given to the
input task which can starve
the packet processing task and in pretty
much any system
that has multiple independent tasks
or sort of sequence of independent tasks
that need to be done to each input
and in which the input rate can't
necessarily be controlled
many systems like that will exhibit live
lock if you push them too hard
and you can get live lock due to many
resources not just cpu but it could be
that the nic you know a nick that dmas
uses up ram cycles to do the dmas
and if the nic is using the ram the cpu
can't use the ram
so another way to get live lock even if
you have lots of cpu time
you know in some other design you might
get live lock because the nic
is using up uh
uh ram resources ram performance
resources so the cpu
is less able to use the ram anyway this
line going down is
is what they mean by live lock you may
ask what happens to the excess packets
um and if you recall the s
structure of their software was that
they have a nic
that basically feeds the receive
interrupt the received interrupt
software
copies each packet into a queue and then
there's
some sort of network thread um
that pulls packets off the queue the
exact place where packets are lost
are right here what's going to happen is
that the interrupt routine
um you know once we get down here was
serious
live lock the interrupt routine is going
to fill this q there's going to be some
maximum q length here you know
at least all the ram but probably much
less
and the interrupt routine is going to
pull a packet off the neck and see that
this queue
is already as long as it's allowed to be
and the interrupt routine will discard
the packet
um but then of course immediately after
that there'll be another interrupt
the rough routine will again discard the
next packet because
the network thread is always interrupted
and never allowed to run
questions about this diagram
is the most important diagram in the
paper
all right well um we've basically run
out of time so i'll try to compress
the answer to this problem into a minute
um the authors propose a solution
uh the most immediate good news about
the solution is that this is the
performance of their solution that is as
the input rate goes up
goes up to 5000 and then it's flat at
5000 regardless of input rate
so this is sort of a perfect non-live
lock
performance line of course it's going to
be flat because
you can only process 5000 packets per
second due to
the speed of the cpu and the way they
get this
they still have this network thread
and they still have an interrupt routine
um
and so the very first time the nick
interrupts um
it'll run the interrupt routine but the
interrupt routine does not copy
pakistanic
it wakes up the network thread and then
retr and
leaves interrupts on the neck disabled
so we'll get no more interrupts
wake up the networking thread and then
the interrupt routine will return so now
interrupts in the snake are turned off
the network thread basically has a loop
um that
uh it'll check the nick you know pull a
few packets
from the nic
five i think is what they ended up using
and then process those packets
um and then if there were none
if this uh it'll check that so it's this
networking thread now that reads packets
off the nick not the interrupt routine
if there were not no packets waiting it
enables interrupts
and then goes to sleep
because it's enabled interrupts um the
next time my packet arrives the inner
protein will wake up this thread
and i'll come out of sleep and go back
to the top of the loop so this just
this is the structure of their solution
and one way to view this
is that they turn an interrupt scheme
into a polling scheme
that is under high load they just sit in
this loop
and they read a packet process it read a
packet process it
with interrupts turned off so they did
since the interrupts are turned off they
never get this effect where they
interrupt steel time from the main
thread
whereas under low load they enable
interrupts
and maybe a while till packets arrive
but they'll be woken up
by the interrupt routine immediately if
a packet does right
and that's all i have to say any
questions
i have a question um is that loop
looking at all of the devices or only
the one that generated
the interrupt if there's multiple nics
so um there's a good question
if there's multiple nicks the loop i
don't actually know how the
how the loop worked um a very reasonable
design is for this network thread
to keep track of um for every
nic whether it's an interrupting mode or
polling mode
um and then it will only
actually because the interrupt routines
no longer read packets from the neck
that means the loop probably checks
every interface at this point
every probably checks every nick at this
point and
pulls up for every nick if it has a few
pack as
pack if that nick has packets waiting
the loop will pull a few out of the neck
and process them
and then if none of the nicks had
anything
if it checked all the necks and none of
them had any packets waiting
the loop will enable interrupts on all
the nicks and
sleep and any nick that interrupts will
wake it up
that's my guess okay yeah sounds
reasonable um i had a quick question
then so
how did the so so while the loop is
running how do packets
actually get into the cues to be
pulled i felt like there would only be
one at a time
initially then initially the packets are
cued inside the nic in its own private
memory
then this loop you know when it when it
goes back to the top of the loop
it'll look at each nick and
actually talk to the nik hardware and
ask it do you have any input packets
waiting in your memory
and if it does then this loop will will
you know allocate a packet buffer in ram
and copy the bytes of the packet out of
the nic
the packet buffer and then process that
packet buffer so you can copy
more than one packet yeah i think they
okay do do it in groups of five in order
to
even if there's a hundred packets
waiting here it would just process the
next five in order to be fair among
input nicks and to avoid
starting the output but this requires
increasing the memory capacity of the
nic
right possibly well
i don't know i don't know how much
the nick might have had a reasonable
amount of
the thing is this interrupt you know
this live lock phenomenon
like below this point we're probably
interrupting
and if a packet arrives
the network thread will almost
immediately be woken up and pull the
packet out
we're over here in this regime where too
many packets are arriving
and the this loop is polling instead of
interrupting
packets are going to be lost we just
know that because the difference
you know this difference between
the id the input rate and the output
rate
this is all dropped packets yep yep and
um adding i don't think adding because
these packers are going to be dropped
anyway
adding buffering to the neck doesn't
probably doesn't help very much
i i don't know i think it's a nick
it's not clear that nick needs more than
a small amount of buffering
yeah that that makes sense yeah you only
need as much as it would need
to take yeah to get saturated so
you know i think in their design they
would pull five packets of either quota
was five packets and so the next
certainly needs five packets of
buffering
oh that to make sense but it probably
anyway
it's not clear that more than that would
be very beneficial
um really the purpose of buffering is to
absorb
transient bursts um
so hold the packets long enough that the
software can get along to reading them
but we're not
talking about transient anything in this
situation we're talking about persistent
overload
so there's so that means there's not
really much function for a lot of
buffering
yeah makes sense thank you
um i think my question is related to
that it's
so if the difference between interrupts
on it in terms
of here is that it's going to be the
same but
like it's it's still going to be putting
things on the queue if it's
able to but it will just not issue an
interrupt but
if there is no place on the queue then
it will just drop
the interrupt the interrupt routine in
this new scheme
never looks at packets oh yes yeah i
mean like
uh you said that you turned off the
interrupts
for the nick right yeah so this what
happens in the interrupt handler is it
disables
um interrupts on this nick and then
wakes up
the network thread and that's all it
does
and it returns right i guess my question
is when the interrupts are disabled
can the nick still put packets on its
own
buffer yes the nick is self-contained
so it has internal buffering whether or
not
regardless of whether interrupts are
enabled or disabled the only
all that happens when a packet arrives
is that the nick
uh adds appends the packet to
its queue of packets in its own internal
memory that's all that ever happens when
a packet arrives
so it never the nickname in this paper's
nick i mean different neck designs are
very different but
for this paper their neck never did dma
it never reached out and touched host
memory
ever okay just kept an internal cue in
its own memory and the hosts could read
packets out if it wanted to
okay i see and if there's no memory then
drop okay so in this design
if packets are these excess packets the
place they're dropped
is actually is inside the nick what will
happen is
a packet will rot you know if if we're
in an overload situation
then the next queue will be full always
or almost always and so when a packet
arrives the next q will typically be
full and it'll drop
the nick will drop the packet without
wasting any cpu time on the main machine
okay yeah okay yeah that the fact that
it can drop without burning up cpu time
here
is one way of explaining how they avoid
uh
live lock right right okay thank you so
much
i had a quick question uh will there
ever be scenario in which
the cpu loop will pull a few packets
but the like internal software cues are
all like full
oh sure yeah there's some other
bottleneck
so for example suppose
these incoming packets some of them need
to be delivered to some application
on a socket if that application isn't
reading packets fast enough
then the socket buffer
leading to you know that that
application should be reading
will get full and then packets may be
dropped
in the networking thread
and that can also lead to live lock
because now because we have the same the
you know the reason live lot comes up is
that
we expended resources processing a
packet that was later dropped
so it was wasted effort um if the
application is not reading it's
well one way we can get live lock is
um as the load goes up maybe we end up
spending a hundred percent of our time
in the networking thread
leaving zero percent of the time for
whatever applications supposed to be
reading the packets
and then we'll again get live lock um
but but it won't be interrupt live lock
it'll be
network processing live lock or
something um the paper actually had a
story for
that um somewhere in section six
they talk about the network if packets
are being delivered to a local
application
the network thread would look at the
socket queue for that application and if
it was getting long
it would turn off it would turn off
interrupts and stop
pulling packets off the network
interface until the queue got shorter
um and so that means that network thread
would stop running and give the
application a chance to run and process
the packets
so you can get live lock-like situations
at any stage if you're not careful in a
kind of multi-stage
processing scheme okay that makes sense
thank you yeah