all right
you guys hear me
yes excellent thank you all right today
i want to talk about talk mostly about
microkernels
um but but first a little bit of uh
context to um sort of help explain why
people
explored microkernels in the first place
um
this uh the p people got the
microkernels by trying to think about
uh a little more broadly about what
kernels should actually do
like we you know with xv6 is sort of
does the things that unix does and we
kind of take
um that set of abstractions and system
calls and
uh keep sort of facilities inside the
kernel is kind of
for granted as the target of what we're
trying to design but
it's totally worth wondering gosh what
should a kernel do in the first place
maybe
maybe the particular kind of stuff that
xv6 or linux does
um is not really the best answer or
maybe it is
um and of course you know we're on
somewhat treacherous ground here because
now we're you know where what kernels
are is kind of a development platform
for programmers
as we know programmers different people
have like very different
um sort of subjective preferences about
what kind of infrastructure they like to
program on so we
can't necessarily expect a single best
answer
but we can expect to maybe learn
something and maybe make some progress
by
trying to think about what answers might
be so first of all
let me try to kind of crystallize what
the traditional
approach is to what kind of kernel
interfaces
we ought to be using and linux and unix
and xv6
are all examples of of what i personally
call the
a traditional design approach but
another word for it that kind of
summarizes
uh what this approach has ended up like
is monolithic
monolithic and what that means is that
the kernel is a single big program that
does all kinds of things all within the
same program
and indeed this really reflects the way
people thought about
what kernels ought to be doing a real
hallmark of
kernels like linux is that they have
they provide powerful abstractions
you know they choose things like file
systems
and which is really a complicated item
and they present file systems and files
and directories and file descriptors
as their interface rather than for
example presenting
disk hardware as their interface to
applications
so um and using
presenting powerful abstractions instead
of very low level abstractions have some
big advantages
um so these monolithic kernels often
have sort of
big abstractions
like file the file system
one advantage of big abstractions is
that they're often portable
um of files and directories you can
implement files and directories on all
kinds of storage
um and it the file you know you can use
files and directories that have
having to worry about what brand of disk
drive it's running on or
maybe it's an ssd instead of a hard
drive or maybe it's a network file
system at all it's the same interface
because
the file system interface is pretty high
level pretty abstract
so an advantage of this is that the
it's a way to get portability you can
write an application and have it run on
all kinds of different hardware without
having to modify the
application another example of this is
that
you know unix linux provides an address
space
abstraction rather than providing
something that's like
rather than providing direct access to
the mmu hardware
and that's useful to for portability and
to sort of hide complexity from
applications
so so another big advantage here these
powerful abstractions is that they tend
to hide complexity from applications
the so for example the file descriptor
interface that xv6 provides it's very
simple interface but
you know just read and write on file
descriptors can get much simpler
but behind it is some very complicated
code for actually reading and writing
the disk the file system on disk
and so it's nice for programmers but it
makes for a big complex kernel
these big abstractions also help the
kernel manage and share resources we
sort of delegated to the kernel
things like memory management the kernel
keeps track of what memory is free
we similarly the kernel keeps track of
what parts of the disk are free and what
parts of the disk are in current use
so programs don't get to think about it
and that again it simplifies programs it
also helps with robustness and security
even
because if programs are allowed to
decide what parts of the disk are free
or not
then maybe one program could use
part of the disk that's already being
used by another program
so the fact that the kernel is in charge
of resource management
helps with sharing it helps with
security um but again it
it's a force that um sort of
causes the kernel to be big um
so anyway so so having the kernel be in
charge of all these
sort of juicy abstractions that
even if they have simple interfaces have
a lot of complexity inside
have led kernels to be big
and complex items and another aspect of
this
monolithic design approach is that
because it's all one program
all the different kernel substances like
the file system and the memory allocator
and the scheduler and the virtual memory
system they're all part of one big
integrated program
it means that they can peer into each
other's data structures and so
that's just tended to make it much
easier to implement
facilities that are sort of parts of
more than one
or what you might think of as more than
one kind of modular subsystem so for
example
a system called like exec exec has his
fingers deeply into the file system
because it's reading binary images off
the
disk in order to load them into memory
it also has his fingers into the
memory allocation and virtual memory
paging system
because it needs to set up the address
space of the new process but it's really
easy there's no
problem with doing that in xv6 or linux
because you know both all the file
system is right there
in the same kernel program and the
virtual memory system is also right
there as part of the same program
um and if you know somehow there was a
rigid
split between the file system and the
virtual memory system it'd be much
harder to implement something like exec
that has sort of fingers in both of
these pies
but in a monolithic system just one big
program
it's much easier another thing that
makes
implementing software inside a
monolithic kernel like xv6 or linux easy
is that
all the code runs with full uh
hardware privileges all of xc6 runs in
supervisor mode for example
which means there's no limits there's no
irritating
oh you can't you know redirect that
memory here because you don't have
enough privilege
um all the kernel code runs with sort of
maximum privilege
and you know the same is true of
operating systems like linux
so this design
strategy is very convenient for kernel
developers
and it's made it easy to build these big
abstractions which are
convenient for application developers
however there's also a certain amount to
criticize
with the monolithic the traditional
monolithic approach
and this is starting to be part of the
motivation for
looking at other architectures
like microkernels so you might ask why
not
monolithic kernels
so one is just that they're big and
complex
so anything that's linux is
depending on how you count linux is
somewhere between many hundreds of
thousands and a few million
lines of code and people really do take
advantage of the fact that one part of
linux can sort of look at the data of
another and that makes the programming
easier but it also make there be a lot
of sort of interconnections
and interrelationships between code and
so it can be
a bit challenging sometimes to look at
linux kernel code and figure out what
it's up to
and anytime you get big programs
especially ones that are
complex structure you get bugs
and operating system kernels are no
exceptions and
over the years they've had all kinds of
bugs including bugs that
are exploitable for security
so
so this is sort of a troubling set of
relationships
if you allow a big model of the kernel
you're most certainly
can't avoid bugs and exploitable
security problems
and that's a real i mean there really is
a problem
another reason why people are
maybe not entirely happy with monolithic
kernels is that
they tend to just grow with
all desirable features over time and so
you know linux is used for all kinds of
different things from telephone handsets
to desktop workstations and laptops to
tablets to servers on the internet to
routers
um and that's caused the next it's
fantastic that linux can support all
those things
but it has caused it to be very general
so it has support in there for many many
different things
and any one application like me running
my web server is unlikely to need
uh for example linux's very
sophisticated sound card support
so there's just a huge amount of stuff
that's there for
to allow linux to be general purpose um
which is good but there's a worry
that uh general purpose is gonna tend to
mean slow
that you know it may be good for all
kinds of different things but
maybe not optimum for anything in
particular
so it's very hard to you know when
you're trying to make something run
really fast
it's great to have it just only do one
or two things so you can focus on
optimizing a single code path
but if your software needs to do any one
of a thousand different things it's much
harder to have focused optimization
so this is linux is not necessarily slow
but it's you know you you might wonder
if it's really as fast as
um it could possibly be for any given
situation
um and so if you think about i mean all
you you think
if you think about almost anything in
linux or xb6
you know you may wonder whether it
really needs to do everything it does so
for example if you write a single byte
over a pipe
from one process to another boy there's
a lot of instructions that get executed
even in xv6 which is a simple kernel
right there's
buffering you know there's locking
there's could be a sleep and a wake up
during a pipe read and write there's
maybe a scheduling may
call to the scheduler or contact switch
that's a lot of stuff that's
maybe not necessarily
the absolute minimum that would be
required to move a byte from
one process to another
another potential problem with these big
kernels is that
they because they're so big and they
sort of intentionally
bite off some very sophisticated
abstractions
they tend to have a lot of design
decisions kind of baked into the kernel
um so you know in ways that you can't
even if you disagree with them you can't
really
you know tough luck like applications
just have to have to live with it
so
you know as a as opposed to you men in
some fantasy world maybe the
applications could
make a lot more of the decisions so you
know some examples of things where
you may just you may be bummed out by
the way the api is designed for example
in uh in unix you can wait for a process
your own children you know if you fork
you can then wait for your children but
you can't wait for some other process
and you know maybe you want to wait for
a grandchild or an unrelated process but
that's just not an option
just not the way things work even if it
would be convenient for you
maybe you want to change the way another
processes address space is set up you
know maybe
call a map on behalf of another process
that you're controlling but
again that's just not an option you can
map
change your own address space but not
change other other processes address
space
maybe you're a database and you know you
have b tree indexes on the disk
and you may know a lot about it the
fastest way to layout a b
tree on a disk but if you're reading and
writing files with the file system
the file system has no idea that you're
actually writing a b tree or
how a b tree ought to be laid out on a
disk for fastest access
and so if you're a database you're going
to be kind of bummed you know maybe
you're happy that you have this file
system at your disposal
but it doesn't really do what you want
it to do um
and that's the sense in which uh design
decisions are often baked into big
kernels
and finally a specific uh
sort of issue that um
sort of came up in a big way in the
1990s probably
um it's a notion of extensibility uh
that it might be desirable for programs
to be able to change the kernel on the
fly like to be able to download new code
into the kernel or change the way it
operates or something
um in order to do things like have
databases be able to control the
layout of data on the disk um
and uh at least
in in decades past monolithic kernels
tended not
to have any particular features that
helped with this kind of extensibility
you're just
stuck with whatever the kernel did
okay so these were sort of
problems in the back of people's minds
that
led them to think about other kinds of
other ways of designing
other architectures for operating
systems um and there were another number
of
a number of ideas some quite radically
different that people pursued
we're going to talk about one of them a
particularly
popular one today and that's the idea of
microkernels
microkernels although the many of the
ideas are
go back to the beginning of computer
history
they became a sort of hot research topic
starting in maybe the mid to late 1980s
and the big idea
so a micro kernel this this word uh by
the way refers to a sort of general
approach or concept
it doesn't refer to any specific
artifact there were many
uh people who who designed and built
operating systems that
followed the general sort of plan for
micro kernels but you know each of these
projects
ended up designing an operating system
was maybe quite different from the
others
so the key idea was the
tiny kernel um
that supported just ipc
or inter-process communication
and some sort of notion of
threads or tasks um so you have a kernel
that that
you know provides you a notion of sort
of process-like abstraction and a way
for processes to communicate with each
other with this
inner process communication and nothing
else and
everything else you might want to do
like have a file system you'd implement
as a process as a task as a user level
code
not in the kernel at all and so a
picture for that
might be now we're going to use mu for
microkernel we've got the microkernel
down here and we got
user space processes up here and we
might have all the kind of usual
processes run maybe
we're going to run vi my favorite text
editor and my compiler
my windows system
but also up here as user level processes
we're going to have the file system
just as a server process in user space
maybe we're going to have a
disk driver that knows how to talk to my
disk hardware
maybe we'll have a network stack that
knows how to talk talk tcp to my
network interface card maybe we'll have
a user level process that's in charge of
doing
fancy paging tricks like memory mapped
files or
maybe implements copy on right fork or
something
and when my text editor needs to read a
file
it needs to talk to the file system and
so
it's going to send a
um a message via ipc
in our process communication um to the
file system server
which has all the file system code in it
knows about files and directories the
file system of server code may need to
you know talk to the disk so it might
send another sort of disk
reader right to the another ipc to the
disk driver which somehow talks to this
hardware
and this driver may return you know a
disk block to the file server
after it does its thing maybe the file
server finally returns the data you
asked for again by inner process
communication messages
back to my text editor but you know the
the critical thing to notice here is
that the only stuff going down here in
the kernel is support
for these these processes or tasks or
threads or
whatever they might be and um support
for the inner process communication
message passing
and nothing else there's no file system
down here there's no
device drivers necessarily down here in
the kernel there's no
network stack all that stuff is up here
is
more or less ordinary user level
processes
and so they lead you to a very small
kernel with
uh relatively little code optimize like
you can optimize ipc and there's not
much else going on
um and so this this is the kind of
picture we're going to talk about for
the rest of the lecture and
just to give you a taste of kind of
where this ended up um
there are actually still uh microkernels
in use today
and indeed the l4 microkernel which is
the topic of today's paper
turns out to be used um there's many
instances many many instances of l4
running because
it's used in a lot of cell phones to in
the little microcontrollers that control
the cell phone radios
and it's also apparently used in recent
iphones
as the operating system that runs on the
special
dedicated enclave processor in the
iphone that hides
the secret cryptographic keys so there's
a bunch of embedded
where these microkernels have won out is
in little embedded specialized
computer systems you know not not
laptops but
um computers are dedicated to
single specialized tasks where you may
not need the complexity
of linux but you do need some operating
system
and the other thing that's uh the other
sort of final result
from microkernels is that the idea of
user level services with
i with other programs talking to them
from with ipc
that also has made its way into a lot of
operating systems like mac os which i'm
running right now to talk to you um you
know it's a
sort of as well as being a kind of
ordinary monolithic kernel
it also has good support for user level
services
and ipc between unix processes to talk
to these services so
that idea also
was a successful idea and widely adopted
okay so uh this is the basic
architecture um
i'm gonna uh go on and sort of talk
about some ways and
uh reasons why this might be attractive
but first are there any just
kind of high level questions about
what it is i mean by microkernel
okay
so what is it that people were hoping
for
um
when they uh started building like
microkernels so one big motivation
although you wouldn't necessarily see it
written down much is just a sense of
aesthetics
right i think just a lot of people feel
that huge complicated
uh single programs like like a linux
kernel
um are just not very elegant that surely
we can build something that's
much more much much smaller but it's a
much more focused design
isn't such a huge grab bag of uh random
different features
um so i think there was a strong sort of
aesthetic feeling that surely we can do
better than big kernels
but other sort of more specific things
that you might be able to quantify
are something a kernel that's small
might be more secure
all right a few lines of code you have
probably fewer bugs you have
less chance of somebody to be able to
exploit one of those bugs to
break security and in the uh
extreme of that you could imagine an
operating system that's actually
provable provably correct
where somebody can sit down and write a
proof that it the operating system has
no bugs or does exactly what it's
supposed to do and nothing else
and indeed there is a at least one
verified proved correct proved secure
operating system named sel4 which is a
one of the many descendants of the l4
microkernel that um
today's paper but you really you know
people know how to verify
sort of small the medium-sized program
so they don't know how to verify huge
programs unless the fact that
microkernels are small
is sort of a critical ingredient and be
able to prove they're correct
another reason why you might like small
is that a small amount of code is
often a lot easier to optimize than
than a huge program
another reason why small might result in
fast is that you don't have to pay for
a lot of features that you don't use if
your microkernel does hardly anything
then
you're not paying for a lot of features
you're not using
another reason for small is that a small
kernel probably bakes in
far fewer design decisions forces fewer
design decisions on application writers
and so it leaves them more maybe leaves
them more flexible flexibility to make
their own design decisions
so by the way these are all these are
not uh
necessary consequences of the
microkernel approach these are things
that people hoped for and tried to
achieve
by using microkernels another set of
reasons why microkernels seemed
attractive has to do with the fact that
a lot of the code was at user level
um that is a lot of features and
functions that we
sort of have grown used to being inside
the kernel where actually user level
services
so they hope that by sort of breaking
the kernel apart and running the
different parts like
in user-level services like a file
service
pro fires file service server
it might cause the uh
the code to be more modular might sort
of
encourage operating system designers to
split up all these functions into
many separate services and that might
that might be a good thing
user level code is also possibly easier
to modify if steps at user level it's
usually easier to
tweak it or replace it or modify it than
doing the same stuff in the kernel so
maybe it's easier to customize
um putting the uh operating systems at
user level also might make them more
robust
you can we can if the kernel something
goes wrong with the kernel
um you know usually you have to panic
and reboot because
um you know you can't necessarily trust
what's in the kernel anymore if it's had
some bug that maybe causes it to
overwrite
a random part of its data whereas if you
have a bunch of user level services and
one of them malfunctions and
devise by xero or d references a wild
pointer
maybe only that one server will crash
and leaving the rest of the operating
system
intact and maybe you can restart it just
that one server so maybe
user level moving os functionality
to user level processors it might lead
to more robustness this is probably
particularly evident for drivers most
bugs in the kernel are actually hardware
device drivers
if we can manage to move the device
drivers out of the kernel then we might
have many fewer
bugs and crashes in the kernel and a
final advantage that people were
thinking about back then is that
you could emulate or run multiple
operating system personalities on top of
a microkernel
so even though the microkernel does does
hardly anything for you directly
you might be able to run a unix server
or something on top of it
maybe more than one on the same
machine
of course that's what today's paper is
about running a unix
running linux as a service on a
microkernel
these were all the set of things that
people were hoping to be able to
get some traction on by uh looking into
microkernel signs
of course there's some um sort of
puzzles you have to think through some
challenges
uh one challenge if you want to design
your own micro kernel is
actually figuring out you want the api
you want the micro kernel system call
interface to be as
simple as possible because the whole
point was to keep it small
now what is the actual smallest set of
useful
system calls you can get away with um
you know what does it look like so
that's not
particularly clear so we're looking at
the minimum
system call
api
you need these this minimum system call
api it's great if it's simple but you
actually have to be able to build
some pretty sophisticated features out
of your minimum system call api because
even if the kernel doesn't do much you
know in the end you got to be able to
run
programs you got to maybe you're trying
to run unix on top of a micro chrome you
got to be able to do things like fork
and map
so as part of the system call interface
simple low-level system call interface
it has to be powerful enough to support
all the stuff people need to do like
exec
and fork and heck maybe even
copy on right fork or memory mapping
on disk files but all in a kernel that
has no idea about files or a file system
right
it needs to support exec but with a
kernel that knows nothing about files
um we need the rest of the
of the operating system somehow you know
sure the micro kernel may be
very simple but you know now we're sort
of requiring the development of
some set of user level servers that
implement the rest of the operating
system
so we need to that has to get done at
least and may require some
uh just solving design puzzles um
and finally the you know this
arrangement requires a lot of chit chat
over
interprocessor communication over ipc um
so there's going to be great pressure to
make the
you know ipc very fast
so we're going to wonder whether ipc can
be made fast enough uh
to keep microkernels competitive
all right um and just in general
actually the
not just ipc speed but in general the
um there's a lot of reason to believe
that monolithic kernels derive
some performance out of the fact that
they're integrated that the file system
code can
talk to the virtual memory code in the
memory allocation code and
it's all sort of one big happy giant
program
and if you require all those things to
be split out into separate servers or
maybe split between a kernel
and user level there may be fewer
opportunities for optimization by way of
integration and that may or may not
end up hurting performance
all right um so these are sort of
cross-cutting
and hoped-for wins and
sort of challenges that all the many
micro-kernel projects faced
because of today's paper i'm going to
tell you a bunch about
l4 specifically which is
the microkernel that the authors of
today's paper developed and used
um l4 is not
um it's certainly not the earliest
microkernel ever made but it's
one of the sort of early microkernels
that came out of all the work in this
uh starting in the 1980s and it's fairly
representative as far as
uh how it works there's been
it's it's a bit of a moving target it
was the
subject of intense development and
evolution for many years and it's still
going strong
if you look at up on wikipedia you'll
see that there's maybe 15 or 20
different variants of l4 that have kind
of come and gone and some are still here
starting i think in the late 1980s and
i know what i'm going to try to explain
to you is my understanding of how l4
worked
at about the time that today's paper
came out
all right so um
just at a a it's a high level um
the l4 was certainly micro in the sense
that it was actually
is a a small kernel it has only seven
system calls some of them are a little
bit complex but still it only has seven
system calls
whereas today's linux the last time i
counted had in the mid 300s
and even xv6 which is an extremely
simple kernel even xc6 has 21
system calls so l4
is only 7. so by that metric it's simple
it's also not very big
i think as of the time this paper was
written at about
13 000 lines of code um
which is not too much uh xv6 is smaller
than that um
i think xv6 is maybe six or seven
thousand lines of code in the kernel
but still xp6 is very simple as kernels
go it's a l4 not much
more complex than that and this is you
know a tenth or
a 20th or a 30th as big as uh as linux
is
this is pretty small it had only a few
basic abstractions
it had a notion of
what they called tasks or address spaces
um and these more or less correspond to
what we would call a process in unix
it's a
bunch of memories um maps starting at
zero and
um and you're able to execute in here
uh just like in a process one difference
from
xv6 is that there can be multiple
threads
per task and l4 was in charge of
scheduling the multiple threads of
execution within each task
and part of the reason for this is just
that it's very convenient to have
threads as a programming structuring
program structuring tool
and it was also
i don't know if they actually supported
multi-core or multi-processor machines
at the time the paper was written but it
um they may well have
and uh threads are of course just what
you need to be able to harness
multiple cores you know executing in the
same program
so whether there were threads supported
by it by
the l4 kernel
so so l source l4 supported tasks
it knew about tasks i knew about threads
and it also knew about address spaces in
the sense that you could
you could ask tell l4 look here's you
know how i want pages mapped in my
address space
um and the other main thing that l4 knew
about
uh process communication so
that was every thread had an identifier
and one thread could say look i want to
send a message
just some bytes to another thread and
here's this identifier please
please send a message to that other
thread
so these are really the only
task threads address spaces and ipc were
really the only abstractions
the system calls i don't know if i can
be able to list them all but
the system calls were there was a thread
create system call which also
you gave it a address space id and a ask
to create a new thread and
if the address space or task didn't
already exist it would create a new task
for you
so to sort of combine thread and task
creation
there's send and receive
various flavors of send and receive ipc
system calls um
there's a way to map pages into your or
other address spaces so um
you could ask the l4 to change the way
your address space was set up the way
your
page table mappings were set up but you
could also ask lford if you had
the right permissions to go and change
the way another tasks
address space was set up so
and um
this was actually done through the ipc
with spent through the ipc interface you
would send a kind of special ipc message
that the kernel knew about to the target
thread and the kernel would
modify the target threads address space
and this is if you were creating a new
thread this is actually new threads are
created with no memory at all
so if you want to create a thread you
first call the thread create system call
to create the new thread and a task an
address space
and then you send it you make one of
these magic ipc's to send it some of
your own memory
to map some of your own memory that
you've prepared with instructions or
data
to map that memory into the new uh into
the
new task address space and then you send
a special start ipc
to this new task with the program
counter and the stack pointer you want
it to start executing with
it'll start executing and that memory
you've set up at the program calendar
that you asked it to start at
um there's a way not through system
calls
in fact i don't know how it worked but
um
privileged tasks could map device
hardware
um you know device control registers
into their own address
spaces
so l4 didn't really know much about
devices like disks or network interface
cards but
user level software could get directly
at
you use a level software that
implemented device drivers that user
level could get directly at device
hardware
there was a way to you could tell l4
to turn and interrupt um
any interrupt from any device l4 didn't
really know which device just turned
a given interrupt into an ipc message
so a device driver tasks could
not just read and write the device
harder but also tell l4 well anytime
that device interrupts
please send me an ipc message to notify
me at the interrupt
and finally one task could tell the
kernel
to give it notifications of another task
page faults
so if this task page faults l4 would
turn that into a ipc message
and send it to another designated pager
task
uh send the notification the page fault
to a designated pager task so every task
had an associated pager task that
handled its page faults
and that's the way you know you get
hooks into the
page faults in order to implement things
like copy on write fork or lazy
allocation
and that's it for the kernel there's no
nothing else in l4 there's no file
system
l4 didn't itself have support for things
like fork or exec
um it didn't have any communication
beyond these very simple ipc
like did not pipes enough device drivers
no networking support nothing
everything else if you wanted it you
need to supply as
user level services
okay so one thing that uh
l4 does supply is switching among
threads l4 would actually do the
scheduling and context switches in order
to multiplex a single cpu among multiple
threads
and the way it did it you would find
completely unsurprising
l4 basically had saved registers
for every task for every thread when it
executed a thread the executed
thread you know would jump into user
space and switch page tables to that
thread and that thread will execute for
a while in user space
then maybe the timer interrupt would go
off and that was actually a device
l4 knew about the timer internet might
go off after a while
interrupt into l4 l4 would save this
tasks user registers in a
per task an array of like tasks
or thread structures would save this
threads
registers away pick a new task to run in
a loop
much like the scheduling loop in xv6
restore
this task's registers out from its
previously saved registers
switch page tables and then jump into
this task and execute it for a while
until the timer interrupt went off or
until this
task either yielded i think there's also
probably a yield system call or
something like it
a task could yield a cpu or a task could
wait to receive an ipc in that case
l4 would jump back into l4 and alpha
would save us registers
switch to a new task and run that task
so that
thread switching part of l4 is very um
be very familiar um
the um
i mentioned this before but i just i
want to uh because it comes up
i want to um just write here
this notion of a pager um the uh
repeat if a process takes a page fault
traps into the kernel and the kernel
turns that page fault into an ipc
message to
a designated pager task and tells it the
address
you know that tells it tells this pager
task
which thread faulted and the address it
faulted on
um and then the pager task if it wants
to say implement
lazy allocation you know maybe this
thread
wrote read or write some memory that
wasn't allocated yet but it
think that it sort of has to be lazily
allocated
its pager task would then be in charge
of allocating some memory from
l4 um sending one of these special
ipc's uh the cause
mem that caused the memory to be mapped
into this task and then
sending an ipc to resume execution
inside this thread
um so there was this notion of page or
task to implement all this
all the stuff that xv6 or linux
implements in
page fault handlers like you could
implement copy on the right fork with
this
if you liked or memory mapped files all
using one of these pager tags so they
were sort of
powerful user level way to
play tricks with uh driven by page
faults
and so this is an example and one of
many examples in which
a micro kernel like l4 might have been
quite a bit more
flexible for user programs than a
conventional kernel like if you just
if you think linux ought to do some
extra thing like maybe
you know some you know if linux didn't
already have copy on right fork and you
wanted to have copy on right fork
you know you really can't implement that
in linux without modifying the kernel
there's no way to write portable code
portable user level code
for linux that could implement something
like copy on right fork
um so i'm not that's not quite true but
it will be very difficult whereas
um in l4 it's relatively straightforward
l4 is like completely set up for you to
be able to write user level code
that gets the page faults that are
required to drive
copy on right fork all in user space
without having to
mess with the kernel
okay so any questions so far about
how l4 works
oh sorry can you just clarify the
difference between a thread and a task
um yes a a a task
corresponds to a it's like a process
in xv6 it has a bunch of memory and an
address space
and you can execute user code in it xv6
if you have a process in xv6 it can only
there can only be one thread of control
on a single on you know executing inside
a process
in xv6 but in modern operating systems
and in l4
in a single process in a single address
space you could have mult
if you have multiple cores you can have
multiple cores
executing in a single task
each you know typically always each set
up with its own stack
inside that tasks address space and so
if you
that means you can for example write a
single program that can get
parallel speed up improved performance
from multi-core hardware by running
one thread on having multiple threads
each running on a different core
thereby getting more work done
okay i see thank you yes
okay um so as you can see this is a
design that relies heavily on
on ipc because you're going to want to
talk to your file server the file server
is going to want to talk to the device
driver
server and you're going to have ipc
messages flying back and forth
for every system call for every page
fault for every device interrupt
the ibc system just has to be fast
however
and now we're starting to
sort of talk about a serious potential
defect in the
microkernel story
so first let me show you um a
straightforward but very slow design
for ipc patterned off of
unix pipes and i'm bringing this up
because some early microkernels
worked in sort of a similar way to what
i'm about to show you which turned out
to be slow
okay so um let's suppose you have
uh you know you have two processes we
got p1
p1 wants to send a message to p2
so how should that actually work well
one possibility is to have
a send system call and you give send
system call the id
of the thread you want to send the
message to and
a pointer to the message to the bytes
maybe
that you actually want to send to that
process so this is a system call so
you're going to jump into the kernel
um you know maybe we designed this
patterned after uh
pipes and xv6 and so you can imagine
there being a
buffer of messages waiting you know
maybe p2 is doing something else right
now
maybe it's a server it's serving
somebody else's request so it's not
ready to handle your request
you can imagine maybe a buffer of
waiting messages
in the kernel like a pipe buffer and
when you call send
it appends your message to this buffer
waiting for pdu to receive it
now in fact almost always
in these systems you rarely just wanted
to send a message
you almost always wanted to get a
response to you wanted an rpc or remote
procedure call
operation so in fact p1 would probably
follow this immediately by a receive to
try to get the response back
but in general let's just imagine we're
doing a one-way ipc for the moment so
send would
append your message uh to the in kernel
buffer
we would have to copy the message bytes
from user space into this buffer
and then return and process one can do
something else like
maybe prepare to receive the response
after a while p2
is going to want to receive the next
message just going to make the receive
system call
and that's going to return the id of the
sender
and copy the message into p2's memory
that's going to take the front message
off the queue copying the p2's memory
and then return
so um
this is called uh
there's some words for this uh whose
opposites you'll see and
you saw in today's paper this is called
an asynchronous
scheme because
p1 sends a message without having to
wait for anything it just appends to
this queue and returns
and it's called a buffered system
because the kernel copies each message
into the buffer into its internal buffer
on ascend and then later when the
receive happens it copies the message
out of the buffer
into the target so this is asynchronous
and buffered
if you're doing a full request response
pair then p1 is going to call send sends
going to return
p1 is then immediately let's assume
we're going to assume that there's
really
sort of two sets of buffers one for each
direction p1 is immediately going to
call receive
um receives gonna wait gonna need to
wait for something to appear in the
reply
buffer so it's gonna have to yield the
cpu it's gonna have to do something i
call sleep in xv6 to yield the cpu
um and on a single cpu system it may
maybe only at this point
that p1 gives up the cpu and now p2 can
run
and indeed um the hardware in this era
was almost always
single core certainly this paper
is running on single core hardware so p1
is going to
it's going to be v1 executing and p1 not
executing until p1 finally gives up the
cpu and receive
waiting for a message to appear here and
only then will p2 be scheduled maybe
it'll call receive
there's people copy the message and then
p2
will make its call to send
um to append its reply
um and then the send system call would
return to p2 and at some point
presumably p2 will give up the cpu
maybe the timer will go off then p1 1
will resume execution in the kernel
see that there's a message there and
return it back to user space
and so that means that in this design
this slow design
there's in order to have a request and a
response
there's four system calls two sends
and two receives and you know eight user
kernel crossings each one of which is
like reasonably expensive
there's a need to sleep this receive has
to
sleep waiting for data to appear
and there's a full call to the scheduler
loop and a context switch from
p1 to p2 i'm in order to make this and
you know each of these kernel crossings
and context switches is potentially
expensive because
you know every time you cross the kernel
user boundary you switch page tables
and that is a has a near certainty of um
disturbing the cpu caches like changing
the page table
probably flushes the ver the tlb
the virtual memory lookup cache which is
going to slow things down
so this is a pretty slow way to go
it involves a lot of kernel crossings
message copying of messages between user
and kernel
maybe allocation of buffers etc
but it turns out that for the for this
stylized case in which you're sending a
request and you want to get a response
back
you can strip this down to a
considerably
simpler design i mean in fact this is
the way l4 worked
and this was laid out in a famous paper
called improving ipc by kernel design
published a few years before today's
paper
so it does a couple things differently
for one thing
it's synchronous
that is um
there's none of this there's no uh
dropping something off and returning and
waiting letting the other guy
letting the other process pick up the
data uh when it feels like it instead
send waits for receive and receive waits
for sand so
if i'm process one and i want to send
and i call send
it it doesn't copy my message into a
buffer
it actually p1 will now immediately if
the p1 send in the l4 kernel waits for
p2 to call receive
and if p2 is already in the kernel
waiting on a call to receive
well p2 is either already in the kernel
waiting on a call to receive or
p1 send wait for it waits for p2's next
call to receive
when both have arrived here when p1 is
in the kernel and it's called the send
and p2's in the kernel is called to
receive
only then does anything happen and
one reason this is fast is that
if p2 is already in receive then p1
when it's executing send in the kernel
can just
without a context switch or a general
purpose scheduling
can just jump back into user space into
p2
as if it was returning from this receive
right and that's a much faster path to
the kernel
than you know saving registers giving up
the cpu
calling the scheduler and finding a new
process to run
instead p1 send knows that there's a
waiting receive
and just sort of immediately
jumps into p2 as if it was returning
from receive
the scheme that they developed is also
unbuffered
and it can do that partially because
it's synchronous
when both the send and the receive are
in the kernel
the message can be you know send is
sending some message
the kernel can directly copy the message
from user space
to user space without having to first
copy it into the kernel and then back
out of the kernel
because because since you know both
sides wait for the other
system call to happen that means that
they've waited for both
pointers to be known receive specifies
where it wants the
message to be deposited so at this point
we know both addresses then colonel can
just do the copy directly
instead of through the kernel
for and if the message is
super small like maybe only a few dozen
bytes then
uh it can be passed in registers without
any copy at all
um what you might call zero copy
remember the send only proceeds if p2 is
already in receive and it
the send basically jumps directly to p2
well this code path through the kernel
takes care to not disturb a bunch of the
registers
and that means that p1 can put its
system call if it's if the message is
short
it can put the message in certain
designated registers the kernel
guarantees to preserve those registers
on its way up to p2 and that means that
when the kernel returns from the receive
system call but
as a result of send the contents of
those
designated registers hold the message
and therefore never had to be copied at
all from memory to memory
um never had to be moved at all they're
just sitting right in the registers
where they can be accessed
very quickly um
and this you know of course this only
works for small messages
for very large messages l4
could carry a page mapping in an ipc
message so for
for huge messages um
you know like the result of reading a
block from a file or something
um you could just
send the page and it'll be mapped into
the target's address space again
without any copy so this is done through
page mapping give away the page
or access to a copy to
access to permission to share the page
and so if small messages are fast uh
huge messages are pretty fast you know
you still have to adjust the page table
of the target but
that's much faster than copying and a
final trick that
l4 played was noticing that
if you're doing an rpc with a request
and a response there's a very stylized
pairs
of um
uh system calls and you may as well
combine
system calls send and receive system
calls in order to
reduce kernel crossings so um for the
special case of rpc which is
almost always what people are doing
when they're using ipc there was a call
system call
and a call was basically a combined send
plus receive
you know but without the return to user
space and then
re-entry into kernel space that a pair
of system
calls would take um and on the server
side there was a um
a single call that would send the reply
um from one system call and then
wait for uh the request message
from anyone for the next system call and
this is basically ascend of
one response plus a wait to receive the
next request
and this again cut in half the number of
kernel crossings
and it turned out that uh the sum of all
of these
optimizations now for the kind of short
rpcs which
are you know one typical workload all
this led to a
20x speed up this is what their paper
reported 20 x speed up over their
previous system which was
presumably a little bit more like what i
showed in the previous design
and so this was an impressive
this paper came out a few years before
the by the some of the same authors
but a few years before the people were
reading and this caused people to
um view microkernels a little bit more
favorably
that the ipc could actually be made
quite fast
any questions about um these ipc tricks
that
l4 plays yeah i
i think i missed this but um when is the
process
uh sending the or like receiving uh
messages
like when is it using that system call
okay actually so for rpcs for request
response
in fact in fact the the
processes use this pair of of system
calls
rather than send and receive so yeah
call
you really give it two arguments a
message you want to send and a place to
put the response
and inside the kernel it just combines
these two now you could view this as a
bit of a hack
but um because ipc is so frequent
it's worth a little bit of hackery in
order
to make it be fast and in the diagram um
up there in the box where um you have p2
sending that or like
running the receive system call why what
what prompted p2 to okay
in in uh in my rbc world uh we got a we
have clients
and they're sending requests to servers
um and the server is gonna do something
and reply so
since p2 is a server we imagine that p2
is sitting on a while loop
in which it in which it's going to
receive the next message from any client
do a little bit of work to process it
you know look up some data in a database
or something and then send a reply
and go back to the top of the loop and
wait again so to a first approximation
we expect p2 to spend all its time
uh waiting for the next message from
anyone
next request from anyone
and this design really
um it does kind of rely on p2 always
at when it's at rest basically sitting
in the kernel in a receive system call
waiting for the next request so that the
next request
can directly basically return from that
system call
right and that's the fast path that's
super efficient
in this design cool thank you
sorry just to follow up on that that
means that um
you said that it goes from p1 it like
returns to p2
so like to come back you would need to
send the response
so that's right we expect p2 to
um send a response and and that sending
of the response actually
follows basically the same code path in
reverse so that when p2 sends a response
um that that effectively causes p1 to
return
from i mean p1 is actually making this
call system call so the delivery of p2's
response
causes the call the return from this
from this system call back into p1
okay i see thank you you know this is a
little bit different from the usual
setup where you think of
you know you jump into the kernel on a
system call and you execute that system
call and it returns
sort of all working on behalf of p1
which is the way pipe
read and write work here you know p1 is
entering the kernel
you know it's p1 entering the kernel
you know but the return goes to p2 so
it's
kind of odd but very fast
okay um so this was a big
uh big sort of uh contribution to people
uh taking microkernels um
people's willingness to take
microkernels seriously as potentially a
replacement for uh
monolithic kernels um however you know
you still have to
still leave open the question even if
rpc's fast like where do you get the
rest of the operating system
right you know this kernel only has like
a few percent of all the stuff like file
systems and network stacks we expect to
be
in a full operating system what do we do
about the rest
um and this question is usually being
asked in the context of some
university research project with
relatively limited resources
we need to get all those user level
services from somewhere
now actually there are specialized
applications for which that's not too
much of a problem if we're
you know running a you know some sort of
device you know controller
maybe the you know ignition
control system for your car that is you
know only running a few thousand lines
of code anyway maybe doesn't need a file
system
then we can get away with like very
little stuff at user level and
microkernels
totally make sense for that kind of
application um but the
people you know in these projects really
they had ambitions that oh gosh
we can totally replace existing
operating systems and
they hoped that they could build
something that people would want to run
on their
on their workstations and run on their
servers and everywhere and just
replace big monolithic kernels all
together i'm but for that you know you
need a real you need all the stuff that
an operating system does
um one possibility the most maybe
sort of philosophically consistent
possibility would be to you know
reimplement
everything you need but in a sort of
microkernel
way as lots and lots of different user
level processes
um but that's just actually people
you know there were projects that did
that but it's a vast amount of work
and more specifically people really want
to run
you know in order for me to use a laptop
it just has to run
emacs right and it has to run my
favorite c compiler
otherwise i'm just definitely not going
to switch to your operating system
and what that meant is that microkernels
in order for to gain any kind of
adoption they had to be able to support
existing applications
they had to be able to be compatible
provide an identical
at least at the system called at the
higher level
service api level they had to be totally
compatible with some exist on operating
system like unix like linux
in order for anybody to be willing to
switch
so these projects faced a more specific
problem of how they were going to get
uh how are they going to attain
compatibility with
you know existing applications written
for linux or maybe windows or
something but for this project it was
linux
and rather than write their own totally
new set of user level servers that mimic
linux
they decided to take the far easier path
and many projects did this of
simply directly running an existing
monolithic kernel as
on top of their microkernel instead of
re-implementing some new thing
and so that's that's exactly what
today's paper is about
it has uh
indeed you know l4 microkernel down at
the bottom
um
but also as like a pretty big server
they run a pretty full
linux kernel as a user level process
and so they may sound a little
surprising the kernels not use a level
process right the kernel's the kernel
you think of it as running on the
hardware but in fact you know linux
kernel
as you can see from running xv6 and qmu
which is
running in user space after all a kernel
is just a program
and so with some modifications it can be
made to run
um at user level and so they had to
modify linux and
they took a lot of the low-level stuff
in linux for example the code in linux
that expects to be able to directly
modify page
tables or read and write processor
registers
there was some low-level stuff they had
to modify so some parts of linux i had
to change
in order to convert them to basically
make system calls or send ipc messages
through l4 instead of directly get at
hardware but for the most part they were
able to directly run without change
almost all of linux so that means they
got as part of linux
you know a file system and a network
support and all kinds of
device drivers and
who knows what that comes with linux
without having to
write their own version of this um
now um in fact the way this was set up
was that
linux the linux kernel ran as one
l4 task and but
each linux process ran as a separate
l4 task so when you log into this linux
and you ask it to run
a shell for you a terminal window or
something it's going to fire up an
l4 task that's going to run that linux
program
at user level so there were one task for
linux and one task
for each linux process that you fire up
um under linux and linux and instead of
directly you know modifying the
page table that uh that vi
that the vi process uses linux is going
to ask
i'll send the right ipc's to l4 to cause
l4 to
change vi's page table
any questions about the about the basic
scheme here
um another thing to uh another thing
that was changed
many small things were changed but um a
specific thing of interest is that
when vi wants to make a system call so
if vi doesn't know it's running on l4
in this scheme it's it's really all
these programs just think of themselves
as running on linux
when vi wants to make a system call um
you know l4 does not
support it it's not making an l4 system
called it's making a linux system call
so vi system calls like fork there's a
little library
basically that was linked into these
linux processes that would turn calls to
things like fork or exec
or pipe or read or write into ipc
messages
that it would send to the linux task
and wait for the response to linux task
and then return as if
the system call it returned so
so these little libraries would turn
system calls into
ipc messages to linux and what that
meant is that if the linux kernel task
doesn't do anything it
isn't doing anything else it's sitting
on a call to receive waiting for the
next system call request
ipc from any one of these processes
and that led to a that leads to a
significant difference between how this
linux works and how ordinary linux works
um
in ordinary linux just like xv6 there's
a basically a
kernel thread that corresponds to every
user-level process and
when a program makes a system call it
the kernel runs a thread on behalf of
that system call
and when in ordinary linux when linux
switches between
kernel threads that basically implies a
switch from one process to another
so there's kind of one-to-one
correspondence between
what kernel thread linux kernel is
running and what process is going to run
when linux is done
here that connection's broken they were
indeed
in this linux server a kernel thread
corresponding to each
i'm sorry let me start again the
linux kernel server was running in a
single l4 thread
so there was only a single sort of
thread of control executing in linux
at a time however just as an xv6
this one thread of control would switch
you know using a technique very much
like
uh xp6's context switch
could switch between um a kernel thread
corresponding to each user process
however
now which of these these
kernel threads were implemented purely
within linux and nothing to do with l4
threads
there's only one l4 thread here
but which user process was running was
determined by l4
so in this setup uh linux might be
serving a request
from executing the kernel thread for vi
serving a vi system call at the same
time that l4 is causing this shell to
run in user space
which is very unlike what happens in xv6
or linux where
there's a direct correspondence between
the sort of active
kernel thread and the corresponding
use a level thread here l4 is off
running whatever it feels like
and these threads in the linux kernel
are really much more private and are
just about
linux being able to um concurrently
execute
system calls in different stages of
execution where maybe
one process is waiting for the disk it
needs thread
linux can run a different processes
kernel thread to
serve that process system call um
so you might wonder uh why
the this design didn't directly use l4
threads
uh to implement the various different
um uh kernel threads inside linux
why you know why did linux implement its
own sort of internal threads package
instead of using l4 threads
and the answer was that in those days um
a they didn't have access to multi-core
hardware they were using
single core hardware so there would no
performance advantage
um to be able to execute multiple
threads in the kernel at the same time
because it was only one core
so a second thread couldn't be executing
only one thread could execute it at a
time due to the hardware
and the other maybe even more powerful
reason is that in those days
the version of linux they were using did
not
did not have the support that's required
to have
multiple threads multiple cores
executing inside the kernel at the same
time
they were using a uniprocessor linux
said old enough linux that
expected only one core in the kernel at
a time
it didn't have things like the spin
locks that xv6 has
that would allow it to correctly
execute multiple multiple cores inside
the kernel so there would have been no
performance advantage
in having multiple l4 threads active
inside the kernel
um but it would have required adding in
you know for no performance when adding
in all the
spin locks and other stuff is required
to support concurrency
so they didn't do it
a drawback of this arrangement is that
um in ordinary linux in native linux
like you would run directly on your
laptop
linux has a lot of sophisticated
scheduling
machinery that can do things like impose
priorities on different processes or
ensure
various kinds of fairness um
and that works fine because in a on your
laptop because linux is
in control of what process is running on
each
core but in this setup linux is not
controlling that at all
linux has no control over what what
process is running
because it's l4 that does this
scheduling not linux
these processes are scheduled by l4 so
they kind of lost the ability to
have linux be in charge of uh scheduling
um you know that's a bit of a defect of
this the
although i'm sure later versions of l4
had some way for linux or something like
it to be able to tell the l4 scheduler
oh look please
give this process higher priority or
whatever
so it's a bit awkward
all right um
so so they went to all this work
um to get this going and
um you should ask yourself you know what
is the
what's the takeaway lesson from from
this paper
about microkernels um
now one thing this so for us you know
this paper has a lot of
interesting tidbits about how micro
kernels work and about how linux works
and how
you know you set up how you can design a
system like this which
may be interesting but um
in the larger world you know people want
to want to draw some lessons
they need to be able to present some
lessons in this paper
the paper is not really answering the
question are microkernels a good idea
that's not really what's going on here
the paper
what the paper is is part of a argument
about whether
microkernels have enough performance
to um to be worth using
and the reason is that in
maybe sort of five years or five or ten
years before this paper came out
um there was a famous set of
measurements on one of the predecessor
microkernels an earlier microkernel
called mock
basically running in very much this uh
configuration
but a different you know totally
different design internally but
kind of the same architecture um this
um the name of this earlier micro kernel
project is mock
there was measurements on mach that
showed that mach was
dramatically slower than just ordinary
unix
when it was run in this configuration
and
you know there are a lot of reasons for
that having to do with the ipc system
not being as optimized as you might hope
there being just sort of more context
switches and
um you know user kernel crossings and
cache misses and whatever you know
there's a whole lot of reasons why mock
uh was slow but many people saw those
benchmark results showing that mock was
much slower than
native operating systems and decided
that microkernels were just
uh hopeless hopelessly inefficient were
unlikely ever to be fast enough to be
competitive and
you know we should just all use
monolithic kernels
today's paper is like an answer
basically
um to that argument it's sort of the
rebuttal to that argument
and the point of this paper is to show
that you can build this architecture
and if you pay enough attention to
optimizing performance
you can get competitive performance with
native operating systems so it's just
directly running unix
and therefore you can't dismiss
microkernels simply on the basis of
performance
you know you may not want them for other
reasons but you can't use performance
as the reason to reject them
part of the a huge part of the
ingredient in
making that argument is that they made
the ibc much faster with the techniques
that i outlined a few minutes ago
and you can see this i think in um
in a very simple benchmark in table two
if you have a copy of the paper with you
um table two has measurements of
just native linux running in the
ordinary way on hardware
um and on native linux they show that uh
you know on their hardware and their
version of linux
that um a single simple system called
get pid
took 1.7 microseconds
and they also show that the
sort of equivalent thing in their in l4
setup
where you have to send an ipc request
and get an ipc response
just for this get process id system call
that that
that took uh four microseconds under l4
linux which is to say twice as long but
there's sort of twice as much work going
on because you're doing
two sets of user kernel crossings
instead of
just a single simple system call that is
they could claim that they had paired
the expense of these ipc based system
calls
down to basically the minimum that is
twice the cost of a
system called native linux and therefore
they were doing roughly as good as
as you could possibly expect
now of course that's still their system
goals are still half as fast as native
linux
and you know it's not clear unless you
did some measurements whether
system calls taking twice or simple
system calls taking twice as long as a
disaster or
not a problem and in order to show that
and you know it might be a disaster
if you do a lot of system calls or might
be not a problem if
uh you do relatively few system calls or
there's a lot of work
per system call because maybe your
system calls it more complicated than
get pid
and their answer to that in the paper is
the figure eight
benchmark using this benchmark called
aim
which is just a more it's a benchmark
that does all kinds of different system
calls it reads and writes files and
creates processes or it does all the
things with the kernel that
processes do and they basically showed
in figure eight
that their setup running a much more
full application that does
you know much more than just get pid
runs
only a few percent slower than native
linux
um and that therefore hopefully you
could expect that whatever it is you
wanted to run on a computer
would run almost as fast under l4 plus
linux as it does under
a straight operating system under native
operating system
now therefore you know they were
basically to a first approximation as
fast
as just running straight linux and
therefore you should take them seriously
okay so that was an impressive result by
the way this is
like like somewhat unexpected and um
cool
just fast forwarding 20 years um
where this ended up as i mentioned
before people actually use l4
in a bunch of embedded situations
particularly it's used a lot
there's many instances of l4 running in
in smartphones
um hidden from view but nevertheless
and all running various kinds of custom
software not not running
you know they don't have to have
compatibility with unix
in these situations microkernels in
other
more general situations like
workstations or servers never
really caught on and it's not because
there's necessarily anything wrong with
that design
it's just they would have in order to
displace some existing
software your new thing has to be you
know like
better so people will be motivated to
switch and these micro kernels were
perfectly good
not certainly elegant um but it was hard
to put for people to put their finger on
why it was
so much better that they should like go
to the trouble of switching from linux
or whatever they were running
this and so it never really caught on
not necessarily for good reasons
but because they weren't like
dramatically better
on the other hand many ideas from this
architecture
had a lasting impact um the
the people had to work out much more
interesting and flexible ways of using
virtual memory in order to support
operating systems on their microkernels
and those more sophisticated interfaces
made their way through things like mmap
into mainstream operating systems like
linux
this idea of running an operating system
kind of on top
as a as a server on top of a
lower level operating system is
extremely popular today in the form of
virtual machine monitors which use all
over the place in
sort of cloud hosting services
the desire for extensibility you could
modify
a user level service the way that played
out in
things like linux was loadable kernel
modules which allow you to
load you know modify the way the linux
kernel works on the fly
um and of course the sort of client
server good support for this client
server architecture
also made its way into kernels like mac
os which has good ipc and
good client server and that's all i have
to say for this lecture
um and i'm happy to stick around for
questions
thank you
thank you you're welcome
oh i wanted to ask so the paper was
talking
about virtual about page tables
at i think 4.2 um
and it was seeing how
i think it was kind of what we what you
mentioned before
where you said that there is a wrong way
to do that
i think might be kind of similar to that
but
um if you do this this
thing that you explain in this in your
picture now
uh would it be i guess how how would the
page tables work in this case well
are you uh you may be referring to
section 4.3 the dual space mistake oh
yes sorry 4.3
yeah that's a bit of a complicated story
but the um
uh let's see the the part of the
background is the way that linux worked
in those days and indeed until recently
is that the when you're running at user
level
um the page table that's active has both
the processes pages
user level pages mapped in and all of
the kernel mapped into that one page
table
on the x86 anyway so when you made a
system call
and jumped into the kernel the kernel
was already mapped into the page table
and therefore no page table switch was
required so when you make a system call
it's
that much more expensive and much more
cheaper because there was no page table
switch if you're calling xv6
you know the trampoline code switches
page tables which
is an expensive thing to do because it
flushes the tlb
cache of virtual to physical mappings
anyway so for efficiency linux used to
map kernel and user space in the same
page table and
had fast system calls as a result
so they um for reasons that aren't very
clear decided to
do this same thing to set up the
mappings in the unix server
well what they wanted was that when
vi when a process sent a system call
over here
they wanted to have the page table that
was active while
in the linux server while processing
that system call
include all the virtual memory mappings
mappings for the
process that sent the system call
and that at least would make it simpler
to look up
virtual addresses passed as system call
arguments like
past or bead the reason why this
worked out poorly there were a bunch of
reasons one is that
um l4 which doesn't know anything about
any of this stuff
l4 just knows there's two processes and
so when you
send an ipc from one press to another l4
just switches page tables
it always just switches page tables this
guy had a page the vi at a page table
l4 associates a page table with a linux
kernel it just always switches page
tables
so you couldn't even due to l4 due to
the different way system calls were
implemented and the fact that l4 was
involved
there was no way to preserve the page
table during a system call
that just wasn't possible because it o4
always switched page tables
when it switched from one process to
another so they were never going to get
the efficiency win
of not having to switch page tables when
uh did when sort of crossing from
process from user to
kernel but i think they
wanted the convenience of being able to
directly use
users applied virtual addresses but that
meant that
the mappings they needed to be active
depended on which
process they were executing a a system
call on behalf of
so there couldn't be any one page table
for linux
they would have you know the page table
linux server wanted to use depend on
what process
sent the system call rpc but l4
did not know how to play that game l4
associated a single
page table with each process with each
task
and so in order and it would just switch
to that page table so tough luck
linux didn't have any way to cause the
page table to differ depending on who
had sent
the system call in order to deal with
that
apparently they made a bunch of
shared memory copies of the kernel one
for each process and so each of these
shared memory copies of the kernel
had exact had all of the kernel memory
mapped into it so they were all
the same kernel data structures but each
process
had a dedicated uh
kernel task associated with it and
therefore that basically
allowed them to trick l4 and to switch
into the appropriate page table that
included
that process plus the kernel you know
depending on which process sent the
system call request
and you know i think that kind of worked
but
or i don't forget what they said that
worked but it was slow or something
because it had there were a lot of tasks
um
anyway it's like a complicated story and
i think it didn't work out very well for
them
okay okay i see i think i think that
explains
oh well why this thing is harder to do
than
oh what we do in xv6 okay yeah yeah this
would be
because there's not yet this picture in
xv6 or even standard linux is
much simpler than this because you're
just jumping directly
into the kernel and the kernel has
control over direct control over all the
paging hardware
which it doesn't have when it runs that
note right
okay i see thank you thank you
we're going to ask um why um
it seems like um some some tasks are
more appropriate to be
put outside the kernel than others but
this
elf like the approach with micro kernels
always seems to be either everything or
nothing or like either
you have a monolithic kernel doing
everything or nothing
just like i feel like paging and some
other things could be very efficient
inside the kernel and then
maybe like file systems that things that
need to be swappable could be outside
uh and then even like you could maybe
even have a kernel that has some
functionality but you can opt
to not use it and provide your own is
there any everything you say
is absolutely well taken and
indeed there were a lot of micro kernel
or micro kernel related projects
um and many of them built various kinds
of hybrids
um like there were actually a couple
different versions of mock and some of
them
were sort of hybrid kernels in which
yeah there was this micro kernel that
knew about
ipc but also in the kernel was a
complete
unix so for instance mach 2.5
was this hybrid with it
but microkernel and unix all sort of in
the same kernel
and you could make system calls either
and some stuff was built in
the sort of microkernel way but some
things really they would just use
the kernel that was in mock that was
built into the mock kernel the unix
kernel was built into the mock kernel
um and modern you know mac os also
is built in a way that like the way you
describe you know
mac os that has a
all right it's a complete operating
system with a file system and everything
inside it but it also has good support
for
ipc and sort of mic threads or all the
stuff you would want to
build micro kernel style services
i think google's fuchsia i'm aware of
also implement some of these ideas now
as well
oh i'll bet yeah
so anyway you know there's no one way
there were people who were sort of
hoping that a pure a very pure
scheme could be made to work
but was not the only possible way
forward
all right thanks uh got around to my
next lecture but
i'll see you guys see you later
thank you you're welcome
oh i i didn't have a i haven't just a
remark i
i think it's fascinating that it it's
like
five percent slower but it does so much
more work yeah i was fascinating with
that
you mean that even though it's doing
much more work it's only slightly slower
yeah
well they really sweat blood over the
ipc performance and it's another thing
to remember
of course is that if you start doing if
you're doing a
significant amount of work per system
call
like you know looking at files and
directories or something
then the cost of the system called the
ipc itself starts to be less
important so the combination of faster
system calls plus real programs do
things other than
making system calls but it would also
like switch
page tables and oh yeah the others
yeah although the paper i did not talk
about it but the paper had some clever
tricks for
avoiding the cost of switching page
tables
i don't know if you remember for some
booths like on page six we're talking
about supporting tag
tobs or small spaces they had some
clever ideas for
not which page tables
which i had not heard of before i read
this paper so
this is pretty cool thank you so much
bye