and can everybody see my uh screen
or the whiteboard that i shared yeah
okay good yeah how are people doing with
the
log lab let me start there and just ask
if
how progress is and whether it's more
difficult or
it's looking okay anybody who want to
sort of report in their experience so
far
i hope lots of people have started
are you welcome yeah go ahead
oh sorry go ahead okay oh okay cool
i'll go i'll go um the lock lab
i think the first part the um
the k lock was
not as bad well and then the second part
um
was a bit harder well it's a lot harder
in my opinion
yep um you just have to figure out
a i guess the hard part was
thinking of a solution that um it's like
hey this doesn't cause deadlock but then
um
if you think there are cases where like
deadlock could happen if you acquire
a bucket slot again and all that stuff
but
yeah just have to think you have to
think like
about extra cases and all that stuff and
after that it shouldn't be that bad
okay anybody else who want to share
their experience
so far i wanted to ask uh are we allowed
to do any part of the lab like
lock free because i know like their
first part for example is pretty
the instructions said pretty clearly
like make apparel memory allocator but
uh can we do it just lock free and a
sing
you know just leave it as it is yeah
you're free to do
uh any solution that passes make great
uh is fine lock free
i would be you could certainly free to
do it
i'd be hesitant to start there if i were
you i would start first with
a more fine-grained lock implementation
and then move to a lock free
implementation
so the re the reason i started with a
lock free is because if you go to a fine
grained you need to do all of the
parallel stuff but if you just go
directly to a lot free one then you can
keep it
on a single free list and you just need
to you just need to
uh uh autonomous size the
free and allocate operations so it
actually isn't that bad
yeah i think maybe in if there's a
single list in the case of the k alert
that might be the case i think you know
the uh
lock free b alec is going to be a little
bit more complicated
yeah that that i'm scared to do but
that's the right reaction to have
anybody else
i found it a bit hard to debug those
problems because it's not
immediately clear what is happening so
you have to
go and sit with gdb and
break break break and yeah
yeah i think the the the one reason i'm
always scared to get these lock laps uh
so the
laps is you know they're harder to debug
and uh
and you know the bug may not show up in
every run
and uh but hopefully it is very
educational because
like learning a lot of programming walks
inside of a kernel is a real thing
and uh but it is definitely a core
challenge
one one thing about uh maybe this is a
node for the the
encouraging node the next lab actually
doesn't involve basically any
concurrency
uh and so hopefully that will be much
much much more straightforward um
i get i guess how do you how do you
efficiently
or effectively debug concurrent programs
like with all those multiple threads
using gdp i i use very basic stuff
i have i use print statements
but the main thing i rely on is i sort
of try to write down or assertions for
invariants that i think should be true
at every point
and if the insertion goes off then i
know that you know there was something
wrong in my thinking or
the assertion was wrong and then i think
for a while
and i tried to decide what it is and
then
go from there the
normal um for many other uh
settings there are race detectors that
can help you
um uh and again you know basically flag
code that may
looks like it might be having problems
or is
prone to race conditions um but that's a
whole set of other tools
uh that we're you know not using uh
and it's not that good but there's a
little bit of a big step to actually
get that all up and going and running so
that's the other
mechanism that people use race detectors
and basically flag any any shared
variable that is
updated or red without actually holding
a lock
no that doesn't help you with dead locks
like example in this lab in
uh be cash lock you know the you get
dead locks
deadlocks are tend to be easier to debug
correct because you can uh
you get the panic and then you can look
at the gdb you know the back trace and
see actually what
was involved in the deadlock
does that make sense thank you
okay another suggestion actually
somebody uh posted on the feedback
uh is you know the class is uh the
tenant is getting a little bit
lower than in the beginning of the
semester and i think we might be small
enough or
uh on the size that it may be perfectly
fine to actually have cameras on
and so maybe i want to encourage you to
if you ask a question to turn on your
camera
and you know it will hopefully improve
you know our experience as if it's in
the classroom as opposed to in a virtual
meeting
um and you don't have to look at me
okay um so
uh okay today's lecture uh so today's
lecture is going to be about crash
safety
uh crash safety and file systems and
this is not crest safety in in
the most general forum i'm actually
really focusing on a particular problem
um or a specific problem
namely that a crash or a power failure
can lead
the on-disk file system
to be in an inconsistent state or an
incorrect state
and what i mean with an incorrect state
is you know for example a data block
belongs to two files
or an inode is allocated to two
different files
and so the scenario where this problem
might sort of appear
is let's say you know you're running a
make
uh make a pretty file system you know
interacts with the file system
region writes files and somewhere you
know during
you know that thing a power philly
happens
you know maybe your laptop runs out of
battery you know maybe
the power just dropped or to your house
uh and uh and you know you reboot
the your power comes back on at some
point you reboot the machine
or machine comes back up and then you
know hopefully you get a prompt again
you run ls
and you hope basically that your file
system is in a good state
in the state it actually can still use
it and so the particular
failures or crashes that we're concerned
about are basically power failures
during file system operations
or the kernel panics you know
while running some file system operation
you know xv6 is panics most kernels are
panics you know maybe there's some
kernel bug that causes a panic and now
suddenly your system
just fails and what you like to be the
case is that after reboot you know you
can actually do something
or you can still use the file system and
this might be something when you're
thinking well
how could that not be right because the
file system you know stored on a
persistent storage medium
and so if the power fails you know the
medium should be good and so when the
machine comes back up you know all the
blocks that you've written should be
there
and we'll see that the tricky case is
that many file system operations have
multi-step operations and really what is
important in those mold and if we if we
crash just
in the wrong place in these multi-step
operations
the file system actually may end up
being on disk inconsistent for
that short period of time and if the
power flow just happened there
you know something bad could happen and
so that is sort of the problem that
we're uh
focusing on uh today and so this is
different from the problem that for
example whatever you know there's a
power failure and your disc you know
caught fire
and so there's nothing there anymore and
so you need to
in that case you know you need to you
need there's a completely different
problem that has different solutions
you know for example you have to go back
to a backup
of your file system you know reinstall
your file system etc etc
so that's the problem we're not worried
about we're really worried about the
specific problem of
failure happening right during a
multi-step operation
okay and the solution for that specific
problem that we're going to be exploring
is something that is called logging and
this is a very popular
uh solution uh originally uh
coming out of the database world but a
lot of file systems
use logging these days
we're going to it's a very one reason
it's popular because it's a very
principled solution
and we're going to see the instantiation
of logging
in xc6 and of course xp6 has a very
simple implementation like a bare
minimal
uh implementation of logging just to
demonstrate you know the key ideas
um and even that sort of uh very bare
bone uh log implementation actually has
some subtle issues that we're going to
be
talking about and that's why it's worth
kind of studying it
one downside to this we'll see if the
xv6 solution is because of simplicity
its performance
is also not so great even though locking
systems in principle can get good
performance
and so what we'll do next week is
actually look
uh how to implement a high performance
logging system
by studying the logging system that the
linux ext3 file system uses
uh but that's next week another
maybe small point one i want to make
today is that this is our last
xv6 lecture uh and from now on we're
going to be switching to
uh papers because in some ways what
we've done is we sort of covered you
know the basic concepts
and we can start looking at more
advanced uh operating system ids by
reading
papers okay
any questions so far
we're all good
okay um so let me go back a little bit
about like the scenario that we really
uh that we're focusing about uh in this
lecture
so uh file systems or file system
operations
like creating a file writing a file are
multi-step
disk operations
and you know we saw that last week or
monday we talked about how
create is implemented like creating a
file or writing to a file we often see
that you know the
sequence of events is or something of
the sequence of steps are you know
allocate an inode or mark the inode
allocated on disk
then you know write the directory block
that contains that inode and so those
are the multi steps that i'm talking
about
and if we get a crash between two of
these steps
that can that crash can leave
may leave the may leave the file system
in variance
violated
and the viola the invariants i'm talking
about are invariants of the form
you know every uh block is either free
or allocated to one file and not to two
files
uh and you know we might want to make
sure that this happens despite you know
these
failures uh right between uh these uh
operations
um and the risk is if
if the violence if if these invariants
are violated
the you know bad things can happen after
reboot
uh you know the you might crash again
immediately
because you know there's some data
structure the file system now now in the
state that the file system actually
can't really deal with you know on this
data structures there's in such a
shape that the file system really can't
uh process them anymore
or more likely you not crash
no crash but you know data may get lost
or you read or write incorrect data
uh and we'll see a couple of examples
you know to make that more clear
uh but so basically the risks that we're
worried about
don't know if anybody actually ever in
personal life or like when in your
daily life uh using computers actually
has experienced this problem where
basically
uh you had a failure in the file system
or
you had a failure you had a power
failure you know your machine rebooted
or your phone
restart it and uh that basically was
unusable afterwards
and uh the one reason that might be
unusual because
the file system just didn't recover
correctly
okay so to make it more clear let's just
let's look at an example
in the context of actually like to make
this
risk a little bit more concrete let's
look at an example in the context of xv6
and to see what actually could go wrong
so remember the uh for monday that the
xv6 file system very simple file system
it has a simple disk layout
uh you know the super block uh
there's the super block there's the log
that we're going to be talking about a
lot today that we didn't talk about on
monday
there are inodes you know it's a set of
blocks that actually contain each and
each block may contain multiple inodes
there's a bitmap block you know to
record which blocks are free
and which are not free and then the data
blocks that actually
you know contain the actual data of the
file system
and remember from monday's lecture i
reproduced the trace here you know we
looked at
actually how a file is created and you
know we
see that the creation of a single file
uh
second uh
uh the the creation of a single file uh
consists of multiple
operations so for example like in this
particular scenario that i have here on
on the slide uh we see that uh
uh you know an internet is allocated
uh and you know we know this because
this block 33 is being written
um and do we see that the audio is being
initialized and then written again to
block 33 then we see the block 46
is written and that reason is written is
predominantly because you know the
directory block that actually contains x
and
the i know number for x is written to
the disk then the inode
root i node is updated to reflect that
the directory has grown in size
to contain this particular uh file x
and then you know the inode is updated
and so
uh what we want to now understand is
like what happens like what could
possibly go wrong
right and so let's say you know we
uh have a power failure like right here
so here is a power failure or kernel
crash
and so what happens after the power
failure correct all the in-memory state
is lost right because that in-memory
state or
the data that's actually in ram like all
the processes
all the file descriptors all the
in-memory
caches are gone because you know memory
is not persistent
and the only thing that we have left
right is what actually is on the disk
so only the data structures and
the bits and bytes that are actually
sitting on the disk are uh
survive the power failure because that
actually medium is you know persistence
or has durability and so we want to know
like we understand
so if we crash here and we have no
additional mechanisms
uh or we have no logging as having that
we're going to be talking about but
we have no additional mechanisms uh how
bad is it
what what risk are we running here
anybody
so basically you know we've written uh
block 33
to record that the inode has been
allocated then we had a power failure
and then we come back up
go ahead brandon this does that mean we
lose the
um lose this block it's like it seems
like it's populated but it's actually
not
yeah i think we're losing the we're not
really the whole block but we use the
inode x
right the inode x or the i note 4 x that
was allocated or this marked as
allocated
is allocated on disk but we have not put
it in any
uh we've not succeeded correct in
putting it in any directory
so basically on the disk you know
there's an eye node allocated but it
doesn't appear in any directory
so we can't even remove it right and so
basically what
will this cause is to happen is we lost
we lose an inode
does that make sense
so you might think well maybe what i
should do is like maybe i should reorder
the right
and in a way you know that hopefully you
know this you know we don't lose the i
know so for example another thing we
could try doing is say well what we'll
do is
we'll uh write 46
first basically update the i know update
the directory
write the directory inode
we're going to write 32 and then we'll
actually mark the inode as allocated
on disk
to mark it as indicate that the market
is allocated
so we do the same a set of operations in
a slightly different order
uh in the hope that we should uh avoid
this losing of the inode
problem and would this work
well the thing that we should do ask
ourselves like you know let's
think about this point in time let's say
a crash happens like right here or power
failure happens right
between uh updating the directory
basically
but before we allocated the inode on
disk and now you know we
power fails machine comes back up and we
look at the file system
you know what what state will the file
system be in
you'll still think it's a free inode and
yeah what would happen if for example we
read you know the file x in the
directory
in the root directory because it is the
in there now correcting this data block
we're going to be reading the inode that
actually is not even allocated correct
there's more only allocated
and worse what could happen is correct
that it might be allocated again
or might actually really be allocated uh
because it's a mark is unallocated to
actually in fact a different file
correct and so now we have two files
that might actually
uh the two files that actually share
even though they're completely different
they share the same inode
and so for example if one you know file
would be owned by user one and one by
user two then basically user two could
read user one's file
a data right so this is no good either
right
does that make sense so basically
switching you know the order you know is
not really going to solve our problem
uh we just basically get a different
problem that we had before
okay let's look at one more example uh
here's the
uh example of writing
to file x
so once we have the files allocated
let's say that all succeeded and now
we're executing the right system call
and the right system call also does uh
multiple writes operations which we saw
in one day
you know example it will allocate a
block in this case to block 45
so it sets a bit in the free map
the block 45 is the bitmap block
so it allocates a block in the bitmap it
allocates a bit in the bitmap block to
indicate that that block has now be
allocated
uh that block turns out to be 595.
and then we write you know uh the
character h you know to
595 and then the character i and then we
update the i dot
right now we can ask ourselves the same
question like you know what will happen
uh uh if
we crash so for example let's say we
allo crash
like right here between you know writing
the bitmap block but before we allocate
uh before we actually write the i note
so crash here
and so we reboot you know we come back
up and the disk is in a particular state
and you know what what is the risk
um we use a data block but we lose it
yeah we lose it again correct because
the block is allocated but it doesn't
show up in any file
because it hasn't been written into any
inode so we lose a data block
so you might think okay well maybe you
know just because we wrote them in the
wrong order what we should have done
is uh what we should have done is at
first write it in the inode
so first write 33 with the
you know with 595 as in the uh
either as an indirect block or a direct
block and then
you know actually we will mark the i
know this
the block is allocated so then we'll
write you know 45.
right so we change the order because we
want to avoid this lost data block and
we change the order in this way
and now let's consider the case if
there's a failure right here
what is the risk
um the size of the file is not
compatible with
uh actually how many data blocks are
allocated
that might be although i think at the
right of 33 actually update both the
size and you know the
uh the block number correct oh yeah
so that might be might work out okay
if there were two separate rights that
would be a problem
but there's some bigger problem here
it's that the so the file
has a so thinks that
it has the data block but the data block
is marked as
uh unallocated and other
um files can also use it yeah right now
that's the real big problem here is that
you know the
the inode things the 590 from the block
595 belong to
belongs to that file but actually on
disk it's still marked
as unallocated and so
when later another file was created you
know that block actually might be
used for that other file and so now
certainly
uh one file thinks it owns 595 but
actually other file does and in fact
both files will have 595
in their uh block numbers for their
inode
and um and basically
you know if one user owns that file the
other usually on the other file the
connection reader writes
each other's data right it's clearly not
what we want
you know the file system should
guarantee that every block
only belongs in one file and no other
file or
is free okay
so this could lead to security problems
but basically block is shared
among multiple files and that's
definitely wrong
does that make uh sense in terms of the
problems that can appear
and again you know this the real issue
here is not to watch
the ordering of the rights uh but the
real underlying problem here is that
we're just doing multiple writes and
then basically have to sort of show up
on disk
as an atomic operation
okay so the solution that we're gonna
explore
in this lecture is you know logging
and as i said before this is a
a common solution used in file systems
and
originating actually out of the database
literature and it actually has a couple
good properties
one it's going to make basically system
calls or file system calls atomic
with that i mean so if a create file or
you know
you call create or you call write
basically all the effects
of the that system call just all appear
altogether or none of them
so that avoids this sort of problem of
only some subset of the rights actually
showing up on disk
the second good property it has it
allows for fast recovery
so after reboot it turns out we don't
actually have to do a lot of work to
repair the file system
actually a very minimal amount of work
and this is in contrast to
some other solution that i'm not talking
about which is basically
you go and inspect the file system and
maybe you read all the blocks of the
file system or read all the inode blocks
read all the bitmap blocks and so check
out whether the file system is still in
the correct shape and maybe repair
things
logging has this nice property that
actually the recovery is fast
and then finally it is in principle it
can be actually very high performance
although the one you know the one we're
going to be looking in the context of
xv6 is not high performance
so we're going to look at that next week
we'll see actually how to build a
logging system that
has atomic file system calls fast
recovery and high performance today
we're going to be just focusing on the
first two
okay the basic idea of logging
is actually straightforward
and so basically what you do is you
divide the disk in sort of two pieces
it runs the log one is the file system
and the file system might be much bigger
than the log
and when uh you need to update the file
system so update
let's say block 33 or update the bitmap
block
we're actually not going to update you
know the file system blocks so
we're not going to update the bitmap
block directly instead the only thing
we're going to do on the right
is so here's our you know memory we have
a block in memory
this is say the bitmap block like it's
and instead of writing it to 45 what we
normally would have done
what we're going to do is actually going
to write it into the log so we're going
to stick it here
and remember that actually should go to
but we don't put it there and we do that
with all the other rights too so for
example we'll put our
inode block there you know that was like
maybe 33 i think
if i remember correctly and we'll stick
it in there and
you know remember that it actually has
to go to 33.
so basically what we do any right is
first walked
and so we don't write directly to the
home location of the block but we just
put it always in the in the log then at
some point you know when the file system
operation is done you know for example
it has you know these four or five
rights that we saw in the previous
slides
are in the log we commit the operation
basically what it means is somewhere in
the log we just record
a record you know in a fixed location
that basically says okay well
you know there are like five blocks in
the log
and that is you know the the the launch
set of locked rights
and then you know when we have all the
rights
stably on disk uh we can actually
install them so this is called the
installation phase
and really what that means is we're
gonna move you know these logs from the
lock to their home location so we know
this one has to go to 45 so we'll put it
at 45. this one has to go to 33
you know report it 33 et cetera et
cetera
and once we're done you know basically
we can clean the log
and cleaning the log
is basically your rewriting you know
basically setting this 5 to 0.
and that is a the basic plan
and why is this plan good well let's
think about it
let's say we crash before here
what would happen
so let me hold that question let me
actually talk about one thing before
asking that question let's say we
crash uh and so we reboot
and on the reboot there's basically you
what the file system does
it looks like the commit record sees
what the value of the commit record is
if it is zero you know do nothing
in our simple scheme and if it's
bigger to zero we know that there are
basically blocks in the log that
need to be actually installed and we
apparently didn't finish the
installation
now we crashed you know after the commit
but before cleaning the log
so basically we reinstall
and after we reinstall we clean the lock
okay and this scheme is good
uh because it actually ensures that no
matter where a crash happens
we either install all the blocks of the
rights or we install none of them
but we're never in this uh we'll never
end up in a situation where we installed
some of the rights
but not all of them and just to see why
this is true let's consider a couple
cases where things could crash
so things could crash between one and
two what will happen
in what situation do we end up
the situation in which on recovery we do
nothing
and that's okay because um nothing has
been written to the file system yet yeah
no no exactly so this is the case where
basically
uh we just do nothing you know as if the
system called
basically never executed right because
as if the failure happened slightly
earlier right before the file system
call started
and so that's perfectly okay that's
acceptable okay what happens
uh if we crash
okay between after committing
before we installed
then you'll just redo all the installs
so you'll kind of restore the correct
state
yeah so exactly so at that point correct
all we have we know they're uh
all the blocks are in the log they're be
all written because we committed so it
must be the case that the whole file
system operation finished
and so we can basically you know put
them in their location where they should
be
and then we're all in good shape and so
in this case now all the file you know
in this case what will end up is as if
the it is if the file system call
actually completely
just before the crash there's like no
difference
okay so what happens if we crash
during reinstall or like install or
during install before re-cleaning
so crash here in this case in this case
and now we'll do the third case
we'll install during installation or
just before
install after installing but before
cleaning
what what what happened then
oh sorry uh on the next restart uh
nothing has really changed in terms of
the recovery process
and so we're just going to redo the log
yeah we're going to redo the log again
and we're going to copy basically the
content
again you know to the locations correct
maybe in fact we might do it multiple
times
is that okay
um yes because those are just rights
and it's they are to a specific location
that we
don't change like it's written in the
log so we know
where we should write every time yeah
basically every time we'll do the same
right correct so let's say
in block 45 you know there's the value
10 and we're going to write 10 you know
to location 45 every time and that's
exactly what it should be
and like and repeating that right
multiple times doesn't really do any
harm
right because we're writing the same
value that actually should be there
anyway
and so it's perfectly fine you know for
us to do reinstallation multiple times
of course we shouldn't serve any other
file system calls at this particular
point of time we should do this before
we restart the file system but the while
you know the
during reboot or during recovery you
know we can just do this right another
way of saying that is that installation
is basically
item potent you can just execute it many
many many times and will have the same
effect at the end
a question about that yeah
because the interface is just read and
write if we had an append
it this would not be safe right
yeah yeah the there's you can make a pen
safe too
ignore fancy logging schemes but for
this particular logging scheme
you know we don't have to worry about
that in fact like in some sense the
append is a file system level operation
and at that level we can make it uh
atomic
using the logging scheme that we have
here
i see thank you i also have a question
yep
go ahead what would happen if the file
system crashed while you were committing
so you want to like
execute multiple rights and then you
only commit like half of them
yeah okay so can you speak up a little
bit more because your volume is low
oh yes sorry so if you wanted to
like commit multiple rights at once like
in an atomic way
but your system crashes in the middle of
committing so you
are only able to commit like half of the
rights
uh what would happen in that instance uh
okay so this is a very important point
i'm glad you asked the question so first
of all the the
the you commit in writing this commit
operation here
correct this you know step two you only
execute that commit operation
after you already logged all the rights
that you were planning to execute
right so at the point you do to commit
all the writes are in the log and so
the commit operation itself you know
it's an interesting question like what
happens there
so uh the way the the way i sort of
indicated this on this like the commit
operation writes a single block
like the single sector on the disk and
the standard assumption that file
systems make
is that a single block write
or single sector write is an atomic
operation
meaning that if you write it the whole
sector will be written
or none of the sector will be written so
the sector will never be written
partially
and so there's always you know clearly
you know valid data in that particular
sector
and so basically this operation that
commit operation writing the log header
uh is the writing the commit record is
the the real commit operation
like if that succeeds and there's
basically a
say a five in the commit header you know
we know that there are five
blocks in the log and we have to
reinstall those five blocks
if the commit header didn't make it to
disk then the value would still be zero
and we'll just treat it as if the
transaction never happened
thank you and the key rule
that you're sort of hinting at that
actually has to be true
is something that's called the right
ahead rule which means that
a logging system cannot install rights
until
all the rights are into the rn are in
the log
any more questions about this sort of
basic plan
okay good
um
let's see
so what i what i'm gonna there's many
many uh different versions of logging
schemes and i sketched out here a very
simple one
uh you know it's perfectly fine you know
they're schemes where basically the law
the cleaning of the log is postponed uh
installation is postponed until later
but i'm just going to run sort of with
this very simple scheme
and then on next week we'll see more
sophisticated logging protocols
but all those logging protocols follow
this right ahead rule that
you know before you write the commit
record you have to make sure that all
the rights
are in the log
but then there's a lot within that still
there's a ton of flexibility in
designing a particular logging protocol
as they're
typically called okay i'm going to look
a little bit uh
how this then is manifest itself in xv6
you know as a sort of a case study and
to make things really concrete
um okay so in xv6
they're sort of uh we're going to look
at two sort of pieces of state if you
will
the stuff that is actually on disk and
that is
um you know things that are in memory
and in-memory contents will disappear
on or the way we should think about it
is that the in-memory contents will
disappear on
on a crash or a power failure um
and the structure of the xv6 log
as always is extremely simple
uh there's actually we have one block at
the beginning
that's the header block and that is
basically our commit record you know it
contains
the number n which is like the number of
blocks in the log
and then for each block the
the block number the home location of
that block
blah blah blah blah so they're going to
be end of those
so then in the log itself r basically is
the data for that
you know it belongs to that so here's
the data of
bn0 here's the data of bn1 etc
to and b n minus one
so that's what's in the log uh and
actually does the only thing that's sort
of in the log there's nothing more to it
then in memory when a while the file
system is running uh there's an in copy
or in-memory version of the header
and it basically has the n and it has
array of block numbers
etc uh and then
you know these block numbers uh refer to
uh blocks that are sitting in the data
that actually
corresponds to the block numbers that
are sort of sitting in this in-memory
data structure
they live in the block cache which you
know
by now you're well familiar with and so
maybe this is like block 10
is the first block in the log or maybe
let me take a more concrete example from
that lines up with our previous thing so
maybe this is like 45
and basically you know somewhere in the
in cash in the broadcast
of course you know whatever block for 45
and here's his data
okay and that's one of the structures uh
that uh
the on disk uh the in-memory file system
has and
on this file system has so the unless
file system just has the log
the in-memory has these data structures
to orchestrate
uh these multi-write operations that
we're going to be doing
okay
so to make this a little more concrete
just let's look at some code
and that will help us understand
how everything works
so let me pull up
some code and let me put this next to it
keep that picture so that we can look at
it if we
want to or i can point to it
can everybody see my code
yeah somebody has to confirm that
they've seen the
emacs window yeah we can see it good
good
is it big enough
i think it's good okay it looks good
okay thank you
okay so let's start with the you know
i i talked about transactions right um
uh you know the fact that
you know the we should not commit until
you know we should not write a commit
writer until all the rights have done
and uh so that means that the file
system operations
must indicate sort of what the beginning
of transaction is and particularly what
the end of the transaction is
and the way that happens in xv6 is that
every file system call
you know here's open the corresponds to
create basically starts with begin up
and
you know basically indicates like okay i
want to start a transaction and i want
all the block rights that i've been
doing between begin up
and end up which is basically at the end
of the transaction to be atomic
meaning you know they should be all
applied to none of them should replied
okay and so every file system call in
uh xv6 has that structure and that
basically has begin
up then the code that implements the
file system call and then end up
and at end up is basically where the
commit operation happens
uh so basically between beginner and end
up
the on disk or the in-memory data
structure should be updated you know
whatever the
memory log may be updated the block
cache might be updated
but nothing really happens until end up
and at end of time we're basically going
to put things into the log
and then if we uh done with putting
everything in the log
we'll actually you know write the commit
record or the log header
okay so let's uh
so what is interesting of course then
what happens is every write correctly
whenever one of these file system calls
does
a disk write um the you know something
must happen
so if we go back for example to fs.c
you know look at ialoc uh i alec
basically what it calls it doesn't call
b write directly but it actually calls
[Music]
logarite and so we're going to see what
log right does and
log right is basically the function
implemented by the logging system
and every rate that basically a file
system called us between begin up and
end up
always goes to log right
so here's log right and log right
actually is reasonable
uh you know straightforward um
the you know we've written the block uh
in the
block cache so somewhere basically
you're 45 maybe this is like the right
to 45.
we've updated you know 45 in
the block cache and now we're basically
record in the in-memory data structures
that
to some point later at commit point we
need to write this block into the
log and so you know basically you know
the code is
oops the code is reasonable
straightforward
uh acquires a lock on the header
and and basically updates the header
uh and in particular what it does you
know it goes through
you know the uh it updates n or actually
the first thing it does it actually sees
if there's already a copy of 45
in the if 45 is already recorded as
being having to write to
written to and if that's the case
nothing else has to be done because 45
will be written to
uh and so we're done and this sometimes
it's called lock absorption
um if you know
block 45 is not in the array yet or not
in the
the list of blocks or the array of
blocks that needs to be written to disk
then basically you know the only thing
this particular piece of code does
is basically bump up and and stick you
know that block number that needs to be
written
into the next entry or into that entry
then the only other thing it does and
i'll talk about this later it will pin
the block in the buffer cache
and uh let me postpone why for a little
while
but i will come back to that later and
that's actually all what log right there
is doing
so every file system call that you know
needs to update
a block you know updates the block in
the block cache and then basically
appends it
uh to this in-memory data structure uh
unless you know it's already there
in which case you know it just absorbs
it
does that make sense
so does that mean that b right shouldn't
be used by itself
at all so you get b write shouldn't be
used
by itself only as yes
that's just correct yeah basically all
the one way to think about it is that
every b
write in the file system is uh replaced
by log right
okay um so now let's see what actually
happens
at end op correct because that's where
the exciting part happens
uh and i'm gonna there's a couple things
cases that i just want to
avoid talking about a little bit later
because they
you know even this simple logging system
actually has some subtle complexities
and
most of the beginning of this code deals
with these subtle complexities
uh but i just want to like at the normal
case you know there's
or there's the simple case where no
other file system operations are in
progress
uh we execute you know create file and
basically we're getting to the point
where we want to commit it
and so the code is pretty
straightforward
and calls commit and so let's look at
commit
so here's commit i miss a commit does
two basically
steps and basically writes the log and
that's basically writing
all these all these block numbers that
are sitting
you know in the in-memory uh header and
writes them basically all to the
the header on disk including you know
this number n
right and so let's see uh that is that's
what right head does
sorry uh a write log basically writes
you know the
blocks from the buffer cache into their
uh respective into the log itself
so let's see what red log is right above
here
and you can see what it does you know it
goes through you know this array
you know one at a time and basically uh
right down to the lock position
in the log okay so it reads you know the
log
block then sticks it in there
by copying it and then writing it
actually out to the disk
so this basically ensures like walk 45
land up here you know it's let's say
this is 32
that will end up there et cetera et
cetera
then in the end so at this point we have
not committed yet right the only thing
we've done is basically putting blocks
into the log
and if we were crash at this particular
point in time you know before
you know calling right ahead before
right hack succeeded
and basically as if uh the transaction
didn't execute at all
so let's look at right head so that
right head is you know what i called
earlier basically the commit point
and the commit point basically you know
basically it's straightforward
and reads the header block
from disk which is probably sitting in
the buffer cache uh
it you know puts the copies the n
you know this end into that block
puts all the block numbers into that
array into that block
and then basically writes that
particular block so
this is the this b rate what is that is
that the commit point
if a crash happens before this b write
what happens then
anybody if the crash happens
before be right isn't the only
modification that we've made
to the in-memory uh hb data structure
so it's not it's going to be fine yeah
it's going to be fine right because
basically we may have written db10dbn
or whatever to the log but we have not
succeeded in writing the log header
and so we'll we'll do on recovery
nothing will happen
and what happens if there's a crash
right after the b right so like a crash
here
and it's no longer zero so the log
header is correctly read and it's
recovered
yeah it will be recovered correct well
at some point hopefully during recovery
as we inspect that you know we
expect that recovery will actually read
the log header see that there is a five
in there for example
and then copy the first five blocks to
their home location
so this is really this this this one
line
is one disk right this one sector right
is really the commit point
correct
you know before the commitment point the
transaction is it is the transaction
didn't happen and after the
commit point the transaction will
definitely be finished
assuming recovery is correct
okay so let's you know uh
go back to commit
so commit after is committed it actually
installs the transactions
and you know that's pretty
straightforward basically you know it
takes the blocks looks at the header
where the blocks belongs and then
basically writes it to that particular
location
and so we can actually look at the
install trends
and see that actually that's what it
does
you know it has a copy of the log header
and it just
reads log header uh it reads the
destination block the home location
copies the data from the log
block into the destination
and then writes the buffer to the
destination
okay so basically effectively what this
does is basically you know you go back
to this previous slide here it copies
you know
it just does these copies from the log
into the home location
actually in the file system
and of course you know we might get a
failure somewhere in you know this code
or while we're doing this
but you know that should be okay because
hopefully on recovery we'll just start
over from the beginning
so let's look at so that was install
so once install is done then
uh basically it sets you know the in
memory header n back to zero
and then writes that log header and
effectively that
causes to uh
cleans the log because basically there's
now zero in it
question uh so
you uh the function you're in just
before
like whereas does the from two or two
from getting so that puts the um
the block that you're going to like
update
uh the log block that you're going to
update into the buffer
cache um could you make it faster by
not putting it into the buffer cache and
just directly writing it to
the device instead uh
let me uh which function we're talking
about
i forget its name it's it's the one
where you uh
copy you know everything into the log
okay install
install trends uh i think so
yeah no no
or maybe it was this one so
i was thinking probably of right head
but it's the same thing
okay they're the uh
the only reason yeah uh the only reason
to this you know basically our interface
is not particularly good you could just
wreck straight you know the you're
wondering why you are doing the read
uh there's no reason to do the read
because we're going to write anyway
uh is that the question
uh yeah that and you're also uh doing
the men move
right and you didn't move yeah so this
actually the sequence of code can
definitely be optimized
uh you can save you know one or two disk
writes
just for simplicity we don't do any of
that
okay thank you
okay uh so i think we're an over
uh commit just let's just go back
and double check uh so we did the right
log we did the right head
and basically this this is the cleaning
operation
uh we erased you know transaction by
sending it to zero
okay so the only thing to sort of
further inspect is like what how how
does recovery work and
so recovery uh happens when
you know when xv6 starts uh so no we had
a crash correct so the system failed
uh we rebooted um and
uh the and one of the first things
the x-rays or one of the things that xv6
does during uh
initialization it actually calls into
log
uh and in a log basically calls this
function recover from log
and so let's see what that does and
basically recover log you know calls
read ahead
to basically extract or read the
the let me see if i can scroll down here
a little bit
yeah basically reads the header from
disk and sees if n
uh well it doesn't really see if n zero
or not but
it just calls install trans and you know
this is exactly the same install trends
that we just looked for
for looked and looked at a little while
ago and basically you know it looks at
this end
and installs all the blocks from zero to
n out of the log
into their home location and if it's
done once it succeeds you know then
actually
it calls clear log as before
and so that's actually all what the
recovery does you know recovery is
basically
always call dusty installation and if we
crash
during installation here no particular
problem again correct because we'll
crash
we'll boot uh xp6 during booting we'll
call
uh log in it which we'll call recovery
log
and it will basically reinstall or
replay the lock as sometimes it's called
again and this might have this might end
uh if we crash every time or you know
many many times
you know it will reinstall replay the
log many many many times
until hopefully at some point it
succeeds and actually you know gets the
whole
log written uh or gets the whole log
installed you know to the
to the home locations does that make
sense
i had a question about so if a process
just runs normally it writes some data
to disk and then at some point after
that
before it commits and installs the
changes
there is a failure the process
the from the process point of view
nothing happened
but something like i guess the failure
happened after the
process ended um what it was doing
so is there anything bad about that
i'm not 100 you're really getting it but
the uh
the short answer is there's nothing bad
right because the disc won't be updated
at all
so just as if you know that file system
operation didn't happen
uh right or i guess i'm saying
the process disappears too but you know
we don't expect the process to survive
failures anyway
right or i guess okay
i i think that answered my question
thank you
yeah it's important to remember that
basically uh
the only thing that really survives
failures or that's persistent across
failures is the disc or the state on the
disk
nothing else right
okay so uh just to make this all
concrete one a little bit more too
let's um i put a
statement in uh be right so actually the
thing that actually does right to disk
like in the
block cache and we're just going to see
what the
trace of actual disk rights are because
basically on monday
i sort of
i didn't tell the full truth because
basically i put the print statement in
log right
and not in b write and so now i put it
in the b
right and so we can actually see all the
blocks that are being written
so we'll do the same thing as before you
know echo high x
and just look at actually the actual
disk rights
and see if they make sense so the first
thing to note correct is that this trace
is way longer
than the trace that we looked at last
time in fact that we looked at uh
slides a couple slides ago right because
if we looked in
fact just to demonstrate this
uh here was that same
echo high right and what we see there is
like only
it's five log right operations but it
turns into
many disk operations
correct so let's look at it
uh so what we think be right three four
and five are
and what is b right two
anybody what's that writing to the log
and then the super block not
yeah so just to look at the uh you've
got it right you know there's looking at
this picture again correct
the logs that's a two so uh that's
probably the header block
click the commit record if you will and
then three is the first data block
fourth the second data block files is
the third data block
right so going back you know this is
the first right the second right the
third right
they're all going into the log and
they're written to disk
uh in the lock lock part of the disk and
then this is the
commit record you know the header and
then presumably what is this face
what is this part is that the bitmap
setting
no so what do we think actually stored
in this be right free okay here aren't
you
creating the file that the inode for x
updating the directory and then also
actually making the file itself yeah so
and we didn't do it here correct because
in these b rights that didn't happen
but now we're doing it so what what
what phase is this of the transaction
installing the changes yeah it's
installing the changes correct what we
did here is
we logged the writes
then we committed the file system
operation to create operation and now
we're installing it
so now we're putting the blocks in their
home location
and now and what does this be right to
you then
it's clearing the log yeah it's clear to
lock exactly
so basically this this this the system
call was writing 33 46 of 32
and to actually do that using the
logging system that basically turns into
this set of
uh disk writes right where the first
part is the installing the law
if the first party is actually logging
the rights and the second part is
installing the log
and these are the two rights to the
commit records
does that make sense is it possible to
infer where begin
up and and up would run from this trace
uh well so we sort of know correct so
where did
uh we don't really know where begin off
start but this is at the beginning
any file system call starts with a begin
up
and it must be the case that the commit
record correct is
written in end up so
we know that this is the end op
of some file system operation
does that all make sense
okay so that was basically xv6 logging
and logging in action um and i want to
talk about a couple complications
uh and even this dirt simple
naive logging scheme actually has
complications one thing to immediately
note of course is
uh you know is this a very performant
implementation
just by looking at this trace
no yeah why not it just
i know this is a basically too simple
question but
that's important to ask
like you're writing the stuff twice
right
yeah you're writing your stuff twice so
whenever i write a file f over a big
file f
i'm going to write that big file f twice
and so uh certainly not particularly
high performance where i mean basically
we're cutting the performance
immediately by factor two
just to get crest safety um and so we'll
see you on
on you know when you're reading the uh
xt xd3 paper for a monday you know one
thing you should keep in your head is
while reading is just get how
how do i get around sort of this factor
of two
okay sorry is it the case that you write
the
h and the i separately
yeah i think so okay
i'll show you in a second why uh what is
happening there
or maybe
well let me not commit too much for that
answer uh but we'll
i'll i'll come back to it uh i'm sorry
am i having the
empty line not the h9i but yeah
the new line is a separate right h and i
just one right and yeah a new line is a
separate right okay
thank you you're welcome um
okay uh there's a complications and i
want to talk a little bit about these
complications
uh so okay here's our basic scheme and
basic data structures
and uh there's a free complication that
i want to talk about
um or maybe i'll call them challenges
whatever you want to call them
the first is eviction
and the issue is as follows let's say we
go back to this picture here
and the whole b cache is full
and um and so the transaction is in
progress
uh let's say we just just updated 45
it's now done with block 45 so it's
going to write the next block
and the cache is full and
the and
let's say you know we don't we don't
have a solution for this yet
uh but the cache decides uh it is it
wants to evict 45.
correct and if it wants to invict 45 but
it will mean that will mean we have to
write it you know to its home location
how bad would it be to write the block
you know
you know evict 45
and write 45 to home location
is that good or bad
would any rule be broken if we did that
i guess that is
if a crash happens before the other
rights in the same transaction
occurs then basically atomicity is
broken
yeah so this is bad correct
that this basically violates this right
ahead rule that i talked about
you have to write all the blocks to the
log before you write any block to its
home location
so it has to be the case correct that
the cache does not evict
any block that sits in the log does that
make sense
so the solution is don't evict
blocks those are in the lock
and this is exactly you know what you
were showing a little bit earlier and
said i didn't want to talk about
so if you go to log right again just to
see
for a second there you know log right
here's log right again
and here we see this call to bpin
and what do you think bpin does
name sort of indicates it
it pins the block in the
in the cache yeah and how does it do it
since you've been looking at this for
your
current lab extensively
what do you think it does so without you
know we could look up the implementation
with b pin but we can also guess
what it does
doesn't it essentially just make it so
that it doesn't get evicted
by increasing the ref count yeah exactly
this is all living a dash
deep interest increases the ref count
and we know from the b cache code
correct that
uh evict won't evict any blocks we have
a recount higher than zero
and so presumably somewhere later in uh
logging code you know when
once actually everything is logged you
know we can actually unpin
the block right okay so that's one
complication so we have this pinning and
unpinning going on
um let's look at the other complication
uh
and the file system operations must fit
in log
you know if you see if we go back to our
picture here or actually maybe this is
the better picture
how big is the log in xv6
30 blocks yeah 30 blocks 42-2
so you know the max size max log size is
30.
of course we could bump it up and you
know real file system runs with a much
bigger log
but it doesn't really matter no matter
what it has to be the case correct that
the file system operation must fit in 30
blocks because if a file system
operation would try to write more to 30
blocks
that means we would have to spill
something to the on disk location and
we're not allowed to do that right
because that would violate the right
ahead rule again
so it has to be the case that every file
system operation fits into the log
does that make sense
and in fact you know how do you think we
got to 32
or 30.
does it have to do anything with how
many blocks actually fit
you know we're another way to find
because basically
how many blocks does what is the maximum
number of blocks correct that the file
system operation could write
and that is really what the this number
30 has to be definitely bigger
than any you know the max number of
blocks
the file system operation
right
and so in fact we know robert and i did
because we went through all the file
system operations looked at them and you
know decided whether
uh what sort of the maximum number is
and it turns out the action number is
much lower than the 30
uh but you know there we'll see in a
second there's a couple interesting
complications
um like for example the operation that
we look so far like creating a file
correct is only a handful of blocks
you know the file system operation is
like five blocks in fact most
operations are you know a handful of
blocks not that many
can you think of any operations that
might write many many many blocks
right on a huge file yeah write a huge
file right so uh what what if we
you know uh called the right system call
and we pass it to buffer with like a
megabyte of data
like a thousand blocks it seems like
we're being serious trouble right
it would violate you know this maximum
rule and so
let's look at right
it's just right
this is right it calls file right so
let's see it's a file right
so here's file right um okay so here's a
there's an eye node a file descriptor i
note everything you see my code
or the code that i have on the display
and
notice that what does this code do
now you can read the comment right on
top you know here and that basically
explains it but this is what happens
because the right is split
in many number smaller rights
so what really is going on here correct
is we're ensuring that the
whole right as a whole is not uh atomic
but that's okay
you know the right unix system called
semantics don't require that actually
all the
thousand blocks you know of our megabyte
are actually written atomically
and this requires that we don't corrupt
the file system you know between
uh don't corrupt the file system while
doing it
and so basically we uh you know xv6
uh splits a big write in a number of
smaller writes and writes them as
individual transactions
and this one basically ensures that in
our example if a transaction allocates
an a block number because
we need a new block for us an
intermediate block or because we need a
new block because we're going to write
to it
at least that part is completely atomic
and the file system will be never left
in an incorrect state violating any of
the file system invariants
and so the right is to split in many
many uh
many systems in many smaller rights or
many transactions
okay in fact that's the main one that
actually is
right fs split in many
many transactions
any questions about this
and note because you know things are
pinned correct in cash that means also
that the
block cache was me bigger than
bigger reader to the lock size
okay uh so now the final challenge that
i want to talk about
is concurrent
file system calls
and the issue is as follows you know let
me first try to explain what the problem
is
and then we'll see what the solution is
um
so let's say we have our log
and uh and we're writing and maybe there
are two transactions
executing concurrently and
you just imagine for a second that you
know they uh
they uh write a lot of blocks so
basically t zero
is executing t zero is executing you
know they're all false so here's the
beginning of the log here's the
uh end of the log and uh
you know t one executes signals and
blocks and etc
etc and by the time we run to the end of
the log neither one is complete yet you
know so
both have still more rights to do
and uh at this point
can we commit any of the two
transactions
no we can't correct because if we would
uh commit
a transaction that is partially done
then
we uh violate the right ahead rule again
and you know the whole purpose of action
login doesn't work out
uh so it has to be the case that
basically
a number of concurrent transactions must
fit
in the lock in fact all concurrent
operations
was fit and so in the way
um so this is sort of a challenge
correct we have you know a file system
called starting and
uh you know we gotta sort of arrange
that basically the
uh that we that we basically do a sort
of a
an entrance you know check you know
before we actually let the file system
operation go we must check whether it
actually is not blocked still
you know if we have like end file system
operations already in progress
we have to make sure that if we add like
allow one more guy to start
that actually the total number of blocks
that right they could write together
actually fits in the log
and the way you know basically xc6 sort
of gets around this
is it basically limits the number of
concurrent file system calls
and the way it basically works is that
uh in begin op you know we just see how
many outstanding
uh concurrent file system operations are
in progress if there are too many
in progress we just stop the current
file system operation it goes to sleep
and it will wait until all the other
guys are done and have committed
and all the other guys will commit
together in fact like you know at some
point that t122 they're basically done
you know maybe t3 is in the two they
finish and then basically
in all these transactions and in a
single time in a single or
basically are committed together
this is sometimes called group commit
because you're committing multiple
system calls
you know all the ones that were
concurrent in action uh
you committed this together as a sort of
a single big transaction so that all
their updates are
visible so that all their updates all
place all the
uh so that all their updates all
take place or none of them take place
okay uh and we can
see that you know if we go to a quick
question
uh is that is the group commit um
is grouping the commits necessary
like could you um say if one system
calls finish first just
commit its trade it's um transaction and
then
commit the other ones later or is it
like a necessary property ah
you got to be very very careful because
you remember one thing i didn't really
state this explicitly as a goal early on
is that we basically execute the system
called still in the right order
right if uh the
if a write or if a read observes a write
and then does it right
then it has to be the case that that
second right happens later than the
first right
and the reason that this is a log
correct is because that basically
reflects the order in which the rights
haven't happened
and so you can't really uh really nearly
change the order of the writes in the
log
because that may actually result into
bizarre uh
bizarre behavior observable by user
programs
and so it has to be the case that
basically you commit you know the
operations transactions in the order
they happened
and also performed their rights in the
order they happened
and so in general you know
it's safe you know it's safe to
basically commit them all together
you're always in a good shape okay
good question though
um okay i just want to go back to one
more thing
and look at the beginner up i talked a
little bit because i said like oh
nothing i don't really want to talk
about it right now
but there we can see
so here's the game up uh first of all
if we're already in committing the log
we're just going to wait until the log
has committed
because you know we can't write to the
log while the log actually being
installed
um if uh we're the
end concurrent operation that basically
makes us go across that lock size we
could just go to sleep
and wait until basically all the
preceding concurrent transactions are
done
and if we're allowed to proceed you know
basically our entrance
is allowed you know we increase lockout
standing by one
because that reflect our thing and then
we basically proceed and start doing
file system operations
and if you look at and off again just to
see you see that end up basically
decreases lock outstanding by one
because one transaction has finished
uh it certainly would be an error if we
were in creating states we panic in that
case
and we actually are the last one from
that set of concurrent transactions
then actually uh and lockouts and it
goes to zero we immediately start
committing
and then when we're done uh or when
actually uh uh if we're not the lie uh
yeah um
yeah we commit
uh and if there's space you know uh left
you know we wake up a guy so that they
can actually start running
okay so even though this dirt simple
file system that uh
or this very simple logging system that
xv6 actually has a bunch of
complications
so i'm starting to run out of time so
let me wrap up here
so in summary
you know what we uh what we talked about
is basically logging
as a solution for for crash safety
or really for multi-step
file system operations
and you know what have you seen so far
you know it works great for crash safety
but you know performance and
that's going to be the topic for monday
and as you read
that hd3 file system paper for monday
you know that's the thing you should be
thinking about
any more final questions and in fact
anybody who has to leave you know please
you know feel free to leave but if you
uh
i want to hang around and ask more
questions uh you know please do so
oh i have a question regarding um cache
size
and the log size so you said that the
cache size has to be at least as big as
the log size but they seem to be the
same size for
this case so would that mean that if the
log
pins 30 um
buffers and then some other operation
tries to do something
it just fails because it it runs out of
free spots in the buffer
no maybe let's let's
look at the uh okay so
let me first actually check one thing uh
okay let's go through bio
uh okay let's
actually first check if and buff is
bigger than
okay let's set some matchbox excited to
the block cache okay so it's set up to
something big
uh so what happens actually if we can't
find bkt and find a buffer
and actually use panics
and
so we if there's no free slot in the
buffer cache you know xv6 panic so it's
not particularly ideal
in fact to be it's terrible uh and so
you hope never to be in this situation
and hopefully we picked our numbers
correctly that basically this is
unlikely to happen
uh but why can't we return an error
because that seems like the obvious
thing to do like you know
you just return an error to the the
caller and then the caller
maybe returns uh back up to the file
system interface and just returns minus
one saying like oh this operation failed
why is that a problem
so ready to think about this is that you
know many file system operations are
multi-step operations correct
uh as we have seen now uh in this
lecture
and in the previous lecture and let's
say
uh we did two writes and then the third
right we run into this case where we
can't actually do the right because you
know there's no place in the block cache
we have done two rights right can we
just bail out of the file system call
okay i see right we cannot correct
because we might have updated in
the in the the directory you know a
directory block of some
uh file for we might have to update the
directory block of some directory and
if we wanted to make this work you know
what we would have to do is basically
undo those changes
right like any uh rights that we did
before
as part of that system call we have to
undo
right and you know that is painful
right so we don't do it does that make
sense
okay so it's not a problem if they
log the the log pins everything
and there's no more space for cash but
it will just pat it
okay yeah yeah of course this banner
should never really happen
right like there's an only off corner
cases where that hopefully happens
right i guess if you just okay yeah
that makes sense okay thank you you're
welcome
any more questions uh i have a question
about
um i guess following up on my earlier
one about uh
the group commits um i was
trying to think of like i think i kind
of understand it at a high level what i
was trying to make sure like i
understand like a
concrete example why group commits is is
important
and uh is this an example that kind of
demonstrates it it's like i guess i was
thinking of like a situation where you
have
um say like this might be convoluted
like one process
generating a stream of like numbers like
one through n
and then two processes consuming
uh that maybe they're listening on the
same pipe um
and say like n like stops on an even
number
um one process is print consuming and
printing out the odd numbers one process
is consuming
the even numbers um and if you didn't
have group commits
so like that the correct behavior is and
say they're they're printing
or like they're they're writing these to
the same file
um and so the correct behavior would be
at the end of at the end of all this you
would expect the file to have
like an even number like the last number
um
but if you didn't have group commits
it's possible that
um the the second to last process
actually gets committed after the last
one and so you actually see
nine is this like a correct example of
why this is important i think
i have to think a little bit more
carefully about it uh but that is
definitely the flavor
uh of the problem that you might run
into if you reorder system calls
okay okay uh i have a
concrete example in the lecture notes uh
let you know it's you know of a shell
command that really you know behaves
weirdly if you didn't commit this is not
really an issue in some sense from group
committee that is really an issue that
like
transactions need to be committed in
order
um i see and grew and if you didn't have
group commit then
yeah that just might not be some people
might think like well what i would i
should if i uh if you didn't have group
commit then
there's a temptation to basically you
know commit some later transaction
because it's already finished but the
first one isn't finished yet
uh to create space but that's not a
solution
okay that makes sense uh where where in
the lecture notes was this example i
think you have a shell command
where it sort of illustrates that like
ordering is important
okay it doesn't tie it directly to
uh group commit but you basically makes
the point that ordering system calls is
important
i see is this in the the like um the
text functions