the lab compares to shade the locking
lab
it was a bit more straightforward pretty
good
are you complete have you finished the
the lab where you're
uh i just started yesterday and um i'm
halfway so oh yeah okay good i guess
that's good news for other people that
are starting
uh anybody finished it yet
i have i finished it and any
any nasty surprises or work that
reasonable well
um i think it worked out okay all right
uh
yeah good what's easier than the log lap
i think so at least well hopefully it'll
be the case for everybody else dude
um yeah really let me
get started uh and the topic i want to
uh talk about today is uh virtual memory
for user applications you know on
sort of guided by this paper uh from
91 uh by appellant lee
uh and so the starting point basically
is that uh
as you well know now that the os kernels
use you know virtual memory page tables
uh in creative ways
you've seen that with the lazy
allocation lab the copy and write
lab as well as many other sort of
features that you know
uh implementation or
aspects of the implementation in xv6 so
um
basically the argument that the paper
makes uh
you know the paper argues that
you know the user application should
actually benefit too or actually have
the same powers
for example these user apps
you can use vm too
a little bit of what i mean with vm of
course user applications running with
virtual memory but i really
mean with uh vm is that you know they
would like to have the same mechanisms
that you know the kernel has to lose
access
in user application or user mode so for
example being able to
take page faults and then you know
respond to those page faults you know be
able to change the protection bits
or the privilege level to levels in uh
the page table
um uh and so uh in
the paper argues this case uh by looking
at a bunch of different applications
um uh like six or seven different types
of applications and maybe it will ask
you
like what was your sort of favorite
application that you
encountered in the paper
anybody who want to chime in and plot
the
twitter
um they can allow the user application
to
decide that a page um is going to be
i guess the change the um access bits
for
some particular page yeah yeah that's
one of the mechanisms i'm just curious
like which applications can so they make
the case with a bunch of different
applications correct like
the garbage collector
or concurrent cartridge collector uh
and they have a couple other ones and i
was just wondering which ones you
thought were most interesting
so what other applications did they use
or did they
did they used to make their case
i thought the data compression
application was pretty cool
yeah okay any other where
people were compelled by
i thought the sort of shared virtual
memory between multiple different
systems that was pretty cool i didn't i
don't think i fully understood how it
how it worked but the general idea of
using the protection bits to make sure
that different machines
are are using that shared memory in the
right way and protecting invariants
makes sense yeah so that's it
you know basically it turns out that
that whole area developed in uh
you know that one paper that or
originally described the
svm uh developed in a whole research
area
uh where you know people have all kinds
of clever tricks to try to make that
actually
that scheme to fly any other
because they go off they do a couple
other paper uh applications and
they basically argue that you know if
you look at all these different you know
quite different applications like the
shared virtual memory the data
compression the garbage collector you
know very different in nature
but it turns out that you know all of
them actually rely on a small number of
virtual memory primitives to actually
make it work and so the first question
that sort of paper
addresses is like okay what what should
the primitives look like
that user application
needs if they want to implement one of
those applications
and so let me talk a little bit about
that first you know what primitives
um and so they uh they
you know the ones the the obvious one of
course you need something of
a primitive that's going to what i call
trap basically to allow
uh a page fault that happens sort of
inside the kernel to be propagated up to
user space
um and then in use space you know the uh
and handler you know can then deal with
the
its page fault and then of course return
in the usual way
back to the kernel and then you know
resume the instruction
so clearly in the primitive like that
it's necessary because otherwise you
couldn't do anything in response to
a page fault the other primitive that
you know that i talk about is prop 1
which
decreases the accessibility of a page
they talk a lot about
accessibility or and what does it what
do they mean
with accessibility
anybody
whether it's read right or
for user yeah so those are different
ways in which you can decrease their
accessibility you know you go from a
page that maybe has read write
you go to just read only or maybe you go
from
you know read only to actually have no
access at all
they also propose that basically there
should be one for each individual page
that's prop one
there also should be one that actually
you can do for that the application can
call for a collection of pages
uh and so basically praden boils down
the principle to you know
calling prod 1 and times but why is it
why
do they argue that you should have
actually a pride n
version of this primitive ii
um is it because
actually it's more efficient because the
overhead of
protecting the end pages is not much
more than protecting one
because they talked about something like
amortizing the work
of uh yeah you're
absolutely right uh so basically if you
do a product one
you know basically you have to change
the page table bits
and uh do some work and then at the end
of that problem you know typically we
want to have to flush the tlb
you may remember this from the xv6
implementation
uh and flushing the dob is expensive and
so it would be nice if you could
amortize basically flushing the tob over
all you know the page table changes
and so basically prime n boils down to
end time
n times a change in page table bits plus
one to b flush
and if you did end times prod one you
would have uh
one page table switch plus or one page
saver table modification plus one to b
flash for each page
and so you can save the pov flushes
does that make sense
okay then you know the
primitive uh unprotected basically this
increases accessibility
as they call it
basically meaning you know if they for
example have washing read only access
now
we're just going to promote it to
actually have read and write access
and there are two other primitives
they're uh mentioning one is you know
primitive to actually find out which
page whether page is dirty
and another payment of you know map2
which allows
to allows an application to map a
particular range
twice in the same address page same
address
space but with different uh
different degrees of accessibility and
we'll see that uh showing up in a second
so you look at these primitives you know
does xc6
support any of these you know for user
level applications
not out of the box but maybe the alarm
handler that we implemented
feels close uh good good yeah keep the
alarm
handler in mind that certainly feels
very close correct to the
related to the trap one
but other than that xp6 sports none of
these correct uh
xc6 has a very minimal unix interface um
and doesn't support
uh any of these sort of more advanced uh
virtual minimum primitives even though
internally the kernel itself does have
all the the mechanism
uh available uh but just not exposed to
user space in terms of in the form of
system calls
so really what the paper is arguing is
that uh any sort of you know good
operating system should provide you know
these uh premises or system calls so the
applications can use them
so that naturally it relates to the
question like what is what's the scope
you know with unix today
are these uh are these available and it
turns out that basically you know any
uh if you look at a modern units like
say linux
uh you know these primitives are there
uh maybe not exactly in the same
flavor as uh argued in the paper but
there are there
and you even saw it in the paper
correctly some of the operating system
did have
some version has a subset of them uh
but today they're basically you know
sort of widely supported so if you look
at unix today
you know let's see how to actually
they're instantiated
and so one of the first ones is probably
the most important one
is something that's a system called
called nmap uh
that can be used to take some object
and map it into the address space of the
caller
so for example if you want to map a file
then you know the system calls us
something of the following form
you know you call nmap uh
nmac actually has quite a sort of
bewildering number of
arguments the first basically says like
whether you uh
you can specify a particular address
where you would like it to be mapped to
or you can let the colonel decide to
choose the address and in that case you
specified just null
and you know the kernel will pick an
address where to map you know the
object you specify the length uh you
specify
the protection bits you know for example
you know read
slash right um and then you know some
argument i don't
really want to talk about but there's
something called like math private
basically
you have to say something about how
what happens if you actually write to
that particular object
but we'll skip that mostly and then you
can project
we can actually pass in the file
descriptor and offset
and basically what this says is that you
know you should map the
content of you know the file object uh
pointed to by the file descriptor uh and
you take the file code to the def
object you can add offset and map that
basically uh
that particular address add a particular
address from them with that length
and so this basically allows you to
serve what is called memory map a file
you know so you can basically bring the
contents of the file
into your address space with actually
having to call read and write
uh system calls and it's sort of
convenient correct because then you can
manipulate the
file just you know with ordinary
pointers you can write at particular
locations and then you know at some
point you can write the content back to
the
uh to the disk and so this is a
convenient interface to uh
you know manipulate data structures that
might be stored into it might be stored
in the file
in fact uh you will be implementing
uh this specific version of nmap or some
version
the file based map actually in the next
lab so this basically integrates you
know the file system
part of xv6 you know where the virtual
memory part of xv6 and you can sort of
hook them up and
by surprising by actually implementing
map
map can also be used in other ways so
you can you can use the map
file you can also use it to map uh
anonymous memory
and that's basically sort of an
alternative to s-break you know where
basically you can sort of ask you know
the kernel please you know give me a
bunch of
memory uh and you know map at that you
know this particular
address um so that is
one of the core uh system calls
and we'll relate it back to the
primitives in a second
uh okay there's a couple more you know
calls that are you know necessary to
actually support the primitives
that the paper argued for uh and unix
house
has them so there's more unix today
there's an improtect system call
so once you have something mapped into
the address space
you can actually you know change
the the permissions
so whatever you can make it just you
know and protect the particular
uh so you map something in address space
then you can protect from an example for
a subset of that
part or all of it and map it at a
particular protection level
and so for example if you did this you
know basically you know loads could be
executed
uh but stores would change into uh
would change into a page fault and
similarly if you want to make sure that
a
range in the dress space is completely
inaccessible now you can
and protect it with none and you know
basically then both
uh you know everything basically any
access you know to that particular page
or to do
that address range starting from address
to address plus link
will result in a page fault
there's a similar invention there's a
corresponding call to nmap called unmap
that allows you to basically remove a
mapping or move an address range
and actually if you're curious you know
exactly how these calls work you know
you should
look up the man page of these
system calls and then finally you know
the the one that we really uh
need uh is a system called called sick
action
and basically this is a signal handler
and it allows the application to say
like you know if a particular signal
happens
uh then you know call this particular
function
so you can install basically the
function f as
the signal handler for a particular
signal and
in the case of you know page faults you
know the the signal
uh that is uh generated is something
that's called sec fault
typically you might have seen sex faults
you know in user code before
you know typically what happens in the
sec folder is basically the application
stops and crashes
but if the application had installed and
a handler
for you know a sex fault event or sexual
signal
then instead of the application being uh
stopped the handler would have been
called
by the kernel and then the application
can maybe respond you know to that
particular
set fault in the same way in some sense
that the kernel responds to
a page fault and you know maybe you know
fixes up the page table so that
uh you know the execution can continue
in this case maybe the handler will
actually you know call
and protect or change the permissions
so that actually the the instruction can
be resumed and continue
uh and um so in this inspector you know
if you were the
the most familiar uh version that we or
the the thing that we have seen
like the six action was like sick alarm
as amir uh mentioned a little bit
earlier
in the slick alarm lab where uh
you could install you know the alarm
program basically installed
a handler that would have to be called
at every clock tick or every
you know period of time um and you know
basically sick action is sort of the
equivalent of that but the general
version of it where it basically can
respond to different type of signals
any questions about this
uh it seems like m protect implies that
you can
add different permission levels on
individual addresses
whereas in in like xv6 that we've been
working with uh you can only apply
permissions on full pages
is that uh is that a difference that's a
present
no it's not a real difference uh you
know that works at the
page level granularity and
it doesn't expo you know there's a
separate call to find out what the page
page size is if you're actually curious
about it
thank you uh so if you think about you
know these
you know the primitives that were in the
paper you know we can sort of map them
correct to like what currently unix or
unix typically provides so
what the equivalent correct for trap you
know that were
in unix would be provided is something
called the six section
sick action call right
and about you know pradeen and prog one
what is the equation for that
okay so basically all three of them
correct you know basically or it can be
implemented
using improtect
and nprotect is flexible enough that you
could do it by
you know a single page uh have access
just ask
or you can actually you know provide
something that consists of multiple
pages and then you could do
you get the same benefit of like one to
b flash for
changing the permissions on a whole
series of pages
okay these calls are almost directly
mapped into some of the primitives
uh it turns out that you know dirty
actually is a little bit harder to do
uh and there's not a direct primitive
for or system call for
although you can sort of uh more or less
get it done with some tricks
and i'll talk a little bit later about
map2
there's also not a sort of there's a way
to do it but it's not completely you
know sort of as a system called just
dragging maps onto map2
it turns out that if you uh with
multiple maps
you can actually achieve uh this
particular
functionality too okay
so you know one way to think about this
paper is the you know kernel developers
uh you know maybe not totally driven by
this paper but kernel developers
um you know have extended
you know these uh or have provided these
primitives actually to
uh you know today's user applications
okay i want to say a few words about you
know the implementation just uh
much more at this sketch level uh
and then talk a little bit about you
know the applications
uh themselves and you know see how they
use these particular primitives
okay so uh let's talk about there's two
aspects that are sort of interesting one
is actually what actually happens you
know inside the virtual memory system to
actually support this
i'm just going to sketch this out like
what the most important pieces are
and in fact you know this is sort of a
little bit relevant to
uh the uh nmap lab that is coming up
because you're going to do something uh
similar so um
so an address space typically in the
unix today is represented by
you know of course the hardware page
table which contains the
translations uh but typically uh it's uh
augmented with a set of sort of os data
structures
not unrelated to any specific hardware
design
and these are called virtual
virtual memory
areas
or in short vmas
and basically what a vma what the vma
represents is you know to record some
information
about the contiguous range of addresses
so if you think about an address space
it might have you know number of
sections in the address space you know
each formula sort of contiguous range
and
basically for each section there would
be a vma
and the vma basically says you know the
vma also has all
the same permissions so all the pages in
that range have the same permissions
and they're backed you know by the same
object
now so for example you know if you have
a mmm
in memphis and mahep file then uh
the uh that would be vma for that file
that describes you know whatever the
the permissions for the for the file as
well
as you know the information about the
file itself you know the file descriptor
for example
uh that goes along with that particular
vma uh
and you know the offset in the file
where uh
the vma uh corresponds to
um and in fact you know in the lab
upcoming lab you know you will
implement a very simple version of you
know vmas and use that to actually
implement
uh uh the map
system call for files where basically
you can record in the vma you know
literally the file descriptor and the
offset that corresponds to that
particular nmap call or the range that
have been mapped
any questions about this
okay so then the second piece you know
that's sort of important
and then we have a little bit of
experience with it there's probably a
worthwhile you know
going through this actually how trap or
sick action
parts of the handler how an actual trap
will
be a work bit more careful
so how user level traps are implemented
and this you know follows very it
follows very much you know the
uh the same uh outline as actually the
sick alarm system call and then the up
call
that happened when a clock tick actually
uh
passed the time limit and so the sort of
setting here is
not you know clock ticks but you know
page tables so let's assume there's some
ptv
pte uh that has a that's marked
you know either invalid or maybe it's
not greed only
and you're actually restored to it and
so what happens you know when the
application
you know accesses that pte that actually
is basically invalid or doesn't
result in a valid translation well
as you know then the cpu you know jumps
into kernel mode
jumps into the kernel at a fixed address
you know you know you
look at the think the trampoline code
the kernel
you know save state so for example
saves to track frame
uh and then basically asks you know the
vm system
and what now
what to do and
the vm system actually might do
something so for example in case if like
this happened in the
laser lab and in the copy on right lap
where you know
you're you know to trap handler code you
know you know sort of looks at the
page table data structures and in this
case resume it will look at the vmas
and you know see you know what the scope
is for the address that were
that was where the processor folded on
and uh see what it needs to be done and
so for example if it
is a sec fault and the application had
installed
you know a handler to deal with it then
basically that
up call or the handler of the the event
would be propagated to user space
and so basically let's say there was a
handler installed then
basically we're going to get an up call
to
into user space
in the same way as in the uh sickle arm
lab
uh you know that will run you know the
handler
in user space the handler you know might
call you know
and protect you know to change the
protections
uh and
then the handler returns to user the
handler returns to kernel code
there's the kernel
and then the kernel basically resumes
you know the interrupted process
okay and you know if the if the when the
kernel resumes that interrupt the
process
you know if for example the handler
fixed up sort of the address space of
the
user program then you know might
actually the instruction might just
execute correctly
or if you know something is wrong you
know maybe trap back into the kernel
right away again if you know the
uh you know the the
hardware still can't translate that
particular virtual address
does this make sense maybe there's a
remember again the the sick alarm lab
and then this should be quite familiar
uh yeah i have a question yeah
what kind of uh i think
when we're allowing the user to
effectively run
a handler code on a page fault aren't
there
additional like security vulnerabilities
that could result as a part of this so i
was wondering if you could
speak to that yeah yeah it's a great
question
uh by the way can you like maybe
everybody turn on their their cameras
just to
if possible if you're comfortable doing
that i really appreciate it i think
uh many students in the class will
appreciate it too um
yeah so you know is there a security
issue
uh and the the first
what do people think you know does this
break
user kernel or you know the isolation
between different processes
another way you're asking that question
did sick alarm break you know
isolation
um wouldn't it be okay because the
um that that code that the handler
would still have access to the same
virtual member i mean if there are
different virtual memories for the
process and for
like for each of the processes then that
handler shouldn't be able to
look into other processes memory so
okay yeah okay make sure when we do the
up call correct we up make the op call
in that specific user space that
actually installed the handler
so the handler basically runs in the
same context as the
runs with the same page table as the the
application that installed the handler
and so the only thing it really can do
is you know affect that application but
you know
that's the application problem it can't
really affect anybody uh any other
application because
not it doesn't have any access to the
other applications
page tables or can force switch into
them
so this turns out to be fine of course
if the handler doesn't return or does
something bad you know in the end the
kernel will just kill can always kill
the process
so nothing really you know you know
the only thing that can go bad is you
know the process can hurt itself
but it can't hurt any other processes
does that make sense yes
thank you okay so now i want to go
through a couple examples
and so to see how you could use it and
i'll start out with a very simple
example
uh to get ourselves into it and then
i'll move to the garbage collector
because lots of people ask questions
about the garbage collector so that
seems like a
good one to dive into
okay the first example i want to talk
about is a
trivial idea but you know in fact it's
not even mentioned in the paper
but it is uh sort of a cool way of
illustrating you know the power
that applications get if they actually
have these primitives available to them
and the basic idea is to actually build
a huge
uh you know memorization
table
uh and the memorization table is
basically what it does it just remembers
you know the result of some computation
and so for example you can think about
it in the following way let's say we
have here's our table
and you know table starts to get
whatever zero to some
n and what the table stores
is the uh the result of running some
expensive function
uh for that argument zero or for
whatever fn
and so if you wanted to you know if this
table was sort of pre-computed you know
once
in the beginning of time and then you
wanted to look up like you know you
wanted to know what like
the value for f i was well what you just
do is you just look up
in the table you know in the slot i
and basically you get the the the value
that f
would have computed and so basically you
turn
maybe an expensive computation you know
maybe f is very expensive
into a basically a table lookup
and sort of a cool trick you know to
basically uh
store the results uh for pre-computers
and restore the results of an
expensive computation and if that you
know same computation is executed many
many times
then you know pre-computing at once you
know might be an advantage
a smart thing to do
does that set up make sense okay so then
the issue uh yeah you of course is is
that the table
or the challenge
now the table might be big
it might be in fact very big it might be
bigger than basically your physical
memory
but it's still nice to have it and so
the solution you know one solution
you know that you could uh
use to solve this problem is to
basically use the virtual memory
primitives
as described in the paper
um and you know what you do is you know
first of all you allocate a huge range
but don't really map you know don't
actually allocate any physical memory
corresponding to that range just
take a huge part of the address space
and say like i'm going to use that part
of my address space to actually store
the table
and then um on a
so the page the the the there's no
content in the table these are the
address ranges exist
and so if you do like a table lookup for
like a table eye
you know that will result into a page
fault
and so the basic plan then is on the
page fault you know you compute
you know all the entries or you know all
the the page basically covers a bunch of
entries in the table
and for each one of them you're
basically you know you compute
the function fi and store it in the slot
table i
and then basically resume you know the
application right
now the
of uh a map the physical page you know
so basically you take the page fault
you allocate a page
and this restore you know in that page
uh the results of
fi for all the slots in the in the page
um and the advantage of it is correct if
you now
uh couple advantages of if you have to
ever you know compute fi again
you know you're going to actually do the
table lookup and you don't actually have
to do any expensive computation just
with table of clubs and in fact
you know even if you do table i plus one
like you know there's going to be a
bunch of entries in the
in that particular page they're all
basically going to now be free you know
just
table lookups of course if you keep
doing this
then you're going to consume all
physical memory uh and so you know the
page fault handler also
you know has to throw out some pages if
you know you're running out of memory so
if you know much memories in use
is in use three some of them three some
pages
and of course then you're gonna have to
change the protection level correct you
have to make
sure that you're gonna get in the future
a page fault for those entries
so you have to presumably call you know
prod 1 or fraud m to
reduce the accessibility of the page and
the terminology of the paper
does this make sense that's sort of a
plan
uh yeah you would need to map it it
would need to
request from the operating system to map
it to a particular
address right because it can anywhere
okay yeah or it could be anywhere as
long as you know the operating system
tells
where it actually is oh okay
maybe to make it a little bit more
concrete actually i have a little
implementation of this
plan and we can just look at it and
see uh whether you know how you actually
do that using the existing you know
the unix primitives um
okay
can everybody uh see the emex buffer
is the font large enough
i assume that is a yes so here's the
application let me go to the bottom
so here's main uh main basically sets up
the square root region
basically allocates address space uh but
doesn't really
allocate the physical pages belonging to
it
and then it calls is function test
square root region that basically goes
through that table
in sort of a random order and you know
basically checks whether the square root
entry in the table for that position is
indeed the correct you know square root
value by just computing it literally
before that okay so basically the test
square region is going to run
and it's going to presumably generate
page faults because none of the
tables actually filled in so far so how
does it
you know how do we get those page faults
well here's the
sort of the fragment of code that you
need to basically install
a handler or signal handler for a
particular event
we're basically saying here uh install
for
uh sick you know the zigzag v event
the handler sticky sec v and so when a
segfault happens or a page fault happens
basically the function the kernel will
call
six handle six sec v and basically
you can extract you know the faulting
address you know this looks very similar
to your
trap code that you've seen many many
times before and
basically the plan is very
straightforward
we map a page at that particular address
you know so
yeah because we that's the address that
we want to fill in
uh with the so my expansion function
here or the
the replacement for the expensive
function or the role of the expensive
function is the square root function
and so we want to basically fill in you
know the uh the square root of whatever
value it has to be there at that
particular location in the table
so we allocate a page uh and and map it
there
and then you know we calculate for that
page all the
square root entries and then we're done
and this this application is a little
bit extreme uh what i did is basically
i run this table with only one physical
page allocated so
whatever the last page was we just
release it by unmet
am unmapping it and so we have a
gigantic table
that's basically representing it by one
physical page
and we can just run you know we wanted
to we could run this application it's
not going to be
that particular exciting uh but
you know why not so
i think i've compiled it you know and
basically go through and just randomly
bounces around in the table presumably
you know cautioning a lot of different
page faults
and all the entries you know actually
work out and so even though there's this
gigantic you know square root page table
or
table virtual square root table uh the
actual
physical representation of that table
just consists of a single page
and this sort of an example of like one
of the you know very simple example of
one of the sort of cool things you can
do
uh if you know these virtual memory
payment is available to user
applications
any questions about this could you just
quickly go over
that um last point on and why there's
only one physical page dude i guess
i was thinking like during it like oh
like this sounds similar to like lazy
allocation why
why is it different and i think that
like answered my question but i i didn't
quite follow
why we ended up okay the reason okay so
when we start when we set it
up we uh we have no pages right so
set up square root region actually
allocates address space
but then unmaps all the physical memory
associated with that
address immediately so at the point of
startup
there's no physical pages allocated to
this particular table
does that make sense
yeah okay then we get it when we get a
page fault
that means there's like one page out of
the whole table that we have not mapped
and we have map no pages
uh but we're gonna page folder now we're
gonna map one page
and in that one page we're going to fill
in whatever you know the square root of
i i plus 1 i plus whatever just you know
for that particular page
and then if we had a page mapped which
in this case the first time around we
didn't
uh there's nothing to be done so now you
know the application runs
you know and looks up some more entries
in the page in the the square root table
i mean you get another page table uh for
another page fault
because it's looking up a square root
entry that actually is not on the
allocated page
okay so at that point we get another
page fault
and then you know we allocate a second
page
we calculate the square roots you know
for that particular page
and then we unmap the last page
and this is of course like in practice
you would never do this correct you know
practice you would try to keep like a
working set of set of pages or something
like that
but just to show that you can go pretty
extreme that you can represent like this
huge page
uh huge table with a single page of
memory uh this particular fragment of
code
unmaps that last the one but last page
and then it keeps running and so at any
point in instance
at any point in time there's only one
physical page being used
does that answer your question
yeah i think so thank you okay good i
just
like it it's more like it this is
clearly not something you would do in
practice but it's more sort of like to
show you know
the power of the primitives you know
that you can represent you know this
gigantic table using one single physical
page
any other questions
okay um what i would like to do next
then is talk about another example
and in particular i want to talk about
the um
garbage collector uh you know since a
lot of questions were about the garbage
collector
um and so as you
you know the so the idea you know
garbage collectors uh
are a way of basically uh for
uh programming languages or languages
that basically uh
do memory allocation and freeing uh on
behalf of the programmer so the
programmer doesn't have to call
like in c correct you have to call malik
and then you have to call free
explicitly to free the memory
uh languages that use garbage collectors
basically the application only has
uh only can basically call malloc but
never has to worry about actually
freeing the memory
basically the garbage collector will do
the work to determine if the memory
still is in use and if the memory is not
in use
then an axle will uh free it and so it
is nice
uh you know what are some example
programming languages that have garbage
collectors
java yeah java python you know
go many of them actually correct almost
you know
other than maybe c and rust uh every
other programming language basically has
a garbage collector
okay and so as you can imagine there's a
huge literature
um design space for garbage collectors
and the point of this paper is not like
to say well here's the best garbage
collector possible but
here we'll basically illustrate that
carbon collectors could take advantage
of you know these user level virtual
memory primitives
and so the particular garbage selector
the paper discusses
is a copying garbage collector
and the basical plan is sort of you know
the top-level outline
is as follows uh you know you basically
have a memory
a heap from which you know memory is
allocated you divide the
memory and the heap in two pieces uh one
is the front piece
or the paper calls the front space and
the other is the two space
and uh let's say we haven't started you
know with the application to start
uh and so all memory is free you
basically start allocating memory
in the from space so let's say we
allocate a
maybe a tree like data structure you
know that has here's the
root of the tree and that maybe has a
pointer
you know to another object and that
maybe has a pointer to another object
and that is also pointed to by the root
you know sort of a
little cycle of objects
and maybe the application we introduced
a lot of other memory too
but there's no no nothing pointing to it
anymore and so basically the only
objects uh
live objects are the ones that actually
are basically accessible from the root
so at some point uh like maybe i've
allocated lots of memory
before and we allocate one more object
and it turns out there's no space
anymore where the application asks for
one more
object that turns out there's no space
anymore for it because the whole from
space is basically
has been used so then the basic idea is
in this uh copying guard
collector is to you know take the
objects and copy them over
uh to the user to the to space
and the way you do it is you start from
the root because that's you know
so every application where every uh has
a set of registers you know where
basically this top level pointers are
stored
or maybe they're the the the local
variables on the stack
uh and basically there's a set of routes
and just for simplicity i'm just going
to assume there's one route
and you start tracing basically from the
top level and so you know
you copy the rudo object over you know
to the two space
and you know and that's the only thing
you do at that point
and then you know of course that leaves
you know the pointers
you know still pointing to whatever
objects there were there before
and then you know once you copy the
object over you go low and inspect where
you scan the object
and you know of course the language
runtime knows exactly you know what type
the object is and knows where the
pointers are
and just looks at these pointers and
says like okay maybe you know i should
copy some more
uh pointers over uh
because those are actually all clearly
you know part of the live data structure
and so basically you know maybe we'll
take the top level pointer
look at that object you know copy that
object over you know to
uh uh the two space
update you know the pointer here you
know to actually indicate that actually
it has been pointing it to the now
copied version of the object
and then of course you know just later
on we need to remember that actually
this cop
object has been copied so we'll restore
a little bit of extra information
and remember that this object is
actually now stored there
and this process you know of sort of
moving an object from the
from space to the two-space and leaving
a forwarding pointer
in the from space is called forwarding
okay so we now we did this you know we
did
fix this pointer we fixed that pointer
there's one more left
so we'll look up that object and we copy
it over
like before and it still has a pointer
pointing to
this object so now we look at that
particular pointer look at that point i
see ah you know that actually has
already been copied
and in fact we know what the new
location is and so we can just straight
update it you know to point to the right
place
okay and so at this point you know all
the pointers have been
you know correctly updated you know the
whole structure
you know the whole cycle basically of
objects has been moved from the
uh from space to two-space and so at
this point we're done
uh the um
at this point we're done uh we forwarded
all the
the objects and uh basically the from
space now
you know all the objects in the front
space are being discarded
and it's now free space
does that make sense that's the basic
plan in a copy and garbage collector
okay now the scheme that definitely is
used in the paper
uh you know has a couple sophistications
uh so i want to talk about them
the first sophistication uh
is that you know they actually they're
called this is called bakers
algorithm it's an old algorithm and one
of the
nice you know featured it has uh is that
it's
sometimes what it is originally called
real time and real what it meant is it's
sort of
it's an incremental garbage collector
so and the main idea is that
here if we have our two
from space and two space
the main idea is that you know we have
our
root again here's our route
it had two pointers
and it's pointing back
the main idea is that you know it's not
really necessary
to stop the world and copy everything
over
and then basically resume competition
the only thing really
necessary is to actually move copy over
the route
and basically do nothing else and so
basically you know at this point you
know the
uh root has been copied but you know
it's
you know pointers are still pointing you
know the year because that object has
not been scanned you know it hasn't been
its points haven't been updated yet um
and the basic idea is then uh whenever
the application
uh calls new
you know on every new call you scan a
few more objects or you forward a couple
more objects
and that's sort of nice greg because
basically you spread you know the cost
of actually you know copying the
complete you know active or live heap
from the application in incremental
steps you know every new every call
allocates you know
contributes a little bit you know to
actually the complete copy operation
uh now of course the application uh
might also be using you know some of
these pointers for example
if you know the root uh will be
dereferencing you know like say this
this
second red pointer it's still actually
pointing into the from space
and of course that is dangerous because
we you know shouldn't be tracking
pointers in the from space
um and so basically this means that like
every time you dereference
your ref is a pointer
you need to check
check if it's in the front space if in
front space
and if so you know do the forwarding
and so the application is allowed to use
like the pointers but basically the run
you know the
the compiler has to instrument the
application that basically every pointer
access is
surrounded by that check so that you
know uh we basically maintain the
invariant that all
uh that any pointer in the two space now
points to objects into two space
and we need to ensure that correct
because when we in the end we're done
you know we want to remove the from
space and
uh have so that we can discard it and
you reuse it as free space
okay any questions about this this is
sort of the basic setup
okay so if there are no questions you
know the paper makes two points
you know about this scheme and um
one is gonna it's annoying or too bad
that you actually have to do this
de-reference every time
uh so basically this means a load or
store instruction
instead of being single instruction it
actually is a bunch of instructions
namely
branch instruction and perhaps knowing
calling a function to actually do the
forwarding
and so you know that increases the cost
of the
application and the second thing that it
actually sort of points out
is that it is not that easy to paralyze
uh uh this uh the the the garbage
collector
because like maybe in a nice setting
it's like if you're running in a
multi-core machine
where you have a lot of free cpus
basically i realize that the collector
you know just could in the background
you know traverse
the the the object graph and you know
copy things incrementally over
uh as it continues but if the
application at the same time
you know is using the graph there's a
risk you know that the application may
be you know there's one of the
reference check the one of these checks
it starts copying an object
while at the same time the collector is
also copying the object and you know
we're not very carefully
we may end up with you know the object
copied twice and the pointers
are not pointing in the right places you
know you can easily see correct that
there is a race condition
or possible of a possibility of a race
condition
and so the the paper basically describes
the scheme
and it says like if you had you know
these you know user level primitives
then actually you could do something
different you can do uh you know a cool
trick
and you can actually use vm
you know virtual memory to uh basically
reduce the cost of the
check and uh almost get you know
concurrency for free
um and so debating the basic ideas as
follows
you know we have our
same uh setup you know our from
and here's our two and what we're going
to do is like we're going to have
you know we're going to have we're going
to have a region
you know we can actually divide the two
space sort of virtually
or not literally when we divide the two
space in an area that is
unscanned
so let me be a little bit more clear
we have an area basically of the area
that is scanned
and that is an area that's unscanned
and initially basically you know the
whole area
is unscanned uh you know so when you
start out you know
you make the flip from the from to the
two space uh nothing has been scanned
yet
uh because there's no objects yet in it
and so but then basically the scheme
starts in the same way
and we copy over the root object
now it used to be there you know copy it
over it has some pointers
you know basically these pointers point
still back into the
um uh
uh whichever oops uh yeah and these
pointers gonna point back into the old
from space
um and so that's it and now we're
basically saying uh
and what we're gonna do is for the
unscanned area
which is at this point everything we're
going to basically map and
map them with no prediction mapping none
and so whatever does that mean well that
means that the first time around
the application you know after we did
the flip uh the garbage collector did
the flip the first time the application
uses the root
uh pointer uh it will get a paid fault
right because
you know the uh that part of the address
range is actually unmapped
and so basically then the idea is in the
fault handler
scan you know one page of objects
and for the ones that need to be
forwarded
so basically you know we in this
particular setting where we're only
copied over just the root
so far you know we have uh we're going
to copy over
uh the root we can scan you know the
pointers
in the object to which the root is
pointing
in this case there are only two of them
you know we kind of copy over those two
objects you know into the
uh unscanned space or maybe let me draw
them a slightly different here
just make it look like we can copy over
those two
objects that we're pointing to and
basically we update you know the
you know we move this scan line you know
from here
to there so this is now scanned
and so after we scan the page you know
we can actually uh
increase you know basically protect or
basically unprotect
you can unprotect the page we protect
the scan page
okay and you know the and then the
application you can just
now access the particular object because
you know we translated you know the
pointers inside of the object so it's
safe to expose it to the application
the application can traverse those
pointers of course if those pointers are
still pointing to objects that are
haven't been
scanned in then we'll uh we'll get a
page fault again and then you know we
scan a little bit more
and so it basically has the benefits you
know it's still incremental
you can still do a little bit of work
you know every time we can also do it
every time on a new we can actually
allocate you know some do some work
but it has the additional benefit
there's no no pointer check anymore
the pointer check is still there but
it's done in hardware
the vm hardware does it for us
does that make sense any questions about
this
about this plan i have a question
um so in
in the handler you're saying that you
scan one page of objects but
how do you know that the objects
that the root has references to will be
will fall into the same like how do you
know that the objects that really need
to be
forwarded in order to not uh violate the
invariant will be in the same page
uh you'll be okay there's some set of
objects in the page
the uh you're starting okay let's say uh
you know what the
okay um
at the beginning when we flip this
spaces there's nothing in the two-space
uh what we could do is like what the
runtime could do is just
copy i i described this copying one page
but basically to copy over
or forward uh one page you can basically
copy n objects over so that they fill a
complete page
all right so now we have n objects
sitting on that one page
all unscanned then at some point the
patrol handler will
or happen and then you know the garbage
collector or the collector
you know go through each object on that
one page
and looks you know for its pointers and
for its pointers it
move copies over those you know uh
objects into the uh
into the unscanned part of the two space
so that if you know anybody or if the
application ever will use
one of those unscanned objects will get
a page fault and they can scan those
et cetera et cetera
does that answer the question yeah good
okay i also had a question
yeah um so after you do this do you flip
the two in the front or
okay yeah so you start out in the front
space you fill it up you flip to the
uh you go copied over to the two space
and then you call the
from once you're done with the
completely with scanning uh
and you're done with the from space is
completely clear you just
you flip the names and you start using
the two space to actually do the
allocations
until it's full and then you flip again
thank you
any further questions
so one of the you know one of the the
things that uh one of the arguments the
paper also makes is that you know the
you know one other thing that the vm
system or using vm
uh simplifies uh is basically
concurrency
and the argument is that uh basically
the collector
you know it can just go through the
unscanned pages so we have
uh yeah we can go through the unscanned
pages and basically scan
one page you know at the time and if
it's guaranteed that the application has
no pointers
or it cannot access in the same time
that page because it's unmapped
and so uh you know as long as the
and so the the paging hardware basically
sort of introduces you know sort of an
explicit synchronization
or protection against races because only
the collector
can access that page and the from and
the application can actually not access
the page
so it gives sort of a nice automatic
sort of parallelism where
the application can run and do its
business the collector can do its
business
and they will never step on each other's
toes
because if the application ever will
touch
an unscanned page it will get a page
fault
and and the
collector never touches scanned pages
and so will never interfere with the
application
so you get sort of
concurrency for free but it actually has
a tricky issue
so although it's almost for free you
know there's actually one thing you
actually have to
arrange which is uh the
the area correct in the unscanned area
was actually unmapped
so if you look at our uh picture from
the before
uh here are you know two here's our from
here's our two and you know we have you
know that sort of split in the unscanned
and scanned area and unscanned it has no
you know
non-protected none so that raises the
question
you know how does actually do collector
you know go through it because you can't
actually
access those pages because you know
they're unmapped correct or the
the protective they're inaccessible and
so
the trick is basically as follows uh and
this is where
map2 comes in what we're going to do is
actually we're going to map that same
physical memory we mapped it once
correctly we mapped it once in this way
i'm going to map it a second time in the
collector's views or the collector's
review of the
two space so here's the collectors view
here's the app
view and in the collector's view you
know where i still have to and from
exactly like before oops let me try
we have two and from
and uh what we're doing actually you
know here's our inscant area
but in the collector you know we map
actually the unscanned area read and
write
and so that the the collector actually
can go through look at the scan the
objects
you know and forward pointers as
necessary and so this is really the
place where
this map two uh call is necessary where
a
range physical piece of physical memory
is actually mapped twice in the address
space of an application one at
two different levels of protection uh to
basically make things the scenario like
this work
any questions about this
um i have a question do you
do you kind of give each like the
collector and the app
um different versions of the page table
or no they have the same page table
correct but they have the
memory mapped in two places the physical
memory mapped in two different places in
the address space in two different
pieces
places in the page table and
uh in one place you
make basically the mappings invalid and
in the other
address range you make the mapping read
write
okay
well just to make me make a make this a
little bit more clear
since there were so many questions about
it uh uh
i sort of have a trivial implementation
of actually um
uh this basic id the id that was
described in the paper
and just to make it a little bit more
concrete um
and so let me walk through this and
ask feel free to jump in this is
basically a toy implementation of what
is described in the paper
and i'm sure it has bugs i mean i
haven't really tested this in any way
seriously
but and it's mostly there to illustrate
you know to make everything
slightly more concrete so the collector
the api if you will that the application
uses is
a new and repointer and repointer is
that basically uh
does the check whether uh the
pointers in the front space and if this
is in from space then it needs to be
copied
and of course when we're using vm uh
tricks then basically this read point is
going to be very cheap because we
basically return the existing
returns argument uh
and for just for the simple application
i have a linked list
and it has two routes you know pointing
one to the head and one to the last node
of the linked list
it's a circular linked list and nothing
really too exciting going on basically
what the application
threat does is it you know a thousand
times makes the
list and makes a list and then checks
the list
and so it generates a lot of garbage
like every time after the make list is
done
it's going to make a new one and so the
last list is basically garbage
and so the collector actually has
something to do and to make a list you
know is basically a little bit of
ugly code uh mostly because you know
every pointer needs to be
wrapped in this re-pointer check right
so no more normally of course this would
be
generated by a compiler but i don't
really have a compiler for a garbage
collected language and so i'm just
simulating
uh what maybe uh a compiler might have
generated
and basically what the you know the code
does it you know it goes through the
builds a list of at least list size
allocates a new element
uh and uh sticks at the prepended at the
beginning of the list and then updates
the last pointer to point basically to
the beginning of the list
so that's circular
any questions about this little fragment
of code
so the most interesting question of
course is what goes on exactly in the
collector and
let's first look at the case where
there's no virtual memory
where we're not using these tricks and
so we just have to look at two
apis one is new and read pointer
so use uh new if we get the mutexes that
is for the vm based
solution uh and basically what uh
if we forget that we're assuming that
we're actually not scanning we're not
collecting for a while
we basically uh we check if there's
enough
space left in free space if there's
enough in a free space
left you know we just bump up the
pointer a little bit you know to
allocate that object
and return it and if there's not
enough space less left then we basically
have to flip you know we have to do a
garbage collection run
and so we're going to look at flip
you know flip basically switches the two
and front pointers around
uh and uh then basically forwards you
know the two routes
that this application has you know to uh
the from the from space to the two-space
so let's look at forward
so here's forward uh it looks if the
you know forming the the object that is
pointed to by o it looks if o is
actually in the front space if it is in
the front space
and it has not been copied before then
uh we're gonna copy it and
uh and then we're done so we moved the
object from the
front space to the two space if we
already copied it then basically we can
replace the pointer
you know with the uh the new pointers
actually the
pointer to the already moved object and
return that
okay so that's forwarding
and so then the repointer you know we
actually have our
pointer basically go through
oops
let's see with the read pointer with the
card selected just with three pointer
uh it's like right here if we're not
using
uh if we're not using vm uh basically
what it does
uh it does a forward operation and the
forward operation is you know checking
if it's in the front space it's not in
the front space
then uh uh do nothing if it is in the
front space then do this copy again
and so here we see this is sort of the
expensive check is really you know
checking if the object actually sits in
the front space
any questions before i jump into sort of
the version that actually uses the vm
tricks okay let's look at
actually what the vm tricks uh
so the setup is uh a little bit
easier um basically you know there's a
call
called shipment open that allows you to
create a shared memory object
uh it's a linux call or a unix call and
it just almost behaves like a file but
it's not
you know it behaves like a file but it
is not a file it just
sits in memory there's no disk space
associated with it or anything it's like
an in-memory file system if you will
and uh basically you know what we're
doing is we allocate one of these
memory objects we truncate the shared
memory object 2 to be the size of the
sum of the two in the from space so we
have a space
and then we map it once
in the for the mutator and we map it
once you know for the collector
um and so this is basically you know
this sort of sequence of operations here
you know the share mem open the truncate
and the two maps
are basically sort of the equivalent of
the map two calls
and so we look at you know uh
let's go back up to our implementation
uh the read pointer in the vm case does
nothing you know there's no check
whatsoever we just return the pointer
straight
um and then you know of course if we use
the pillow pointer we're going to get a
page fault
like as before in the sig roots table
application
and here's the page fault handler uh
so if it is a if it's a page on and
actually let me
i'm running a little bit ahead here uh
if you know the object was uh moved
somewhere earlier
and it's sitting in the unscanned area
we're getting a page fault and basically
the
scan page you know function runs
um and but you know the the scan page
function runs actually with
you know the address ranges of the
collector and so it actually can work
because otherwise uh the mutator correct
you know the application cannot
uh touch those pages because that would
take a result in a page fault
and once you know we even unscan you
know once we have scanned all the pages
then you know the uh the
collector actually uh makes the page
actually accessible to the user
application
it may be helpful to look at flip again
just to see
what happens okay so that flip what
happens uh
we switch from the so the front space is
full
uh we make basically mark the whole two
space as non-accessible
you know to the application and then we
move the collector moves actually the
root head and the root last you know to
the two space that uh
the application cannot access uh or at
least not directly and you know that
will result whenever the application
accesses root head or last it will
actually result in a
page fault and then the collector can
copy things over and then unprotect the
one page
this makes sense
okay note in the handler correct that is
actually crucial that first the page is
scanned before
you know you make you know the page
accessible to the application because
if you were to uh make it
accessible before you scanned it uh you
know and if there were multiple
application threads
then those applications we might be
looking at you know objects on the
in the unscanned area and of course that
we need to forbid that that's over
the this code basically fur scans and
then uh
raises the protection level so that the
application can access the pages
any questions about the collector and
the tricks to use
virtual memory
okay well in that case i want to wrap up
and a couple points
uh i want to make or one point basically
um before uh wrapping up
uh you know one question to ask you know
should you use vm for this
and really is you know does these tricks
pay off and
uh because many of the uh you know
example the garbage collectors and there
are many garbage collectors out there
that actually don't use you know virtual
memory
uh at all but use basically instrument
you know the compiler is actually very
aware of the code generated and
instrument you know the code correctly
and has all kinds of other tricks to
reduce you know the performance overhead
so the activation is that in most cases
you know
it can be uh most cases could have been
implemented with extra instructions
and you know that is you know if you're
basically if it's a compiler or a
runtime or for a programming language
then maybe that's not that's so bad
because the compiler can do the
instrumentation
uh but if you know there's not a runtime
application it's not a compiler
application or a programming language
sort of setting then that might be
painful
and so it turns out that for you know
some of these applications
where you know like there's no compiler
involved at all for example like you
know check pointing
or you know the shared virtual memory
um you know those actually you know
really you know need these
these kind of primitives and so in
practice you know it is the case that
you know
enough application programmers have find
these primitive worthwhile that
basically today's operating system
support them
okay
some people ask or a lot of people
actually asking what has changed
you know since
what's it changed since 91
yeah one thing that has changed of
course like you know most unixes do
support the primitives now
and in fact there are many changes you
know since 91 yeah
you know maybe uh you're hard to imagine
but basically the there's a continuous
development
in the vm system so if you look at like
the
linux you know git log uh you'll see you
know there is uh
you know there's continuous development
of all aspects of the kernel
uh but including you know a contiguous
development of the vm system
um and you know some of the bigger
changes you know what are some big
changes in the last
you know whatever and years uh
there are there's a you know there's now
a five level page table
you know to deal with really large uh
you know
bigger addresses uh there is uh address
space identifiers to
deal with uh tob for the cops of tob
flushes
uh more recently a year ago or something
like that something that's called this
introduces called kpti kernel page table
isolation
uh which you know
is there because of the meltdown attacks
and which we'll talk about later in the
semester
uh so uh you know the the virtual memory
system is absolutely not a static
uh system almost after no aspect of any
kernel of the linux kernel is static
there's a dramatic amount of changes
like almost you know every couple months
uh in different aspects of the kernel
yeah and so in systems
once in a while actually completely
rewritten so
it's always in flux okay let me
stop with that and you know if anybody
has more questions you know people
please feel free to ask them or if you
have to go feel free to go
um could i ask about one of the first
slides
where um sorry i'm trying to see it
it's vm implementation like two slides
after
this one yep oh yes that one
um what do you mean exactly by
contiguous
range of addresses
yeah a continuous range of virtual
addresses
so you know the vma you know the vma
covers a range say from a thousand to
two thousand
and if you had another address range
like
2100 or something like that that would
be has its own vma
so every vma covers a continuous range
of addresses
so no holes in it okay
and it makes it easier as you will see
in the uh
as you will see in the map lab that will
make it much easier to reason about
things
okay in the range of the vma has no hole
in it
okay okay so those are for
um this particular um
use case for map i guess
right yeah yeah okay see
thank you so basically you can think
about it like for every nmap called
there's one vma
if the mf's don't overlap
oh okay okay i think i think i
understand
thank you you're welcome
i wanted to ask um so for um
um for the hi uh the to and from like
um garbage collection when do you stop
and start again like i i guess collector
runs can run all the time
if it's concurrent yeah that's like one
of the cool things about this
the vm solution the collector can just
run all the time and it can stop
once basically it has uh there's no more
unscanned objects
okay so you have but you have to go
through that means you
so so you'll go through all of the stuff
like all of the objects in the front
section and all
you're either like gonna collect them or
copy them over
how do you know you've gone through all
of them ah at some point you know you
you trace the object graph down correct
uh and at some point
you're not adding any objects anymore
because you already copied them in the
past
okay okay that makes sense yeah you
don't add any more you know basically
your
unscanned area is not growing so if your
unscanned grader is not growing anymore
you're done
okay okay and then when you copy it over
you
unmap it so if someone tries to like
access the old pointer it's going to be
invalid
yeah right okay that makes sense thanks
all right i'll see you guys
later
thank you you're welcome
okay i think that made it big yet for
today