started um and everybody could share
see my screen that i shared
and i hope everybody can hear me
let me i think we're good yep okay
um so i'm going to talk about fire file
system today and
um it's going to be actually we're going
to spend three lectures on file systems
two in the context of xv6 and one in the
context of
linux in fact so this is the sort of
last topic
uh that we're covering uh uh
off xv6 after uh this week we're
basically done
uh with xv6 um so
uh you know file systems uh you all
know them you use them uh they're one of
the most
sort of uh user-facing
aspects of an operating system in
addition to the shell
and uh and so we sort of want to
understand now and
these set of lectures actually what
really happens under the hoods and how
the file system is implemented
and that's sort of exciting because you
know you use it you use them all the
time
and maybe you just start off as a
question uh before diving in any of the
details
i in what way uh you know since you use
file systems uh
almost daily uh in one way is the xv6
file system different than the file
system
that you're using in a day-to-day
uh work and maybe i'll collapse them to
people and
see what they think for example kendall
kendall garner what did you notice
anything particular about xv6 that is
different or similar
i'm not sure we can hear your candle
no there you go yeah there you go okay
yeah
so one of the problems is size or at
least like the size of the files
that actually 16 support are much less
than a lot of other file systems also
the names
for some files are relatively short
and another feature it's more introduced
because i use
butterfast is it doesn't i don't think
it has copy on write
for a file system
in one way is a similar
it's similar in the general structure
so the idea of you have file names you
have the inodes
directories and all that yeah
that seems good and how about
[Music]
uh adela yang
how have we how do you compare xv6 file
system to the file system that you use
sorry also the question is like how
would you how would you compare the xv6
file system
to the file system that you might be
using in daily life
or on your laptop or whatever computer
you're using
um see similarities
yeah like the the file system path
system yeah like paths uh
in the file system are like hierarchical
yeah that's a good uh good point okay so
you know the so let me uh sort of dive
in a little bit and sort of you know
talk a little bit about properties or
file systems gonna that you know
sort of stand out uh and one i think you
know you just mentioned here uh vanilla
is a user
friendly
user-friendly names in particular path
names
you know how i encourage hierarchy to
help you know people to organize the
files in directories
or folders whatever term you want to use
um
and it makes it easy for you know people
to you know share
files
between users
and processes you can
name them with you know conveniently to
remember names
um and then probably most importantly uh
compared at least for all the uh
subsystems that we've looked so far in
xy6 and they provide persistence
or sometimes called durability
with that i mean like if you turn off
your computer uh you know you did some
work you turn off your computer and you
turn off your laptop uh and then you
know a couple days later you come back
you turn your computer on
uh the files are still there and uh
and you can continue uh working with
them
um which is sort of different from like
processes or uh
the thing of the resources that we've
seen so far which basically you know
the computer reboots you know they're
gone uh and you have to start them again
but file systems can provide this
persistence and so there uh
all of you are using them and what we're
going to be doing in the next couple
lectures is actually understanding how
to actually
work internally and this is interesting
for a number of reasons
one you know the abstraction
itself is just useful
and so it's interesting to understand
like under the hood it's actually how
the abstraction is actually implemented
and it turns out there's sort of a
couple key interesting aspects
one is crash safety
you'd like it to be the case that you
know if for example during a file system
operation
the computer crashes that after reboot
you know basically your file system is
still intact you know the you know all
the invariants sort of
the file system still hold and that you
can actually get access to most of your
files
it would be a disaster if like the
computer crashed in the middle of files
from operation
uh you reboot and there's no file system
anymore or you know the data structure
don't disk have been garbled
and you lost them and so this is
actually turned out to be a really
important topic and involved
and so we're going to talk about that on
wednesday this is basically the main
topic for wednesday's lecture
then there's sort of the general
question about like how to
lay out the file system on disk
you know the files the files the
directories
uh they all have to be represented in
some way on the disk because like after
you if you shut down your computer you
can back up you know the
all the data still has to be there and
so there's some basically on this data
structures
to represent uh the structure of the
file system or the content of the file
system
and uh in xy6 of course you know the the
representation or the data structures
used are quite simple you know just to
for pedagogical reasons and real file
systems use more complex uh data
structures but you could just think
about this as on this data structures
and so we'll see a lot of that in
today's lecture and then finally
uh what makes it interesting is
performance
the devices typically in which you know
file systems are stored you know storage
devices
are typically slow
the meaning example would be to write a
block you know on a solid state disk and
an ssd disk
that's going the order of a millisecond
and so in the middle second you can do a
ton a ton of work
uh and so it's important that you know
you try to avoid uh going to disk
and you'll see that in multiple ways so
we see that for example
all the file system will have something
of a buffer cache or a block cache
and you also see it in basically
additional forms or more concurrency
so for example if you do a path name
lookup
you know then that typically is an
involved operation
required to sending the directory
hierarchy you know looking up blocks in
for uh you know a directory finding the
file name in the directory then going to
the next directory etc etc
and you wanted to be the case that if
like one processor is doing path name
lookup another process can sort of run
concurrently
or in parallel with the first process
doing a path name lookup
and so we'll see that sort of
concurrency you know shows up again as a
big topic
uh in the context of file systems
the other reason why it's interesting is
it's going to be the topic of two labs
so we're going to have the next upcoming
lab is completely focused on file
systems and
the lab after that is a combination of
virtual memory and file systems and
even the lab for today or this week
correct has a component
trying to make the buffer cache more
parallel
so that's why it's interesting
and you know just to sort of get off the
ground and uh to understand like what
the file system must provide
just let's look again at the basic uh
file system system calls right so
the
example and from looking at that you
know api or there's these file system
calls
then we can sort of deduce a couple of
interesting properties that must be true
about the implementation um and so the
you know the file system calls
we've seen them early on in uh
in the semester and uh you know we've
looked at most other
unix system calls how to implement it
like fork and exec
pipes all that stuff and basically this
set of lectures is really focusing on
like how to implement the file system
calls
so uh so first of all let's start up
you know the simple case let's look at a
simple scenario
we have you know say we create a file x
y uh or file y
in the directory uh uh
x um
yeah i'll probably have to oops
in the file x we have to provide some
flags we don't really care about their
flag so i'm just going to ignore them
so this will create a file return a file
descriptor
uh you know to the caller and then the
caller the user apple application can
then actually for example write you know
to that file descriptor
as we've seen many times before there's
a write fd
maybe a b c you know three characters
uh and one thing's actually uh you know
already a couple things that we can
point out right from this uh these two
calls is that first of all
um the
path names that show up in the interface
and we're going to
have to implement uh names are uni
human readable they're not numbers
you know they get selected by the user
uh another interesting thing here is
that in the write system call
there's no offset as an argument so the
offset is implicit
so the file system somewhere must store
you know the offset if you do a second
call to right correct it will end up at
you know
the next set of bytes will written at
location four
um you know so maybe some more
interesting calls that we haven't looked
at much but for example you know the xv6
and the
all unit file systems basically support
calls to create
uh links uh to have multiple names
for the same file system for the same
file so for example
we might call a call like link that
basically creates a second
name for the original file so for
example creates name z
for the file y that we earlier created
um
so multiple names
so the file system probably internally
has to keep track you know in some way
that multiple names might be pointing to
the same file
uh you know we might actually remove
or change name space while a file is
open
so for example why we could call
you know user might actually call
another processor or the same process
might call you know unlink you know to
remove a particular file
um in fact you know we'll remove the
file x y that we actually opened earlier
but we still have a file descriptor open
and so in fact you know we can still
write to it
so we can still write it to fd you know
for example the characters whatever
d e and f
and that actually works out fine uh so
basically while you know a file file is
in use you know the name space that sort
of surrounds it there could actually be
changed and so it has to be the case you
know if you sort of look at this
you know set of things that there's a
bunch of interesting things going on
internally in the file system
so for example the file system the file
descriptor must be associated
with some you know object that
is independent of the name right you
know the
because you know even if the name
changes you know the file descriptor
still points or you know
uh uh references the the same file
object itself
and uh so in fact you know if you think
about this it has to be the case that
basically
uh there has to be some internal
representation of
you know the file inside of the
operating system that's independent of
the name
uh itself uh
and so we're gonna look at that in a
second but there's one other point i
wanted to make here is
you know the goal of the file system is
to implement an api like the ones that
we're looking here
which is the sort of typical file system
api
now this is of course not the only way
uh to build a storage system
or you know to store the information on
disk you know one could imagine
completely different apis um
and for example you know maybe
you know the database correct you know
stores data persistently
uh but accessing the data you know and
provides a very different programming or
api or user api
than a file system does and so just
important to keep in mind that
you know that you know there's other
ways of organizing
storage systems and where our focus is
going to be on a file system which is
typically provided by an operating
system and databases are
typically you know implemented on top of
the file system or in
almost work around you know the file
system
they can have direct access to disk
we have uh two questions in the chat
yeah ah yeah good
let me just gonna ask any questions
uh so link increments a reference to the
underlying file descriptor
and unlink the grant documented yes that
is correct
uh we'll talk a little bit more about it
later uh
another question here is about soft
links versus hard links
uh uh i'm probably not gonna talk much
about it
today but you will be implementing soft
links
in the next in the file system lab that
is upcoming
so xv6 by itself implements hard links
and then you will implement soft links
in addition any questions
other questions
link operates on the inodes not on the
file
descriptors right that's correct link
and
work on the item so let me since let's
let's go there so
file system structures
so what structures does the file system
maintain to
implement uh you know this api that i
just talked about
so first of all you know most important
probably is the inode
and so this is the object that
represents a file
independent of the name so file info
independent of the name
in fact you know the way you know your
name actually and i know this by an
know number it's just literally an
integer
so the file system internally refers to
inodes
by a number instead of flexibility by
path names
and we also know this is based on this
discussion uh you know the inode
must actually have a link count
to keep track of the number of um
to keep track of the number of names
that are pointing to that particular
inode
and the file should only be deleted you
know when the link count actually
reaches zero no earlier
it's actually slightly more complicated
there must be also
an open fd count
you know number file descriptors that
actually have the file open
and the file can only be deleted when
both of these are zero
uh we also know that basically based on
you know the rights have no
offset nor does read you know that the
file descriptor implicitly
must maintain an offset
okay and so basically the central really
data structure
in the file system and is the the inode
and then
and the file descriptor to actually uh
interact you know with processes
um so um even though like the file
systems are very similar
in terms of their api you know they're
all implemented
differently but
many of them have sort of a similar
structure
[Music]
and because the file systems are quite
complex you know it just helps to sort
of organize them and
they're typically organized in a sort of
set of layers and
you know one way to think about it this
is that at the very bottom there's the
disk
you know some storage device that
actually holds you know the data
and that actually provides the
persistence and durability
typically you know there's something
like a buffer cache or a block cache
right above it so that
to avoid you know going to disk uh many
times so we're going to cache basically
data inside
in memory so this is going to be
basically you know
memory
and this is the device
um for persistence there's something
typical of a logging layer
you know many file systems have a form
of logging
and we're going to talk mostly about it
wednesday so i can skip that
um then in the top of the logging
language in this in xv6
there's an i cache or an inode cache
this is mostly for
synchronization as well talk about a
little bit later
so now you notice typically smaller than
a disc block and then the i notes are
packed into a single disc block
and to basically provide synchronization
to those individual inodes
i you know xc6 maintains an i cache
um and then typically that you know
we're going to there's the inode
implementation itself you know that sort
of ranges for region rights
bytes
and then you know on top of that we have
names like path names and file
descriptor operations
um anywhere every file system is
slightly different organized
and the layers may be slightly different
maybe the layering is not always that
strict and even in xc6 it's not always
super strict
but it's conceptually a good way to
think about it and almost all file
systems have components in their file
system there's correspond to the
different pieces you know the buffer
cache then the logging uh to the inode
and to uh path names and so we're going
to basically work my crew a little bit
uh through you know these different file
system layers
let me talk a little bit starting with
the bottom layer
um
yeah okay let's just looking at the
chat so let me start with the talk a
little bit about
storage itself storage devices
it turns out there are many many many
different types of storage devices
uh and the differences are in
performance you know capacity
uh and the degree of durability um
but you know two of the common ones you
know are you know you're probably all
familiar with you know
an ssd and there may be
you know some people may still make
using hard disks
or magnetic disks and
you know they provide a ton of storage
uh
reasonable cost uh in the different
performance so
ssds have typically in the order of like
100 microseconds
to the milliseconds access time
while magnetic disks tend to be more in
the order of 10 milliseconds
to individually rewrite a block
um the terminology is actually slightly
confusing here you know
the terms sector that are being used
blocks
and so in sectors is typically the is
historically the sort of smallest unit
uh that uh this drags uh
can read and write in uh and so it used
to be typically five and twelve bytes
versus the common number
uh the block size is basically where
block is basically an os or a file
system
idea or defined by the file system and
in xv6 for example it is 1024 bytes
and so it's two sectors so typically the
block size is one or more
sectors sometimes you know people refer
to the sectors on disk also as blocks
and so you know the terminology is not
particularly
precise so these devices you know
basically sit
you know on some bus and you know the
bus is you know connected to the cpu
right uh you know there might be memory
here on the side here
and there's maybe multiple cpus uh and
if the file system runs on you know the
cpu uh stores its internal data
structures in memory
and basically reads and writes uh
you know to uh
to the ssd or the hard disk to actually
write a block or read a block
and so actually the interface is quite
simple
so it's typically just read you know or
write with block number
now there's a little bit of
oversimplification but like but the core
of the interface is
roughly that um and internally of course
the ssds and the ad
hard disk work completely differently
and
but the hardware extracts it mostly away
typically the sort of standard protocol
like pci
or pci extended uh that
the the processor or the file system
users or
the disk drivers used to actually talk
to
disks and often from the disk driver
you know most discs can sort of look the
same uh
and you can just read and write them you
know by providing a block number and
some data
and then uh you know send it off or
write it to the control registers you
know to the device and then the device
actually will do its job
so this from a file system perspective
uh although you know the the disk have
quite the storage device have quite
different properties
uh they're actually uh uh from the
driver perspective you know they're sure
you can program it
roughly in the same way
any questions about that i'm not going
to talk much about the storage devices
so but
so if you have any questions this would
be really good good time to ask them
yes i have a question is the interface
for uh calling read or write
something that offers synchronous and
asynchronous options
yeah uh often this is the case in fact
it's generally like it's almost
very similar to actually basically you
can think about the driver for a disk
in the same way as the console driver
where
the cpu or the driver issues a command
to the device
basically say start read or do right and
then at some point later when the device
is done it will generate an interrupt
saying like okay i did the read or i did
the right
and then you know that indicates the
completion
uh and you know of course the driver you
know since the this device is more
complicated than
the console you know it's quite a bit
more complicated driver than the console
driver that we saw in uh
in previous lectures it's basically the
same structure the bottom half
top half interrupts uh and reading the
writing to control the registration
okay thanks
okay so so from the final system
perspective
uh the way to think about the disk is
uh pretty straightforward uh since
there's a read and write of block
or sectors we can just think about the
discuss basically a gigantic
you know array of blocks
you know starting at you know whatever
zero you know one
and going up to whatever the size of the
disk is
uh and basically the file system's job
is to sort of lay out all the data
structures
on the disk in a way that you know it
can reconstruct you know the
file system after uh reboot
and so you know there are different ways
you're going about it
xv6 also c uses a very simple layout
structure uh
but but not
completely unusual not pretty typical in
uh or prototypical for uh how file
systems operate
uh so typically the block zero is
generally not used or
used actually for the boot sector so to
boot the operating system
uh block z1 is often what's called the
super blog
and the superbob basically describes you
know the file system
and it may say like well there's so many
blocks on this can that constitute the
file system
and we'll see in a second that in xc6
there's a little bit more information in
it as you can make most of the file
system
so for example in xv6 the log starts at
block 2 and runs into block 32
and so this is the log and of course law
could be different size and in fact in
the super block it just says like the
log is
whatever 30 blocks long um
then uh and xv6 after that
stores from 32 to basically block 45.
if i remember correctly it stores inodes
and i said before uh multiple i notes
are packed into a single
uh this block i think can i notice
i believe i don't actually remember at
the top of my head but i think it's
either 64 bytes
or 128 i believe 64.
and after that you know there's uh
a bitmap block it turns out in the
default way we built the file system
is next to the bitmap block is one block
in size
and so these basically keep track of
actually the data blocks
uh whether they're free or not and after
that you know it's all
from basically here to there it's all
data blocks so data blocks that actually
store contents or files or contents of
directories
often all the bitmap blocks and inode
blocks and
logging block are often sometimes
referred to as metadata blocks
and they don't actually store actual
data but they help you know they store
meta information for the file system to
do its job
like bitmaps and ions um
any questions so far about this
um i have a question about the boot
block does it contain
the code for the operating system to
boot or something else
yeah uh exactly it typically contains
you know
uh you know one block of uh code
enough for the operating system to get
going and then load maybe more
of the operating system actually from
the file system itself
thank you so does that mean that the
code for xv6 is actually stored on like
the virtual disk
or is it like how to uh
the way we do the qmu you know we cut
some corners
uh and qmu actually has a flag you know
dash kernel that basically
points to the where it boots the kernel
from and loads you know that at a
particular address
into physical memory at 08000
and so basically when we're using qmu
the way we're using qmu we don't
really have to worry about boot sectors
and anything like that
okay so basically like when you run
qe mu you just um
you just pass in like the the program
yes through the command line and then
it'll just run that it doesn't need to
like read it from the virtual disk and
everything
exactly that makes sense
okay so like you know the uh so for
example um
so assuming that i know it's uh uh 64
bytes you know so example now if you
want to read
uh inode 10
what do you do how do you read i know
10.
anybody
when which block will i know 10b
you'd need to add you take the inode
number
and add the offset into the disk so 10
32 yeah so 32 correct
and is it literally plus 10 or something
else
is it 10 divided by the size
yeah it's going to be whatever it's
going to be the note number
high note number uh
multiplied times we do it in bytes you
know multiplied
by 64. directly divided by
5's and 24.
so i know 0 will end up in block 32
uh i note whatever
524 divided by 64.
16. yeah 16 that sounds about right so i
know it's 17
where will it where will it end up
should be an item it should be in block
33 correct
does that make sense so given an unknown
number we can always find
the bytes on disk where the inode
actually stored
okay
okay so then let's look at the
what actually is in an on disk inode
so as we you know before you know we'll
see there's a
basically a little data structure you
know 64 bytes in size
and you know typically has a type which
we'll talk about a little bit later but
for example the type is file or
directory
end link you know the link count
you know to track if multiple names are
pointing to the same inode
a size in bytes
and then uh in x36 you know that can be
slightly different in different file
system exactly how the representation is
but in xv6 a little bit more space
the nexus 6 basically is followed by a
number of block numbers
uh and so it has a block number zero
block number one the factors are there
there are 12 of those guys it's called
direct block numbers
and those direct node block numbers
basically correspond to the first you
know
12 blocks that constitute that file so
for example if the file was only two
bytes long
you know there would be only one uh
block number zero
and that block number zero is the the
block number of the disk block that
contains
you know the first and a few bytes of
those that file
and then there's one indirect block
number
and basically that's a block number that
corresponds to a block
which then itself you know block is 5 to
24 bytes you know which holds
uh 256 block numbers
so block number zero for block number
eleven
are all uh direct block numbers and so
then
block number twelve cannot be stored in
that
uh in that indirect block
that basically is pointed to by you know
the indirect block number
uh and that is basically the
layout of the file in
xv6 and so what is the maximum file size
in xv6 based on this
anybody
maybe 268 times a 1024 bytes
basically yeah right so it's just 256
plus 12 the 12 uh direct
times 1024 and then we get the maximum
file size in bytes
right how much is that
another way of saying it's basically 268
kilobytes correct
what can you store in 268 kilobytes
can you store a video in it
or a song
if it's a short song yes
[Laughter]
very short song correct uh so these are
it's a really small file size correct
like real file systems
much much much bigger file size so what
could you do during file system
representation to make this
to a lot of the file system be much more
files to be much bigger
could you uh extend the indirect portion
yeah like for example you could have
another block sitting here below correct
which is maybe double indirect
almost like you know in the sort of the
page table type data structures that
we've seen before
right then that double indirect block
points to 256 indirect block numbers
each which point to
another block number right and so
suddenly the file size is gonna
the maximum file size is much there and
basically this turns out to be just a
sort of an exercise in on
this data structure you could pick a
like a structure like this like
a tree but there's also possible to like
maybe implement it as a b3
or something other sophisticated xv6
does something extremely simple
uh and basically it's remodeled after
the original version six units
unix but you can implement more
sophisticated schemes in fact in the
file system lab you will implement
double indirect
block numbers to support much bigger
files
any questions about this
sorry so is it 256 blocks
because it's uh like one block as a
whole
this is an indirect block number so that
doesn't count so there's 256
sitting in this indirect block plus 12
direct
block numbers that makes it 268.
oh sorry my question was why is it to
oh because it's uh block numbers four
bytes probably
so 1024 divided by 4 is 256 entries
okay thank you which is also a little
bit ridiculous
if a block number is only four bytes how
big can this be
anybody
2 to the power 32 right
some things are bigger than that and so
typically you know people use larger
uh sizes for
block numbers than 32 bits
okay any questions further questions
for the max file size or could you
could you help um could you explain that
again like
okay sure could each block in the
could each block in that's referenced by
the indirect block could that
also um point to more blocks
if that makes sense well in the default
xp6 design uh that's not the case
basically they're 12 block numbers 12
direct block numbers and 256 inbreak
block numbers
and nothing more and
in the next lab you'll be adding a
doubling direct block to the inode
so you will take one of these bnl 11's
and turn that into a double indirect
and that double indirect you know it's
going to point to
basically that's going to have 256
indirect block numbers which itself then
point to
you know blocks and that way the file
can be
substantially bigger
oh okay thanks
okay so now let's say you know we want
to implement the read system call
and uh you know basically we start from
uh
uh so the operating system boots that
wants to read
say byte you know read
by 8 000.
how would you you know which block would
you read
which block will contain basically byte
8 000.
how would you compute or how you would
look up you know given this data
structure
this extremely simple data structure how
would you compute
actually the block number that or find
the block number that contains
by 8 000.
uh anybody do you just um
subtract like first of all subtract the
number of bytes in the first 12 direct
blocks
and then see what the offset is in the
indirect blocks
yeah so okay so in case of 8 000 just
what we will do correct we'll divide it
by 1024 because that's the block size
and that is uh seven right
and so that means that basically the
seventh block
actually has the second entry in this
direct block number
has the block number that contains you
know byte 8000
correct so bnn7
whatever number is there is the block
number that contains
for this particular file uh
byte8000 and to actually find out
exactly where that
byte is inside of that block you know
basically we have to compute 8 000
micro of 24
which is probably i think is 832
okay so basically to read by 8000
you know the file system looks at the
inode well
takes the byte number divides it by 1024
indexes
into uh c c's if it falls below 12 then
there's a direct block number
uh and just picks up the direct block
number from
the inode reads that block and then
fishes out you know the 8 000 byte by
computing 8 000 divided by found by
module 1024
and so it will give us an offset of 832
and that's the
location for uh byte8000.file
okay so basically this is enough
information you know the thing to
conclude from this is like there's
enough information here now to actually
uh implement you know read and write
system calls at least to find out which
disk blocks
need to be written written write for
written uh
in response to a reader write system
call
okay
so let me talk a little bit about
directories
one of the cool things about you know
file systems where you have a
hierarchical
namespace and you can still store
symbolic user-friendly names inside of a
inside of a inside of the file system
and and the interesting aspect actually
uh one of the cool
uh design features of uh most of these
unix file systems is actually the
directory
is basically the file except the file
with some structure
that the file system understands and in
fact in xv6 you know the structure is
extremely simple every
the directory consists of directory
entries and every entry
has a fixed format namely it contains an
inode number
in the first two bytes
and it contains the file name
in the remaining 14 bytes and so the
total thing is 16 bytes
and this is enough information
you know basically for uh you know to
actually implement path name lookup
so for example just to make it clear
let's say we want to look up
you know the path name uh y
uh x uh how we go about doing that
so well you know this path name explain
indicates that we have to start at the
root i note
and it turns out that through guideline
basically has a fixed you know there's a
fixed inode number
the root high note number has a
pre-agreed fiction number and in fact in
xv6 that number is one
so how can we find the root inode number
now we have to go back to our earlier
picture correct uh it's number one
you know we know that you know i know
start at block 32 so it must be infinity
block 32
and so it's the byte 16 to whatever
byte 64 to 128 in that first block
that contains the root i node number and
so the files
who can just read the root i node number
okay
and then basically the way path name
lookups works is it just scans
the blocks
therefore you know the name
y so the file system basically go
through
reach the blocks of the inode
of file inode one one by one and just
looks kind of for the date of those
blocks
uh whether the string y appears and how
can it find
all the blocks of the i note one well
just can look at the it reads the
bn0 the first block you know sees if uh
x is in that you know if it's not it
will read the second block etc etc
until hopefully at some point either it
finds it or doesn't find it
and if it finds it say let's refine file
x
in the directory you know it's going to
have some inode number say 251
and then we can just proceed from there
right we can say it's like well
okay we'll now read you know block
number you know read
inode 251
and scan its blocks
for uh okay i just did my example wrong
this was y and this again is blocks for
x
and that joomla is going to find us you
know so my note number again and we'll
return that as the result of the
pathetic lookup
any questions about this
so this is the layout of the directory
in
the disk but is there some bit somewhere
uh in the metadata blocks that indicates
whether the current thing is a directory
or a file
yeah it's actually in the inode so the
type of the inode
says whether it's a directory or file so
if you do look up on
an inode that actually happens to be a
file then actually the file system will
return an error
i see thanks
okay
now clearly this structure is not uh
particularly efficient uh you know to
actually find an uh
directory name you know you have to scan
uh and so a real file system you know
probably uh would look
would use more sophisticated data
structures to uh actually
make these lookups much faster than xv6
does
but again that's sort of almost you know
more design or question of data
structures then that is a question of
operating system design
and so you could plug in your favorite
uh data structure and turn it into an on
this data structure
and then hopefully you're going to get
better performance
but for simplicity and easy explanation
you know
actually uses this very simple structure
okay okay so what i
want to do next is going to get a little
bit more concrete feel for this and just
to see actually how things work out in
practice
uh in xc6 and this will be helpful you
know for the
next lap so i'm going to
look at xv6 for a second here's the
usual
screen
[Music]
um so the first thing i'm going to boot
xv6 again as always
and i did make clean and as you probably
remember you know where many of you have
run into this you know if you want
actually a new file system
you have to run make clean because then
make qmu will build you a new clean file
system
so here we go
and we'll see that xv6 uh
has started but the thing i want to
point out first is
uh here here you'll see there's a call
to uh basically make a file system so
this makes a
a fresh disk image uh and in the disk
image you know contains
you know a bunch of files that we
specify in the command line
and aft and make it fast basically
builds your new file system that
contains those files as the content of
the file system
and you can see you know the xv6 always
prints out a bit of information about
the file system
so it basically says there are 46 meta
blocks you know that includes the boot
block the super block
the 30 log blocks 39 note blocks one
bitmap block
and then followed by 954 data blocks so
it's a tiny file system in total of only
a thousand blocks
and one of the things you will do in the
lab
for to support bigger files you also
will have to use a much bigger
file system
then i modified xc6 slightly to
basically
write or print something whenever we
write to a particular block
uh so for example we see a couple of
file system calls with the
x26 when it starts up does a bunch of
file system calls
and apparently wrote you know block 33
43 46 or 42
and now we're going to run basically
command and we're just going to see
what block numbers are are being written
uh by that command or as a
cause of that command and we're going to
try to understand what are those
where do those rights make sense well we
expect more of it uh to see if that when
actually uh
to see what is happening is what we
actually expect
so we're just going to create a file uh
echo hi
and i'm going to create a file x
and let me actually
copy that a little bit over so i can
delineate this i'm going to delineate it
in a couple places just for
help for understanding uh
probably right here and
and then probably here yeah
okay uh so basically it turns out
there's going to be
a couple phases here one is the face to
actually create
the file
then uh there is right the file
namely right hi the file and then
you know one more right right actually
the new line
into the file
so you look at the echo you know program
that is basically what it does
i can actually pick it up
just do it for completeness right so
echo
uh looks at his arguments writes
the arguments to uh file the script one
and then at the end of the pence
a new line okay so these are the
basically the sequences
of disk rights involved in each
operation
and let's you know look at them one by
one and try to understand what's going
on i'm gonna
basically maybe the easiest thing to do
actually is to
move this over
[Music]
okay so uh it's convenient
uh to understand what's going on instead
of looking at the code we're gonna
actually just look at this
disk layout and try to figure out
what might be going on in these
particular operations
um
okay good so what do we think
this right is
any idea what this might actually be
we're creating a file so what do we
expect the file system to do
it writes the inode entry yes the first
thing i got
there's two uh so okay so good it's 33
so what do we know about block 33
if we look at the disk layout picture
it contains a free eye node yeah
it contains uh we know that i know one
lives in 32 correct
uh and so we're whatever apparently uh
uh the ionite that's being allocated is
probably an i know that lives in block
4d3
and presumably the first right might
just be marking you know that this inode
actually is now going to be used and so
i think the way
xv6 does this it uses the type field
uh in the inode to actually indicate
where an eye notes is free a file or a
directory so
basically change it from free to a file
and
write it to the disk to mark it as in
use
what do you think the next write 33 is
actually populating the inode entry with
like
info yeah exactly is indeed populating
the i know name for
you know i know it's probably with
entries like setting the link count to
one
uh and things like that right
and what is 46 what do we expect 46 to
be you in 32 maybe that's it
is 46 the first data
no actually bitmap bitmap
no it's just it's a data block and
you're right it's the first data block
okay so whose data block do you think
this is
it's the uh root directory
uh entry yeah correct this is
this is probably the block first block
of you know the root directory here
which i node one
right and why where are we expecting you
know
actually that to be written one has
because
because we're um
we're creating like x in we're adding a
new file x in the current directory so
we're adding it to like the file
hierarchy
yeah exactly so we presumably what i
have done is like we just uh
added an entry to the root the root
directory namely the entry x
without whatever inode we allocated in
you know the
stack two steps before does that make
sense
what do we think this writer 32 is
to block 32 well the easy thing to do is
go back and look at the dick's layout
picture
and what is block 32
i know the one probably yeah well
it will include i not one it includes
also other i knows correct because i
know it's smaller than a block but you
know we'll
include inode one why do you think it's
going to be written
what what might have changed in the
inode that requires that the i node
actually be written to disk
the size yeah the size of change exactly
the size of change because when we grew
the directory correct by
16 bytes to actually store the entry x
and then there's one more right to 34
and i'll leave that hanging for a second
but basically we're updating the know
for x one more
time uh even though nothing actually
really was written yet
uh okay
so that's the first phase so let's now
look at uh the second
you know the so this was creation now
let's look at the second phase or the
first
right you know the right of height to
file x
where what do we think 45 yes
bitmap yeah it's the bitmap so remember
what happened here is correct that the
file system uh scanned the bitmap block
to find a block that was not in use you
know so find a bit
bit zero and then uh
set that bit you know to one to indicate
that that particular block now is in use
and so it wrote you know 45 to the disk
because it updated the bitmap block
and what block do you think the bitmap
allocator picked
595. yeah most likely correct because
right after it we see you're right to
5.95
uh and that's presumably you know that
was allocated to the file x
and so basically in the inode correct of
file x now in bn0
we'll have the number 595
and and basically what will be the first
byte
what's the value of the first byte of
block 595
after this right h
h yeah and what do you think the second
right is
this one i
yes i right because every
echoed you know there's a character by
character
okay what do we think this right 33 is
validating the size again yeah updating
the size of the inode of x because now
it has two bytes in it
does it make sense
uh question 595 seems
very high up in the disc is that because
there's other
stuff that's currently living there like
the kernel boot code and other
things that have already been stored
well yeah we can look at we go back to
the
this screen and we can look at what make
fs did right so make a vest stored a
whole bunch of
files there in the files before we
actually created filex
and in fact we've created all these guys
and so presumably a good chunk of the
disk is already filled you know by the
files the
for the blocks the number of the blocks
already
used basically by these set of files
regardless um would it
write down that block 595 is
related to that to that i know
during the last uh like during the write
three two that yes exactly correct so
this right through three probably a
bunch of things happen right the size
got updated
and you know bn0 and bn1
were updated or actually only bn0 is
updated correct to contain 595 and both
pieces of information
are updated in the inode and then
written to the disk by this right
what makes sense yeah yeah thank you
good so that's uh you know sort of the
essence of
sort of disk layout and hopefully you
know you have a pretty good
understanding uh
uh what goes on uh to make this work and
so let's
we're gonna look at a little bit more in
detail now at the code uh
to see actually uh things in them
uh you know one more level of detail
okay so the first thing since we
allocated now i know let's first look at
actually
uh how uh how that happened
uh so in cis file let's actually
kernel
so here are all the calls related to
file system calls so the first thing
that actually happens correct was just
open
because we're going to create a file sys
open we'll call create
and here's create create
we'll look at this later the resolve the
path name
to basically the last directory
walks the directory and then does lookup
and i really care about that
just to see if the file already exists
and if the file exists you know maybe
you'll turn an error
and then it calls inaudible and so this
is the
call that is going to allocate this
inode for
the file x so let's look at that that is
going to be in
fs.c
and here's iai alec and like most xv6
code you know it's just
very simple but not particularly
efficient uh
and so what it does basically it goes
from all the it numbers
possible uh from one to whatever the
maximum number of inodes that are
possible in this particular file system
and then reach
the block for that i know number so for
example starts with one
reach you know the block that contains i
note number one
and uh and
then sees if that i know number uh is
free
and if it's not if it is free then
uh it sets it to uh file and
that way marks it as allocated and
writes it to disk
and this log right you know actually the
print statements i had
i could actually log right and so that
log right
um uh was the first write that we've
seen
uh in that sequence of writes that we
did
or that the file system did does this
make sense
so an interesting uh so this is
basically sort of the sequence of events
that get you to the first
you know right to the disk uh
interesting uh question of course is
uh what what happens if like multiple uh
processes
uh are calling create at the same time
kind of
a multi-core machine you know that can
be running in parallel you know coming
down
and all will get to iallic roughly at
the same time
and then all they're going to call
they're going to call b reit right and
so there has to be some story
for how these rights don't interfere
with each other
and this is really more of what i'm
looking into uh because in some sense
you know this is actually the
part of the uh last part of this lab
that you're currently doing
so that gets us into the buffer cache
uh so let's look at b read so b
read what the first thing it does
actually is called b get and so
basically b get gets a versus slot in
the buffer cache
let's look at the be get for a little
while
because there's a reasonable tricky code
and so what's going on in the first
couple lines here
i imagine some of you already looked at
this code quite a bit of detail as part
of this lap
the locking lock so what's going on here
um it blocks the linked list and checks
if any of the um things in the
cache are matching with what we're
looking for
yeah right so the so basically this is
the cache in action
uh we're looking for whatever the block
number uh i guess block number
33 and we're basically seeing if the
cache already has
block number 33 and
um and if that is the case it bumps the
ref count
up and uh and then releases the b cache
lock
because we're done looking in the cache
itself we know it's there
or we know that there's a buffer buffer
for that particular block there
and and then the next step that actually
happens
is sort of interesting the next step
the block cache basically tries to uh
get a lock
on the buffer so
uh so what happens is like multiple
processes at the same time called bcat
well one of them is going to get the b
cache lock
right it's going to scan the buffer
cache and so nobody can actually modify
the buffer cache at this particular
point
find if the block number is there and if
the block number is there
uh it bumps the ref count indicating
that basically
it has a reference you know to this
this particular block and then releases
the the cache lock
so if there were a second process
waiting
uh or to also scan the this cache
it might now actually acquire the lock
right away right in fact there might be
a second process you know scanning for
one also want to scan
for this block 33 and it will also get
you know basically a reference to
uh b uh bump up the reference count uh
two two or three whatever it is and then
you know both of them will try to call
acquire a sleep
on that particular buffer buffer 33. and
acquire sleep is just basically another
type of lock
uh there we call them sleep locks and
we'll talk about it in a second uh
but basically the this acquires the lock
on the buffer so one of the two
processes will get the
the lock of buffer 33 and we'll proceed
and that will be returned and it will
go through the motions you know of like
scanning that block 33 to see if there's
an eye node that exactly is free
and the other process will just be
sitting in the acquired sleep here
you know waiting until the first process
is done
with all its operations
any questions about this
um i have a question
um while the ref count of a block
is not zero can anything important about
that block
change because something can happen
between the release of the big cash
and acquiring the lock of the block
yeah actually the the the the protocol
okay so there's a couple points i want
to make here the
the protocol that basically uh uh xv6
follows is that you know for any
modification to the b cache itself
you need to hold the b catch lock for
any modification to this block 33
you need to hold the sleep lock on block
and so at any particular point of time
uh
so after the release um the
b ref count is uh larger than zero
and there will be no modification to the
buffer cache okay the buffer cache will
only invict
or things that actually have a ref count
of zero never that has a ref count of
something bigger than
zero and so we know for sure that this
block basically this buffer
won't be touched in the b cache itself
you know other processes might be
looking up
might be looking up the entry in the b
cache
but it won't be removed from the b cache
correct yeah makes sense this lock
that second lock this sleep lock is
really what protects the content of the
buffer
and ensuring that only one process
actually will be reading and writing the
buffer
at any particular point in time
and it's important correct that
ken is saying would it be bad if this
like say
would it be bad if block 33 ended up in
the cache twice
in different slots
yeah because then you could have the
correct information right
yeah okay for example let's say process
one writes i note
you know 19 and the other process writes
i know 20 correct and
so if they both get a handle on the
buffer for
that represents you know the block 33
that one might power update i note 18
the other guy
19 the first one maybe writes it right
18 back to the disc
then the the guy that does modified 19
writes 19 back
but will overwrite the changes that 18
made right that were made for inode 18.
and so that's terrible so it has to be
the case
the block number uh only appears in the
buffer cache only exactly once
and there's an invariant correct that
you know that you sort of have to
maintain while you're doing this uh
block cache lab
uh locking lab in uh in this week's lab
does that make sense that invariant
yeah i guess tangential question to this
there might be
some blocks that have multiple
references to them
and then maybe one of the processes that
has
is touching this block flushes the cache
by forcing a right to the disk uh what
happens
to what everyone else sees well as
uh the if the right okay so if the first
process is done
at some point we'll call release again
where it is it's called uh so basically
you can think about
uh at the end when the first process is
done with its reading and writing to
that block 33
and we'll call b release for that buffer
and that will actually
uh decrease the reference count what
releases sleep lock
and that means that if anybody was
waiting any other process was waiting
for that particular buffer
it will now be able to get the uh sleep
lock on the buffer
and go read uh it and we'll observe
uh the preview the new make changes
right so if the two processes we're
trying to maybe update i note 18 and i
know 19 that all both live in block 33
then if the first process is done it
changes of 18 are visible
and so the next and so the next guy will
actually allocate
i know 19 because actually 18 is marked
as a file now
so anybody afterwards will observe the
changes
make sense yes
thanks and this is exactly what we hope
to be the case correct
if you know if one process creates an
inode or creates a file then the
impression later process does read you
know it should observe that file
okay then uh one more
smaller detail as you can see here in
the code you know the
process actually takes a sleep lock on
the buffer and so the sleep lock is
slightly different than
a regular or spin lock so let's look at
sleep lock for a second
and you see what it is so you require a
sleep lock
yeah and what it does it requires
you know some field it basically
requires a spin lock that is associated
with the sleep lock
if the lock is actually held
if the spin lock is held then uh
if the lock is actually held so there's
okay let me
first see the h5 so the h file contains
a locked field
um and
uh and that's it
and so basically
[Music]
that was the spin lock yeah where's the
spin lock
oh uh
yeah there's a spin lock and
sorry about that uh and then if the lock
is actually held there's the sleep lock
is held it actually goes to sleep
so it deschedules itself uh and
why why do you think for these buffers
are we using
slip blocks instead of spin locks
because indirectly we're using spin
locks to implement sleep blocks
but why not just use regular uh
because disk operations take a long time
yeah you know so multiple reasons
uh there are all kinds of rules correct
restrictions on uh
on spin locks like what is one of the
restrictions on spin launch
what do you think traps have to be off
yeah they turn interrupts off correct
and so we were would start a disc
operation
uh while holding a buffer while holding
a spin block on the buffer then we would
never hear from the disc
well maybe another cord will hear but
like if we had only one core and we
would never hear from it
right and furthermore
and for the same reasons you know you're
not allowed to go to sleep while holding
a spin lock
uh and so therefore we have these slip
blocks that are sort of long-term locks
if you will
uh that uh for for that particular use
case
so that we can hold uh locks or
one of the advantages of sleep locks is
that we can hold them across interrupts
and we can
hold them because disc operations and we
can hold them for long periods of time
and we're not if if we're waiting on
that lock we're also not uh
keeping the cpu busy or spinning on the
cpu we're basically releasing the cpu by
calling
sleep does that make sense
any questions about this
okay let's look at one more
thing which is
uh uh b release
uh so we looked at it already a little
bit you know basically what b release
does it releases the sleep lock
then acquire ftb cache log decrements
reference count to indicate that one
process is not interested anymore in
this particular buffer
and then if if the left count is zero
it manipulates the
list of buffers a little bit what does
it do here
um it inserts the
b into the position after
the head inside of the like list
yeah where does it basically go what
does that mean
so let's go back up correct and actually
look at that
it was the most recently used
yeah you know basically moves it into
the position of the most recently used
buffer
right and this is important because when
uh when we cannot find the block in the
block cache
then we need to evict something to make
space
right and so we're going to go through
the blocks as we go and we basically
start from the most from the least
recently used one
and that one first uh
and so if we just use the buffer it's
very unlikely that it actually we
evicted
why is that a good policy
generally systems obey uh temporal
locality
yeah right so if a block is recently
used
it's probably a good indicator that it
might actually be used again quickly
and so it is a good idea not to evict it
uh you want to
and it's generally sort of if you even
you know have locality
uh catholic then the block that is you
know the least
uh recently used is probably the block
that is also most likely to be
used in the future and so that's a good
one to evict
does that make sense
okay so
uh let me just go back to my slice here
so
um so this is a little bit of sort of an
uh
slight excursion in the
be cache code or the
block cache
and there's a couple interesting things
to point to correct you know there's
this invariant that there's only one
copy of a block in memory
and that's an important variant that
must be maintained by the block cache it
has these sleep blocks and different
type of locks
than the ones that we've seen before
that can span io operations
it implements you know lru at least
recently caching replacement policy
and it has sort of this uh two levels of
locking
to uh uh in its implementation one level
to basically protect the be cache
internal data structures and then one
level of locking through sleep locks to
actually
lock individual buffers
does that make sense okay um
so i'm gonna about to grow another time
so we'll just may uh stop here
uh you know quickly summarize that we
what we have seen so far and then
wednesday we're gonna focus really on a
crash uh
safety so basically you know a file
system is on this data structure
and basically most of the lecture today
was sort of focusing on the layout
of the on this data structure of the xv6
this data structure on disk and you know
we saw that xv6 has a very simple one
but you can imagine like you know
implementing more a complicated one
the other thing that we spend a bit of
time looking at is this block hash which
is crucial for performance
because reading and writing typically to
the disk is actually expensive you know
in order for you know hundreds of
microseconds to do milliseconds
and the block cache basically ensures
that um
you know if a block was recently read
from the disk you know we're actually
not reading it again from the disk
okay and then wednesday i'm going to
talk about
crash safety which is a
fascinating other aspect of file system
design in fact we'll spend two lectures
on crash safety
we'll see a logging design on wednesday
that's slow and then next week we'll
look at
how linux ext3 does logging which is a
much more faster
scheme if you have any other questions
please feel to hang around and i'm happy
to answer
them otherwise you know see you
wednesday
all right thank you um i have a question
about
b-release yes
um so it seems like it releases the
blocks lock and after that it
modifies the ref count
why is that okay yeah good question
so what do we know you know so let's say
we do release the sleep lock
uh so if some other guy or some other
process actually
uh was waiting or was doing an acquiring
slew flock
what does that mean about the ref count
that it was zero
no correct like if n processes are
waiting for
uh a buffer oh okay
that was at least one yo
more than one great if ten prices you're
waiting then the reference would be ten
yeah okay and so
uh basically this only this only line of
code what it does is basically it
updates the ref count for this one guy
which is one process that actually did
the release and it releases the
breath cam to buy one and
if other people were waiting it will
never the ref cup will definitely not be
zero and we'll do it we'll never execute
this code
okay okay okay i see i think i think i
see it okay
um and my other question was why is uh
why is two bits to two bytes enough for
a nine node number it's not
it's ridiculously small correct uh
because how many i knows can you have
two to the power of eight yeah six uh
yeah
uh whatever two bytes sixteen sixteen
bits
sixteen worked so thirty two thousand i
notes
that's a lot of i know for uh 90 or the
60s and 70s
but certainly would not be sufficient
for today
and so uh today's file system would use
a bigger number
or more bits okay
i see i guess my question was in the
architecture that we have
for xv6 um
the those two 16 bits for i knows
like where where else do they um where
else can we see this number
show up uh well the the one that is
two bytes right is really on on disk
that it is two bytes
uh any number in uh
and when it's compiled when it's sort of
sitting in a register where it's sitting
in memory
the disk i node is we can look at it
let's see so this guy node as we said
before
actually the uh
here's the directory entry correct we
say it's an inside short and that is
there's two bytes 16 bits uh the in
memory representation of an inode
uh there's the d-i note okay that's in
you're the in-memory representation of
an i-note
that actually number is uh
uh an integer and you know the way we
compile
c code and integer happens to be four
bytes
okay okay i see thank you thank you so
much