all right
i'd like to get started um
today i want to talk about virtual
machines um
and i'm gonna the lecture is really
gonna be divided into three pieces one
is i'm going to start with
what's called trap and emulate
virtualization which is basically an
overview of how you could build your own
virtual machine scheme
on risk 5 and qmu now i'm going to talk
a bit about
recent hardware support in
microprocessors for virtualization
and then about today's paper dune which
uses
this modern hardware support all right
so
first what's a virtual machine
it's really uh you can think of it as a
simulation of a computer that's
accurate enough to run an operating
system
so qmu is a uh
example of uh you could consider to be
an example of a virtual machine
the way i'm going to talk about it is
that
down to the sort of the lowest level
sitting on top of the hardware
we're going to imagine a virtual machine
monitor or vmm
and this more or less takes the place of
the standard operating system kernel
and the virtual machine monitor's job is
to simulate a bunch of
computers for guest operating systems
so um so up here in
in you know what used to be user space
in our usual diagrams um but it's now
guest
space so this is um
we're gonna call this guest space and
down here
host space we're going to have a bunch
of
one or more guest operating systems
kernels so
we might have a linux kernel
as one guest and
this linux kernel is gonna you know it's
just a it thinks of itself as an
ordinary kernel and it runs a bunch of
processes maybe a
vi and a c compiler and we might have
other guests
um i might have other guests who guessed
virtual machines
uh running here there might be maybe
another linux or maybe even uh
some other operating system like windows
um
all running on the same machine and
there would be
windows processes running within as
within this guest
operating system so with the host
the host world where the virtual machine
monitor runs in a guest world
where these uh ordinary operating
systems run
and furthermore we're going to talk
about a lot about um
in within the guest world uh guest
supervisor mode which is
the mode that
the kernels run in the guest kernels run
in and
guest user mode
and again the the the kind of classical
goal of the virtual machine monitor is
to provide an emulation of a machine
that's so good that you can just boot
ordinary linux ordinary windows
unmodified um and have it run
inside this virtual machine never
suspecting uh that anything funny is
going on
so for example the virtual machine
monitor has to be in a position to
emulate the difference between
supervisor mode and user mode in a way
that is just completely convincing
simulation of how the actual hardware
does it
even though that's you know can't really
be exactly what's going on
so that's why we talk about guest
supervisor mode and guest user mode
these are the
vmm's emulation of those two modes
so so why would you want to use a
virtual machine
it turns out there's a lot of reasons to
run lots of distinct guest operating
systems
on a single computer
sometimes maybe you're running a big
company and you
you know you need to have lots and lots
of servers maybe you get name servers
and security servers who knows what
and each one of them doesn't use many
resources so it's sort of a waste of
time to have to
buy a physical machine for it but you
want to run lot you know you you want to
run lots of these low-intensity servers
on a single piece of hardware so you can
save money
by using a virtual machine
it turns out virtual machines are also
very uh
very widely used in cloud computing
where it's an outfit like amazon
amazon aws
they don't want to rent out physical
machines to people because that turns
out to be
difficult to manage what they want to do
is rent their customers
their cloud customers just a machine
that amazon can on the fly
you know decide what harvard run it on
whether to run it on a bigger or smaller
machine amazon can decide oh
um you know it's it's current customers
maybe there's two customers
on this piece of hardware right here but
they're not using the computer very much
maybe you can pack a third or a fourth
customer on to that same piece of
hardware
you know without spending it extra money
but get more revenue
so this um virtual machines allow kind
of
extra level of flexibility and
you know it's the kind of trick that's
being used is that
we're kind of shifting up the existing
operating system kernels in user space
and
adding a new layer underneath
to provide this flexibility it turns out
there's um
you know there's other reasons why
people use virtual machines one is
certainly kernel development which is
why
we all use qmu the ability to run
xv6 in a kind of virtual environment
rather than on a real
computer makes this course much more
convenient for all of us
it also makes it a little bit easier to
debug because we can
turns out that once you're running xv6
and
in this virtual machine environment the
qmu provides it's easier to provide gdb
access than it would be on a
physical computer and a final reason
that people use
virtual machines is that there's a bunch
of tricks that can be played
using this extra layer of indirection
provided by the virtual machine monitor
for example
you can checkpoint an entire running
operating system and user processes you
can take a checkpoint of it
stash it away somewhere maybe on disk
and then later restore that checkpoint
sort of exactly the state of that
operating system and its processes
as it was at the time of the checkpoint
that's useful for reliability for
debugging
for maybe cloning the image of a virtual
machine so you can run it
multiple times another game you can play
is you can might
migrate a guest an entire guest to
another computer
if you have a guest operating system
running on a physical computer
and you need to shut down or replace
that physical computer
you can actually turns out move the
running
virtual machine image without disturbing
it to another physical computer so you
can
shut down the first one so there's just
examples of
why people really like virtual machines
and people really do virtual machines
are very very widely used
and they also have a long history this
ideas first came up in the 1960s and
they've been
developed over time until they're
quite pervasive and easy to use
for this course um the reason why we're
looking into them is that
virtual machine monitors provide a sort
of different view
on what an operating system can be you
know instead of
the process abstraction we're all used
to you know we have some analogous
structures here but
that's sort of providing a different
kind of container it's not a
process it's a sort of simulated machine
so it allows us to kind of think about
all the stuff we've been talking about
you know memory allocation scheduling
protection from a different point of
view
maybe give us some ideas which we can
take back to traditional operating
system kernels
um and indeed much of the action
the sort of development design
development research action
has shifted from conventional kernels
um down into the virtual machine
monitors themselves as
as they've gotten more prevalent so in
some sense kind of the topic of
operating systems
is drifting downwards a bit by one layer
okay for the first part of this lecture
i want to talk about
a bit about how we could implement our
own
uh virtual machine and
i'm going to use risk 5 as the sort of
assume that we're trying to emulate risk
five hardware so we can run operating
systems designed for risk five like
xv6 um and
just to repeat the uh specific goals
what we'd like what or for kind of
classical virtual machines
what we'd like to build is something in
which the guest software is just
completely
not aware that it's running inside a
virtual machine
we want to build something that makes it
impossible for the guest software to
distinguish
and to decide whether is this am i
running on a real machine or a virtual
machine right we want the emulation to
be that good
and the reason for that is that we don't
want we want
to be able to run it we'd like to be
able to run anything in our virtual
machine
any operating system even maybe an
operating system we haven't heard of
um and that means that you know whatever
funny stuff the
operating system does and the way it
uses hardware um
the virtual machine has to provide that
an emulation of exactly the hardware so
that any
tricks that work on the real hardware
are also going to work in the virtual
machine
um sort of similar
goal that we'd like is we want there to
be no way not only no way for a guest
to decide if it's running on virtual
machine but
no way for a guest to be able to escape
from the virtual machine
a lot of the reason why people use
virtual machines is to provide strict
confinement
for untrusted software even untrusted
operating systems running inside the
virtual machine
for example if you're amazon and you're
selling cloud service and your
it's your customers often who provide
the operating system
that runs in the virtual machine as well
as the applications and gosh for all you
know your customers are not running
ordinary linux
they're running a special hacked version
of linux who's
intended to try to break out of its
virtual machine and break into amazon's
um either the virtual machines of
amazon's other customers or
into the virtual machine monitor that
amazon uses to enforce isolation
so it's quite important that guests
not be able to break out of their
virtual machines and they'll be able to
use the memory
that they're allowed to use by the
virtual machine monitor for example
but not other memory and similarly they
shouldn't be able to reach out
without permission and use things like
storage devices or
network interface cards so we want to
have very strict isolation
and in many ways virtual machines
provide stricter isolation than ordinary
unix processes ordinary unix processes
can often interact you know they can
kill each other or they can all rewrite
the same files or
communicate over pipes um but
in a sort of ordinary virtual machine
system none of that's possible
the different virtual machines running
on the same computer are just
completely isolated from each other by
the virtual machine monitor so people
like them for security
right it's a way of being able to run
untrusted software
without having to worry if it's buggy or
malicious
now in practice i've
pitched the goal as being a sort of
completely faithful
emulation of a physical machine in fact
it turns out that for performance
reasons this is often blurred and you'll
find for example that um
linux and the most common virtual
machine monitors have co-evolved a
little bit so that
in real life linux may actually be aware
that it's running on a virtual machine
monitor and with the virtual machine
monitor's permission
for efficiency linux sometimes knowingly
talks
down to the virtual machine monitors to
do things like get high-speed access to
devices
but that's a carefully controlled
exception and the general strategy is
completely faithful simulation okay so
um how could we build our own virtual
machine monitor
um well one possibility would be to do
it entirely in software you can imagine
writing something like qmu that
interpreted the machine instructions
that is you could write a program that
would
open up the xv6 the read the
file that has the xv6 instructions in it
and your program could look at each
instruction and say oh that's a
that's a load instruction or a move
instruction and your program could
you know sort of simulate risk five
state like might have 32 registers
implemented in software and as your
software sort of reads each instruction
and picks it apart and figures out what
kind of instruction it is it would apply
the effects of that instruction
to the 32 registers and control
registers that it was simulating all in
software
and people do this um
and it's conceptually straightforward to
make it work although it
may be a lot of work to get all the
details right the
reason why uh um
sort of pure software
interpretive virtual machines aren't
widely used
is that they're slow if you play this
game
your virtual machine is going to run
guest software at a small fraction
of the speed of the of the hardware that
you're using because for every ins
your your virtual machine monitor
software has to look at every
instruction as it's executed up here
your machine monitor is going to maybe
run dozens of instructions
um in the process of interpreting each
one of the guest instructions and so
it's going to be orders of magnitude
slower
than a real computer and for something
like cloud computing
it really would not be practical so
people don't use the software
interpretation
to build virtual machines for production
systems
instead
the sort of core of
one of the main uh widely used
strategies
is to run the to actually run the guest
instructions
on the real cpu um
so if you were gonna run xv6 in your um
virtual machine monitor you would
actually load
xv6's instructions the kernel the
beginning you know the
entire xv6 instructions in a memory and
then jump to the first instruction in
xv6
right in order to have your computer
actually run the instructions in xv6 and
of course this requires that your
computer have the same
microprocessor in it that xv6 is
expecting but
um that's easy to arrange
now it turns out you can't literally do
this
um the point at which you'd run into
trouble is when
your guest operating system first
executed a privileged instruction
right if it um and you know that's
really the difference between a kernel
and ordinary
user code is that uh kernels which is
what we're trying to run here in our
virtual machine kernels use privileged
instructions so
the guest your guest colonel might for
example try to load a new page table
into the sat p register on risk 5 and
so that's starting to present a puzzle
if we're
executing our guest kernel as an
ordinary user process in linux for
example
boy loading sat piece an illegal
instruction
in in user mode and so our program's
going to crash
if we are so foolish as to load our
guest
kernel into and run it in supervisor
mode
um somehow then our guest colonel will
now be able to modify the real page
table
and would be able to escape from its
virtual machine and because it can
control the contents of ptes read and
write
any memory so we can't use a strategy
that's
as simple as just running the guest
kernel directly
instead we're going to start playing
some tricks the
first step is to run the guest kernel
in user mode
so um this is sort of the
fundamental strategy here um i'm going
to run the guest kernel in user mode
you know in the risk five user mode and
so what that means
you know we're we're writing uh we're
writing our own virtual machine monitor
and when we tell it look please boot xv6
it's gonna load xv6s
kernel instructions into memory
somewhere
maybe set up a page table appropriately
that makes it look to xv6 like
its memory starts at zero and goes up to
whatever
high memory is and then
the virtual machine monitor will use a
trap you know s-red instruction as
uh you've all come across in xv6
to uh jump into the first instruction of
the guest os um
in user mode and so the guest operating
system will execute along and now many
instructions will work fine if the guest
operating system is just
adding two registers together or even
loading or storing from memory that'll
just work
and as soon as the guest operating
system uses privileged instruction
what's going to happen is it's going to
trap that risk 5 hardware will cause it
since it's running in user mode not
supervised mode will cause it to trap
back into the our virtual machine
monitor
and we'll get control so if the guest
operating system for example tries to
change
sat p the page table pointer boom
the risk 5 cpu will trap into our
virtual machine monitor and our software
will get control back
and our software will be able to look
and see what instruction
caused the trap and do something
appropriate
but the cool thing here is that the
guest operating system didn't actually
get
to set the page table pointer but
how does how does the vmm uh um
intercept this like it has to set the
trap handler right
isn't that something only a privilege
process can do
yeah vm is a user program on the host os
right okay
what i'm assuming um what i'm assuming
is that the virtual machine monitor
runs in supervisor mode so in this
simple picture
the virtual machine monitor is the
kernel that boots on
this piece of hardware so instead of
booting linux or whatever you would boot
this virtual machine monitor
it boosts in supervisor mode it has
complete control over the hardware
so we can set up you know st vec and all
this other stuff however it likes
that makes sense um now and actually
some virtual machine monitors work
exactly that way you just boot them on
the hardware and it's just the virtual
machine monitor only that's running in
supervisor mode
um in fact there's also many many
virtual machine schemes out there
in fact um boot linux
and then once linux is up and running um
you load you load the virtual either
linux i mean actually linux
comes with a virtual machine monitor or
you load the virtual machine monitor as
a
as what's called a loadable kernel
module into linux
and it runs in the kernel in supervisor
mode
and that's that's the way actually
today's paper works is you boot linux
and then
run this little loadable kernel module
but the the main point is the virtual
machine monitor software you know the
software rewriting that we trust
runs in supervisor mode and we're going
to run the guest
in user mode but arrange
for it to look like it's running in
supervisor mode as far as it's concerned
okay so the good news is that on risk
five
um everything dangerous
um traps if you try to do it in uh
user mode that is all the sort of
privileged things the supervisor
node can do with the exception of stuff
having to do with the page table or
pte's which we'll talk about in a bit
but basically every pr
every supervisor only instruction
causes a trap if you try to execute it
in user mode
so that means that every time the guest
operating system does anything like
reads s
calls or reads and writes st vac or does
any of those things that
xv6 for example does to kind of
configure the privileged part of
5 hardware will cause a trap into the
virtual machine monitor
and we'll get control and then
the game is going to be the virtual
machine monitor is going to
maintain virtual state
a whole table of virtual state
information
for
for the guest so the virtual machine
monitor will have for example
um an s a virtual st
vec register just implemented as a
variable and software in a
you know a virtual um
sepc register and all these for all
these protected registers there'll be a
whole array of them down here
implemented by the virtual machine
monitor and when the guest operating
system for example tr
runs the instruction that reads one of
these registers
boom it'll take a trap because it's
legal in user space
the virtual machine monitor will inspect
the instruction and say aha
that's an instruction that's reading the
scpc register
and so the virtual machine monitor will
then emulate that
instruction it'll read the sap virtual
scpc value
out of this array it'll
copy that into the hardware
or well what really happened here if is
that the um
uh um
i forgot the name of the the uh
um there's there's some
instruction whose name might forget
which is basically supervisor
read um although that's not its name and
you give the name of an ordinary
register
and the name of a privilege register
like scpc
and so what the virtual that will track
the virtual machine monitor will read
that
instruction we'll see oh it's an s read
the virtual machine monitor will copy
the virtual copy of scpc
into a0 in the trap frame after all when
entering the vmm that's going to have
created a trap frame of copies of all
the
guest registers that will copy this scpc
into azer and the trap frame
then return from the trap using sret
that you know after copying the trap
frame registers and the real registers
and return from this uh trap to the
instruction after the s read and
continue
reading there with now uh a0 set to the
uh virtual scpc
and now the guest operating system will
proceed you know
but not i'm not realizing that something
funny happened here
um but it will have gotten a copy of the
virtual scpc that the vmm was keeping on
its behalf
so any questions about this about this
strategy
how does the vmm differentiate between
different guests
um it it um it's basically the same way
it would keep one of these tables a
virtual state
per guest and it just knows just like
xv6 knows which process it's running it
has a variable maybe a per core variable
saying
here's the process i'm currently running
similarly a vmm would
have a per core variable that indicated
which virtual machine
would be multiple of these state
structures
vmm would know which virtual machine was
executing and it would look in the
appropriate
virtual machine state structure defined
s-t-s-e-p-c or whatever it is it's
looking for
can it run multiple can it
assign multiple cores to one of the
guests
yeah sophisticated virtual machine
monitors can do that yes
so if you sorry go ahead oh sorry so the
guest operating system it will have uh
like some registers in the actual
hardware will be
the registers that the guest os uses so
why do we not use the actual scpc
but we use the virtual one um
the the reason is that the virtual
machine monitor needs to use these
registers
use use the real registers um so for
example think about s
cause when a trap occurs
what happens on the when you know when
the guest operating system uh
tries to do anything privileged the trap
will occur and the hardware
sets the real hardware s-cause register
to the cause of the trap
right which is illegal instruction or
unprivileged instruction
whatever it is but if the
um guest operating system you know
supposing the guest operating system has
just taken a system call
from a guest user process the guest
operating system needs to see an s
cause that's whatever the right s calls
value is for system call
right even though maybe the last thing
that you know so
the guest operating system is going to
read s cause
you know in the trap hand and what it
thinks is the trap handler handling a
system call from one of its guest
processes the s calls that the guest
operating system
needs to see is the value that says that
means system call
but the s calls is going to be in the
real s cause register
is the s cause that means illegal
instruction or unprivileged
or you know instructions violating the
privilege rules
so um
there are actually some times when you
could
um well anyway in general
the vmm you know the vmm is the one that
needs to see the real
the vmm needs to see different values in
the in the real registers than the
operating system should see and it's for
in its vision of the registers
does that make sense thank you yeah
okay um so this is called the name for
this style
of um virtual machine implementation in
which the guest runs at user level
and therefore traps whenever tries to do
anything privileged and the vmm can
emulate the privileged instruction
and the name for that is trap and
emulate
and it's nice because
you can you can build this for yourself
actually you can build this for
yourselves
entirely in software um and
you could modify xv6 for example to be a
virtual machine monitor
on risk 5 and run little virtual
machines perhaps
regular xv6 just
by writing software of course your
software does have to run in
supervisor mode
the state here all the registers that
begin with s
all those supervisor control registers
have to be part of this virtual state
there's also some other things that are
not directly accessible from those s
registers that nevertheless need to be
down in this state one of them is the
mode
the virtual machine monitor needs to
know whether the virtual machine is
running in
guest user mode or guest operating
system mode because
for example if you if user code executes
the privileged instruction like trying
to read s cause sure that'll cause a
trap into the vmm too
but in that case the vmm should not just
emulate the instruction in return
because that's not a legal instruction
in user mode so the vmm has to track
um whether the guest is in guest
supervisor mode or guest user mode and
so there's going to be a mode
slot down here as well and the vmm will
know because
when the guest operating system jumps
into
user space it'll execute the s red
instruction s-red is a privileged
instruction so the vmm will actually get
control there and we'll see oh
the guest is running an s-red
instruction among other things i'm going
to change the virtual mode from
supervisor to user
and another hidden piece of state is the
heart number
that is the core number
you can't get that that directly even
with the privileged instruction
um uh but the via manager needs to keep
track of
which heart it's emulating right now
okay um the
risk 5 it turns out different cpus or
different levels of difficulty and
how hard it is to write a trap and
emulate virtual machine on them
the wrist vice particularly well suited
to it because the designers
had that in mind when they were
designing the instruction set
and so they knew what the requirements
of a trap and emulate
virtual machine were and for example um
they've
been quite diligent at making sure that
every single privileged thing that
supervisor code can do
will cause a trap if you try to do it in
user mode which is what you need
in order to make sure the virtual
machine monitor sees a trap for every
privileged instruction
um oh i have a quick question uh so
does anything actually run in the guest
os itself
or does it always trap into the virtual
machine monitor
well all ordinary instructions
like if you just have an ad instruction
that
you know adds i don't know how to write
this press 5 assembly but let's just say
you add a 0 to a1 and you want to put
the result in a2
that instruction just executes directly
on the hardware at full hardware speed
if you make a function call just an
ordinary function call
up here in the guest world that just
executes
without anything special it's just
ordinary you know all the instructions
that are legal
in you in user code um on non-privileged
instructions just execute directly at
full speed
when the guest operating system executes
them
okay so is there a semblance of like
user mode and
kernel mode in the guest os
yes the guest operating system is
well the guest operating system is
unchanged
so what we're running up here is exactly
the linux kernel or exactly the xv6
kernel
and of course xv6 is all you know it
knows the xv6 kernel
knows it's running in supervisor mode
yeah
right that's just it just is of course
it's not here but
as far as the code is concerned it's
just definitely running in supervisor
mode it just
does all kinds of privileged things and
expects them to work and then it knows
when it executes an
s-red to get into user space it knows
aha
i'm going to enter user space now
and you know the vmm sort of makes
everything look like
that's indeed what's happening okay okay
even though it's actually in in the real
machine it's in user mode
in both places but this looks just like
supervisor mode and this
looks just like you survived
okay um
okay so when the uh so for example when
the guest when we execute s-red to enter
user space
um the s-ret's privileged uh
luckily um it traps into the virtual
machine monitor
the virtual machine monitor changes the
virtual mode to user
even though of course the real mode is
still supervisor because we're still
executing down here
change the virtual mode to user um
it just before it returns from the trap
the virtual machine monitor sets the
real scpc
to the virtual scpc because in order
that when
the virtual machine monitor returns
using its own
srat that the uh the
program counter value it returns to is a
program valid
is the program calendar that the guest
operating system wanted to return to
so here's the case where very briefly
the real scpc was set equal to the
virtual scpc um
and i'll talk about this in a bit but
the virtual machine monitor also is
going to be switching page tables
when it uh goes back into into the
virtual machine
um when the guest user code wants to
make it then the guest user code if it
for ordinary instructions
just execute the machine excuse them
directly at full speed
when the uh guest
code wants to make a system call you
know executes the e-call instruction
um that causes a trap that trap goes to
the virtual machine monitor in this
scheme
the virtual machine monitor says aha
we're in you know consults the virtual
mode it's
virtual mode is user space it looks at
the instruction
uh that trapped defaulted it's an e-call
and then the virtual machine monitor
sort of does all the virtual changes
makes all the changes in the virtual
state required to
simulate a system call trap into the
guest operating system
so it's going to set the virtual scpc to
be whatever program counter
was the e-call instruction was at it's
gonna change the virtual mode back to
supervisor
it's gonna set the virtual s cause to be
system call
um it's gonna set the real epc
to be equal to the virtual st vec and
then call
srat so that it'll
jump into the guest operating system's
trap handler
which is what um or trampoline page or
whatever it is
which is what the virtual stbec was
pointing to
okay
we have two remaining pieces of business
which are quite important one is
what about page tables and the other is
what about devices um
so the um
page table sort of there's two pieces to
that um
one is that at various points the guest
operating system is going to modify the
sat
p register um and of course you know
that'll turn into a trap and the virtual
machine monitor and the virtual machine
monitor gets a chance to do something
but what we don't want the virtual
machine monitor to do is simply
let the guest set the real sat p
um and then execute after having changed
the wheel sap because that would let the
guest get at
any memory not just the memory that the
virtual machine monitor has allocated to
it
so we cannot let the guest operating
system simply set the sat p
but we do need to do something to this
app because we need to
provide the illusion to the guest
operating system that yes
indeed the page table's been changed and
more than an illusion when the guest
software runs load and store
instructions or fetches and instructions
to execute
we need those to come from the right
place from the place that the
guest operating system pointed its page
table entries to
so what actually happens when the guest
sets the sat p
is we you know we can't let it we can't
directly use the guest operating systems
page table
but the virtual machine monitor cooks up
a new page table
um that simulates
the uh guest operating systems desired
ph
table so um the
so now the page translation situation is
a little bit different
um we have the guest
what the guest was trying to set the
page table to so this is the guest
page table of course it's the current
you know the guest kernel
um and that maps uh sort of guest
uh virtual addresses to what i'll call
guest
physical addresses of course the guest
physical addresses are
um the virtual machine monitors you know
given the guests
you know 32 gigabytes or however much
simul you know physical memory um
for its use um presumably starting at
uh uh telling the guest operating system
that it's
physical addresses start at zero and go
up for 32 megabytes but of course
you know they don't in real life on the
real hardware they're just 32 gigabytes
worth of pages somewhere
not contiguous um so we can't you
can't directly use the guests physical
addresses because they don't
correspond to the uh real physical
addresses so instead
the vmm is going to maintain
a map for each
virtual machine that maps guest physical
addresses
to real physical addresses what i'll
call host
physical addresses um so this map is you
know it's like a page table
it has an entry for every page every
physical page that the guest thinks
exists and indicates what real physical
page
that guest physical address refers to
that the vmm has allocated for it
and then when the guest writes
a new page table to sat p
in the trap handler for that the vmm
creates
a sh what's called a shadow page table
which is going to be what the vmm puts
in the real
sat p and this shadow page table is
um constructed by the combination of
these two page tables and so it maps
guest virtual addresses
to host physical addresses
and is constructed by taking every entry
in the guest page table
looking at the guest desired guest
physical address
using the vmm map to translate that
guest physical address to a real host
physical address
and putting that virtual physical pair
um
into the shadow page table and then the
virtual machine monitor sets
this to be in sat p as the real page
table before returning back
to the guest kernel
and so the guest kernel thinks it's that
one page table but actually the real
hardware is using this
shadow page table instead um and this
way there's the
this is what prevents the guest from
escaping from the memory it's allowed to
use
the the the shadow page table can only
contain
host physical addresses um
that the vmm had allocated for that
guest so i guess there's nothing the
guests can put in the page table it asks
for
that'll allow it to access a page that
wasn't allocated to it by the virtual
machine monitor
um that's a critical piece of the
isolation story here
any questions about the paging setup for
trap and emulate
sorry so if it's if the operating system
the guest just wants to make a new
a new process and a new page table for
the process
what does it do like what happens the
the guest
the guest does the usual just does
exactly what linux or xv6 does right now
it
it formats up a page table entries to
make a page table and then it executes
the instruction to
assign that address to the page table
into sat d so that's what the guest
operating system
does and when the
but it can't actually assign to sat p
because that's a privileged
operation so there's a trap into the
virtual machine monitor
the virtual machine monitor inspects the
instruction that trapped sees oh gosh
that guest is trying to assign to sat p
and then the virtual machine monitor
would create this new shadow page table
from the combination of the page table
the guest ask
was trying to set up the virtual machine
monitor looks at the page table the
all the pte's and the page table the
guest was trying to set up
it runs it translates the physical
address in each guest
page table entry through this map to get
a real
physical address or to cause a real
fault if
if the guest is trying to use a physical
address that it's not allowed to
um and then the virtual machine monitor
installs the shadow page table and the
real sat p
and returns back to the guest
okay okay i see i see okay thank you yes
okay um
okay so this is this this shadow page
table stuff is certainly one of the
tricky aspects of um
implementing a virtual machine monitor
there's actually another thing that uh
there's another way in which the guest
operating system can interact with the
page table the guest operating system
actually
you know xv6 sometimes directly reads
and writes page table entries
in in its page table um
and you know so xp6 could modify a page
table entry or
read the dirty bits for example in a
page table entry
now on the risk 5 um if
if software modifies the page table
entry if you read the wrist 5 spec
risk 5 is not required to do anything
at that point so if you modify a page
table entry um
the risk 5 microprocessor does not
promise to immediately observe
that modification to a page table entry
you may completely ignore it for the
time being
instead what the manual says is that if
if you modify page table entries and
and you actually want the hardware to
mmu to see them
you have to execute um the s
fence dot
vma instruction and it's
the spec says only it's only this
instruction that causes the hardware to
pay attention
to your page table modifications and so
if you're building a virtual machine
monitor your virtual machine monitor on
risk 5 can completely ignore
the guest modifications to page table
entries but since you know the guest
is is going to issue is going to execute
an s fence
vma instruction after modifying page
table entries
and this is a privileged instruction you
can tell because it starts with s
that's going to trap into the virtual
machine monitor the virtual machine
monitor is going to
re-knows that an s fence was executed it
looks the instruction
it's going to rescan the guest
the guests version of the current page
table and the current page table
and look for page table entries that
have changed and reflect those changes
if they're legal
into the shadow page table um
reset the executor real estate vma to
get the real hardware to pay attention
to the shadow page table and then return
to the guest operating system
so this means that um there's only like
the mmu actually just uses one page
table right which is the shadow it's not
like it's using the ept or anything like
this
there's no ept yet okay so the guest
just like thinks it has a page table
like the gva to gpa but that's not
actually doing any translation
it's not in this vmm yeah makes its own
page table based on both of them
combined that's right that's right just
to be clear the ept is part of a
different a
quite different virtual machine
implementation
virtual machine design that requires
hardware support i'm assuming this is a
story about how to
build a virtual machine with no special
hardware support other than
trapping on privileged instructions
um does this mess up direct mapping in
any way
well there won't be a direct map
this will allow the guest i mean
this will cause the guest colonel to run
correctly with what the guest colonel
thinks is a direct mapping
but i mean it's not a direct it's a
direct mapping in the virtual world but
it's not a direct mapping in the
uh on the real machine
but it doesn't matter because
because we're tricking the yeah we're
tricking the guests into
everything looks just like it was a
direct mapping
uh one more question you may be
addressing this later but i wonder
like when we discussed the trap
mechanism earlier in the semester we
mentioned
the high performance cost to trapping
so this sounds like there's way more of
a performance hit when we use
a vmm yes yes there's all these
instructions you know
if you if you're if your operating
system maybe x uses a lot of
privileged instructions which you may
and you spend a lot of time in the
operating system then the traps you may
have quite a few traps
and then that may cost you quite a bit
of performance and that's what motivates
i mean a little bit we'll talk about
modern hardware support virtual machines
which is what today's paper was using
and the high cost of the of the traps is
a lot of the motivation
for why intel felt compelled to uh an
amd felt compelled to add
hardware support for a much more
efficient
or for a virtual machine scheme that had
much
many fewer traps yes
that's quite important but this actually
ran i mean for many years this is what
people did for virtual machines and
it was very successful and it works and
it's you know so much slower
but not so much slower that people
didn't like it people liked it a lot
okay any more questions about the trap
and emulate
strategy for page tables
okay let me uh as a final piece of the
trap and emulate story
um uh let me talk about devices
um and so here i'm talking about uh
you know ordinary operating system
expects to be able to get at a disk
drive
to store its file system on and maybe
network interface card and
maybe even if it's xv6 a uart so it can
talk to its console and you know who
knows a sound card
a graphics adapter a mouse a keyboard
all kinds of stuff
um so the operating system we need to uh
our virtual machine scheme has to have
some provision
to allow allow guests
to at least trick them into thinking
that all these devices that they need
really exist
and there's three main strategies
that people use one is
just pick some very commonly used device
in the class that you need
say a disk drive and just do an
emulation
that is nothing you're not actually
having a real device
the vmm just makes it look like this
particular kind of disk drive
exists and that the guest is talking to
it
and the way you would drive this
emulation uh typically
uh the guest operating system is gonna
try to talk to the device through memory
mapped control registers so
this is how xv6 talks to its uh ua it's
uart you know the serial port
uh the console uh
device that you type characters to and
that displays characters to you
xv6 is talking to some control registers
that are mapped that it assumes the
hardware
um has mapped in a known address
in the address in the kernel's address
space and so the way you'd emulate that
in a virtual machine monitor is you
actually not map those pages in the
guest instead you would
allow or have those pages be invalid so
that every time the
guest operating system tried to use the
uart hardware or whatever
device hardware the vm virtual machine
monitor will get a trap
and the virtual machine monitor we're
going to look at the instructions say oh
it's trying to send a character
on the uart or read from the disk or who
knows what
and the virtual machine monitor would
have some simulation of a disk or
simulation of a
serial device um
and you know sort of invoke its
simulation to figure out
uh how to respond to the guest's
instruction and then
allow the guests to resume
and so this is basically how qmu
implements the
the uart console device that xv6 uses
it just has a there's actually no
physical serial port in sight but
qmu emulates one to keep
xv6 happy and so this is a common
strategy
it's can be very low performance though
because it involves a trap
into the operating system for every
interaction between the guest and the
device hardware
but for low speed stuff it's works
pretty well
a second strategy that's often used
and actually but if you're if your goal
is to provide
is to be able to boot operating systems
that have no idea they're running on a
virtual machine
um this is pretty much the way you have
to go
um there's really no other choice but
in the modern world you know uh it's
often the case that the operating
systems
are aware that they're actually running
at a low level at least aware that
they're running on top of a
virtual machine and so um a different
strategy is to provide virtual devices
that is not try to emulate a real device
but cook up a device interface that is
particularly efficient
for the um provides efficient ways for
the
uh device driver in the guest to be able
to talk to
um the device support inside the virtual
machine monitor
um and so so you might not have memory
map control registers instead you might
have
sort of a queue of command
structures in memory in which the
guest operating system would write its
commands to the
to the device and in fact
xp6 also uses one of these if you look
at the um
xv6 vert i o disk
um bird iodis.c you'll see the guest
and of a um
device driver intended to talk to a disk
virtual device that's implemented by qmu
and it it uses either little or
almost not either either little or no
uh memory map control registers and so
it doesn't really rely on traps
um and instead it formats up this sort
of
hue of commands and memory um as i
mentioned
and and then qmu looks at these commands
in memory and
applies them not to a real disk but to
um a file like for us it's fs.image
um qmu applies these commands to
fs.image instead of
instead of using a real piece of device
hardware
which is another strategy um
and a third strategy that people use so
this is higher performance than straight
emulation because
um you can design the interface so it
doesn't require a lot of traps
a final strategy people use
um is a pass-through of a real device
and that's our classic situation for
this is network interface controllers
you know
that provide access to the network and
modern network devices
actually have hardware support for
talking to
multiple guest operating systems running
under a virtual machine
monitor and so you can configure a
modern nic to actually
act as if it's multiple independent
apparently independent mix one for each
guest operating system
and then the guest operating system can
talk directly
can be configured by the virtual machine
monitor so that it's allowed to talk
directly
to its sort of slice of the nic the
network interface card hardware
um with very high efficiency so this is
the modern
high performance way and the guest
operating system probably
in theory i think you could design you
could set this up so the guest operating
system wasn't really aware
that anything odd was going on but i
think in practice the guest operating
system device drivers kind of know
that they're talking to one of these
special network interface cards
all right so um so these are the options
for devices
in fact i i believe
that most of the difficulty in
implementing a uh
virtual machine monitor today um
comes in in the form of trying to cook
up
device emulations and device drivers
that are um
uh sufficiently good that will act that
they'll actually work correctly with
uh real guest operating systems this is
where
probably the majority of the work is
particularly if you need to use this
emulation
strategy
any questions about devices
so what what exactly is i i didn't quite
get the difference between the virtual
and the emulation because they don't
like they they're similar they're
similar um
the here's the way to think about it um
if you're booting an operating system
that has no idea about virtual machine
it probably has a lot of disk drivers in
it but they're all for real hardware
that you can go out and like
physical chunks of hardware that you can
go out and buy and that means that if
you want to boot that kind of operating
system on your virtual machine
you need to have an exact emulation you
need to choose one of those real pieces
of hardware and have a precise super
accurate
emulation of that hardware um so that
the
and then i mean people totally do that
so that works
however and that would be fine um
except most of these
for real hardware that the device
interfaces
were not designed the hardware
interfaces were not designed
to be efficient with a trap and emulate
virtual machine monitor
and so it's very often the case that the
real device just
requires you to read and write its
control registers a lot
but the virtual machine monitor has to
get control for every right of a
device control register because it needs
to emulate
um and that means that every right of a
device control
register results in a trap into the
virtual machine monitor which you know
costs maybe hundreds of cycles
um and that means this is slow this is
inefficient
and so the difference here is that
instead of
slavishly mimicking a real device some
designer has come up with a
a device interface
that's not implemented by any real piece
of hardware but only implemented by a
virtual machine monitor and it just
happens to be designed in a way that
doesn't require a lot of traps
but then instead of chit chatting with
control registers and expecting the
device to respond
immediately which really requires a trap
instead that
the device driver and that sort of
virtual hardware are decoupled
and don't ever require sort of immediate
uh interaction
in that case the guest needs its own
like a new driver
so it's just like the guests will have a
driver for like this model of the disk
and that model of the disk and they'll
also have a driver for that virtual disk
right and so indeed xv6 does so so the
so at the functionality level you play
this game maybe you can boot
any operating system whereas if you play
this game you can only boot operating
systems that have been taught
about your virtual devices if you want
to use you know the virtual devices
it turns out this is actually a standard
that's
provided by multiple different virtual
machine schemes
so with this you know except for the
fact that we never tested it on anything
other than qmu
this disk driver and xv6 might work or
it could probably be modified to work on
other virtual machines
so if every xv6 was compiled for that
board that you showed sometime in the
beginning
um in that case it would have to have a
different disk driver based on what disk
that was running right
yeah yeah they're i think you may be
able to buy disk interface real hardware
disk interfaces that now
support this interface but in but most i
mean
most disk drive don't and we would have
to implement a new as as you said
we'd have to implement a new disk driver
for a real piece of
hardware
yes
okay any other questions about devices
all right next topic i want to talk
about
hardware support for
virtual machines
um in particular intel's
vt x scheme
so what's motivating what motivated uh
intel and other hardware providers to
add direct hardware support for virtual
machines
is a the fact that virtual machine use
is pervasive
so a lot of their customers were running
a lot of virtual machines
and b the fact that trap and emulate as
i just described it
often involves a lot of expensive traps
and so it's not particularly efficient
um and a third sort of less interesting
perhaps
motivation was that although the risk
five is
pretty well suited to trap and emulate
virtualization the x86
intel's microprocessor has a number of
detailed features which make it
actually very difficult possible but
very difficult to virtualize
and so intel was also motivated to try
to fix that because so many of his
customers wanted to
run virtual machine monitors all right
okay so this hardware is uh
the main point is to make it be allow
you to build faster virtual machines
using this hardware support and another
motivation was to
make it easier to implement a virtual
machine
and this support has been around for
maybe
10 years and is now very very widely
used
to build virtual machines okay so um
the basic strategy is that
all that virtual state that in my trap
and emulate scheme
all the virtual state that was being
maintained by the virtual machine
monitor just
in software all that virtual state
is going to be going to be implemented
in the hardware
in these hardware supported schemes
and that will allow guest software to
execute privileged instructions
affecting these virtual hardware
supported registers directly
so rather than trapping
so the goal is now that guests will be
able to execute privileged instructions
but not trap and the reason
you know the way that works is that
again we have a
virtual machine monitor and
a guest operating system and user level
and the hardware
now you know we know the the in the
hardware we have a
uh you know uh sd vac
and all those you know hardware
registers um
um
and there's all the when we're running
in the virtu in these new schemes
hardware support schemes we'll run the
virtual machine monitor we just use the
real
versions of these registers but the
hardware when the virtual machine
monitor
tells the hardware look please switch
into guest mode
the hardware has a complete separate set
of registers
dedicated for use by in guest mode
so the guest mode can read and write
these registers but it's not you know
it's reading it's reading writing it's
hardware copies of these right it's
versions of these registers rather than
the real registers
and the hardware has you know has some
kind of
extra checks it makes on what the
guest operating system can do to make
sure that it can't abuse these registers
to
escape from the virtual machine um
this is the basic this is most of the
basic strategy
and in the terminology of these hardware
supported virtual machine schemes
the name at least the intel one the name
for guest mode is
non-root
and the name for uh
um host mode where we're using the real
registers is root and so there's a
set of non-root or virtual registers for
the virtual machine to use and there's a
set of registers that are used when
we're in root mode
so now when we're running in the guest
kernel it can execute
any privileged instruction without
trapping
so if it wants to read or write the s t
vec ah the hardware just lets it read or
write the
non-root copy of the hardware s t vec
register
and so all this stuff proceeds at full
speed without
having to trap it in the vmm so it's
much faster
for code that was incurring a lot of
traps
the uh you still have to there's a whole
bunch of stuff having
involved in configuring this the when
the virtual machine monitor wants to
create a new virtual machine it actually
has to tell the hardware
um and so there is uh down in the
virtual machine monitor's memory there's
this structure that the
virtual machine monitor and the vtx
hardware used to communicate which is
called the vmcs or vm
control something structure
and when the virtual machine monitor
wants to create a new virtual machine it
creates one of these in memory and fills
in a bunch of configuration flags and
also initial values
for all these registers and then tells
the
vtx hardware look and i want to start
running a new virtual machine and here's
the initial state
and so there's these new instructions
which the paper mentions
there's vm launch it's just like a new
new machine instruction which you tell
it the address of this and it
starts running you know starting with
these registers like
um starts running the guest kernel um
and there's also this vm resume
because sometimes you break out of the
kernel
trap out of the kernel into the bmm and
you need to resume it um
and then code up here can run a new
instruction called vm call which
sort of intentionally exits from
non-root mode and basically traps into
the virtual machine monitor and root
mode
all right so when the virtual machine
monitor uh excuse one of these
instructions
to jump into a guest the ways that it
may come back
i mean the guests now can execute
ordinary privileged instructions without
trapping
but there's a bunch of reasons why you
may nevertheless return to the virtual
machine mode one is an intentional
exit but also if the device interrupt
goes off like the timer interrupt goes
off
that'll the microprocessor will force a
trap
out of non-root mode out of the guest
into root mode in the virtual machine
monitor so in general device interrupts
um trap back into the virtual machine
monitor and so that means that a guest
operating system can't hog the cpu every
time the timer hardware timer ticks the
virtual machine monitor gets control
and if there's multiple guests it can
now
basically time share the machine using
the timer interrupts among all the
different guests
um okay so this is a basic strategy
basically
there's a second set of registers um
uh the other
may the other big piece of machinery
that vtx provides
is a page table support
you know we're operating up here in the
guest world we you know we still need a
page table
now we need to change people for two
reasons one is
the guest colonel wants to be able to
configure its own page table it wants to
be able to load
uh cr3 which is the um
intel equivalent of uh the sat p
register so we'd love to be able or vtx
allows the guest kernel
to load any value it likes into the
cr3 register to set the page table and
the hardware will actually obey that
page table that the guest kernel loads
but we know that can't be though which
is fantastic right because now the guest
ground can load a page table without
trapping
the vmm um but we know that we
we can't just let the guest kernel put
anything it likes in its page table
without because i would allow it to read
and write arbitrary memory
so this vtx scheme actually has an
another
um important register which is in fact
part of the um
sort of real well who knows where i
should draw but i'll draw it right here
the extended page
table register and
the virtual machine which points to a
page table right
uh that maps well that's one kind of
address to another kind of address
and the virtual machine monitor sets
when it's gone about to run
a guest kernel it sets up an ept
for that kernel tells the hardware look
here's the ept
for the um virtual machine i'm about to
run and then jumps into the virtual
machine
and then the game is that the mmu
on this machine when it's translating a
guest virtual address it first
translates
the guest virtual address to a guest
physical address to the guests
the page table that the guest sets up
and then does another translation of
that guest physical address
through the ept to get a host physical
address
and the hardware does that automatically
for every memory reference the guest
does
that's this double level of translation
and so this again
gives the vmm control over what physical
memory
uh the guest is allowed to use the
guests can set up any page table that
likes
and can do it quite efficiently because
it can directly execute the instructions
but it's still constrained
by the ept which the vmm configures to
be able to only
use physical pages that the vmm wants to
let it use
any questions about the ept
oh sorry i have a question out about the
ability but about the um
the second set of registers so if you
have
two cores and you want to run two vmms
does it do you get us like a third copy
of the register every core
has its own set of these registers every
core has a sort of independent
uh in an independent instance of
all this vtx hardware so every core
every core has its own 32 general
purpose registers
its own real control registers and its
own
uh virtual registers for guest mode
and its own in its own ebt
so you can be running two different
guests on two different cores they all
have their own
every register uh every core has its own
one
so you need a new vmm too well i mean
it could just like an ordinary operating
system the xv6 can support multiple
processes and it's
all the same xv6 but although
and just like xv6 has a struct separate
struct proc
for every process our virtual machine
monitor would have a separate struct
struct vm or whatever it is one for each
guest to keep track of that guess
information for that guest
okay i see thank you yes and as i
mentioned before the switching
if you have you know one core and three
guests the switching can be driven by
timer interrupts which
go to the virtual machine monitor not
the guest
okay more questions about virtual
machines
before i switch to the
the paper
all right the paper takes
this hardware as a starting point and
uses it for something else
not a virtual machine so that's a lot of
the interest in the papers that they
they took this harder which is like
absolutely designed just for virtual
machines
and the paper saying gosh we could just
use this hardware to do something it's
not a virtual machine
um and uh
what their sort of high level view of
what they're doing is
um they're just they want to implement
the ordinary processes
so now we're back in just linux no no
virtual machines anymore just linux
but assuming vtx hardware so this is
dune
um we have
linux and we've assumed we've loaded the
dune
loadable kernel module into linux and
now this dune software is running
in supervisor mode as part of the linux
kernel
um but for the most part we're you know
we're running linux and we're expecting
to run
linux processes so
so the abstraction we're trying to
support is mostly the process
abstraction with system calls and
all the sort of ordinary things that
linux processes can do
but we want to use this vtx hardware to
give sort of
more um sort of allow
ordinary processes to do some extra
things
and there's really
so we're actually going to run so dune
runs these processes
or you know allows a process to switch
into dune mode which means that instead
of
just being protected being isolated by a
page table now this
process is isolated by the complete vtx
apparatus
so for this process dune is going to
maintain
this process now has this virtual set of
of all the re control registers like its
own
cr3 and it's therefore its own page
table
um because these this process is going
to run in
non-root supervisor mode so it can run
all the privileged instructions although
against the
virtual state implemented by btx
um so so one of the critical things this
process can do under dune
is set up its own page table using its
own
hardware cr3 of course doom you know
controls an ept
for this process so and the ept
is going to be set up to only have
entries for this processes
ordinary process memory so the process
can put anything it likes in cr3 but
because the mmu
translates through the ept after
translating through the ordinary page
table the process still cannot
escape its allocated memory so the
process doesn't have any
sort of additional powers with respect
to other processes or kernel memory
um it just has now a more flexible way
of
setting up its own memory all right so
one thing a dune process can do is
have its own page table in fact it's
basically required to have its own page
table because
otherwise it won't work and the other
thing a process can do
is have a supervisor mode
and uh user mode you know within
its little virtual machine and be able
to run
be able to have the supervisor code set
itself up to be protected
against the code that it runs in guest
user mode
so the paper really talks about these
two different uses
two different things you can do with
doom
so the uh this ability to
get at for a process to get at the
hardware support for supervisor use
versus user mode
um allows them to run untrusted
uh plug-in code here in a sandbox
and so the idea is oh maybe your maybe
the main program is like a web browser
um you know you can download web browse
download plugins that your web browser
runs
maybe a new
video decoder or a new ad blocker or
something but we don't totally trust
that plugin so we'd like to run it with
restricted privileges somehow
it's actu it's it's possible but a
little bit tricky to do in ordinary
linux but with dune
we can run the plugin up here in user
space
and the web browser which runs in the
process and supervisor mode
can configure the page table
configure a different page table for use
by this user code because it's allowed
to write cr3
um and that can allow it to run this
untrusted plugin code
with only allowing it restricted access
to just some
pages of the web browser's memory
uh so that the even if the web uh plugin
code is malicious it can't
just arbitrarily read and write the main
web browser's memory
um and if the user code you know the
user could may be expecting to make
system calls but those system calls
actually trap into
the supervisor mode of the process and
not into linux so the user this
plugin code may think it's calling fork
or read or write or who knows what
but actually those attempts to execute
system calls
trap into the web browser in the process
and they can do whatever it likes they
can not do the system call or execute
some call or who knows what i'm so now
our web browser has sort of
full control over the sandboxed plug-in
code
that's a quick overview any questions
about using due into sandbox
um and to be fair this is something this
is an effect that
could be achieved by quite different
techniques
using existing linux um facilities but
dune allows you to provide in a
particularly kind of elegant and
efficient way by using the vtx hardware
the other thing that the paper talks
about
using dune 4 is to make garbage
collection faster
and here it's um the way it does that is
by
allowing the garbage collector
when not doing sandbox anymore we're
actually not even using
user mode we're just having one program
um
we're assuming that we're writing just
whatever program who knows what but in a
garbage collected language like
you know java or python or something
garbage collection can be slow you know
there's
dozens and dozens of tricks for making
garbage collection faster but one of the
things that's important in garbage
collectors is the garbage collectors
is some many garbage collectors trace
find the
memory that's still alive it's still
active by just tracing all the pointers
through all objects
starting at the registers and if it
doesn't find some
object after it's completed the trace
then that object
isn't can't be reached isn't referred to
by any uh any pointer
and can be freed um but many garbage
collectors run at the same time as in a
different thread or something as the
main program
and so maybe the garbage collector has
started tracing pointers from you know
maybe from some set of registers and
this followed a pointer to this object
which had pointers to these objects and
you know the garbage collectors
following into these pointers
down to the tree or graph of objects and
maybe the garbage collector's gotten you
know down here so far
and actually traced through all these
objects but then because the garbage
collector is running concurrently with
the
program itself maybe the program
modifies
this object that the garbage collector's
already traced through
so that's a bad deal you know because
now that the
list of object pointers the garbage
collectors decided are live or dead or
whatever
may not be correct because some object
it's already seen
has been modified by the program
so dune using page table support
provides a way for the garbage collector
to detect
rights like that and in particular
dune sets up the uh cr3
the you know the virtual cr3 supported
by vtx
to point to its own page table um
and then the it leaves all these page
table entries valid but
it looks at the d bit you know every
page tab boundary has a dirty bit
that indicates that there's been a right
to that page so if the program writes
some object
then the dirty bit in the corresponding
page
in the page table the dirty bit will be
set and so the government the garbage
collector's finished tracing through the
objects
it goes back and looks at the d bits in
the page table
to find all pages that contain objects
that might have been modified and
re-scans those objects
um and it turns out that this facility
of getting at the d
bits is difficult and slow with ordinary
linux
i don't even know if linux supports it
there are operating systems where you
can make system calls to ask for d
bits but if you use dune and vtx
then the process can just use
ordinary load and store instructions to
get the ptes and therefore the dbits
and it's very fast and so they showed
you know that this makes this trick
for some programs that are you know
garbage collection intensive
uh makes the programs significantly
faster
any questions
what would happen if um the sandboxed
program um
wants to like run its own garbage
collector or something
like with that i see so you're sort of
using all right all right so we got uh
we're using dune
we have a dune process that's actually
using
vtx's uh supervisor versus user mode
we're running a plug-in up here in user
mode in the plug-in but also
it's also written in a garbage collected
language and was like to use
like to have its own page table
its own cr3 pointing to its own page
table with its own v
bits um so no that doesn't work because
um we're gonna run the the way doon
wants you to run plugins
sandbox plugins is to run them and use
in
guest user mode guess user mode is not
allowed
it's just like user mode it's not
allowed to think about cr3
and so in user mode in guest user mode
we don't get
to have our own page table and so we
don't get quick access to the d bits
it's only in guest supervisor mode
though we can have our own co3 so
you can't well there's no obvious way to
combine the two tricks
the two kinds of tricks that june allows
what about let's say somebody wrote a
draw
a browser uh actually using dune
um that would mean like that would be
quite tough to
make if some computers didn't support
dune or something right
like it's hard to just put chrome into
and you to use dune
if not not everyone has that kernel
modules right so
so first of all you have to be running
on a computer that supports the vtx
you know the underlying computer has to
support vtx which means many intel chips
many um
so you need vtx to run dune and you and
dune had to be loaded in order to run
the browser
that takes advantage of doing so yeah
you gotta set all this up correctly
um um
yeah i mean it's a research project it's
you know
it's it's intended to sort of get people
thinking about things that
could be deployed in the real world if
they were
if it seemed like they were valuable
enough so and you know just like linux i
mean linux has
hundreds and hundreds of features it has
and so if somebody decided to add
dune to linux you know as a standard
feature then i
would start relying on it and chrome
could just use it it would not be a
problem
but
sorry so in a high level doing this like
like be like making a vm but instead of
a vm you run
a process or yeah or
yeah you can phrase it either way it's
it's
it it's reporting what's mostly a
process abstraction
because but but it's using instead of
using the page table hardware
it's using the cpu hardware to support a
process abstraction
but instead of that the particular cpu
hardware it's using is the
vtx hardware which has a few extra
features
like like the ability to
set up your own page right right i see
i remember in the paper i read process
level abstraction but i didn't
understand what that means but now i
understand it
thank you
all right time is up and i'm happy to
continue
if anybody has any more questions happy
to answer
yeah so i had a question in particular
about
something that said in the paper was uh
if a dune
like a processor process inside dune
forks
it becomes a non-doing process isn't
that
like a security flaw in a way or or
what's the attack um well you've run
something as a doom process
thinking that it's now safe but then it
can run
it can just fork or escape so here's the
possibility yeah
okay so if um let's see code down here
in supervisor mode
you know there's no security problem for
this you know with respect to this code
because it would already have
whatever privileges were possible it
already had it's not going to gain the
extra pillar just like pork
right okay coda but you know maybe it's
using dune to sandbox a plug-in
and we have untrusted code up here that
that it would be dangerous to you know
let it run without doom
because it's not trusted and we're using
doom to sandbox it
so then if we forked you know okay
so this code cannot fork right you can
try to call the fork system call
but oh a system call instruction up here
traps into the supervisor part of this
process
and presumably the supervisor process
part of this process is carefully
written
not to be tricked and so it's not
actually going to work
so that doesn't work if the supervisor
code it is allowed to fork it is allowed
to make
linux system calls it'll get a fork of
this process with the same memory image
so we'll get the
plug-in up here and i see
if it didn't realize that fork turned
off dune
and it did
well i mean it's hard to see how this
could actually happen but you know
if it did something to to resume
execution of the plug-in now
that would be very foolish because now
the plug is in sandbox you know in fact
this you know the code to jump into the
sandbox here involves privileged
instructions just like it does on risk
five
because it switches it switches uh
guest modes and if you execute that
instruction here that's an
illegal instruction i guess
i guess what i was misunderstanding was
i think that the
plug-in is not a process like the the
dune process is the sandbox the plug-in
is just
inside there the process is just enabled
to use
features to let the plugin run faster
basically
that's right and we're absolutely
assuming that this software down here
is clever with is careful about what
what it likes about preventing you know
the sandbox
to actually going forward in real life
and it's not it's not uh unsafe for the
dune process to have supervisor mode
because it's actually supervisor mode
and non-root mode which is the same as
supervisor
mode in a go guest os right that's right
it's like you can let it do everything
just
but because it because of etx it's gonna
be like a virtual machine so it's not
gonna hurt us
that's right it can't escape from its
address spaces ept
is a set of bpt to constrain it to its
address space
that makes sense so one last thing i had
um i i there was like a paragraph
on uh on epts and it said that the user
page table can just
expand the addresses like like
remap them to their original layout that
was something
i i just didn't understand the whole
paragraph so i i don't complain
maybe that's a bit specific i think
what's going on
is that the um physical addresses
are on the x86 are have fewer bits than
virtual addresses
so i'm kind of guessing and so that
means that the
ept you know the
the ordinary page table maps virtual
addresses to physical addresses the
physical addresses have fewer bits
and so that constricts the the uh
that means um that when dune is setting
up
an address space for a process one way
to look at is when doing setting up the
address space for a process
the process address space has to fit in
the smaller number of bits
for a dune process okay regular
processes can maybe use
i don't know what the numbers are let's
say 48-bit virtual addresses
but maybe physical addresses are only 36
bits
again i'm making this up okay ordinary
process could use all 48 bits for
virtual addresses a dune process can
only use
36 or whatever so there's like different
rules for
things have to fit down
okay
um i had a question about the btx scheme
um and how we're accessing page tables
so um when like in the way we're
accessing page tables
um because we're going to the ept and
then um
like doing the second layer layer of
translation there from the um
guest physical address to the host
physical address
um is the latency of accesses um to the
page table actually lower
uh takes more time potentially takes
more time possibly much more time to
train for the hardware mmu to translate
it and dress
good because now it has to do too well
that
the worst case is very much worse
because
you know um on the risk 5 there's
multiple
levels of the page table and so the mmu
esther b
an entry participate from this page
table page and then next to the next
each of those the x86 also has multiple
levels
and so in the x86 in the lookup in the
first in the main page table also has to
make multiple memory references
potentially
each of those multiple memory references
has to go through the ept
and the epd is also a multi-level page
table
so i don't even know what the worst case
number of memory references is but it's
quite a bit worse under vtx than it is
with a
non than it is an ordinary case so
there's a potential there now in fact
there's lots of caching
and so usually you don't run up against
that worst case but okay okay
um and so virtual machines are they
still
like generally slow today and if so
i guess i was wondering how does aws
work if um
it seems to be fast and it seems to be
working well so
um my my belief is that they use vtx
hardware
they use the support that we're talking
about and that it is
as well as clever device schemes for
efficient device access
um and that the result is that aws
virtual machines are
like fast or we're not much slower than
a real computer
cool thank you so much yes
oh i had also another question on the
shadow coffee
for uh trump and eminently so you said
that
it it like i understand how you would
make it but
does it actually make the shadow of
coffee or does it just
i think it has to make the shadow
copyright because it has to allow the
process just to do it
itself not like to go to all the traps
but let's
do it every time does it remember the
previous version oh
okay yes so so so yeah um yes and yes
the virtual machine monitor has to
create a new page table
or there you know yes has to create a
new page table and it's the virtual
machine monitors
you know page table which format it up
which is what the real hardware uses
now of course there are plenty of
opportunities for caching
and for reuse so if the if the clever
virtual machine monitors if they notice
that oh the guest
changed just one pte um then the virtual
machine monitor may
be able to do correspondingly limited
amount of work to update
um its shadow page table and it also may
keep you know when it if it's
sort of multiplexing time sharing among
multiple virtual machines the virtual
machine monitor will keep around
the shadow page tables for the virtual
machines that aren't running
so that it can reuse them directly
when it switches back to that virtual
machine okay
i see so it doesn't mean that you have
like you have to remember
a shadow copy for like each
process for each virtual machine
yes there are many many right there are
many many page tables
uh running around in the virtual machine
the virtual machine is aware of all
page table switches that the guest does
yeah it's uh
that the specific issue of maintaining
the shadow page tables um
has consumed a lot of work right
thank you thank you so much before you
know this is one of the many things that
hardware supported virtual machines
uh made quite a bit easier
oh okay okay i see i see okay because
the ept means you don't have to cook up
your own shadow page
right right right yeah that's that's
nice yeah thank you
yes
all right gotta head out but i'll see
you guys on wednesday thank you
thank you bye-bye thank you
is it okay um you have time for one more
question yes
please um this one is about the garbage
collection
of how it like re-scans um to see if
like they're dirty bits
um like
it's just like a sort of a continued
process where like it continues to
rescan like
indefinitely because um could it
you're asking oh yeah would it ever
terminate supposing oh there's always
something new
modified so in fact potential problem in
fact what the garbage collector does is
it
it it does one pass
one pass through to completion and then
it freezes
everything else but the garbage
collector so nothing else can happen
then it goes back and look at the dirty
pages but of course everything else is
frozen
and so no more no more dirty pages can
occur
and then the garbage so the garbage can
looks all the dirty pages and then it
knows it's done
it you know does whatever it's supposed
to do to finish up and create the free
list and then it be
resumes all the threads that it stopped
okay yeah okay that makes a lot more
sense i i know it froze everything else
but
yeah yeah this is complex stuff and of
course there's not enough room in the
paper the
dune paper to explain all the ins and
outs of what the garbage collector is up
to
sadly all right uh yeah
thank you so much thank you see you