Alright, can you guys hear me?
Yes.
Thank you.
Alright, today I want to talk about talk mostly about micro kernels,
but first a little bit of context to sort of help explain why people explored micro kernels in the first place,
this people got the micro kernels by trying to think about more broadly about what kernels should actually do,
like we've you know with xv6,
is sort of does the things that Unix does
and we kind of take that set of abstractions and system calls and keep sort of facilities,
inside the kernels kind of for granted is the target of what we're trying to design,
but it's totally worth wondering gosh, what should a kernel do in the first place,
maybe maybe the particular kind of stuff that xv6 or Linux does,
it's not really the best answer,
or maybe it is
and of course we're on somewhat treacherous ground here,
because now we're we're what kernels are is kind of a development platform for programmers
as we know programmers different people have very different sort of subjective preferences
about what kind of infrastructure they like to program on.
So we can't necessarily expect a single best answer,
but we can expect to maybe learn something,
and maybe make some progress by trying to think about what answers might be.
So first of all, let me try to crystallize what the traditional approaches
to what kind of kernel interfaces we ought to be using
and Linux and Unix and xv6 are all examples of, of what I personally call a traditional design approach,
but another word for it, that kind of summarizes,
but this approach has ended up like is monolithic.
Monolithic and, what that means is that the kernel is a single big program
that does all kinds of things, all within the same program.
And indeed this really reflects the way people thought about what kernels ought to be doing
a real hallmark of kernels like Linux is that they have, they provide powerful abstractions,
you know they choose things like file systems and which is really a complicated item,
and they present file systems and files and directories and file descriptors as their interface
rather than for example presenting disk hardware as their interface to applications,
so, and using presenting powerful abstractions instead of very low-level abstractions has some big advantages,
monolithic kernels often have a sort of big abstractions,
like, file, the file system.
One advantage of big abstract is that they're often portable of files and directories,
you can implement files and directories on all kinds of storage
and file, you can use files and directories [after] having to worry about what brand of disk drive is running on
or maybe it's an ssd instead of a hard drive,
or maybe it's a network file system
and all its the same interface,
because the file system interface is pretty high level pretty abstract.
So, an advantage of this is that the way to get portability,
write an application and have it run on all kinds of different hardware
without having to modify the application.
Another example of this is that Unix Linux provides an address space abstraction
rather than providing something that's likes rather than providing direct access to the MMU hardware
and that's useful to, for portability and sort of hide complexity from applications.
So another big advantage of these powerful abstractions,
they tend to hide complexity from applications.
The, so for example the file descriptor interface that xv6 provides,
its very simple interface, but you just read and write on file descriptors couldn't get much simpler,
but behind it is very complicated code
for actually reading and writing a disk, the file system on disk.
And that's nice for programmers, but it makes for a big complex kernel,
these big abstractions also help the kernel manage and share resources,
we've delegated to the kernel things like memory management,
the kernel keeps track of what memories free,
we similarly the kernel keeps track of what parts of the disk are free,
in what parts of the disk current current use.
So programs, don't get to think about it,
and that again, it simplifies programs,
it also helps with robustness and security even,
because if programs are allowed to decide what parts of the disk are free or not,
then maybe one program could use a part of the disk that's already being used by another program.
So the fact that the kernel is in charge of resource management,
helps with sharing and helps with security,
but again it's a force that a sort of causes the kernel to be big.
So anyway, so having the kernel being charge of all these sort of juicy abstractions,
that even if they have simple interfaces,
have a lot of complexity inside, have let kernels to be big and complex items.
And another aspect of this monolithic design approaches,
that because it's all one program,
all the different kernel substances, like the file system and the memory allocator and scheduler and virtual memories,
they're all part of one big integrated program,
it means that they can peer into each others data structures,
and so that's just tended to make it much easier to implement facilities,
that are sort of parts of more than one
or what you might think of as more than one kind of module or subsystem,
so for example a system call like exec,
exec has its fingers deeply into file system,
because it's reading binary images of the disk in order to load the memory,
it also has its fingers into the memory allocation and virtual memory paging system,
because it needs to set up the address space of the new process,
but it's really easy,
there's no problem with doing that in xv6 or Linux,
because both [] the file system is right there, in the same kernel program
and the virtual memory system is also right there as part of the same program
and if you somehow there was a rigid split between the file system and the virtual memory system,
would be much harder to implement something like exec,
that has sort of fingers in both of these [pies].
But in a monolithic system just one big program, it's much easier.
Another thing that makes implementing software inside a monolithic kernel like xv6 or Linux easy is that
all the code runs with full hardware privileges, all xv6 runs in supervisor mode for example,
which means there's no limits there's no irritating,
oh, you can't you know me to write that memory here, because you don't have enough privilege,
all the kernel code runs with sort of maximum privilege.
And you know the same is true of operating systems like Linux.
So, this design strategy, it's very convenient for kernel developers
and it's made it easy to build these big abstractions
which are convenient for application developers,
however, there's also a certain amount to criticize with the monolithic, traditional monolithic approach.
And this is starting to be part of the motivation for looking at other architectures, like micro kernels,
so you might ask why not monolithic kernels.
So one is just that they're big and complex,
so anything that's Linux is depending on how you count,
Linux somewhere between many hundreds of thousands and a few million lines of code
and people really do take advantage of the fact that one part of Linux
can sort of look at the data of another and that makes the programming easier,
but it also makes there'd be a lot of interconnections and interrelationships between code
and so it can be a bit challenging sometimes to look at the Linux kernel code
and figure out what it's up to
and anytime you get big programs especially ones that are a complex structure,
you get bugs, and operating system kernels are no exceptions
and over the years they've had all kinds of bugs,
including bugs that are exploitable for security.
So, so this is sort of trouble set of relationships,
if you allow a big model of the kernel,
you almost certainly can't avoid bugs and exploitable security problems
and that's a real I mean there really is a problem.
Another reason why people are, maybe not entirely happy with monolithic kernels is that
they tend to just grow with all desirable features over time
and so you know Linux is used for all kinds of different things,
from telephone handsets to a desktop workstations and laptops to tablets to servers on the Internet to routers
and that's caused Linux, it's fantastic that Linux can support all those things,
but it has caused it to be very general,
it has support in there for many many different things
and any one application like me running my web servers unlikely to need for example Linux is very sophisticated sound card support,
so there's just a huge amount of stuff, that's there for, to allow Linux to be general purpose,
which is good, but there's a worry that general purpose is going to tend to mean slow,
that you know may be good for all kinds of different things,
but maybe not optimum for anything in particular.
so it's very hard to,
you know when you're trying to make something really fast,
it's great to have it just only do one or two things you can focus on optimizing a single code path,
but if your software needs to do any one of a thousand different things,
it's much harder to have focused optimization.
So this is, Linux is not necessarily slow,
but it's you know you might wonder if it's really as fast as it could possibly be for any given situation.
So if you think about it,
how do you think if you think about almost anything in Linux or xv6,
you know you may wonder whether it really needs to do everything it does,
so, for example if you write a single byte over a pipe from one process to another,
but there's a lot of instructions that get executed,
even xv6 which is a simple kernel, right,
there's buffering, you know there's locking, there's could be a sleep and a wakeup during a pipe read and write,
there's maybe a scheduler in may called the scheduler context swhich,
has a lot of stuff that's maybe not necessarily the absolute minimum
that would be required to move a byte from one process to another.
Another potential problem with these big kernels is that,
they, because they're so big and they sort of intentionally bite off,
some very sophisticated abstractions, they tend to have a lot of design decisions, kind of baked into the kernel.
So, you know in ways, that you can't, even if you disagree with them, you can't really you know [tough luck] applications just have to live with it,
so, you know as a as opposed to you, in some fantasy world,
maybe applications could make a lot more of the decisions,
so you know some examples of things where you may just you may be bummed out by the way the API designed,
for example in a Unix you can wait for a process your own children if you fork,
you can wait for your children, but you can't wait for some other process
and maybe you want to wait for a grandchild or an unrelated process,
but that's just not an option, it's just not the way things work,
even if it would be convenient for you,
maybe you want to change the way another processes address space is set up,
you know maybe call and map on behalf of another process that you're controlling,
but again, that's just not an option,
you can map change your own address space, but not changes other process address space,
maybe a database and you have B-tree indexes on the disk
and you may know a lot about it the fastest way to layout B-tree on a disk,
but if you're reading and writing files with the file system,
the file system has no idea that you're actually writing a B-tree or how a B-tree ought to be laid out on a disk for fastest access.
And so if your database you're going to be kind of bummed,
you know maybe you're happy that you have this file system at your disposal,
but it doesn't really do what you want to do.
That's the sense in which a design decisions are often baked into big kernels.
And finally, a specific sort of issue that,
so it came up in a big way in the 1990s probably,
a notion of extensibility,
that it might be desirable for programs to be able to change the kernel on the fly
to be able to download new code in the kernel
or change the way it operates or something,
in order to do things like have databases able to control the layout of data on the disk.
At least in decades past, monolithic kernels tended not to, to have any particular features that help with this kind of extensive ability,
you're just stuck with whatever the kernel did.
Okay.
So, these were sort of problems in the back of people's minds,
that let them to think about other kinds of,
other ways of designing other architectures for operating systems
and and there were a number of, a number of ideas,
some quite radically different that people pursued,
we're going to talk about one of them, particularly popular one today
and that's the idea of micro kernels.
Micro kernels, although many of the ideas
or go back to the beginning of computer history,
they became a sort of hot research topic,
starting in maybe the mid to late 1980s.
And the big idea,
so micro kernel this this word by the way refers to a sort of general approach, a concept,
it doesn't refer to any specific artifact,
there were many people who designed and built operating systems that followed the general sort of plan for micro kernels,
but you know each of these projects ended up designing and operating systems may be quite different from the others,
so the key idea was the tiny kernel,
that supported just IPC or inter process communication,
and some sort of notion of a threads or tasks.
So you have a kernel that provides you a notion of sort of process like abstraction
and away for processes to communicate with each other, with this inter process communication
and nothing else
and everything else you might want to do,
like a file system you'd implement,
as a process as a task as a user level code, not in the kernel at all.
So picture for that,
maybe now we're going to use u for micro kernel,
and the micro kernel down here
and we got user space processes up here
and we might have all the kind of usual processes run,
maybe we're gonna run vi, my favorite text editor,
and my my compiler, my windows system.
But also up here as usual processes, we're going to have the file system,
just as a server process in user space,
maybe we're going to have a disk driver, they know how to talk to my disk hardware,
maybe we have a network stack that, knows how to talk talk TCP to my network interface card,
maybe we'll have a user level process, that's in charge of doing fancy paging tricks,
like memory mapped files or maybe implements copy-on-write fork or something.
And when my text editor needs to read a file, it needs to talk the file system
and so, it's gonna send a a message via IPC inter process communication, to the file system server,
which has all the file system code, it's about files and directories
and file system server code may need to talk to the disk,
so it might send another sort of disk read or write,
so another IPC to the disk driver which somehow talks this hardware,
this driver may return you know a disk block to the file server after it does its thing,
maybe the file server finally returns the data you ask for again by inter process communication messages,
back to my text editor.
But you know the the critical thing to notice here is that
the only stuff going down here in the kernel is support for these processes or tasks or threads, whatever they might be
and support for the inter process communication message passing and nothing else,
there's no file system down here,
there's no device drivers necessarily down here in the kernel,
there's no network stack all that stuff is up here as more or less ordinary user level processes.
So they lead you to a very small kernel with a relatively little code optimize,
like you can optimize IPC and there's not much else going on.
And so this is the kind of picture, we're going to talk about for the rest of the lecture
and just give you a taste of where this ended up,
there are actually still a micro kernels in use today,
and indeed the L4 micro kernel which is the topic of today's paper turns out to be used,
there's many instances many many instances of L4 running,
because it's used in a lot of cellphones in the little micro controllers that control the cell phone radios
and it's also apparently used in recent iPhones
as the operating system that runs on a special dedicated enclave processor in the iPhone
that hides the secret cryptographic keys.
So there's a bunch of embedded where these micro kernels have won out in little embedded specialized computer systems,
not not laptops, but a computer dedicated to single specialized tasks
where you may not need the complexity of Linux,
but you do need some operating system.
And the other thing, that's the other sort of final result from micro kernels is that,
the idea of user level services with with other programs talking to them with IPC,
that also has made its way into a lot of operating systems,
like Mac OS, which running right now to talk to you,
you know it's a sort of as well as being a kind of ordinary monolithic kernel,
it also has good support for a user level services and IPC between Unix processes to talk to the service,
so, that idea also, it was a successful idea and widely adopted.
Okay, so this is the basic architecture,
I'm going to go on and talk about some ways and reasons why this might be attractive,
but first are there any just kind of high-level questions about,
what it is, I mean by micro kernel.
Okay.
So, what is it that people are hoping for, when they started building micro micro kernels,
so, one big motivation, although you wouldn't necessarily see it written down much,
it's just a sense of aesthetics right,
I think just a lot of people feel that huge complicated a single programs like like Linux kernel are just not very elegant,
that surely we can build something that's much more much much smaller much more focused design, isn't such a huge grab bag of random different features,
so I think there was a strong sort of aesthetic feeling.
Surely we can do better than big kernels.
But others are more specific things that you might be able to quantify
or something a kernel that's small might be more secure.
Write a few lines of code, you have probably fewer bugs,
you have less chance of somebody be able to exploit one of those bugs to break security,
and then the extreme of that,
you could imagine operating system that's actually provable provably, correct.
Where somebody can sit down and write a proof
that the operating system has no bugs
or does exactly what it's supposed to do and nothing else
and indeed there is a, at least one, verified proved correct proved secure operating system named seL4,
which is one of the many descendants of the L4 micro kernel,
today's paper,
but you really you know people know how to verify small to medium sized programs,
but they don't know how to verify huge programs unless the fact that micro kernels are small,
sort of critical ingredient and be able to prove their correct.
Another reason why you might like small is that
small amount of code is often a lot easier to optimize than, than a huge program.
Another reason why small might result in fast is that
you don't have to pay for a lot of features you don't use,
your micro kernel does hardly anything then you're not paying for a lot of features, you're not using.
Another reason for small is that,
small kernel probably bakes in far fewer design decisions,
forces fewer design decisions on application writers
and so it leaves them more maybe leaves them more flexible flexibility to make their own design decisions.
By the way, these are all these are not necessary consequences of the micro kernel approach,
these are things that people hoped for and tried to achieve by using micro kernels.
And another set of reasons why micro kernels seemed attractive has to do with the fact that
a lot of the code was at user level,
that is a lot of features and functions
that we sort of grown used to being inside the kernel were actual user level services,
so they hope that by a sort of breaking the kernel part
and running the different parts like a user level services, like a file service, profiles file service server,
that might cause the the code to be more modular,
might sort of encourage operating system designers to split up all these functions into many separate services,
that might that might be a good thing.
User level code is also possibly easier to modify,
its user level it's usually easier to tweak it or replace it or modify it
than doing the same stuff in the kernel,
so maybe it's easier to customize.
Putting the operating systems at user level that also might make them more robust,
you can, you can if the kernel something goes wrong with the kernel,
you know, usually you have to panic and reboot,
because, you know you can't necessarily trust what's in the kernel anymore,
if it's had some bug that maybe causes it to overwrite a random part of its data
whereas if you have a bunch of user level services
and one of them malfunctions and devised by zero or dereferences a wild pointer,
maybe only that one server will crash and leaving the rest of the operating system intact,
then maybe you can restart it, just that one server
so maybe user level moving OS functionality, a user process might lead to more robustness,
this is surprise, particularly evident for drivers, there most bugs in the kernel or actually hardware device drivers,
if we can manage to move the device drivers out of the kernel,
then we might have many fewer bugs crashes in the kernel.
And the final advantage, the people were thinking about back then is that
you could emulate or run multiple operating system personalities on top of a micro kernel,
so even though micro kernel does does hardly anything for you directly,
you might be able to run a Unix server or something on top of it
maybe more than one on the same machine.
Of course, that's what today's papers about, running a Unix running Linux as a service on a micro kernel,
these are all the set of things that people were hoping to be able to get some traction on by looking into micro kernel designs.
Course there's some sort of puzzles, you have to think through.
Some challenges.
One challenge, if you want to design your own micro kernel is
actually figuring out you want the API you want the micro kernel system call interface to be as simple as possible,
because the whole point was to keep it small
and what is the actual smallest set of useful system calls you can get away with.
You know what does it look like.
That's not particularly clear.
Look at the minimum system call, API.
You need these this minimum system call API, it's great, it's simple,
but you actually have to be able to build some pretty sophisticated features out of your minimum system call API,
because even if the kernel doesn't do much,
you know in the end, you've got to be able to run programs,
you got maybe you're trying to run Unix on top of a micro kernel,
to be able do things like fork mmap, so as part of the system call interface,
simple low-level system call interface,
it has to be powerful enough to support all the stuff people need to do,
like exec and fork and [heck] maybe even copy-on-write fork or memory mapping on disk files,
but all in a kernel that has no idea about files or file system
needs to support exec, but with kernel that knows nothing about files.
We need the rest of the, the operating system,
somehow ensure that micro kernel maybe very simple,
but you know now we're requiring the development of some set of user level servers,
that implement the rest of the operating system,
so we need, that has to get done at least and may require some solving design puzzles,
and finally the you know this arrangement requires a lot of chitchat over inter processor communication over IPC,
so there's going to be great pressure to make the you know IPC very fast,
so to wonder whether IPC can be made fast enough,
to keep micro kernels competitive.
Alright, and just in general, actually the not just IPC speed,
but in general a lot of reason to believe that monolithic kernels derived some performance
out of the fact that they're integrated that the file system code can talk to the virtual memory code and memory allocation code,
it's all sort of one big happy giant program.
And if you require all those things to be split out into separate servers
or may be split between the kernel and user level,
there may be fewer opportunities for optimization by way of integration
than that may or may not, end up hurting performance.
Alright. So these are sort of crosscutting, hoped for wins and sort of challenges that all,
the many micro kernel projects faced.
Because of today's paper, I'm gonna tell you a bunch of about L4 specifically
which is the micro kernel the the authors of today's paper developed and used.
L4 is not, it's certainly not the earliest micro kernel ever made,
but it's one of the sort of early micro kernels that came out of all the work in this starting in the 1980s
and it's fairly representative as far as how it works.
There's been, it's a bit of a moving target was the subject of intense development and evolution for many years
and it's still going strong,
if you look at on Wikipedia, you'll see that there's maybe fifteen or twenty different variants of L4
that have come and gone and some are still here
starting I think in the late 1980s
and I know what I'm gonna try to explain to you is my understanding of how L4 worked,
at about the time a today's paper came out.
Alright, so, just at a high level,
the L4 was certainly micro, in the sense that it was actually is a small kernel,
it has only seven system calls some of them a little bit complex,
but still it only has seven system calls,
whereas today's Linux the last time I counted had in the mid three hundreds
and even xv6 which is an extremely simple kernel,
even xv6 has 21 system calls,
so L4 it's only seven,
so by that metric is simple,
it's also not very big,
I think, as the time this paper was written at about 13 000 lines of code,
just not too much xv6 is smaller than that,
I think xv6 maybe six or 7000 lines of code in the kernel,
but still xv6 is very simple as kernels go,
L4 not much more complex than that,
and this is you know a tenth or twentieth or thirtieth as big as as Linux, is pretty small.
It had only a few basic abstractions.
It had a notion of what they called tasks or address spaces.
And these more or less correspond to what we would call a process in Unix,
it's a, it's a bunch of memories map starting at zero
and and you're able to execute in here, just like in the process,
when different from xv6 is that there can be multiple threads per task.
And L4 was in charge of scheduling multiple threads of execution within each task.
And part of the reason for this is just it's very convenient to have threads as a programming structuring program structuring tool
and it was also I don't know if they actually supported multi core multiprocessor machines,
at the time the paper was written,
but, they may well have and threads,
of course just what you need to be able to harness multiple cores executing the same program,
so there's are threads supported by L4 kernel.
So so, L4 supported tasks, it knew about tasks, it knew about threads
and it also knew about address spaces,
in the sense that you could, you could ask tell L4 look, here's how we want pages mapped into address space.
And the other main thing that L4 knew about is inter process communication,
so that was every thread has an identifier
and one thread could say look I want to send a message, it just some bytes to another thread,
and here's this identifier, please, please send a message to that other thread.
So these are really the only task threads address spaces
and IPC were really the only abstractions,
the system calls, I don't know if I can be able to list them all,
but Um the system calls were there was a thread,
thread create system call which also you gave it a address space id has to create a new thread
and if the address space are tasked in already exist,
it would create a new task for you,
sort of combine thread and task creation.
There's send and receive, various flavors of send and receive IPC system calls.
There's a way to map pages into your or other address space,
so, you, you could ask the L4 to change the way your address space was set up
the way your page table maps were set up,
but you could also ask L4 if you had the right permissions to go
and change the way another task's address space was set up.
So, this was actually done through the IPC,
would spent through the IPC interface,
you would send a special IPC message that the kernel knew about to the target thread,
and the kernel would modify the target threads address space.
And this is if you are creating a new thread,
this is actually new threads are created with no memory at all,
so if you want to create a thread,
you first call the thread create system call to create a new thread and task and address space,
and then you send it,
if you make one of these magic IPCs to send some of your own memory maps of your own memory
that you've prepared with instructions or data
to map that memory into the new, and so a new task address space,
and then you send a special start IPC to this new task with the program counter and stack pointer, you want it to start executing with,
that will start executing and that memory you've setup at the program counter you ask startup.
There's a way not through system calls,
in fact I don't know how it worked,
but privileged tasks could map device hardware, you know device control registers into their own address spaces.
So, L4 didn't really know much about devices like disks or network interface cards,
but user level software could get directly at.
User level software that implemented device drivers that user level could get directly at device hardware.
There was a way to you could tell L4 to turn an interrupt,
any interrupt from any device,
L4 didn't really know which device just turned, given interrupt into an IPC message.
So a device driver task could not just read write the device hardware,
but also tell L4 well anytime that device interrupts,
please send me an IPC message notifying me the interrupt.
And finally one task tell the kernel to give it notifications of another task page faults,
so if this test page fault, L4 would turn that into an IPC message
and send it to another designated pager task.
Send the notification the page fault to a designated page task,
so every task has an associated pager task that handled its page faults,
and that's the way you know you get hooks into the page faults,
in order to implement things like copy-on-write fork or lazy allocation.
And that's it for the kernel, there's nothing else in L4,
there's no file system,
L4 didn't itself had support for things like fork exec,
didn't have any communication beyond these very simple IPC,
like did not pipes, did not device drivers, no networking support nothing,
everything else if you wanted it,
you need to supply as a user level services.
Okay, so, one thing that are, L4 does supply is switching among threads,
L4 would actually do the scheduling and context switches in order to multiplex a single CPU among multiple threads
and the way it did it you would find completely unsurprising,
L4 basically had saved registers for every task for every thread,
when it executed a thread, the executing thread would jump into user space, switch page tables,
so that thread and that thread will execute for a while in user space,
then maybe the timer interrupt would go off
and that was actually a device L4 knew about,
the timer interrupt might go off after a while,
interrupting the L4, L4 would save this tasks, user registers in a per task,
an array of tasks thread structures,
would save this threads registers away,
pick a new task to run in a loop, much like the scheduling loop in xv6,
restore this tasks registers out from its previously saved registers,
switch page tables, and then jump into this task and execute it for a while,
until the timer interrupt went off or until this task either yielded,
I think there's also probably a yield system call or something like it.
A task can yield a CPU or a task could wait to receive an IPC in that case.
L4, we jump back into L4 and L4 see this registers switch to a new task and that task,
so that thread switching part of L4 is very, that would be very familiar.
The, um.
I I mentioned this before I just want to because it comes up.
I wanna write here, this notion of a pager,
the repeat if a process is a page fault, traps into the kernel
and the kernel turns that page fault into an IPC message to a designated pager task
and tells it the address, tells this pager task which thread faulted and the address it faulted on on.
And then the pager task if it wants to say, implement lazy allocation,
maybe this thread wrote or write some memory that was allocated yet,
but I think but it sort of asked to be lazily allocated,
its pager task would then be in charge of allocating some memory from L4,
sending one of these special IPCs,
cause that caused memory to be mapped into this task,
and then sending an IPC to resume execution inside this thread.
So there was this notion of pager task
to implement all this all the stuff that xv6 or Linux implements in page fault handlers,
like you could implement copy-on-write fork with this, if you liked,
or memory mapped files,
all using one of these pager task.
They were sort of powerful user level way,
play tricks with a driven by page faults
and so this is an example, one of many examples in which micro kernel like L4 might have been quite a bit more flexible for user programs than a conventional kernel,
like if you think Linux ought to do some extra thing,
like maybe you know some you know if Linux didn't already have copy-on-write fork
and you wanted to have copy-on-write fork,
you really can't implement that in Linux without modifying the kernel
and there's no way to write portable code, portable user level code for Linux
that could implement something like copy-on-write fork.
That's not quite true, but it would be very difficult,
whereas L4 its relatively straightforward,
L4 is completely set up for you to be able to write user level code
that gets the page faults that are required to drive copy-on-write fork,
all in user space without having to mess with the kernel.
Okay, so any questions so far about how L4 works.
Oh, sorry, can you just clarify the difference between a thread and a task.
Yes, a task corresponds to it's like a process in xv6,
it has a bunch of memory and address space and you can execute user code in,
xv6 if you have a process in xv6, it can only there can only be one thread of control, on a single you know executing inside a process in xv6,
but in modern operating systems and L4, in a single process, in a single address space,
you could have if you have multiple cores, you can have multiple cores executing a single task for each,
typically always each set up with its own stack inside that task's address space.
And so if, that means you can for example, write a single program that can get parallel speedup,
improved performance from multi core hardware by running one thread on having multiple threads each running a different core,
thereby getting more work done.
Okay I see, thank you.
Yes.
Okay, so as you can see,
this is a design that relies heavily on IPC,
because you're going to want to talk to your file server,
a file server is going to want to talk to the device driver server,
you're gonna have IPC messages flying back and forth,
for every system call, for every page fault, for every device interrupt,
the IPC system just has to be fast,
however now we're starting to talk about a serious potential defect in a micro kernel story.
So first let me show you a straightforward, but very slow design,
for IPC patterned off of Unix pipes
and I'm bringing this up because some early micro kernels worked in sort of a similar way to what I'm about to show you,
which turned out to be slow.
Okay, so, let's suppose you have, you know you have two processes,
we got P1, P1 wants to send a message to P2.
So how should that actually work,
well, one possibility is to have a send system call,
and you give send system call the id of the thread you want to send a message to
and a pointer to the message to the bytes, may be that you actually want to send to that process,
so this system call are going to jump into the kernel,
you know maybe we design this patterned after pipes and xv6,
so you can imagine there being a buffer of messages waiting,
maybe P2 doing something else right now,
maybe it's a server it's serving somebody else's request,
so it's not ready to handle your request,
you can imagine, maybe a buffer of waiting messages in the kernel, like a pipe buffer,
when you call send, it appends your message to this buffer waiting for P2 to receive it,
now, in fact almost always,
in these systems you rarely just wanted to send a message,
you almost always wanted to get a response too,
you wanted an RPC, remote procedure call operation,
so in fact, P1 would probably follow this immediately by a receive to try to get the response back,
but in general, let's just imagine we're doing a one-way IPC for the moment,
so send would append your message to the in kernel buffer,
we have to copy the message bytes from user space into this buffer
and then return and process one can do something else,
like maybe prepared to receive the response,
after a while P2, it's gonna want to receive the next message just gonna make the received system call,
and that's gonna return the id of the sender,
and copy the message into P2's memory,
just gonna take the front message off the queue, copy into P2's memory,
and then return.
So, um.
This is called, there's some words for this, whose opposite you'll see saw in today's paper,
this is called an asynchronous scheme,
because P1 sends a message without having to wait for anything,
it just appends to queue and returns.
And it's called a buffered system, because the kernel copy this message into the buffer into its internal buffer on the send
and then later when the receive happens it copies the message out of the buffer to the target,
so this is asynchronous buffered.
If you're doing a full request response pair,
then P1 is going to call send,
send going to return P1 is then immediately,
let's assume we're going to assume that's really two sets of buffers one for each direction,
P1 immediately gonna call receive, receive gonna wait, need to wait for something to appear in the reply buffer,
so it's going to have to yield the CPU,
it's got to do something and call sleep in xv6 yield the CPU,
on a single CPU system, it may be only at this point that P1 gives up the CPU and now P2 can run.
And indeed the hardware in this era was almost always single core,
certainly this paper is running on single core hardware,
so P1 is gonna be [one] executing and P1 not executing until P1 finally gives up the CPU
and receive waiting for a message to appear here
and only then will P2 be scheduled maybe to call receive,
receive copy the message and then P2 make it's called to send, to append its reply.
And then the send system call return to P2
and at some point presumably P2 will give up to CPU,
maybe the timer will go off,
then P1 will resume execution in the kernel,
see there's a message there and return back to user space
and so that means that in this design is slow design.
There's in order to have a request and a response,
there's four system calls two sends, and two receives,
you know each user kernel crossings, each one of which is reasonably expensive,
there's a need to sleep, this receive has to sleep, waiting for data to appear,
and there's a full called the scheduler loop and a context switch from P1 to P2,
in order to make this.
And you know each of these kernel crossings and contexts which is potentially expensive,
because, you know every time you cross the kernel user boundary,
you switch page tables and that is,
it has a near certainty of disturbing the CPU caches,
like changing the page table, probably flushes the TLB, the virtual memory lookup cache,
which is going to slow things down.
So, this is a pretty slow way to go involves a lot of kernel crossings message,
copying of messages between user and kernel,
maybe allocation of buffers etc,
but it turns out that for the, for this stylized case in which you're sending a request and you want to get a response back,
you can strip this down to considerably simpler design
and in fact, this is the way it forward.
And this was laid out in a famous paper,
called improving IPC by kernel design published a few years before today's paper.
So it does a couple things differently,
for one thing, it's synchronous.
That is, there's none of this, there's no dropping something off
and returning and waiting, letting the other guy letting the other process pick up the data,
when it feels like, instead send waits for receive and receive waits for send,
so, [] P1 and I want to send and I call send,
it doesn't copy my message into a buffer,
it actually P1 will now immediately if the P1 send in the L4 kernel, waits for P2 to call receive
and if P2 is already in the kernel waiting in a call to receive,
well P2 is either already in the kernel, waiting in a call to receive
or P1 send and wait for it, wait for P2's next call to receive,
when both have arrived here, when P1 is, in the kernel and it's called a send,
P2's in the kernel is called to receive,
only then does anything happen,
and one reason this is fast is that,
if P2 is already received,
then P1, when it's executing send in the kernel,
can just without a context switch or a general purpose scheduling,
can just jump back into user space into P2,
as if it was returning from this receive, right,
and that's a much faster path through the kernel,
than you know saving registers, giving up the CPU calling the scheduler and finding a new process to run,
instead P1 send knows that there's a waiting receive,
and just sort of immediately jumps into P2,
as if it was returning from receive.
The scheme that they developed is also unbuffered.
And it could do that partially, because it's a synchronous,
when both the send and receive are in the kernel,
the message can be you know send sending some message,
the kernel can directly copy the message from user space to user space,
without having to first copy into the kernel, and then back out of the kernel,
because because since both sides wait for the other system call what happened,
that means that they've waited for both pointers to be known,
received specifies where it wants the message to be deposited,
so at this point, we know both addresses then kernel just do the copy directly,
instead of through the kernel.
For and if the message is super small,
like maybe only a few dozen bytes,
then, it can be passed in registers without any copy at all,
what you might call zero copy.
Remember the send only proceeds if the P2 is already in receive
and send basically jumps directly to P2,
well this code path through the kernel takes care to not disturb a bunch of registers
and that means that P1 can put its system call, if the message is short, it can put the message in certain designated registers,
the kernel guarantees to preserve those registers on its way up to P2
and that means that, when the kernel returns from the receive system call as a result of send,
the contents of those designated registers hold the message
and therefore never had to be copied at all from memory to memory,
never had to be moved at all,
they're just sitting right in the registers, where they can be accessed very quickly.
And this you know of course only works for small messages,
for very large messages, L4 could carry a page mapping in IPC message,
so for huge messages,
you know like the result of reading a block from a file or something,
you could just send the pages will be mapped into the target address space, again without any copy.
And so it's done through page mapping,
give away the page or access your [copy], access to this permission to share the page.
And so small messages are fast, huge messages are pretty fast,
you still have to adjust the page table to target,
but that's much faster than copying,
and final trick that L4 played was noticing that if you're doing an RPC with the request and response,
are very stylized peers of system calls
and you may as well combine system calls send and receive system calls in order to reduce kernel crossing,
so for the special case of RPC, which is almost always what people are doing, when they're using IPC,
there was a call, system call, and the call was basically combined send plus receive,
but without the return to user space,
and then re-entry into kernel space, that a pair of system calls take,
on the server side, there was a a single call that would send the reply from one system call
and then wait for the request message from anyone for the next system call.
And this is basically a send of one response,
but wait to receive the next request,
and this again cut in half the number of kernel crossings
and it turned out that, the sum of all of these optimizations,
now for the kind of short RPCs which are, you know one typical workload all this led to a 20x speedup.
This is what their paper reported 20x speedup over there previous system,
which was presumably a little bit more like what I showed in a previous design.
And so this was an impressive,
this paper came out a few years before the by some of the same authors,
but few years before the people were reading
and this caused people to view micro kernels a little bit more favorably.
The IPC could actually be quite fast.
Any questions about these IPC tricks that L4 plays.
Yeah I I think I missed this,
but, when is a process a sending there are receiving messages,
like when is it using that system call.
Okay, actually, so for RPCs, for request response,
in fact, in fact, the the processes use this pair of of system calls
rather than sending receive.
So yeah, call, you really get two arguments,
message you want to send and a place to put the response
and inside the kernel just combines these two,
you could view this is a bit of a hack,
but because IPC is so frequent,
it's worse a little bit of hacker in order to make it fast.
And in the diagram up there, in the box,
where, you have P2 sending that are running the received system call,
why, what prompted P2 to.
Okay it in a in my RPC world, we got, we have clients,
and they're sending requests to servers,
and the server is going to do something in reply,
so since P2 is the server,
we imagine that P2 is sitting in a while loop,
in which in which it's going to receive the next message from any client
do a little bit of work to process it,
you know look up some data in a database or something,
and then send a reply and go back to the top of the loop and wait again,
so to first approximation, we expect P2 spends all its time waiting for the next message from anyone, that can request from anyone.
And this design really, it does kind of rely on P2 always
and when it's at rest, basically sitting in the kernel in a receive system call waiting for the next request,
so that the next request can directly basically return from that system call.
And that's the fast path, that's super efficient in this design.
Sorry, just to follow up on that,
that means that, you said that it goes from P1 and returns to P2,
so like to come back, you would need to send a response, so.
That's right, we expect P2 to send a response,
and that sending of the response actually follows basically the same code path in reverse,
that when P2 sends a response,
that that effectively causes P1 to return from,
I mean, P1 was actually making this call system call,
so the delivery of P2's response causes the call
the return from this from this system called back into P1.
Okay, I see, thank you.
This is a little bit different from the usual setup,
where you think you jump into the kernel and system call
and you execute that system call and it returns sort of all working on behalf of P1
which is the way pipe read write work,
here, you know P1 is entering the kernel,
P1 entering the kernel, and you know that the return goes to P2,
kind of odd, but very fast.
Okay, so this was a big big sort of contribution to people taking micro kernels,
people's willingness to take micro kernel seriously as potential replacement for a monolithic kernels,
however you know that you still have to still leave open the question even if RPC is fast,
like where you get the rest of the operating system,
like this kernel only has a few percent of all the stuff,
like file systems and network stacks, we expect to be in a full operating system.
What do we do about the rest
and this question is usually being asked in the context of some university research project with relatively limited resources,
we need to get all those user level services from somewhere.
Actually there are specialized applications for which that's not too much of a problem,
if we're running you know some sort of device you know controller,
or maybe the you know ignition control system for your car,
that is only running a few thousand lines of code anyway,
maybe just need a file system,
then we can get away with very little stuff at user level
and micro kernels totally makes sense for that kind of application,
but but the people, you know when these projects really they had ambitions,
that oh gosh going to totally replace existing operating systems
and they hoped that they could build something that people would want to run on their on their workstations
and run on their servers and everywhere,
just replace big monolithic kernels altogether
and but for that you know you need a real you need all the stuff that an operating system does.
One possibility, the most maybe, sort of philosophically consistent possibility would be to re-implement everything you need,
but in a sort of micro kernel way as lots and lots of different user level processes,
but that's just,
actually, people, there were projects did that,
but it's a vast amount of work
and more specifically, people really want to run,
you know, in order for me to use a laptop,
it just has to run Emacs and it has to run my favorite C compiler,
otherwise I'm just definitely not going to switch to your operating system.
And what that meant is that micro kernels in order for to gain any kind of adoption,
they had to be able to support existing applications,
they had to be able to be compatible provide identical
or at least the system call at the higher level service API level,
they had to be totally compatible with some exist on operating system like Unix like Linux,
in order for anybody to be willing to switch.
So these projects face a more specific problem of
how they were going to get,
how are they going to attain compatibility with existing applications written for Linux or maybe Windows or something,
but for this project, it was Linux
and rather than write their own totally new set of user level servers,
that mimic Linux, they decided to take a far easier path
and many projects did this of simply directly running an existing monolithic kernel as on top of their micro kernel,
instead of re-implementing some new thing
and says that's exactly what today's paper is about.
It has, indeed, you know L4 micro kernel down at the bottom,
but also as like a pretty big server,
they run a pretty full Linux kernel as a user level process.
And so, that may sound a little surprising,
the kernel is not a user level process right, the kernel is the kernel,
you think of it as running on the hardware,
but in fact you know Linux kernel as you can see from, running xv6 in QEMU,
which is running in user space after all,
a kernel is just a program
and so with some modifications, it can be made to run at user level
and so they had to modify Linux
and they took a lot of the low-level stuff in Linux,
for example of the code in Linux,
that expects to be able to directly modify page tables or read and write processor registers,
there were some low-level stuff they had to modify,
some parts of Linux had to change,
in order to convert them to basically make system calls
or send IPC messages through L4 instead of directly get at hardware,
but for the most part they were able to directly run without change, almost all of Linux,
so that means they got as part of Linux,
you know file system and network support and all kinds of device drivers.
Who knows what that comes with Linux.
Without having to write their own version of this.
Now, in fact, the way this was set up was that Linux,
the Linux kernel ran as one L4 task,
but each Linux process ran as a separate L4 task,
when you log into this Linux
and you ask it to run a shell for you, a terminal window or something,
it's going to fire up an L4 task.
That's going to run that Linux program at user level,
so there were one task for Linux
and one task for each Linux process that you fire up under Linux
and Linux instead of directly modifying the page table the VI, VI process uses,
Linux is going to ask send the right IPC L4 to cause L4 to change VI's page table.
Any questions about that, about the basic scheme here.
Another thing to, another thing that was changed,
many small things were changed,
but, a specific thing of interest is that when VI wants to make a system call.
So, If VI doesn't know it's running on L4,
[] in this scheme, it's really all these programs,
just think of themselves as running on Linux,
when VI wants to make a system call, you know L4 does not support,
its not making L4 system call, it's making Linux system call,
so VI system calls like fork, there's a little library, basically that was linked into these.
Linux processes that would return calls to things like fork or exec or pipe read or write into IPC messages,
that it would send to the Linux task
and wait for the response to the Linux task,
then return as if the system call returned.
So so these little libraries return system calls into IPC messages to Linux
and what that meant is that,
if the Linux kernel task isn't doing anything, it isn't doing anything else,
it's sitting in a call to receive waiting for the next system call request,
IPC from any one of these processes.
And that led to it,
that that leads to a significant difference between how this Linux works and how ordinary Linux works,
in ordinary Linux, just like xv6, there's a basically a kernel thread that corresponds to every user level process
and when program makes a system call,
it, the kernel runs a thread on behalf of that system call,
and when in ordinary Linux, when Linux switches between kernel threads,
that basically implies a switch from one process to another.
So there's kind of one to one correspondence between what kernel thread Linux kernels running and what process is gonna run when Linux is done,
here that connection is broken,
they were indeed in this Linux server, a kernel thread corresponding to each.
I'm sorry, let me start again,
the Linux kernel server was running in a single L4 thread,
so there was only a single sort of thread of control executing in Linux at a time.
However, just as in xv6, this one thread of control would switch using a technique very much like xv6 context which,
could switch between a kernel thread corresponding to each user process,
however, which of these, the these kernel threads were implemented purely within Linux,
had nothing to do with L4 threads,
there's only one L4 thread here,
but which user process was running was determined by L4,
so in this setup Linux might be serving a request from executing the kernel thread for VI,
serving a VI system call,
at the same time that L4 is causing this shell to run in user space,
which is very unlike what happens in xv6 or Linux
where there's a direct correspondence between the sort of active kernel thread and the corresponding a user level thread.
Here L4 of running whatever it feels like
and these threads in the Linux kernel are really much more private
and are just about Linux being able to concurrently execute system calls in different stages of execution,
where maybe one process is waiting for the disk in its thread,
Linux can run a different processe's kernel thread to serve that process system call.
So, you might wonder why this design didn't directly use L4 threads to implement the various different kernel threads inside Linux,
why did Linux implement its own sort of internal threads package instead of using L4 threads
and the answer was that in those days, a, they didn't have access to multi-core hardware,
they were using single core hardware,
so there were no performance advantage to be able to execute multiple threads in the kernel at the same time,
because there was only one core,
so a second thread couldn't be executing, only one thread could execute at a time due to the hardware
and the other may be even more powerful reason is that
in those days, the version of Linux they were using, did not did not have the support,
that's required to have multiple threads multiple cores executing inside the kernel at the same time,
they were using a uni-processor Linux,
said old enough Linux it expected only one core, the kernel at a time.
It didn't have things like the spin locks the xv6 has,
that would allow it to correctly execute multiple multiple cores inside the kernel,
so there would have been no performance advantage in having multiple L4 threads active inside the kernel,
but it would have required adding in you know for no performance,
when adding in all the spin locks and other stuff that's required to support concurrency,
so they didn't do it.
A drawback of this arrangement is that
in ordinary Linux, in native Linux like you would run directly on your laptop,
Linux has a lot of sophisticated scheduling machinery that can do things like impose priorities on different processes
or ensure various kinds of fairness.
And that was fine, because in on your laptop,
because Linux is in control of what process is running on each core,
but in this setup Linux is not controlling that at all,
and Linux is no control over what, what process is running,
because it L4 that does this scheduling, not Linux,
now these processes are scheduled by L4,
so they kind of lost the ability to have Linux be in charge of a schedule.
You know, it's a bit of a defect of this,
although I'm sure later versions of L4 had someway for Linux or something like it
to be able to tell the L4 schedule,
look, please give this process higher priority or whatever,
so it's a bit awkward.
Alright.
So, so they went to all this work to get this going.
And, you should ask yourself
you know what is the, what's the takeaway lesson from from this paper about micro kernels.
Now, one things, so for us, you know this paper has a lot of interesting tidbits about how micro kernels work,
about how Linux works and how you set up how you can design a system like this,
which may be interesting,
but a larger world people want to want to draw some lessons they need to be able to,
I present some lessons in this paper,
the paper is not really answering the question are micro kernel is a good idea,
that's not really what's going on here,
the paper what the paper is part of argument about whether micro kernels have enough performance to, to be worth using
and the reason is that in in, maybe five years five or ten years before this paper came out,
there was a famous set of measurements on one of the predecessor micro kernels
and earlier micro kernel called Mach, basically running in very much this configuration,
but it's different, you know, totally different design internally,
but kind of the same architecture,
this, the name of this earlier micro kernel project is Mach,
there was measurements on Mach, that showed that Mach was dramatically slower than just ordinary Unix,
when it was run in this configuration
and you know there are a lot of reasons for that having to do with the IPC system,
not being as optimized as you might hope,
they're being just sort of more context switches
and you know we use our kernel crossings and cache misses and whatever,
there's a whole lot of reasons why Mach was slow,
but many people saw those benchmark results showing that Mach was much slower than native operating systems
and decided that micro kernels were just hopeless, hopelessly inefficient,
we're unlikely ever to be fast enough to be competitive
and you know we should just all use monolithic kernels.
Today's papers like an answer, basically, to that argument,
it's sort of the rebuttal to that argument
and the point of this paper is to show that you can build this architecture,
and if you pay attention to optimizing performance,
you can get a competitive performance with native operating systems just directly running Unix,
and therefore, you can't dismiss micro kernels simply on the basis of performance,
you may not want them for other reasons,
but you can't use performance as the reason to reject,
part of, a huge part of the ingredients in making that argument is that
they made the IPC much faster with the techniques that I outlined a few minutes ago
and you can see this I think in a, in a very simple benchmark table two,
if you have a copy of the paper with you,
table two as measurements of just native Linux running in the ordinary way on hardware
and on native Linux, they show that you know on their hardware and their version of Linux,
that a single simple system call get pid took 1.7 micro seconds,
and they also show that the sort of equivalent thing in there L4 setup,
where you have to send an IPC request and get an IPC response
just for this get process id system call,
that that that took four microseconds under L4 Linux,
which is to say twice as long, but there's twice as much work going on,
because you're doing two sets of user kernel crossings
instead of just a single simple system call,
that is they could claim that they appeared the expense of these IPC base system calls
down to basically the minimum that is twice the cost of system call native Linux
and therefore they were doing roughly as good as you could possibly expect.
Now, of course that's still their systems are still half as fast as native Linux.
And you know it's not clear unless you did some measurements whether system calls taking twice
or simple system calls taking twice as long as a disaster or not a problem
and in order to show that you know it might be a disaster, if you do a lot of system calls
or might be not a problem, if you do relatively few system calls
or there's a lot of work per system calls, maybe a system calls are more complicated than get pid.
And the answer to that in the paper is the figure A benchmark,
using this benchmark called AIM,
which is just a more, it's a benchmark that has all kinds of different system calls,
it reads and writes files and creates processes does all the things with the kernel that processes do,
and they basically showed in figure A that their setup running a much more full application that does,
much more than just get pid,
runs only a few percent slower than native Linux,
and therefore, hopefully you could expect that whatever it is you wanted to run on a computer,
would run almost as fast under L4 plus Linux,
as it does under a straight operating system, under native operating system
and therefore you know they were basically to a first approximation as fast as just running straight Linux
and therefore you should take them seriously.
Okay, so that was an impressive result by the way,
this is like someone unexpected and cool,
just fast forwarding twenty years, where this ended up,
as I mentioned before people actually use L4 in a bunch of embedded situations,
particularly its used a lot, there are many instances of L4 running in in smartphones,
hidden from view but nevertheless.
And all running various kinds of custom software not not running,
they don't have to have compatibility with Unix, in these situations,
micro kernels in other more general situations like workstations or servers never really caught on
and it's not because there's necessarily anything wrong with that design,
it's just they would have in order to displace some existing software,
your new thing has to be you know like better,
so people will be motivated to switch.
Then, these micro kernels were perfectly good, naturally elegant,
but it was hard to put for people to put their finger on why it was so much better,
that they should go to the trouble of switching from Linux or whatever they were running fits,
so it never really caught on not necessarily for good reasons,
but because they were like dramatically better.
On the other hand, many ideas from this architecture had a lasting impact,
the the people have to work out much more interesting and flexible ways of using virtual memory
in order to support operating systems on their micro kernels
and those more sophisticated interfaces made their way through things like mmap into mainstream operating systems like Linux,
this idea of running an operating system kind of on top,
as a as a server on top of a lower level operating system,
is extremely popular today in the form of virtual machine monitors,
which use all over the place and sort of cloud hosting services.
The desire for extensibility, you could modify a user level service,
the way that played out in things like Linux was loadable kernel modules
which allow you to load modify the way the Linux kernel works on the fly
and of course the sort of client server, good support for this client server architecture,
also made its way into kernels like Mac OS,
which has good IPC and good client server.
And that's all I have to say for this lecture,
I'm happy to stick around for questions, thank you.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Oh, I wanted to ask so the paper we're talking about virtual, about page tables,
at I think 4.2 and it was saying how,
I think it was kind of what what you mentioned before,
where you said that there is a wrong way to do that,
I think might be kind of similar to that,
but if you do this, this thing that you explain this in your picture now,
would it be I guess how how would the page tables work in this case.
Well, are you, you may be referring to section 4.3 the dual space mistake.
Oh yes sorry 4.3.
Yeah that's a bit of a complicated story,
but the let's see, part of the background is the way that Linux worked in those days,
and indeed until recently is that the when you're running at user level,
the page table, this active has both the processes pages user level pages mapped in
and all of the kernel mapped into that one page table, on x86 anyway,
so when you made system call, and jumped into the kernel,
the kernel was already mapped into the page table
and therefore no page table switch was required
when you make a system call, its that much more expensive and much more cheaper,
because there was no page table switch,
if you're calling xv6, you know the trampoline code switches page tables,
which is an expensive thing to do,
because it flushs the TLB cache of virtual to physical mappings.
Anyway, so for efficiency Linux used to map kernel and user space in the same page table
had fast system calls as a result,
so they for reasons that aren't very clear,
decided to do this same thing to setup the mapping in the Unix server.
Well, what they wanted was that when VI, when a process send a system call over here,
they wanted to have the page table that was active,
well, in the Linux server while processing that system call,
include all the virtual memory mappings, mappings for the process that sent the system call.
And that, at least would make it simpler to look up virtual addresses past a system call arguments like pass to read,
the reason why this worked out poorly,
there are a bunch of reasons, one is that, L4 which doesn't know anything about any of this stuff,
L4 just knows there's two processes
and so when you send an IPC from one process to another,
L4 just switches page tables, it always just switches page tables,
this guy the page table, VI, the page table,
L4 associates a page table with Linux kernel, just always switches page tables,
so you couldn't even do the L4 due to the different way system calls are implemented
and the fact that L4 was involved, there was no way to preserve the page table during a system call,
that just wasn't possible,
because L4 always switched page tables when it switched from one process to another,
so they were never going to get the efficiency win of not having to switch page tables,
when that once a crossing from from user to kernel.
But I think they wanted the convenience of being able to directly use user supplied virtual addresses.
But that meant that mappings they needed to be active depended on which process they were executing a system call on behalf of,
so there couldn't be any one page table for Linux,
page table Linux sort of one is used depends on what process sent system call RPC,
but L4 did not know how to play that game,
L4 associated a single page table with each process with each task,
and so in order and it would just switch to that page table,
so tough luck, Linux didn't have any way to cause the page table to differ depending on who it's sent to the system call,
in order to deal with that, apparently they made a bunch of shared memory copies of the kernel, one for each process
and so each of these shared memory copies of the kernel,
had exact had all of the kernel memory mapped into it,
so they were all the same kernel data structures,
but each process had a dedicated kernel task associated with it
and therefore that basically allowed them to trick L4
and to switch into the appropriate page table
that included that process plus the kernel depending on which process synthesis system call request.
And you know I think that kind of worked,
but I don't forget what they said they worked was slow or something,
because there were a lot of tasks.
Anyway, it's a complicated story,
and I think it didn't work out very well for this.
Okay okay I see, I think I think that explains well why this thing is harder to do than, well, what we do xv6, okay.
Yeah yeah, this, because there's not, you have this picture xv6 or even standard Linux is much simpler than this,
you're just jumping directly into the kernel
and the kernel has control over direct control over all the paging hardware,
which doesn't have when it runs L4.
Right, okay I see, thank you, thank you.
We're gonna ask, why, it seems like some some tasks are more appropriate to be put outside the kernel than others,
but this L4 like the approach with micro kernels always seems to be either everything or nothing,
like either you have a monolithic kernel doing everything or nothing,
just like I feel like paging and some other things could be very efficient inside the kernel,
and then maybe like file systems that things that need to be swappable could be outside,
and then even like you can maybe even have a kernel that has some functionality,
but you can opt to not use it and provide your own,
is there any thing.
You say is absolutely, well taken and indeed there were a lot of micro kernel or micro kernel related projects
and many of them built various kinds of hybrids,
like there's actually a couple different versions of Mach
and some of them sort of hybrid kernels,
which yeah there was this micro kernel that knew about IPC,
but also in the kernel was a complete Unix,
so for instance Mach 2.5 was this hybrid with it.
But micro kernel and Unix all sort of in the same kernel
and you can make system calls either and some stuff was built in,
the sort of micro kernel way,
but some things they were just used the kernel that was in Mach,
that was built into the Mach kernel,
the Unix kernel was built into the Mach kernel, a modern MAC OS also built in a way that like the way you describe,
you know Mac OS has a complete operating system with a file system and everything inside it,
but it also has good support for IPC and sort of like threads,
all the stuff you would want to build micro kernel style services.
Is Google's Fuchsia, I'm aware of also implements some of these ideas now as well.
I'll bet yeah.
So anyway, there's no one way, there were people who were sort of hoping that a pure, a very pure scheme could be made to work.
It's not the only possible way forward.
Alright, thanks, got around my next lecture, but I'll see you guys.
See you later.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Oh I I didn't have a,
I have just a remark, I I think it's fascinating,
that it it's like 5% slower, but it does so much more work,
yeah was fascinated with that.
You mean that even though it's doing much more work is only slightly slower,
really have a really sweat blood over the IPC performance
and it's another thing to remember, of course is that,
if you start doing, if you're doing a significant amount of work per system call,
you know, looking at files and directories or something,
then the cost of the system call, the IPC itself starts to be less important.
So the combination of faster system calls plus real programs do things other than making system calls.
But you would also like switch page tables and.
Yeah.
The others have.
Yeah, although the paper, I did not talk about it,
but the paper had some clever tricks for avoiding the cost of switching page tables,
I don't know if you remember for some of its on page six,
we're talking about supporting tagged TLBs a small spaces,
they have some clever ideas for not swhich page tables,
which I had not heard of before I read this paper.
This is pretty cool, thank you so much, bye.
Goodbye.