Alright, anyone hear me.
Good.
Alright today we got meltdown,
the reason why I'm reading this paper is that
security has kind of been a topic all along and comes up a lot in the design of the kernels
that we talked about in the class
and as we know the main strategy, we've talked about for,
what it means for a kernel to provide security is isolation,
in the sense that user programs can read data from the kernel
and user programs can't read other user's data from other user programs
and the specific techniques that you know we've seen operating systems used in order to get isolation
or things like the user supervisor mode in the hardware
and the page tables in the hardware
as well as just sort of well designed kernel software,
like the system calls are all defensive about how they use user supplied pointers.
But it's worth thinking about, looking at examples of how this kind of stuff goes wrong,
I mean in fact you know kernels try hard to provide isolation and security,
but there are problems that come up,
and this paper is a one of the most interesting problems,
that's come up with operating system security in recent times.
Meltdown is came out it, was published at the beginning of 2018 so not too long ago
and a lot of people like me found it surprising
and actually pretty disturbing, pretty disturbing attack on user kernel isolation.
It really undermined faith or sort of this very basic assumption
that the page tables that the hardware supplies, just get you isolation
and that's the end of the story
and this attack does not support that view at all,
further it was an example of, one of a number of recent examples of what's called a micro architectural attack,
an attack that involves exploitation of hidden implementation details inside the CPU,
that are often not even known how this how CPU's work,
but people guess and they're able to make successful attacks based on correct guesses about hidden details of CPU implementation.
Meltdown turns out to be fixable and seems to be pretty completely fixed,
but nevertheless people it sort of set people up to fear,
that there might be an open-ended supply of similar micro architectural attacks.
So it's a pretty important recent event worth understanding.
Let me start by just laying out the basic core of the attack,
and we'll talk about what's going on here,
but this is somewhat simplified version of the code in the paper for how the attack works,
the basic idea is that you're an attacker
and for one reason or another you're able to run software on some computer
that has some secrets that you'd like to steal,
you're not allowed to directly get up the secrets,
but they're in memory, maybe kernel memory or another processes memory,
but you've been able to run a process,
maybe because you logged into a time sharing machine like Athena machine,
or maybe because you bought time on some hosting service.
So what the attack allows you to do is run a program in which you declare a buffer in your own memory,
so this buf is a just ordinary user memory, that's accessible,
you have the virtual address in the kernel of something that you're interested in stealing.
And you issue, what I'm writing out here is sort of you know mix of C and assembler,
but what I mean in line 3 is that,
you have the address of the kernel virtual address of the data you want to steal
and register one and r1 and line 3 were,
or just imagine that this is instructions to dereference register one and load its results into register two,
that's the instruction that we're going to run
and then there's an instruction that, just gets the low bit of register two,
so this attack, this particular version of this attack reads just a single bit,
just one low bit of a one memory location from the kernel,
multiply that four thousand 4096
and since it's either zero or one, that means that r2 will end up being zero or 4096
and then we simply read the contents of our buffer, which is a buffer user memory,
we simply read either buffer zero or buffer 4096,
and that's the basic attack.
So, one question is, why doesn't this just directly work,
line three reading this kernel address,
can we just read addresses from the kernel.
No, no, we all have faith that the answer can't possibly be yes,
we can't possibly be able to just directly read from the kernel for in user space
and the machinery that we know the CPU somehow is invoking to make this not work out
is that when we use kernel virtual address, that implies a lookup in the page table,
and there's permission bits in the page table
and we're just assuming that the operating system has not set the flag in the page table entries for kernel virtual addresses,
has not set that flag that allows users to use those addresses,
that's the PTE_U flag on the RISC-V
and that therefore this instruction must fail, must cause a page fault.
And indeed, if we ran this code, this instruction would cause a page fault,
and if we tried to if we added a code after this,
to say print the value in register three, we get a page fault on line three,
and we never get to the print statement
and we find we couldn't directly steal data out of the kernel.
Nevertheless, the sequence turned out to be useful as the paper shows.
One thing that, one thing that the paper assumes which is no longer really true for the most part is that
the kernel is mapped into every user processes address space,
that is a user user codes running a full set of kernel PTE is present in the page table,
but they have the PTE_U bit clear,
so user code will get a fault, if it tries to use a kernel virtual address,
so all those mappings in, at the time this paper was written, all those mappings were there, when executing in user space,
they just couldn't be used by user code
or they cause a fault, they were used by user code,
and the reason why people by operating system designers mapped both kernel and user addresses when running user code is
that made system calls quite a bit faster,
because that meant that on a system call happened, you don't have to switch page tables
and switching page tables just usually takes time itself and also typically causes CPU caches to be flushed,
which makes subsequent codes slower.
So people got a boost by mapping both user and kernel mappings always in user space.
But this attack actually, and this attack relies on that habit.
Okay, I'm going to explain what's going on here, that makes this code useful,
but before I do that, any any questions about, any questions about this, this code fragment.
I was actually wondering if you could repeat what you just said about kernel to user mapping, and don't really register.
Okay, let's see,
you know how in xv6,
when you're executing when the process is executing in user space,
if you look at the page table, that page table has mapping for the user addresses,
and for like the trampoline page and the trapframe page and nothing else,
so that's how xv6 works.
The page table that this paper assumes we're different from that,
this, in the time this paper was written,
most operating systems would have a set complete set of kernel mappings in the page table
while user code was running,
and so all those page table entries would be there,
all the kernel page table entries would be there when user code is running,
but since the PTE_U bit was clear on each of those page table entries,
user code wouldn't actually be able to use a kernel virtual address,
but the mappings were there
and the reason for that is that when you do a system call,
you didn't have to switch page tables,
because you do a system call into the kernel
and boom you're using the same page table,
but now you can use all those kernel PTEs, because you're in supervisor mode
and that saved a bunch of time getting into and out of the kernel during system calls.
Everybody, everybody used that technique
and that was almost certainly what Intel had in mind,
for how you should write an operating system.
Okay, so that for the whole paper that structure is assumed for the attack,
of course getting rid of it is what's the most immediate solution to this problem,
at the time, the paper was written all those kernel mappings were present in user space.
Other questions?
So you need to know the address and you want to get.
Yeah, that's right, it is and.
So you know that's a good point,
you need to know the kernel virtual address and that's actually maybe no joke.
Yeah, you might think that would make the attack harder.
But first of all point of philosophy in security,
you just have to assume that the attacker has infinite time and patience.
And if there after some valuable secrets,
they are probably willing to spend a couple of months trying to steal that secret,
or longer right,
because you know it's gonna be somebody's password,
that protects all kinds of valuable stuff, maybe money or secret email.
So that means for example the attacker probably has time to try every single kernel address, right,
looking for whatever precious data there after,
maybe a password,
or the attacker may have time to study to look through the kernel code
and look through typical compiled kernels and find addresses
and maybe put print statements in their kernels to examine the structure of data in kernel memory,
until they understand how the kernel works, well enough to be able to get an address here.
Now, actually, because this game has been going on, other versions of this game,
the security game had been going out for a long time,
kernels actually defend themselves against attacks that involve guessing kernel addresses
and one of the things that was actually mentioned this paper is
this called thing called kernel address space layout randomization,
so modern kernels actually load the kernel at a random address,
in order to make it harder to guess kernel virtual addresses
and they did this before this, long before this paper came out,
because it was helpful in defeating other attacks.
So, so this is the game,
but we have to assume that the attacker, in the end, the attacker will probably win this game.
Okay, so let's just assume the attacker either knows a juicy kernel virtual address
to look at or can guess one or is willing to exhaustively try every address.
And the paper suggests that that's a plausible strategy, once you have meltdown.
Okay.
Okay, so what's gonna happen,
well, so we're wondering how can this code be, possibly be useful to an attacker
and the answer has to do,
like if the way CPU's work was just what you read in the CPU manual,
this attack clearly is nonsense, like it'll fault at instruction three
and that'll be the end of it,
but it turns out CPU's work in far more complex ways than is in the manual,
and the way the reason the attack works is because of some CPU implementation details.
And there's actually two main things that the attack relies on,
one is implementation trick of CPU's called speculative execution, which I'll talk about first
and the other implementation trick, the attack relies on is the way CPU's do caching.
Okay.
So first speculative execution,
let me, I have a code example for that also,
and for the moment I'm not talking about security at all,
the specular execution and stuff is just a technique to improve the performance of a CPU's,
some optimization trick that CPU's use,
so imagine that we're just, we have, which is running this code,
this is somewhat contrived example,
but it's sort of illustrates what speculative execution is all about,
supposing I have address in some say register zero
and just because the logic my program, the address is either valid or not valid,
maybe it contains zero if under some circumstances, like we haven't initialize my data yet.
So this will assume there's a valid variable that's sitting in memory somewhere,
so before using the address here, so this address in register zero here on line four,
we're going to test, we're gonna load valid from memory
and we're only going to use the address if valid is set to one,
then a valid is set to zero which is not going to see address at all,
and if valid is set to one, then we're going to de reference the address,
you know load the data points to at register two
and add one to it and it doesn't really matter,
we're going to do something with that data we loaded,
in this case, add one to it and set register three equal to the data plus one.
Alright, well, in a simple CPU implementation,
at line two here, you can load,
now it's a variable sitting in memory in RAM
and you have to issue some kind of this is going to be,
line two is going to be some sort of load instruction that reads valid out of RAM,
all else being equal if we actually have to load it from RAM,
that'll take hundreds of cycles on our say two Giga Hertz machine,
like any load that actually has to go to RAM will take hundreds of cycles,
the machine can execute an instruction, up to an instruction every cycle,
so if we actually had to wait a couple of hundred cycles here,
we'd be the machine to be sitting there idling for hundreds hundreds of cycles, are wasting its time.
And because that's a significant significant slowdown right,
if everything went well, we'd be able to execute an instruction every cycle, instead of every couple hundred cycles,
all modern, all serious modern CPUs do use something called branch prediction,
so this if statement is a branch,
if we actually turned it into machine instructions,
we see there was a branch here
and it's a conditional branch, branch based on this test whether register one is equal to one
and what CPU's do is they use,
it's called branch branch prediction,
that is for every branch more or less the CPU essentially remembers a cache of information about each of the branches in your program,
or at least each recently executed branch,
then remembers oh did that branch was the branch taken or not taken,
and if the CPU doesn't have enough information to predict,
so that's prediction based on the last time you executed the branch,
even if the CPU doesn't have a prediction, it may still just go ahead and execute the instructions,
either that the branch takes you to or the fall through instructions,
assuming the branch wasn't taken, that is.
Even before the CPU knows whether this conditional is true,
it'll choose one way or the other and start executing down that path,
even though it might be the wrong path, doesn't know yet.
And so in this case,
maybe before this load completes,
and before or the value of valid is known,
the CPU may start executing instruction four
and do the load with whatever value is sitting in r0
which may or may not be a valid pointer
and once that load yields something, maybe even add one to it and set register three equal to that value.
And then maybe a long time later,
when this load at line two finally completes,
now we know what the value of valid is,
the CPU will then this real,
you know you know it kept track of the fact that it executed lines four and five without really knowing whether that was proper,
if valid is one then that's fine, it just keeps going,
if valid is zero, then the CPU has enough cleverness to cancel the effects of its execution of line four and five
and restart execution in the proper place after the branch at line seven.
And this execution of code before you know whether you really should be executing it is called speculation,
and again, the point is performance,
if the CPU guess is right, then it got a big head start executing these instructions
and didn't have to wait for the expensive memory load.
Any questions about what this means?
Okay, this machinery, the hardware, the transistors in the CPU for speculation are extremely complex,
there's a huge amount going on in the CPU to make this work,
none of which is published,
right, it's a whole Intel internal stuff, not in, not in the machine manual.
So surrounding meltdown and attacks like it is a huge amount of speculation
about what's probably going on inside the CPU
in order to make such attack work or not work.
Okay, back to speculation though.
One thing that's going on is that,
in order to undo speculative failed specular mis mis predicted speculative execution,
the machine had keeps shadow versions of registers essentially,
you know it assigned to registers two, register three,
but it's a sign it's kind of a temporary registers,
if speculation succeeds then those registers those shadow registers become the real registers,
if it fails then those shadow registers discarded the CPU discards the shadow registers.
So these two assignments r2 and r3 would just be as if they never happened.
So in this code, we need to think about what happens if register zero is a valid pointer
and what happens if it's not a valid pointer, right.
If we're speculatively executing line four, and register two is a valid pointer,
then it turns out the CPU will actually do the load,
and loaded into at least the transient version of register two,
so we'll actually go out and and try to fetch what r0 points to
and that will certainly work if the data r0 is pointed to, is sitting in the cache
and I don't know if if the CPU will do the load,
if it misses in the cache and has to load from RAM, it might.
But, maybe the more interesting question for us,
for this attack is what happens if register zero is not a valid pointer.
In that case, if we're speculatively executing here,
the machine can't fault at this point,
because we're speculatively executing machine doesn't know,
it may know that r0 was an invalid,
that this speculatively executed instruction tried to use an invalid pointer, an invalid address,
but it can't page fault,
because it's not sure whether this execution is valve is correct speculative execution or mis mis speculation
and so it's only,
so, so it can't actually raise a fault on line four until after valid value of valid is known,
and after this branch, this speculative predicted branch,
after we know after the machine knows what the condition is,
if the machine see if the machine's that line four sees oh register zero is an invalid address,
and then valid turns out to be one,
then, and only then does the machine actually generate the page fault,
if r0 is an invalid address, then valid turns out to be zero,
the machine does not generate a page fault.
So the, the decision about whether to fault is deferred possibly for hundreds of cycles until the value of valid is known,
then the technical term for the point at which we know
whether an instruction was correctly speculatively executed rather than being thrown away is called Retirement.
So we say an instruction is speculative and at some point it's retired
and that's when we know it's either going to be thrown away or what's real
and should be its effect should be committed to the visible state of the machine
and the rule is that,
instruction can only be retired, if first of all is finished executing loading memory, you're adding one to something,
and every instruction before it, was executed before it has also retired,
so this line four can't be retired until the load of valid completes and the conditions is evaluated,
only then can be retired,
so it's going to fault, it may it's gonna fault, possibly hundreds of instructions after it is the memory load,
or tempted to do the memory load.
And as a critical detail for this attack,
there's an even more.
If lets its, if the address in r0 is invalid and has no mapping in the page table at all,
then actually don't know what happens.
If the address in r0 has a page table mapping,
but there's no permission for it, that is the PTE_U flag is not set,
then what Intel machines actually do is,
load that data and assign it into the transient register two,
and where it can be used by the speculative execution of line five,
so even if r0 was was an address for which we don't have permission,
because it's a kernel address,
we'll still see it's value loaded into r3 and its value plus one,
sorry, we won't see it, but it will be loaded into r2
and that plus one at r3
and then when this load is retired,
the machine will realize aha, that was an invalid load,
because the page table entry didn't allow it
and so we're going to raise a fault
and cancel the execution of the subsequent instructions
and cancel the effects of this instruction, undo the modification to r2 and r3.
So in this example, there's two speculations going on,
one is we're speculating about where this branch, machines speculating about where this branch went
and just saying oh it went one way or the other,
just gonna give that a shot speculatively,
in addition there's speculative execution after each load
were essentially speculating about whether the machine is speculating,
about whether that load complete successfully.
And in the case of a load, Intel machines always just go on, you know if data could be provided,
because it's in the cache
and at least the page table entry exists, permissions are not,
the machine will speculatively continue to execute
and only on retirement, the load will actually generate the fault,
and that will cause the speculation to be cancelled.
Alright, any questions about this stuff?
I'm a little confused about, the second speculation
which is loading r0 into r2,
so, does that mean that like the value of r0 is loaded into r2 and the flags are checked later.
Yes, yes, so what happens, yes, that's exactly right,
so what actually happens is that during the speculative phase,
whatever it is that r0 points to,
if there's sort of if it points to anything,
if r0 points to anything,
then the data that memory location will be loaded into r2,
later, when this load is retired,
and it turned, then the permissions will be checked,
and if we didn't have permission to do that load,
then all subsequent instructions effects will be cancelled,
like all these modifications registered will be undone,
and fault will be raised,
with the state of the machines and registers as they were just before instruction four.
Okay, that's interesting.
Yes.
Yes, I also have a question,
is there no possible way to restrict the CPU from checking permissions before doing a speculative load.
Um, you mean, is there a way to cause the machine to do the check before the load.
Yes, I guess more concrete,
like the only reason this is a problem or,
but one of the ways is that we're just loading a page that,
if we can be aware that it has permissions that are going to be bad somehow,
we're accessing a page that we don't we shouldn't be able to access,
the can the speculative execution be cancelled,
given that we can read these permissions.
Yes, in a, yes that's,
yeah, well, there's two answers,
one is that's not the way the Intel chips CPUs actually worked,
and the other answer is yes, it would have been,
I I believe it would have been easy for them to have done and enforce that check even for speculative loads,
so that even in speculation register two would never have been written.
So maybe.
And indeed, it turns out that
you may know, I've noticed the paper mentioned that the meltdown seems not to work on AMD CPUs,
even though AMD CPUs, the instruction manual is the same as for Intel CPU's,
essentially on the same instruction set and the instructions mean the same things,
the attack doesn't work on AMD CPUs
and it's widely believed that the reason is that AMD CPUs,
you even went speculatively executing, if you don't have permission to read this address,
won't even speculatively loads, the value in r2,
and that's why the attack didn't work on AMD CPUs
and recent Intel CPUs apparently have adopted that approach
and actually won't won't speculatively load, if they don't have permissions.
And as far as I know, there's no particular sacrifice at performance,
I think the information was all there,
but for just I don't know, just say maybe a few [gates], they decided only to apply it on retirement.
Because they seem to.
That's very interesting.
Yeah, I mean let me just warn you this there's a lot of guesswork here
and I believe what I'm saying is true,
but in Intel and AMD have not been very revealing about what's going on.
Okay, thers's some terminology here that's important,
the what you read in the manual for the CPU,
that says oh you know an add structure takes two registers and adds them and puts them in a third,
that stuff, that aspect of the design is called architectural, a sort of advertise, behavior,
the advertised behavior of the machine,
and so the advertised behavior of machine is that
if your load from an address you turn permissions for you get a page fault period, you're not allowed to load,
that's in distinction to what the machines actually doing which is called Micro-Architectural.
That is actually the machine has specular executions doing all these crazy things without telling you
and the intent of the CPU designers when they design all these complex micro-architectural optimizations is that they be transparent,
that yeah yeah it's doing all this stuff internally,
but it looks the results you get from programs are the same results you get from a simpler machine
that just did the straightforward thing that was in the manual.
They are intended to be transparent
and so you know, for example, at some level, what Intel is doing here is transparent,
yeah, maybe they don't check for permissions when you when you do the memory load,
but if there was a problem on retirement,
it's gonna undo all these effects
and so you'll never see that memory you weren't supposed to see,
so gosh that looks just like what the manual said,
you're not allowed to load stuff you don't have permission for.
So this distinction is, a lot of what this attack is playing,
on that it knows all the attack knows a lot about what's going on inside.
Okay, other questions about speculative execution?
Okay, I'm gonna put that aside for a moment
and talk about another piece of micro-architecture,
that's a caches.
And these again, everybody knows caches are there,
but you know they're supposed to be more or less more or less transparent.
And let me draw a picture of the caches,
I think are relevant to the cache structure,
I think is most relevant to meltdown.
So first of all, you have the, we have the core which is the,
you know part of the machine that parses instructions and has registers
and has an addition unit and division unit
and you know whatever the execution part of the machine,
and then, whenever it needs to do a load or store,
it talks to the memory system
and the memory system has a bunch of caches,
so in particular in the machines, we're talking about, there's a data cache called level one data cache,
that is maybe you know 64 kilobytes in size or something not very big,
but it's extremely fast,
if you, if the data you need is in the L1 cache,
that you get back to you in a couple of cycles
and the structure of the L1 cache, it has a bunch of lines are called lines,
each of which holds probably 64 bytes of data,
the lines are indexed, it's a table really the cache,
the lines are indexed by virtual address,
if the virtual addresses in the cache,
then, the cache holds the data with that virtual address
and in addition as it turns out,
it's believed, the L1 cache entry contains a copy of the permissions taken from the page table entry that corresponds to this virtual address.
So, there's a whole, this is it a table,
when the core is used load instruction,
the first thing that happens is that the hardware looks in the L1 cache
and see if there's a cache entry whose virtual address matches the requested,
the address we're trying to load from it,
and if so that we can just the machine just returns this data from the cache were done very quickly,
if they did is not in L1 cache,
then the next step is that we, the rest of the memory system is is in is addressed with physical addresses,
so we at this point, we're going to need a physical address,
if we missed the L1 cache,
this translation look-aside buffer is a cache of page table entries,
it's going to look up the virtual address that the program issued in the translation look aside buffer,
it may not be there in which case now we got a lot of work to do,
because we've got to load the relevant page table entry for memory.
But let's assume we hittin the translation look-aside buffer,
we can now get the needed physical address,
typically there's another cache, another much bigger cache,
that's physically indexed index with the physical address.
And so we might now that we have a physical address, we can look at this cache
and if we miss there, then we have to send the physical address after the RAM system,
takes a long time,
but when we finally get data back then we can populate the L2 cache
and populate the L1 cache with the stuff we got back from RAM
and return the the data back to the core.
So this is caching.
Just, by the, by the hidden L1 cache practice a few cycles,
hidden the L2 cache probably takes a dozen or two cycles
and miss that requires you to go around probably takes you a couple hundred cycles,
these cycles are, you know, let's say half a second on a two Giga Hertz machine.
So it's extremely advantageous to have caching you would,
if you didn't have cache and you would be sacrificing a factor of a couple of hundred in performance,
these are just absolutely critical to decent performance, these caches.
Now, this caches is the L1 cache,
well, both turns out both both these caches can contain,
if we're running in user space, both these caches in the operating system's meltdown was aimed at,
both of these caches can contain both user data and kernel data,
the L2 cache can contain kernel data,
because it's physically addressed, there's no problem.
The L1 cache is a little bit trickier,
it's virtually addressed when we change page tables,
the contents of the L1 cache are no longer valid,
because we change page tables, that means that the meaning of virtual addresses changed,
so you'd have to flush the L1 cache, which change page tables,
although there's more complex tricks that allow you to avoid that,
and so but the fact that these operating systems in the days of this paper,
didn't change page tables, when changing between user space and kernel space, because both were mapped,
meant that, data we didn't have to flush the L1 cache
and that meant the L1 cache would have both user and kernel data in it
and that it made system calls even faster,
if you call a system call, the system call returns there's still gonna be likely still to be useful user data in the caches,
because we never changed, we never changed page tables are changed the meanings of these addresses.
Anyway, so there's likely to be kernel data,
even if you're running a user space is likely to be kernel data in the old one cache
and it's these permissions which are copied out of the TLB,
copied out of page table entries,
that tells the machine that oh even though the data is in the cache,
you're not allowed to see it,
and raise raise a page fault.
So this is a good time to mention that,
even though the intent of micro-architectural optimizations is they be completely transparent,
that can't possibly be true,
because the whole point of these micro-architectural optimizations is almost always to improve performance
and so they will be guaranteed to be at least visible in terms of performance
as you could tell if your machine has a cache or not,
because if it doesn't have a cache, it'll run a couple hundred times slower, right,
in addition you can tell whether the data you're trying to fetch,
if you're capable of measuring time accurately enough
and you do a load, you can tell,
if the load returned in a couple cycles, the data must have been cached,
if the load returned after a hundred times that, they probably had to be loaded from RAM
and so the differences are profound,
and if you can measure time to you know a few nanoseconds or even tens of nanoseconds,
you can tell the difference,
so in the performance level, is micro-architecture is absolutely not transparent.
And all the things we talk about branch prediction caches or whatever,
all that stuff is at least indirectly visible to timing.
And so, of course many people even though the micro-architectural design is sort of in any detailed level secret,
to Intel, it's their private business how they implement this,
in fact it's all along been of extremely intense interest to a lot of people,
because it affects performance a lot.
So a compiler writers for example know a lot about micro-architecture,
because, the most many many compiler optimizations are implicitly exploiting people's good guesses about what the machines actually doing inside.
And indeed the CPU manufacturers publish optimization guides,
that reveal some of the micro-architectural tricks,
but they rarely go into much detail,
{} certainly not enough detail to really understand exactly why meltdown works.
So the micro-architecture stuff is sort of sits somewhere between supposed to be transparent and visible and hidden and sort of partially,
you know certainly a lot of people are interested and a lot of people know all kinds of random things about it.
Okay, so the reason why this cache stuff is interesting for meltdown,
first of all, any questions about about caching.
Okay, let me talk then, about sort of main way that the paper uses caching,
the paper talks about this technique called flush, flush and reload.
And, what flush and reload is up to,
is that it's answering the question did a particular piece of code use the memory at a particular address.
And it's not directly a security exploit,
because it only works for memory that you can get at.
So if your user code and you have some memory, that's your memory
and you're allowed to use it,
you can and you call one of your own functions
or then you'll be able to tell, you can use flush and reload to tell,
whether the function your function, you just executed used your memory,
you can't directly use this attack or it's not an attack,
you can use this technique to figure out, if some other process use that process is private memory.
Although, because processes sometimes share memory, yeah,
you may still be able to do,
well the right way to put it is you can only find out about memory you're allowed to access.
Okay, so answering the question, did did a particular function use this memory.
So, step one, is we're gonna flush, supposing we were interested in address x,
we want to flush the cache,
we want to make sure the cache doesn't contain the memory location x
and it turns out that for our convenience,
Intel supplies an instruction, called clFlash,
and you give it an address
and it will get rid of, it will ensure that that location is not cached any of the caches
and so that's super convenient,
even if the machine didn't provide this instruction,
that it turns out there's ways of getting rid of stuff from the cache,
like for example if you know the cache holds 64 kilobytes,
then it's likely to be the case that if you load 64 kilobytes of random memory,
you know just load instructions that,
those will be loaded into the cache,
and after you've loaded 64 kilobytes of new data into the cache,
everything that used to be in it must be gone,
because the cache can only hold 64 kilobytes or whatever it may be.
So, even without this [] instruction,
you can still flush everything in the cache.
Then step two is you're interested in whether some particular piece of code uses data x,
you just call that code whatever it is.
and it does what it does maybe uses x, maybe doesn't,
now you wanna tell effects is actually in the cache,
because if it is since you flushed from the cache,
if it's in the cache now,
it must be that f causes to be loaded, unless something else is going on,
so you need to, you want to do a load,
but you wanna know how long the load takes,
so we're only talking about nanoseconds like five nanoseconds versus hundred nanoseconds here,
how can we measure time that accurately that's a tough assignment,
however again the CPUs come to [ra],
in fact provide instruction which gives you cycle granularity time,
and it's called rdtsc,
So we're just gonna execute the rdtsc instruction,
which tells us essentially the number of cycles that have elapsed, since the machine cycles have elapsed since the machine started.
And since it's probably two Giga Hertz machine,
that means that the precision we have here is half a nanosecond,
its pretty small.
Now we're gonna load,
we're just gonna say junk equals star x,
we're going to load the data of location x,
I get the time again,
and look at the difference right, b minus a,
if b minus a is you know five or six or seven or something,
that means that this load hit in the cache,
and that means that this function used the data,
if b minus a is 150, then that means that x wasn't in the cache
and yeah you know that may probably means that f that may mean that did never used x,
that's not quite that cut and dry,
because f might have used x and then use something else,
that conflicted with x in the cache
and caused x to be kicked out of the cache again.
But, for simple situations, a very large value of b minus a, means f didn't use it,
in a small value of b minus a, means that f did use that data.
So this is not an attack yet,
because again, we have to be able to access this memory,
so this is our memory.
Any questions about flush plus reload?
Alright, I think that's all the preliminaries, let's go back to meltdown.
So this is a more full version I showed you sort of core meltdown at the beginning,
this is a more complete meltdown.
And so we actually now have I added the flush reload part.
Again we're going to declare this buffer.
And the idea is that depending on we're gonna be just fetching one bit from the kernel,
we're going to multiply that one bit by 4096,
so we're hoping to use flush plus reload to see that
either buf of zero is in the cache or buffer of 4096 is in the cache
and the reason for the large separation there is that apparently the pref-, this hardware has a prefetcher in it,
so if you load one thing from memory, it will load the next couple things up from memory too, the next couple of cache lines
and so we can't have the two different cache lines,
that we're going to apply flush and reload to be to be particularly close,
need to be far enough apart that even prefetch, hardware prefetching won't cause confusion.
So we put the whole page apart, the flash part now,
we just call this clflush instruction to make sure that the relevant parts of our buffer are not catched.
Now, we're exploiting, this line seven is not maybe may or may not be necessary,
but what what's going on here is we're exploiting this sort of,
I'm going to be exploiting the gap in time between,
you know, we we're doing this load line ten to load a kernel address, so it's gonna fault,
but we're hoping to be able to execute another couple of instructions speculatively before this instruction is retired
and before it actually raises the fault and cancels these instructions right,
if the fault if this load would be retired,
say at this point, that would be too early for us,
because it's going to turn out we actually need line thirteen to be speculatively executed in order to complete the attack,
so we want to make sure that this load isn't retired for as long as possible,
in order to delay the fault and delay the speculative cancellation.
Now we know instructions aren't retired until all previous instructions have retired,
it's one of the rules.
So at line seven, I'm imagining that we're going to launch some expensive instruction that doesn't compete for a long time,
maybe it loads something else that's known to have to come from RAM,
so it'll take a few hundred cycles,
or maybe it does a divider a square root or something,
who knows what something that takes a long time,
it won't be retired for a long time,
and therefore will cause this load not to be retired for a long time,
giving these instructions time to execute speculatively.
Right, now we're assuming again we have a virtual address in the kernel,
gonna execute line ten,
line ten won't raise a fault, until that,
we know it's going to raise a fault, won't raise a fault until retires,
but we're intending, we believe we've set things up, so won't retire for a while, since it hasn't retired
and because on Intel CPUs the data is returned even if you weren't allowed to see it,
the data return for speculative execution, even if you did not permission,
that means that we can speculatively execute, the machine will speculatively execute line eleven and get the low bit of kernel data now,
multiplied by 4096,
line thirteen is itself a load, it's another load,
using an address basically the address of buffer plus the contents of r2,
we know it's going to get cancelled,
because we know this will fault right,
we know the actual write to r3 will be cancelled,
but line thirteen will cause some data from buffer to be loaded into the cache,
even if it doesn't end up affecting register three,
so r3 line thirteen is going to cause something to be loaded into the cache,
and this case depending on whether the low bit is zero, one,
line thirteen will cause the actual cache to contain either buffer zero or buffer 4096,
then, right, then that even though r2 and r3 are cancelled,
the change in the cache, because it's supposed to be hidden micro-architectural state,
that will actually be the cache will be changed.
Finally, at some point the fault will happen,
and we need to sort of recover after the fault,
but it's just a page fault,
and it turns out you can or user process can register a page fault handler and get control back after a page fault
and the paper mentions a couple of other ways of being able to continue after the fault.
And now all we have to do is figure out whether it was buffet zero or buffet 4096, that was loaded into the cache,
and now we can do the reload part of flush and reload,
we read the accurate time,
load buffet zero, read the time again,
load buff one, read the time again
and compare the two differences in time
and whichever one of these took a shorter amount of time,
is likely to indicate whether the low bit of the kernel data was zero or one.
And then we report that repeat that a couple of billion times,
we can scan all of kernel memory.
But in this example, if b minus a smaller than c minus b,
doesn't that mean that buf of zero was cached.
Let's see if I got this wrong,
you might say yeah means the buf zero was cache,
oh yeah yeah yeah you're right.
Now we're [cooking], good catch.
Oh, sorry do you need for, before we had an if before like nine nine,
do we need, if now or is it is still gonna.
The efforts to help me illustrate the legitimate reasons for speculative execution,
keep computing even though we don't know whether the branch took or not,
but here the real core of the speculation is that we don't know if this load will fault, right,
and so were the machines speculatively executing past the load,
on the theory that it's probably most don't fault, right,
even though they may take a long time,
like a load could take hundreds of cycles
and so we'd love to be able to, so the machine will speculatively execute pass the load,
even though it doesn't, not knowing whether it's going to fault or not,
and if the load did fault,
it will then undo all this speculative execution,
there's a speculative execution comes up, any time you have a long running instruction that may or may not succeed,
so like divide, so we know whether it's going to be divided by zero or not,
you know so instructions after divider also speculated.
Anyway, the speculation, the real critical speculation starts here,
now, in fact we tried, in order to make the attack likely more successful,
we sort of ensure that speculation starts here,
but this is the real speculation we care about.
Other questions?
For, this example we've only read one bit,
is is there some likes really small, simple modification that we could make to read like a full register size of bits.
Yeah, run this 64 times, one for each bit.
Why is it not possible to just read 64 bits at a time.
A sixty, sixty, well you need the buffer, the size of this buffer has to be a to the,
you know two to the number of bits, you're reading times 4096 or something,
so 64 bits is two big, we don't have enough memory to a make a buffer that big,
we need this, the way this is set up.
But anyway, yep, 64 bits too much,
you could certainly read a bit of time
and have this buffer size be 256 times 4096.
The paper actually argues in a,
the paper observes that, since the most of the time is here in the plus reload,
if you read a byte at a time, then figuring out what the bits of that byte are takes flush and reloads,
one for each possible value.
If you load a bit at a time, then each bit takes just one flush plus reload,
are sort of two two probes are two flush plus reloads,
so if you need a bit of time,
then you end up only doing sixteen flush plus reloads,
if you read a byte at a time, you end up doing 256 flush plus reloads,
the paper says that it's faster to do it a bit at a time than a byte at a time.
Which seems a little counterintuitive, seems to be true.
Other questions?
So where would this user program, will this program have to be run from,
is there any particular location on the machine, that doesn't have to be,
where would you write it I guess.
Where would this program be run from, can be a user program.
Well yeah, that depends on what kind of access, you have to the machine
and where the data is that you want to steal
and then you know, who knows right.
But one example is supposing, you're logged into Athena dial up machine,
it was a couple hundred other users
and you want to steal somebody's password, and you're patient,
you can use and let's assume that Athena is now a couple years ago
and Athena was running a version of Linux that mapped the kernel into every user's every processes address space,
then you can use meltdown to get out bit by bit,
everything in the kernel including [] IO buffers and the network buffers and stuff
and if somebody's typing their password,
if you're lucky or patient, and somebody's typing your password
and you load all of kernel memory,
you're going to see that password in kernel memory, right.
And because in fact the kernel probably maps like xv6 maps all of physical memory,
that means you can probably read all physical memory that is all of all other processes memory,
using this technique on a time sharing machine.
So I can see what's everybody's in text editor contents or whatever I like.
Now you have to, that's a way you could use it, if you're using a time machine,
for other situations, yeah it would be different.
Make sense.
In time sharing is not that pervasive anymore,
but the sort of killer scenario would be some kind of cloud computing thing
where you're using a cloud provider like Amazon
and you know which runs many customers on the same machine.
And depending on the details of how they set up their virtual machine monitor
or container system or whatever it may be.
If you buy time from Amazon,
then you may be able to peer into the memory of other customer's software running on the same Amazon machine maybe.
So I think that's really, yeah, that's how people actually use this probably.
Actually another time that might be useful is your browser,
when you're browsing the web browser actually runs a lot of code in it that is not trusted,
that is supplied by the random websites you visit,
maybe in the form of plugins,
may be in the form of Javascript, that's loaded in your browser
and compiled by the browser and execute it
and it is possible that this attack could be carried out by code that you run in your browser when you browse the web.
That you may not, even though it's running their load from websites and they would steal whatever stuff is sitting in your laptop.
I don't know if the details of that quite work out.
Has anyone demonstrated an attack through either Javascript or like WebAssembly.
I don't know, I don't I I feel certainly people worried about WebAssembly.
I don't know whether the attack was literally possible,
for Javascript I know that, maybe the sticking point was the accurate time, I mean.
You couldn't quite get this nanosecond timing,
so you couldnt quite execute supposed to be load now,
where somebody with a bit more cleverness could figure out a way to do it,
I don't know we have assembly is much closer to running machine code
and you know I I don't know exactly how the details worked out,
but oh boy was, so many people rapidly thought about.
Okay, it turns out the attack doesn't always work,
like and for reasons that I don't think the authors never explained or only speculated about
and you can see I don't know if you can see this,
well maybe you can't see this,
but if you turn the last page of their paper,
you'll see the output it's actually,
you know, they mounted the attack on their own machines and extracted a bunch of data from their own, the kernel on their own machine.
And, if you look closer you'll see there's a huge all these lines are just xx xxx xxx, all these lines x x with dots,
these are places where they didn't manage to extract anything, where meltdown failed,
even though they repeated it many times.
And you can tell they must have been, you know they were the papers version of this attack was re-trying many many times,
because for example section 6.2 talks about performance,
says that in some cases the rate at which they could extract data was only ten bytes per second,
which means they were sitting there trying again and again and again,
and after thousands of times they finally managed to get some data that is that, flush plus reload indicated
that the two cache lines at different load times.
So there's something unexplained going on about why it's quite frequent for meltdown actually fail,
get some data actually got real data here,
there's also a bunch of data that they didn't get,
and I don't know if people as far as I know, people are not really sure what all the conditions are about when it succeeds when it doesn't,
you know the most straightforward possibility is that
if the kernel data is in the L1 cache, the meltdown succeeds
and the kernel data is not in the L1 cache, doesn't succeed.
That's very easy to believe that that could be what's going on,
because if it's not in the L1 cache, then there's a whole bunch more machinery involved in a speculative load
and it's easy to imagine that the CPU for a speculative load,
that's maybe not known if it's even needed,
would not bother doing all the work required to load stuff from RAM.
But, it's not quite that simple,
you can tell it's not quite that simple,
because the paper says that sometimes when they tried, we tried many times and it finally worked,
so there's some more complex condition,
maybe a race effectively race inside the CPU under which it occasionally works,
even for data that's not not in the cache.
The end of the paper is actually also,
if you didn't get that for worth reading,
because it does explain a sort of more real world,
like we wanted to find out this particular thing,
you know this, we know there's passwords stored in our Firefox's password manager,
we wanted to get them out and steal them using meltdown,
you know what are all the, how do you find out what the addresses,
for example, they sort of lay out a complete attack,
I mean, a complete attack done by academics not real attackers, but nevertheless
and filling many of the pragmatic details.
The only thing I want to talk about is his fixes,
you've already touched on a little bit.
When this paper came out, it got a lot of attention
and there was actually another second paper by overlapping set of people about a different attack,
that also used different, different kind of speculation inside CPUs, called spectre.
So the pair of papers came out at the same time
and was very exciting.
And so people hustled, people realize that boy, this is extremely damaging,
because now we're talking about is that you know isolation has been broken, right.
You're gonna hardly, so basically hardly even think about it anymore,
but you know this thing, this is a technique for breaking page table protections,
which is you know how we enforce isolation between user and kernel,
it's like deeply fundamental attack,
or anyway undermines an extremely important piece of security,
in a very general way right,
seems like you could read anything.
And so people really really hustled, to a deploy fixes for this,
in the immediate fix that a lot of operating systems installed within weeks of this paper coming out
and sometimes had already installed this thing called KASLR,
which is now called kpti in Linux
and it's a pretty straightforward idea,
the idea is just like not to put the kernel mappings in the user page table,
and instead a as in xv6, switch page tables during system calls to user space,
just user mappings make a system call, there's some kind of trampoline arrangement like in xv6
and you switch page tables to a page table that has the kernel mappings in order to execute the kernel.
And that causes attack cannot work,
because the, in that because you switch page tables,
this virtual address in r1, it's not only no longer valid, it's no longer meaningful,
because there's no translation for it,
so the CPU doesn't know what to do with it,
like this virtual address won't be cached,
it's not even in the TLB,
so there's just no way for the kernel to decide what memory corresponds to this virtual address.
You know when this attack is executed in user space,
because this virtual this kernel virtual dress no longer means anything,
it's not it's not illegal, it's just meaningless
and so that would cause the attack not to work.
The downside of this KASLR fixes, that now system calls are more expensive, because switching page tables.
If you don't do anything switching page tables, causes the TLB flushed,
because now all those virtual addresses and TLB are the wrong virtual addresses,
that don't correspond to this page table anymore
and it causes the L1 cache to be flushed, because it's virtually address
and so on on some machines, the switching page tables made system calls considerably slower.
In an recent machines actually have this trick called PCID which you can look up,
but basically makes it so you can avoid flushing these caches on a page table switch,
although it still takes some time.
And if you [poke] around the web looking for people,
there was a lot of worry at the time, that this split, that this two page table idea would be unacceptably slow,
now in fact, that didn't really turn out to be a serious problem,
and if you poke around you'll see that people's guesses about typical workloads,
you know how much it impacts overall performance of typical workloads,
which after all don't spend all their time entering and exiting kernel, is like 5%,
so it wasn't such a bad deal.
Any questions about this KASLR fix?
So people adopted this pretty rapidly,
in fact there had been kernels that had already adopted it,
because it defended against some other attacks.
There's also a reasonable hardware fix,
that I believe Intel it's actually made in recent processors and that AMD had already made
and that's basically to because the, in fact, the permission,
you know this is the structure of the cache,
when an instruction loads something from the L1 cache,
like this kernel data, we're trying to attack,
the permissions or people believe that the permissions are sitting right there in the cache entry
and so there's no trouble with the CPU checking the permissions at that point
and indeed, AMD. CPUs and perhaps modern Intel CPUs will actually do the permission check very early
and won't return this data, they won't even return it to the core,
if the permission checks don't workout.
So there's none of this speculative instructions are able to see forbidden data.
So I I don't know if you know the answer to this question is probably just speculative, but no [pun] intended,
but why, why do you think Intel would do this,
like this seems like.
Okay.
Because to me, it seems like it was a discussion,
shall we check permissions on transient instructions
and they were just like no why, why bother will need just a simple check.
Why bother, indeed stuff transparent and the users not be able to see the data either way, during the check early.
You know that's like some gates on a pretty critical path right,
the the you know the core of L1 data cache,
path is extremely performance critical,
you know if you can shave a few transistors off the, you know off the critical path here
between issuing instruction and getting the data back,
you know that may may allow you to have a slightly faster cycle time and run programs faster.
And so it's got to be the case, that I don't know got to be the case,
but it's easy to imagine that it would have cost them a few transistors to actually enforce the permissions early,
because after all they still need all of the stuff at retirement,
it's not like doing it early would save them some work later on,
they still have to defer the fault until retirement.
So all that stuff, still there,
just guessing that it didn't seem like it would have any advantages
and would have been a little bit of extra work.
And into either way completely invisible, theoretically invisible too, at the architectural level.
Did any kernel decide to like revert this KASLR fix,
now that be like Intel has fixed the CPU, do improve performance, again.
I know it's optional on a lot of kernels,
I I'm not totally sure what's going on with the Intel fix,
I'm fairly sure that they have this fix out there,
but exactly you know I I I don't really know what's going on.
I think in the Linux kernel, you can just ask which hardware fixes have been implemented
and Linux you know changes the mitigation that enables depending on what actually the hardware tells it.
So might.
Oh so, so you can, you can actually do that,
like you can read enough info about the processor as the kernel to know whether what to do.
You can run your run your laptop there's a Linux command,
that is actually yeah on like which is why it tells you
exactly what fixes have been implemented where things are mitigated in hardware,
this is a wide range of these respective applications attacks.
Are you saying that Linux will actually use the combined page table if the CPU.
Cool.
I think it was, for 99%,
I haven't checked it recently,
I believe that's still the case.
Sorry, so what were people doing like like how did they find find this,
what are they trying to do.
What are they trying to do, trying to break into computers.
Well, the, who knows what they're really trying to do,
I mean the papers are written by various academics,
maybe you know their research is finding security problems.
I think more that guys find that one thing the motive for a long time is they wanted to break address space randomization.
And they had earlier papers, you know the different schemes trying to make a great interest in [rotation],
so only one group of one stream of researchers that were in this area had that as a background.
I think project zero people came from a completely different angle.
This is people have seen Roberts said before, people have been working in this area for decades,
you know trying find bugs they can exploit I understand.
So, I guess is how this is a hard question to answer,
but like how likely is it that there's another like meltdown out there,
because it seems.
Extremely likely.
Okay, like micro, the fundamentally clean with micro-architecture like exposing changes.
That's right, I I think what's going on is that
the CPU manufacturers have for decades and decades have been,
you know often adding more and more and more optimistic,
there's many many many sort of cool little tricks inside the micro-architecture for making things go faster
and you know now and end people didn't worry that much
or it just wasn't on the radar, that this could be a serious security problem
and so now people now very aware that this stuff could be a serious security problem,
but we're now in a position where we're living with you know thirty years of clever ideas inside the CPUs.
And so, indeed a bunch of, since this paper came out, and indeed before this paper came out,
a bunch of kind of, a bunch of this style of attacks have come to light exploiting various different micro-architectural, these and CPUs, so I think this is gonna be a while before this all day to rest.
We've looked at security conferences in the last you know two years,
basically every year every conference basically session on like exploiting speculative execution properties
and see if they can make attacks work.
And maybe a larger question is whether, you know whether the situation is,
well you know there's you know fifteen or twenty or thirty things that sort of have to be worked out
and then we'll be done,
or whether there's some much higher levels approach gone wrong,
you know that we all, this is probably way too pessimistic,
but people have a lot of faith in isolation as an idea,
that there's a totally reasonable thing to do,
assume that isolation works and will design stuff
like cloud computing and running Javascript in the browser and all this stuff under the assumption,
which is not actually true, but it was close enough believed to be close enough to true,
that isolation will just you know cause they're not to be serious security problems
and that's actually probably still doable,
but this whole bag of micro-architectural attacks not made that story seem more convincing, that's for sure.
Just to add on to that,
I'm not sure a payoff levels expertise would like CPU design,
but to what extent can CPU design be made straightforwardly without a micro-architecture
while still preserving its high performance.
Performance, I mean, people believe this stuff.
Nicely security too, but yeah.
Well, some of this clearly can be fixed like this meltdown thing,
I mean there is a fix this you actually check the permissions,
that probably doesn't sacrifice any performance,
for some of the other attacks that have come up,
it's not clear that you could fix them without sacrificing performance,
I mean some of this very very deep,
like the fact that we're sharing you know, this there's a lot of sharing,
like a time sharing a cloud environment, there's just a lot of sharing
and so, for example suppose there's a disk drive or a network on your cloud server right,
gosh, you might be able to get information about the other people on that cloud server,
simply by watching how their traffic interferes with your traffic disk traffic or network traffic or memory traffic or something.
So there's some sort of, I, you know I don't know,
but that's practical, maybe it's not although you know for many many things in which people said point that attack just doesn't seem to be practical,
you know it turned out to be practical enough.
And I think.
And so a lot of this micro-architectural stuff, maybe could be cleaned up without performance loss,
or maybe can't be cleaned up without performance loss,
but I think it's, I think it's a much more serious problem than just we're gonna applies fixes,
they'll go away.
And the place is the most acute is cryptography,
there's been many many years of people looking into these kind of clever
often cache timing based ways of sensing bit set of keys and other people's cryptographic,
people running running at cryptographic encryption on the same machine as you,
can you guess anything about my key by watching, by doing cache timing,
answer is absolutely.
And it's not a micro-architectural bugs,
it's just a consequence of sharing often.
Anyway I don't know how this is gonna play out,
but it's not it's not straightforward.
I mean this curious part is when people made progress on,
just measuring the like [EM] radiation from a CPU and figuring out what instructions are run and what data is in it
with machine learning with like some accuracy,
you know not a hundred percent not nearly, but like a scary amount of accuracy,
because anything over zero is scary.
Yeah, we all live in you know that's all,
well there's a boundary between attacks that are,
there's some threshold between the attacks that are possible,
but you know gosh just seems like that would be too expensive or awkward painful whatever complex to carry out.
And, attacks really could be carried out,
of course we only should defend against the second class,
because the first class is often too expensive to defend against,
but as the value of stuff containing computers gets larger
and attackers get more clever get more closer access to shared environments,
kind of threshold by which attacks are feasible enough to defend against changes.
Alright, I'm done with the lecture,
I'm happy to take more questions, if people have.
Thank you.
Thanks, I actually had a question about the cache,
so the L1 cache is its per CPU right.
Yes.
And L2 isn't shared.
Well, so this picture is different for each CPU, for different models of CPU, etc,
the the habit today, is looks it's a little bit more complex than this,
typically a multiple cores,
two four eight or 64 something,
each one has a L1 cache,
that's quite close to the CPU,
but it's small fast and small,
each core typically also has a bigger L2 cache,
this you know it's sort of dedicated to that CPU.
And then, and then there's often a shared L3 cache, often but not always
and another approach is to make the summation of the L2 cache is sort of convenient for all the CPUs to use,
so that I have super high speed access to my L2 cache,
but I can get at other people said a slightly bigger penalties,
the effective cache size larger,
so often three see either three level caches or or a sort of joint to second level caches.
And typically the L2 and L3 are physically addressed, L1 is virtual.
Sorry, so what's the point of having physically address, yeah, yeah it's.
Yeah it's easy, the stuff in L1 cache, a virtual address cache.
If the same data is used with different virtual addresses,
you can't you know the virtual address cache doesn't help you find it,
if it was cache under a different address where these L2 caches, the data is independent is usable,
no matter what virtual address you address it and.
Where does the MMU use, it relative to all these caches in the TLB.
Oh, it's not it's distributed really,
because the I mean the most obvious,
I mean I think in real life,
the TLB the most critical thing is that TLB
and I believe it's indexed in parallel with the L1 cache typically.
So if you hit in the cache, the L1 cache great, although there may be a.
Anyway, and if you miss the L1 cache,
then now you have the physical you were looking up in that TLB at the same time,
now your physical can addressed,
the MMU that was not just a single box that sits somewhere,
it's actually kind of involved.
Okay, but isn't it hardware, so.
Oh, everything is yours hardware, yeah.
But remember these you know these chips have billions of transistors on them,
so yeah, maybe it's hardware, but we're talking about massively complex hardware,
that's designed using very sophisticated software like design techniques,
so that it can do very very complex and sophisticated things,
so yeah its hardware but, yeah, it's not at all at all straightforward.
So do table mapping like page table mappings ever end up in the caches at all
or are they always just routed through that TLB,
because if you miss it, that TLB you have to go to memory retrieve.
That right, so they're certainly the L2 cache will hold,
the form the point of view the L2 cache, TLB misses, TLB reloads are just memory accesses,
so that TLB needs to load a bunch of page table junk,
it's just a memory load
and it could use, stuff could easily be cached in the L2.
But it has to skip to L1,
because L1 has virtual addresses, but.
I don't know think that TLB would consult the L1 for its.
Okay.
Because it's virtually address, yes.
And then one thing about the spectre attack.
How would you, I,
so so the thing is like I've heard about meltdown inspector like at least a dozen times
and every time I looked it up I would not understand it,
so this is the first time I actually understand what's going on,
but for spectre is there, like how similar is it to meltdown.
It's not.
It's not, okay.
Or, that they will,
my understanding the spectre attack is by training the branch predictor,
that you know the other code that you're trying to get attack stuff from.
Let's suppose it's another process you share some memory with it, right.
Yeah, because you're it's really the same program as you,
but it's some other user running the program, right.
You can, the branch, the branch, the tables the branch predictor uses are shared between different,
if I run a CPU [forbidden], that you run or maybe run on different hyper threads of the same CPU,
everybody sees the same branch sees the same branch predictor,
so I can train the branch predictor to predict branches in a certain way,
and then I'll let you run,
you're running with my branch predictor training right
and so that means I can essentially trick your program into speculatively executing instructions of my choice.
Right, now it's only speculative, so of course they'll be undone,
but they they will cause cache loads,
that to some extent I can control.
Because I control how you speculatively execute
and then if we share memory I can use flush and reload to sense
what cache lines your program loaded this speculative execution.
Oh, so in that case, you don't need to, you don't need to,
like know like directly address address a piece of memory,
you just need to make sure that program will specularly executed,
like in meltdown, we did it ourselves,
but in spectre just directed there,
that's kind of cool, because you can just say oh you know just go and load that secret by training the branch predictor,
without knowing where the secret is,
like you gotta know someone,
yeah you kind of have to know.
You need to know great [] and great detail.
Yeah sorry, you have to know.
But you have to yourself.
Yes.
That's not secret, you're probably running a program that,
I know what program you're running.
Yeah, okay, that makes sense, thank you.
Yeah, I was just wondering,
it seems like when you when a research paper, like this gets released,
it's out there for like people, Linux and Windows and like Intel for them to try to go and scramble to patch the bug,
but it's also out there for hackers can start to learn from the paper,
like oh this is a method we could use,
and I'm I'm wondering, like it as a researcher is there a general practice
of like as we're working on the paper will sort of tipoff the quote unquote good guys first,
so that they can have.
Yeah, authors informed every you know the CPU manufacturers and OS manufacturers before they publish the paper.
There's a whole, there's a whole protocol,
you know these kind of things would even be accepted anymore, unless you follow the protocol.
That doesn't mean the attackers weren't already using it right,
because you probably know the attackers discovered this twenty years ago, but.
Great, thank you.
It's not straightforward, I think in this particular case, I think you know what some Intel was not too excited about,
the collaboration between the Linux community and Intel was not completely smooth, I think.
When this happened, I think they worked at some of the [], but.
I think it was kind of scary,
because I I read on Wikipedia, that the Ubuntu fix was published after the paper was published,
which I found scary, but.
Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Thank you, well see you next week.