And can everybody see my screen or the whiteboard that I shared.
Okay good.
How are people doing with the lock lab,
let me start there, just ask if, how progress and what its more difficult or it's looking.
Okay, anybody who want to report on their experience so far.
I hope lots of people have started.
Oh yeah.
Yeah, go ahead.
Oh, sorry, go ahead.
Okay, cool.
I'll go, I'll go.
The lock lab, I think the first part, the the kalloc on was not as bad,
well, and then the second part was a bit harder,
well it's a lot harder in my opinion.
You just have to figure out a,
I guess the hard part was thinking of a solution that,
It's like hey this doesn't cause deadlock,
but then if you think there are cases where like deadlock ha- could happen
if you acquire a [] it's lock again and all that stuff,
but yeah I just have to think, you have to think
like about extra cases and all that stuff
and after that it shouldn't be that bad.
Anybody else who want to share their experience so far.
I want to ask, are we allowed to do any part of the lab like lock free,
because I know like their first part,
for example it's pretty the instructions said pretty clearly like make apparel memory allocator,
but can we do it just lock free
and think, you know leave it as it is.
You're free to do any solution to pass which made great,
it's fine lock free,
I would be a you are certainly free to do it.
I'd be hesitant to start there,
if I were you I would start first with a more fine-grained lock implementation
and then move to the lock free implementation.
So the reason there is not started with a walk free,
because if you go to a fine grain you need to do all of the parallel stuff,
but if you just go directly to a lock free one,
then you can keep it on a single free list
and you just need to you just need to [automata] size,
the free and allocate operations which actually isn't that bad.
Yeah I think maybe in a,
if there's a single list in the case of the kalloc that might be the case,
I think you know the lock free [balloc] is going to be a more complicated.
Yeah, that I'm scared to do.
But that's the right reaction to have.
Anybody else?
I found it a bit hard to debug those problems,
because it's not immediately clear what is happening,
so we have to go and set with gdb and break break break, and yeah.
Yeah I think the only, one reason I'm always scared to get these lock labs I said,
labs you know they're harder to debug,
and you know the bug might not show up on every run.
And but hopefully it is very educational,
because learning a program locks inside the kernel is a real thing,
and but it is definitely a core challenge.
One thing about maybe there's a node for the course,
you know the next lab actually doesn't involve,
basically any concurrency and should hopefully that will be much more straightforward.
Okay.
I gue-, I guess, how do you how do you efficiently or effectively debug concurrent programs,
like with all those multiple threads using gdb.
I use very basic stuff, I have use print statements.
But the main thing I rely on is I sort of tried to write down or assertions for invariants,
that I think should be true at every point.
And if the assertion goes off,
then I know that you know there's something wrong in my thinking or assertion was wrong.
And then I think for a while and try to decide what it is,
and then go from there.
The normal for many other settings,
there are race detectors that can help you,
and again basically flag code that mean looks like it might be having problems
or as prone to race conditions,
but that's a whole set of other tools,
that we're not using.
And it's not that [good],
but there's a little bit of a big step to actually get that all up and going and running.
So that's the other mechanism that people use race detectors.
Basically flag, any any shared variable that is updated or read without actually holding a lock.
That doesn't help with deadlocks,
for example in this lab in a bcache lock, you and you get deadlocks,
deadlocks are tend to be easier to do debug correct,
because you can get the panic and then you can look at the gdb in the backtrace
and see actually was involved in the deadlock.
Does that make sense? Thank you.
Okay, another suggestion, actually somebody posted on the feedback,
is you know classes are ten is getting a little bit lower than in the beginning of the semester,
and I think we might be small enough for the size
that it may be perfectly fine to actually have cameras on.
And so maybe I want to encourage you to if you ask a question to turn on your camera,
you know will hopefully improve in our experiences,
if you've seen the classroom as opposed to in a virtual meeting.
And you don't have to look at me.
Okay, so, okay, today's lecture,
so today's lecture is going to be about crash safety and crash safety file systems,
and this is not crash safety in its most general form,
actually I'm really focusing on a particular problem, or a specific problem,
namely a crash or power failure can lead on-disk file system to be in an inconsistent state for an incorrect state.
And what I mean, with an incorrect state is known
for example a data block belongs two files,
or an inode is allocated to different files.
And so the scenario where this problem might sort of appear is,
let's say you know your running make, makes pretty file system interact with the file system,
reads writes files
and somewhere during you know that thing [] a power failure happens,
you know if maybe your laptop run out of battery,
you know maybe the power just dropped to your house,
and you know you reboot, the power comes back on at some point,
you reboot the machine, machine comes back up
and then you get a prompt again,
you run ls and you hope basically that your file system is in a good state,
in the state actually can still use it.
And so the particular failures or crashes that we're concerned about
are basically power failures during file system operations
or the kernel panics you know while running some file system operation, xv6 is panics,
most kernels are panics, you know maybe they're some kernel bug that causes a panic
and you know suddenly your system just fails.
And what you'd like to be the case
that after rebooting you can actually do something,
or you can still use the file system.
And this might be something where you're thinking well,
how could that not be right, because the file system stored on a persistent storage medium
and so if the power fails, you know that medium should be good, then so once machine comes back up,
you know all the blocks that you've written should be there.
And we'll see that the tricky cases that many file system operations have multi-step operations.
And really what is important to note
and if we if we crash just in the wrong place, in these multi-step operations,
the file system actually may end up being an this inconsistent for that short period of time
and if the power fail just happened there, you know something bad could happen.
And so that is sort of the problem that we're focusing on today
and so this is different from the problem that for example whatever you know there's a power failure
and your disk caught fire and so there's nothing there anymore
and you need to in that case, you need you need there's a completely different problem,
that has different solutions, you know, for example you have to go back to backup of your file system,
reinstall your file system, etc etc,
so that's the problem, we're not worried about.
We're really worried about the specific problem of failure happening right during a multi-step operation.
Okay, and the solution for that specific problem that
we're going to be exploring is something that is called logging,
and this is a very popular solution,
originally coming out of the database world,
but a lot of file systems that use logging these days.
We're gonna, it's very one reason it's popular is because it's a very principled solution,
and we're going to see the institution of logging in xv6
and of course xv6 has a very simple implementation,
like a bare minimal implementation of logging, just to demonstrate in the key ideas,
and even that sort of a very bare bone,
log implementation actually has several issues, that were going to be talking about
and that's why it's worth you know studying it.
One downside as we'll see, is the xv6 solution is
because of simplicity, its performance is also not so great.
Even though logging systems in principle can get a good performance,
and so what we'll do next week is actually look how, how to implement a high performance logging system
by studying the logging system, the Linux ext3 file system uses,
but that's next week.
Another, may be small a point I want to make today
is this is our last xv6 lecture
and from now on, we're going to be switching to papers,
because in some ways, what we've done is we've covered you know the basic concepts
and we can start looking at more advance operating system ideas by reading papers.
Okay.
Any questions so far?
Well good.
Okay, so let me go back a little bit about the scenarios that were really,
that we're focusing about in in this lecture.
So file systems, file system operations,
like creating a file, writing a file, are multi-step disk operations.
And we saw that last week on Monday,
we talked about how create is implemented,
like creating a file, or writing to a file,
we often see that you know the sequence of events, or something the sequence of steps are allocated inode,
mark the inode allocated on disk,
then you know write the directory block that contains that inode
and so those are the multi-steps that I'm talking about.
If we get a crash between two of the steps,
that can crash can leave, maybe mayb leave the file system invariance violated.
And violent, the invariance I'm talking about are invariance of the form,
you know every block is either free or allocated to one file and not to two files.
And you know we want to make sure that this happens,
despite you know these failures right between these operations.
Yeah, and the risk is if if the invariance are violated,
that bad things can happen after reboot,
you know the you might crash again immediately.
Because you know there's some data structure, the file system you know in a state
that the file system actually can't really deal with on this data structures in such a state,
[shape] that the file system really can't process them anymore,
or more likely you're not crash, no crash,
but you know data may get lost,
or you read or write incorrect data.
And we'll see a couple of examples, you know to make it more clear,
but so these are the risks that we're worried about.
I don't know if anybody actually every personal life or in your daily life using computers
actually has experienced a problem where basically, you had a failure in the file system
where you had a failure had a power failure,
your machine rebooted or your phone restarted and a basically unusable afterwards.
One reason that might be unusual,
because actually the file system just didn't recover correctly.
Okay, so to make it more clear, let's just let's look at an example in the context of xv-,
I like to make this risk a little bit more concrete,
let's look at an example in the context of xv6 and to see what actually go could go wrong.
So remember the, for Monday the xv6 file system, very simple file system has a simple disk layou,
you know super block, a super block,
there's the log, that we're going to be talking about a lot today, that we didn't talk about on Monday,
where inodes you know set of blocks that actually contain each and each block may contain multiply inodes,
just bitmap that block to record which blocks are free and which are not free,
and then the data blocks actually contain the actual data of the file system.
You remember from Monday's lecture I reproduce the trace here,
you know we looked at actually a how files created
and you know we see that the creation of a single file.
Well, wait a second.
The, the creation of a single file consists of multiple operations,
for example in this particular scenario that I've here on the, on on this slide,
we see the, you know inode it's allocated
and we know this because there's block 33 is being written,
do we see that the inode is being initialized,
then write again to block 33,
then we see the block 46 is written
and that reason is written is presumably, because you know the directory block that actually contains x
and the inode number for x is written to the disk.
Then the inode, root inode updated to reflect that the directory has grown in size to contain this particular file x
and then you know inode updated.
So, what we want to understand is what happens, like what could possibly go wrong, right,
so let's say you know we have a power failure right here,
so here is power failure or kernel crash.
So what happens after the power failure,
correct all the in-memory state is lost,
because in-memory state data that's actually in RAM,
like all the processes all the file descriptors, all the in-memory caches are gone,
because memory is not persistent
and the only thing that we have left is what actually is on the disk,
so only the data structures, the bits and bytes,
they're actually sitting on the disk are survived the power failure,
because that actually medium is you know persistence or has durability.
And so we want to know, like we understand,
so if we crash here and we have no additional mechanisms,
or no logging as we're going to be talking about,
we have no additional mechanisms, how how bad is it.
What risk are we running here.
Anybody?
So basically you know we've written block 33 to record the inode has been allocated,
then we had a power failure and then we come back up.
Go ahead Brandon.
This does that mean we lose the, lose this block,
it's like it seems like it's populated, but it's actually not.
Yeah, correctly, I think we're losing we're losing the whole block,
but we used inode x, correct inode x,
and inode for x that was allocated os marked as allocated is allocated on disk,
but we have not put in any, we've not succeeded, correct, put in any directory.
So basically on the disk, you know there's an inode allocated,
but it doesn't appear in any directory,
so we can't even remove it right.
And so basically what will this cause has to happen is we lose lose an inode.
Does that make sense?
You might think, well maybe what I should do is maybe I should reorder the write.
And, in a way you know then hopefully you know this, you know we don't lose the inode,
so for example another thing we could try doing is say well what we'll do is,
we'll write 46 first, basically update the inode updated directory, right,
the directory inode you know write 32
and then will actually mark the inode is allocated on disk, to mark indicate that mark is allocated.
So we do the same set of operations in a slightly different order.
In the hope that we should avoid this losing of the inode problem.
And would this work.
Well, the thing that we should ask ourselves like you know let's think about this point in time,
let's say a crash happens like right here
or power failure happens right between updating the directory basically, but before we allocated the inode on disk
and now you know we power fails machine comes back up
and we look at the file system,
you know what state will the file system be in.
You'll still think it's a free inode in.
Yeah what would happen if for example we read you know file x in the directory, in the root directory,
because it is in there, now correcting this data block.
We're going to be reading the inode, that actually is not even allocated correct, marked unallocated.
And worse, what could happen is correct inode it might be allocated again,
or it might actually really be allocated,
because marks unallocated to actually in fact a different file, right,
and so now we have two files that might actually,
two files that actually share even though they're completely different,
they share the same inode,
for example if one file would be owned by user one and one by user two,
then basically user two could read user one file data right.
So that's no good, either, right.
Does that make sense?
So basically switching the order you know it's not really going to solve our problem.
You would just basically get a different problem that we had before.
Okay, let's look at one more example.
Here's the example of writing to file x.
So once we have the files allocated, let's say that all succeeded,
and now we're executing the write system call
and the write system call also does a multiple writes operations which we saw on Monday,
for example it will allocate a block, in this case block 45,
so it sets a bit in the free map,
block 45 is the bitmap block,
so it allocates a block in the bitmap,
allocates a bit in the bitmap block to indicate the the block has to be allocated,
that block turns out to be I guess 595.
And then we write you know at the character h you know to 596
and then the character i you know we update the inode.
Right, now we can ask ourselves the same question,
like what will happen if we crash,
so for example let's say we allocate crashed right here,
between you know writing the bitmap block, before we allocate before we actually write a inode,
so crash here.
And so we reboot, we come back up
and this is in a particular state and you know what, what is the risk.
We use it data block, but we lose it.
Yeah, we lose it again, right,
because the block is allocated but doesn't show up in any file,
because it hasn't been written into any inode, so we lose a data block.
You might think okay, well maybe you know just because we wrote them in the wrong order,
what we should have done is a what we should have done is at first write in the inode,
so first write 33 with the, you know with 595 as in the ether is an indirect block a direct block.
And then you know actually we will mark the inode, a block is allocated,
so then we'll write you know 45.
If we change the order, because we want to avoid these lost data block, we change order in this way.
And now let's consider the case if there's a failure right here.
What is the risk.
The size of the file is not compatible with actually how many data blocks are allocated.
That might be, although I think it's the write of 33 actually update both the size and you know the the block number.
Oh.
So that might be might work out OK.
If there were two separate writes, that would be a problem,
but there's some bigger problem here.
Is that the, so the file has the,
so things that it has the data block, but the data block is marked as unallocated
and other files can also use it.
Yeah, that's the real big problem here is that,
you know the the inode things 595, block 595 belonged belonged to that file,
but actually on disk it's still marked as unallocated
and so when later another file was created,
you know that block actually might be used for that other file.
And so now certainly one file things, it owns 595,
but actually other file does, in fact both files will have 595 in there block numbers for their inode
and basically you know if one user owns that file, the other user in the other file,
the connection read right to each other's data, right,
that's clearly not what we want.
You know the file system should guarantee
that every block only belongs in one file and no other file or is free.
Okay.
So this could lead to security problems,
basically block is shared among multiple files.
And that's definitely wrong.
Does it make sense, in terms of the problems that can appear.
And again, you know the real issue here is, not to watch the ordering of the writes,
but the real underlying problem here is that we're just doing multiple writes
and it basically have to show up on disk as an atomic operation.
Okay, so the solution that we're gonna explore in this lecture is logging.
And as I said before, this is a common solution used in file systems
and originating actually out of the database literature,
and it actually has a couple good properties,
one it's going to make basically system calls or file system calls atomic.
With that, I mean, so if a create file or you can call create you call write,
basically all the effects of that system call use all appeared altogether or none of them,
so that avoids this problem of only some subset of the writes actually showing up on disk.
Second good property, it has, it allows for fast recovery.
So after reboot, turns out we don't actually have to do a lot of work to repair the file system,
actually a very minimal amount of work.
And this is in contrast to some other solution and I'm not talking about,
which is basically you go and inspect the file system,
maybe you read all the blocks of the file system or read all the inode blocks, read all the bitmap blocks
and so check out whether the file system is still in the correct shape and maybe repair things.
Logging has this nice property that actually the recovery is fast.
And finally, it is in principle, it can be actually very high performance,
although the one, you know what we're going to be looking in the context of xv6 is not high performance,
so we're going to look at that next week,
we'll see actually how to build a logging system that has atomic file system calls faster recovery in high performance,
today we're going to be just focusing on the first two.
Okay.
The basic idea of logging is actually straightforward,
and so basically what you do is you divide this into two pieces.
One is the log, one is the file system.
And file system might be much bigger than log.
And when you need to update the file system,
so update, let's say a block 33 or update the bitmap block,
we're actually not going to update the file system blocks,
so we're not going to update bitmap block directly,
instead the only thing we're gonna do on the right is,
so here's our memory, we have a block in memory, is say the bitmap block, it's 45
and instead of writing it to 45, where we normally would have done,
what we're gonna do is actually going to write into the log,
we're going to stick it here and remember that definitely should go to 45,
we will put it there.
And we do that with all the other writes too,
so for example we'll put inode block there,
you know like maybe 33 I think, if I remember correctly
and we'll stick it in there
and you know, remember that actually has to go to 33.
So basically what we do any right is first log.
And so we don't write directly to the home location of the block,
but we just put it always a log.
Then, at some point when the file system operation is done,
for example as you know these four five writes that we saw in the previous slides are in the log,
we commit the operation.
Basically what it means is somewhere in the log,
we just record a record, you know in a fixed location,
that basically says okay, well you know there are like five logs in the log,
and that is you know the log, set of log the writes.
And then you know when we have all the writes stably on disk,
we're going to actually install them, was called the installation phase.
And really what that means is, we're gonna move you know these logs from the log to their home location,
so we know this one has to go to 45, so we put it at 45,
this one has to go to 33, we put it to 33, etc etc.
And once we're done, you know basically we can clean the log
and cleaning the log, basically you're rewriting, you know basically setting this five to zero.
And that is a basic plan.
And why is this plan good, well let's think about it.
Let's say we crash before here, what would happen.
So let me hold that question, when you actually talk about one thing before asking the question.
Let's say we crash and so we reboot,
and on the reboot, there's basically what the file system does,
it looks at the commit record,
sees what the value of the commit record is,
even zero, you know do nothing in our simple scheme.
And if it's bigger to zero,
we know that there are basically blocks in the log that need to be actually installed.
And we apparently didn't finish the installation,
we crashed you know after the commit, but before cleaning the log,
so basically we re-install, and after we re-install, we clean the log.
Okay?
And this scheme is good,
because it actually ensures that no matter where the crash happens,
we're either install all the blocks of the writes or we install none of them,
but we were never into we will never end up in a situation where we installed some of the writes, but not all of them.
Just to see why this is [true], let's consider a couple cases where things could crash.
So things could crash and between one and two, what will happen,
in what situation do we end up.
Situation in which on recovery, we do nothing
and that's okay because nothing has been written to the file system.
Yeah exactly,
so this is the case where basically we we just do nothing,
you know as if the system could basically never executed,
because if the failure happened slightly earlier, right, before the file system calls started.
And so that's perfectly okay, that's acceptable.
Okay, what happens, if we crash, okay between after committing before being installed.
Then you'll just redo all the installs, so you'll kind of restore the correct state.
Yeah, so exactly,
so at that point correct, we have we know there are all the blocks are in the log
and they'll be all written, because we committed,
so it must be the case that the whole file system operation finished.
So we can basically put them in their location where they should be.
And then we're all in good shape and so in this case now all the file in this case will end up
as if the, it is if the file system call actually completely just before the crash, there's no difference.
Okay.
So what happens if we crash during install or like install during install before re-cleaning,
crash here, in this case, in this case and I will do the first case,
we'll install during installation, or just before install after installing before cleaning.
What, what what, what happened then.
On the.
Oh, sorry, on the next restart,
nothing has really changed, in terms of the recovery process
and so we're just going to redo the log.
We're going to redo the log again
and we're gonna copy basically the content again, you know to the locations,
where maybe in fact we might do it multiple times,
is that okay.
Yes, because those are just writes,
and it's they are to a specific location that we don't change, like it's written in the log,
so we know where we should write every time.
Yeah basically every time we do the same write, correct,
so let's say in block 45, you know there's the value ten,
and we're going to write ten at location 45 every time
and that's exactly what it should be
and repeating that write multiple times doesn't really do any harm, right.
Because we're writing the same value, that actually should be there anyway.
And so it's perfectly fine, for us to do re-installation multiple times.
Of course, we shouldn't serve any other file system calls at this particular point of time,
we should do this before we restart the file system,
but while you know what, during reboot during recovery, you know we can just do this, right.
Another way of saying, that is that installation is basically idempotent,
you can just execute it many many times and will have the same effect yet.
Question about that.
Because the interface is just read and write,
if we had an append, this would not be safe, right.
Yeah yeah, this [],
you can make append safe too, a more fancy logging schemes,
but for these particular logging scheme, we don't have to worry about that.
In fact, in some sense, the append is file system level operation
and at that level we can make it a topic using the logging scheme, that we're, what we have here.
I see, thank you.
I also have a question,
what would happen if the file system crashed while you are committing,
so you want to execute multiple writes and then you only commit like half of them.
Yeah OK, so can you speak up a little bit more, because your volume is low.
Oh, yeah sorry,
so if you wanted to like commit multiple writes at once, like in an atomic way,
but your system crashes in the middle of committing,
so you are only able to commit like half of the writes,
what would happen in that instance.
Okay, so there's a very important point, I'm glad you ask the question.
So first of all, the the you commit, in writing this commit operation here, correct,
this you know step two,
you only execute that commit operation after you've already logged all the writes, that you were planning to execute, right.
So at the point you do to commit, all the writes are in the log.
And so, the commit operation itself is an interesting question, what happens there.
So, the way the way I indicated this on this,
like commit operation writes a single block, like a single sector on the disk.
And the standard assumption that file systems make is that a single block write or single sector write is an atomic operation.
Meaning that if you write it, the whole sector will be written, or none of the sector will be written.
So the sector will never be written partially.
And so there's always you know clearly you valid data in that particular sector
and so basically this operation that commit operation writing the log header,
is writing the commit record is the real commit operation,
if that succeeds, and there's basically say of five in the commit header,
you know we know that there are five blocks in the log and we have to reinstall those five blocks.
If the commit header didn't make it to disk, then the value will still be zero
and we'll just treat it as if that transaction never happened.
Thank you.
And the key rule that you're sort of hinting at, that has to be true,
is something what's called the write-ahead rule, which means that a logging system cannot install writes, until all the writes into, are into log.
Any more questions about this sort of basic plan.
Okay.
Let's see.
So what I want to there are many many different versions of logging schemes
and I sketched out here a very simple one,
you know it's perfectly fine,
you know their schemes where basically the cleaning of the log is postponed,
installation is postponed until later,
but I'm going to run sort of this very simple scheme,
and then next week we'll see more sophisticated logging protocols.
But all those logging protocols, follow this write-ahead rule,
that before you're ready to commit record, you have to make sure that all the writes are in the log.
But then there's a lot of within that,
still there's a ton of flexibility in designing a particular logging protocols typically called.
Okay, I'm gonna look a little bit, how this then is manifest itself in xv6,
you know as a case study and to make things really concrete.
Okay, so in xv6, there's sort of, you're going to look at two sort of piece of estate you will,
the stuff that is actually on disk.
And that's you know things that are in memory, [] [] in-memory contents will disappear,
on the way we should think about it is that in-memory content will disappear on a crash or power failure.
And the structure of the xv6 log as always pretty simple.
There's actually, we have one block in the beginning, the header block,
and that's basically our commit record,
you know it contains the number n, which is like the number of blocks in the log
and then for each block, the block number, the home location of that block, blah blah blah,
are going to be any of those.
And so, then in the log itself are basically is the data, that it belongs to that,
so here is the data of bn0, here's the data of bn1, etc,
to b n minus one.
So that's what's in the log.
And there's the only thing, that's sort of in the log, there's nothing more to it.
Then in memory where, while the file systems running,
there's an in copy version in-memory version of the header.
And it basically has n and it has array of block numbers, etc.
And then you know these block numbers refer to block, that are sitting in the data,
that actually corresponds to the block numbers that are sort of sitting in this in-memory data structure,
they live in the block cache.
Which you know, but now you're well familiar with.
And so, maybe this is like block ten, is the first block in the log,
or maybe let me take a more concrete example, from that lines up with our previous things, maybe this is like 45.
And basically you know somewhere in the in cache,
the block cache there's of course whatever block for 45, here is data.
Okay.
That's sort of the structures,
that the [on disk] in-memory file system has and on disk file system has,
on-disk file system just has the log,
the in-memory has these data structures to orchestrate.
These multi write operations that were going to be doing.
Okay.
So, to make this a little more concrete, let's look at some code.
Then that will help us understand how everything works.
So let me pull up some code.
Okay, let me put this next to it, we keep that picture.
So that we can look at if we want to or I can point to it.
Can everybody see my code.
Somebody have to confirmed they seen emacs window.
{Yeah,we can see it.
Good.
Is it big enough.
I think it's good.
Okay.
That looks good.
Thank you.
Okay, so let's start with,
you know I I talked about transactions,
where you you know the fact that you know we should not commit until,
we should not write to commit a writer, until all the writes have done.
And so this means that you should file system operations,
must indicates what the beginning of transaction is and particularly at the end of the transaction is.
And the way that happens in xv6, that every file system call,
here's open corresponds to create basically starts with begin_op
and basically indicates like, okay I want to start a transaction
and I want all the block writes that I've been doing between begin_op and end_op which is basically the end of the transaction to be atomic,
meaning they should be all applied to, or none of them should applied.
Okay, so every file system call in xv6 has that structure,
basically has begin_op, then the code and implements the file system call and then end_op.
And that end_op is basically where the commit operation happens.
So basically between begin_op and end_op, on disk or in-memory data structure should be updated,
whenever the in-memory log may be updated the block cache might be updated,
but nothing really happens until end_op
and then end of time, we're basically going to put things into the log
and then we are done with putting everything in the log,
will actually you know write to commit record or log header.
Okay.
So let's.
So what is interesting, of course what happens is every write correctly,
whenever one of these file system calls does a disk write, you know something must happen,
so if we go back for example to fs.c, you look at ialloc,
ialloc basically what it calls it doesn't call bwrite directly,
but it actually calls a log_write.
And so we're going to see what log_write does,
log_write is basically a function implemented by logging system,
and every write basically a file system called us between begin_op and end_op, always goes through log_write.
So here's log_write and log_write actually reasonable straightforward.
Yeah, you know we've written the block, in the block cache,
so somewhere basically 45, maybe this is like the write to 45,
we've updated you know 45 in the block cache,
now we basically record in the in-memory data structures,
that at some point later, at commit point we were able to write this log into log.
And so you know basically you know the code is,
oops,
the code is reasonably straightforward,
it acquired a lock on the header and basically updates the header,
in particular, what does goes through you know the updates,
and when actually the first thing it does it actually sees, if there's already a copy of 45 in the,
if 45 is already recorded as being having to write to written to,
and if that's the case nothing has to be done, because 45 will be written to.
And so we're done, sometimes called log absorption.
If you know block 45 is not in the array yet
or not in the the list of blocks or the array of blocks,
that needs to be written to disk,
then basically you know the only thing, this particular piece of code does is
basically bump up and stick that block number that needs to be written
into the next entry or into that entry.
Then the only other thing it does and I'll talk about this later,
it will [ping] the block in the buffer cache
and let me postpone why a little while,
but I will come back to that later.
And that's actually all that log_write there doing,
so every file system call that needs to update a block, updates to block in the block cache
and it basically it appends it to this in-memory data structure,
unless you know it's already there, in which case, you know just absorbs it.
Does that make sense?
So does it mean that bwrite shouldn't be used by itself at all.
Sorry, say again.
Bwrite shouldn't be used by itself, only as.
Yes that's correct,
basically all you, one way to think about is
that every bwrite in the file system is replaced by log_write.
Okay, so now let's see what actually happens at end_op,
because that's where the exciting part happens.
And there's a couple of cases that I just wanna avoid talking about, a little bit later,
because they even this simple logging system actually has some subtle complexities
and most of the beginning of this code deals with these subtle complexities.
But if you want to get a normal case,
you know there's or there's the simple case
where no other term file system operations are in progress,
we are executing create file and basically we're getting to the point where we want to commit.
And so the code is pretty straightforward and calls commit,
so let's look at the commit.
So here's commit, [] commit does to basically steps basically writes the log,
that's basically writing all these, all these block numbers,
that are sitting you know in the in-memory header,
writes them basically all to the header on disk, including you know there's number n.
Right, and so let's see,
that is that's what write_head does, sorry,
write_log basically writes you know the blocks from the buffer cache into their respective into the log itself.
So let's see write_log, right above here.
You see what it does,
it goes through you know this array one at a time
and basically writes down to the log position in the log.
Okay so read you know the log block, then sticks it in there,
by copying it, and then writing it actually out to the disk.
So this basically ensures that log 45 land up here,
you know say this is [32] that will end up there etc etc.
Then, at the end, so at this point we have not committed yet, correct,
the only thing we've done is basically putting blocks into the log,
and if we were crash at this particular point in time,
before calling write_head before write_head succeeded,
and basically as if the transaction didn't execute at all.
So let's look at the write_head.
So that write_head is what I called earlier,
basically the commit point, and the commit point,
basically you know basically it's straightforward and reach the head of block from disk,
which is probably sitting in the buffer cache,
it you know puts the copies the end,
you know this end into that block, puts all the block numbers into that array into that block
and it basically writes that that particular block.
This is the this bwrite, what is that is that the commit point.
If a crash happens before this bwrite, what happens then.
Anybody?
If the crash happens before bwrite, isn't the only modification that we've made to the in memory hb data structure,
so it's not, it's going to be fine.
Yeah, it's gonna be fine,
because basically we may have written [db one zero db n] whatever to log,
but we have not succeeded in writing the log header.
And so will do not, on recovery nothing will happen.
And what happens if there's a crash right after to bwrite, so like crash here.
And it's no longer zero, so the log headers correctly read and it's recovered.
Yeah, will be recovered, correct.
Well, at some point hopefully during recovery as we expect that,
we expect the recovery will actually read the log header see that there is a five in there for example,
and then copy the first five logs through their home location.
So this is really this, this, this one line,
there's one disk write, there's one sector write is really the commit point.
Right.
Before the commitment point, the transaction, is the transaction didn't happen after the commit point,
the transaction will definitely be finished, assuming your recovery is correct.
Okay, so let's you know go back to commit.
So commit, after its committed it actually installs the transactions and that's pretty straightforward,
basically it takes the blocks looks at the header where the blocks belongs
and then basically writes into that particular location.
Yeah, so we can actually look at install_trans,
you see that actually that's what it does.
It has a copy of the log header and use or reads log header,
it reach the destination block the home location,
copies the data from the log block into the destination,
and then writes the buffer to the destination.
Okay.
So basically effectively what this does is
basically you know you go back to this previous slide here
and copies, you know it just does these copies from the log into the home location or actually in the file system.
And of course you know we might get a failure somewhere in you know this code
or while we're doing this,
but you know it should be OK, because hopefully in recovery will start over from the beginning.
So let's look at we, so that was installed.
So once install is done, then basically it sets you know the in-memory header and back to zero
and then writes that lock header.
And effectively that causes to cleans the log,
because basically there's now zero in it.
Question.
So, you have the function you're in just before,
like whereas, does the from to, or to, from getting,
so that puts the, the block that you're going to like update log
that you're going to update into the buffer cache,
could you make it faster by not putting into the buffer cache
and just directly writing it to the device instead.
Let me, which function we're talking about.
I forget its name, it's the one, where you a copy, yeah, everything into the log.
Okay, install install_trnas. I think so.
Oh, maybe it was this one.
So this I thinking probably of write_head, but it's the same thing.
Okay good.
The only reason, the only reason to this,
you know basically our interface is not particularly good,
you could just read straight, you know you're wondering why you are doing the read.
There's no reason to do the read, because we're going to write anyway, is that the question.
Yeah that and you're also a doing the memmove.
And [] the memmove, yeah,
so these are actually a sequence of code can definitely be optimized,
you can save you know one or two disk writes.
Just for simplicity, we don't do any of that.
Okay, thank you.
Okay, so I think we're in over commit,
just like, just go back. and double check.
So we did the write_log, we did the write_head
and basically this the cleaning operation, we erased you know transaction by sending it to zero.
Okay.
So the only thing to further inspect is like how, how does recovery work
and recovery happens when you know when xv6 starts,
so now we had a crash, and the system failed, we reboot it,
and the, one of the first things that xv6,
one of the things that xv6 does during initialization, it actually in the log.
And in the log, basically calls this function recover from log
and so let's see what that does.
And basically recover block you know calls read_head, to basically extract or read the.
Then, let me see if I can scroll down here a little bit.
Basically reads the header from disk,
and sees if n, well doesn't really see if n is zero or not,
but it just calls install_trans
and you know this is exactly the same install_trans we use look for it, for a look at it a while ago
and basically you know look at this n
and installs all the blocks from zero to n out of the log into their home location.
And if it's done, once it succeeds you know then actually it calls clear log as before.
And so that's actually all what the recovery does, recovery is basically always called [dust] installation.
And if we crash during installation here,
no particular problem again, correct,
because we'll crash we'll boot xv6 rebooting will call log in it,
which will call recovery log and it will basically re-install, replay the log is sometimes called,
again and this might have this might end, if we crash every time or you know many many times,
you know we'll reinstall or replace the log many many many times,
they'll tell hopefully at some point it succeeds
and actually you know gets the whole log written gets the whole log installed,
you know to the, to home locations.
Does it make sense?
I had a question about,
so if a process just runs normally, it writes some data to disk,
and then at some point after that before it commits and installs the changes,
there's a failure, from the process, the further process point of view nothing happened,
but something like, I guess the failure happened after the process ended of what I was doing,
so, is there anything bad about that.
Not hundred percent getting it, but a short answer is there's nothing bad,
because the disk won't be updated at all, so just as if you know that file system operation didn't happen.
Alright, I guess.
Process disappears too, but, you know we don't expect the process to survive failures anyway.
Right or I guess,
Okay I I think that answers my question, thank you.
Yeah it's important to remember to
basically the only thing that really survives failures or that's persistence across failures is
the disk or the state on the disk nothing else, right.
Okay, so just to make this all concrete, one little more to let's.
I put a statement in bwrite,
so actually the thing that actually does write to disk, like in the block cache.
And we're going to see what the trace of actual disk writes are.
Because basically on Monday I sort of, I didn't tell the full truth,
because basically I put the print statement in log_write and not in bwrite,
and so now I put it in the bwrite and so we can actually see all the blocks are being written.
So we'll do the same thing as before, you know echo hi x,
and just look at actually the actual disk writes.
And see if that makes sense,
you know so the first thing to note correctly, that this traces way longer than the trace that we looked at last time,
the fact that we looked at a slide a couple slides ago, right.
Because you're looking at, in fact you just demonstrate this,
here was the same echo hi correct.
And when we see there's like only it's five log write operations,
but it turns into many disk operations, right.
So let's look at it.
So what we think bwrite three four and five are and what is bwrite 2.
Anybody?
So writing to the log and then the super block.
Not the super block.
Now let's say that log_head.
Yeah, so just look at, you got it right,
you know just looking at this picture again, correct,
the log structure two, so, that's probably the header block to commit record if you will,
and then freeze the first data block, [] the second data block, finds the third data block.
So going back, you know this is the first write, the second write, the third write,
they're all going into the log and they're written to disk,
in the log log part of the disk,
and then this is the commit record header.
And then presumably what is this face.
What is this part?
Is that the bitmap setting?
No, so what do we think actually stored in this bwrite three.
Here you creating the file of the inode for x,
updating the directory and then also actually making the file itself.
Yeah, and so and we didn't do it here, right,
because in these bwrites that didn't happen.
Now we're doing it.
So what, what what phases of the transaction.
Installing the changes.
Yeah, installing the changes, correct,
what we did here is, we log the write,
then we committed the file system operation to create operation
and now we're installing it.
For now we're putting the blocks in their home location.
And now, and what does this bwrite two [then].
Clearing the log.
Yeah, it's clear log exactly.
So basically this, this this, the system called was writing 33 46 32
and to actually do that using the logging system that basically turns into this set of disk write,
right, where the first part is installing the log, in the first part is actually logging the writes, in the second part is installing the log.
And these are the two writes due to commit records.
So it makes sense?
Is it possible to infer where begin_op and end_op would run from this trace.
Well, so we're sort of no, correct,
so where did, we don't really know what begin_op start,
but this is any file system calls starts with the begin_op.
And it must be the case that, the commit record, correct is written in end_op,
so we know that this is the end_op of some file system operation.
Does that make sense?
Okay, so that's basically xv6 logging logging in action,
and when I talk about a couple complications,
and even this dirt simple naive logging scheme actually has complications.
One thing to immediately note of course is, you know is this a very performance implementation.
Did you by looking at this trace.
No.
Why not, I know this is a basically two simple questions, but it's important to ask.
Like, you're writing the stuff twice right.
Yeah, you're writing your stuff twice,
you write a file f or a big file f,
I'm going to write that big file f twice.
And so, certainly not particularly high performance,
where I mean basically re-cutting the performance immediately by a factor of two, just to get crash safety.
And so we'll see on on you when you're reading the ext ext3 paper for Monday
and one thing you should keep in your head, while reading is get how, how do I get around for this factor of two.
Okay?
So, is it the case that you write the h and the i separately.
Yeah, I think so.
Okay, okay.
I'll I'll show you in a second why, what is happening there.
Or maybe well, let me not commit too much to answer, but I will get back to it.
Oh, sorry, am I having the empty line, not the h and i, but yeah.
The new line, new line is a separate right.
Okay, thank you.
You're welcome.
Okay, there's complications and I want to talk a little bit about these complications.
Here's our basic scheme, basic data structures,
and there's three complications I want to talk about.
Maybe I'll call them challenges whatever you wanna call them.
The first is eviction.
And the issue is as follows,
let's say we go back to this picture here,
and you know bcache is full,
and, and sort of transaction in progress,
let's see, we've just updated 45,
it's now gone block 45, so it's going to write the next block,
and the cache is full.
And, the and,
let's say you know we don't we don't have a solution for this yet,
but the cache decides, it wants to evict 45 correct,
and if it wants to evict 45, but will mean that will mean we have to write it through its home location.
How bad would it be to write the block here,
you know evict 45, and write 45 to home location.
Is that good or bad.
Would any rule be broken, if we did that.
I guess, that as if a crash happens before the other writes in the same transaction occurs, then basically atomicity it is broken.
That is basically violates this write-ahead rule that I talked about,
you have to write all the blocks to the log, before you write any block to each home location.
So it has to be the case right,
the cache does not evict any block that sits in the log.
Does that make sense?
So the solution is don't evict blocks, those are in the log.
And this is exactly what you were [showing] a little bit earlier
and said I didn't want to talk about, so you go to log_write.
Again just to see for a second there,
log_write here log_write again
and here we see this call to bpin, and what do you think bpin does,
name sort of indicates it.
It [bends] the block in the, in the cache.
Yeah, how does it do it, since you've been looking at this where your current lab extensively.
What do you think it does.
So we can look at the implementation with bpin,
but we can also guess what it does.
Doesn't it essentially just make it, so that it doesn't get evicted by increasing the ref counts.
Yeah, exactly this is all thing does,
bpin just to increases the ref count and we know from the bcache code, correct,
evict won't evict any blocks, we have record higher than zero.
And so presumably somewhere later in a logging code,
when once actually a thing is logged,
we can actually unpin the block, right.
Okay, so that's one complication, so we have this pinning and unpinning going on.
Let's look at another complication.
And the file system operations must fit in log.
If you seem to go back to our picture here, or actually maybe this is a better picture,
how big is the log in xv6.
Thirty blocks.
Yeah, thirty blocks, 32 minus two,
so you know max size, max log size is 30.
Of course we could bump it up in real file system runs with a much bigger log,
but it doesn't really matter, no matter what it has to be the case, correct,
the file system operation must fit in 30 blocks.
Because if a system operation would try to write more to 30 blocks,
that means we would have to spill something on this location
and we're not allowed to do that,
because that would violate the write-ahead rule again.
So it has to be the case that every file system operation fits into the log.
Does that make sense?
In fact, you know how do you think we got to 32 or 30.
Does it have to do anything with how many blocks actually fit.
You were a way to like basically how many blocks does the maximum blocks correct, the file system operation could write.
And that is really what the number 30 has to be definitely bigger than any you know the max number of blocks the file system operation write.
And so, in fact you know Robert and I did, because we went through all the file system operations, looked at them
and decide whether what's the maximum number is
and it turns out that the actual number is much lower than the thirty,
but you know we'll see in a second a couple interesting complications,
like, for example the operation that we look so far like creating a file correct,
is only a handful of blocks, the file system operation is like five blocks,
in fact most operations are a handful of blocks not that many,
do you think of any operations that might write many many, many blocks.
You're right on a huge file.
Yeah right, a huge file, right,
so, what if we you know, called the write system call and we pass the buffer,
we have a megabyte of data, like a thousand blocks.
It seems like we're being serious trouble right, it would violate you know these maximum.
And so, let's look at, write, write,
sys_write calls filewrite, filewrite here's filewrite.
Okay, so here's an inode, file descriptor, inode
and bring to my code or the code that I've on the display
and notice that what does this code do.
Yeah, you read the comments write on top here and then basically explains it,
but this is what happens when the write is split in many number smaller writes.
So what really is going on here correctly,
we are ensuring that the the whole write as a whole is not atomic,
that's OK, you know the write Unix system called semantics, don't actually require that actually all the thousand blocks,
if a megabyte or actually written atomically
and user requires that we don't corrupt the file system,
between don't corrupt the file system while doing it.
And so basically we, yeah xv6 splits a big write in a number of smaller writes
and writes them as individual transactions.
And this would basically ensures that our example if transaction allocates a block number,
because we need a new block for an intermediate block were,
because we need a new block because we're going to write to it,
at least that part is completely atomic and the file system will be never left in an incorrect state,
violating any of the file system invariance.
And so the write is displayed in many, many, many system in many smaller writes or many transactions.
Okay.
In fact, that's the main one that actually is write fs split in many, many transactions.
Any questions about this?
A note because you know things are pins correct in cache that means also that
the block cache was may bigger than the [reader] through the block size.
Okay.
So now the final challenge that I want to talk about is a concurrent file system calls.
And the issue as follows,
let me first try to explain what the problem is and then we'll see what the solution is.
So let's say we have our log.
And, and we're writing and maybe there are two transactions executing concurrently.
And usually imagine for a second, that you know they read a lot of blocks,
so really t0 is executing t0 is executing and there also is the beginning of the log, here end of log.
And, you know t1 executes some blocks and etc, etc,
and by the time we run to the end of the log, neither one is complete,
yet you know, so both have still more writes to do.
And, at this point, can we commit any of the two transactions.
No, we can't correct, because if we would commit a transaction that is partially done.
Then we violate the write-ahead rule again
and you know the whole purpose [action] log in there doesn't work out.
So it has to be the case, that basically a number of concurrent transactions must fit in the log,
in fact all concurrent operations, must fit.
And so, in the way,
so this is sort of a challenge correct,
we have a file system called starting and you know we gotta arranged basically the that we, we basically do a sort of a an entrance you know check,
you know before we actually let the file system operation go,
we must check whether there actually is enough blocks still,
you know if we have n file system operations already in progress,
we have to make sure that if we add an, allow one more guy to start,
that actually the total number of blocks right, they could write together actually fits in the log.
And the way you know basically xv6 you know gets around this, basically limits the number of concurrent file system calls.
And the way it basically works is that, and begin_op you would see, how many outstanding concurrent files with transaction are in progress,
if there are too many in progress, we just stock the current file system operation and goes to sleep
and it will wait until all the other guys are done and have committed.
And all the other guys will commit together,
in fact you know at some point t1 to two, they're basically done,
maybe freeze into two, they finish
and then basically in all these transactions and in single a single [] basically committed together.
This is sometimes called group commit.
Because you're committing multiple system calls, you know all the ones that were concurrent in action,
you committed together as a single big transactions, so that older updates are visible.
So that although they all place all [] [] take place or none of them take place.
Okay.
and we see that at you, if you go to.
A quick question.
Yeah.
That is a group commit, this group to commit necessary,
but could you say if one system calls finish first, just commit it's it's transaction
and then commit other ones later,
or is it a necessary property.
You gotta be very careful,
because you remember one thing I didn't really state it explicitly as a goal early on is
that we basically execute the system calls still in the write order.
Right, if a if a if a reader observes write and then those are write,
then it has to be the case that that second write happens later than the first write.
And the reason that this is a log correct,
because that basically reflects the order in which the writes haven't happened.
And so you can really really nearly changed the order of the writes in the log,
because that made me actually result into [bizarre] behavior, observable by user programs.
And so it has to be the case that basically you commit,
you know the operations of these actions in the order they happened.
We also perform the writes in the order they happened.
And so in general you know, it's, it's safer,
you know it's safe to basically commit them all together you're always in good shape.
Okay. good question, though.
Okay I just want to go back to one more thing,
and then look at the begin_op yet I talked a little bit,
because like all [] I don't even want to talk about it right now.
But, there we can see.
So here's the begin_op, first of all, if we're already committing the log,
we're just gonna wait until the log has committed,
because you know we can't write to the log while the lock actually being installed.
If we're end, concurrent operation that basically makes us go across the block size,
we could go to sleep, and wait until basically all the preceding concurrent transactions are done,
and if we're allowed to proceed basically our [entrance] is allowed,
we increase log.outstanding by one,
because they reflect our thing and then we basically proceed and start doing file system operations.
And if you look at end_op again just to.
So you see the end_op basically decreases log.outstanding by one because one transaction is finished.
It certainly would be an error in [creating] states with panic in that case
and we actually are the last one from that set of concurrent transactions.
Then, actually, and lockouts and goes to zero, we immediately start committing.
And then when we're done, we're when actually, if we're not the log, yeah, yeah we commit.
And if there's space you know left, we wake up the guy so they can actually start running.
Okay.
So even though this dirt simple file system, that are just dirt simple logging system that xv6 actually has a bunch of complications.
So I'm starting to run out of time, so let me wrap up here.
So in summary, you know what we what we talk about is basically logging,
as a solution for, for crash safety, or really for multi step file system operations.
And you know if you've seen so far, it works great for crash safety,
but you know performance, and that's going to be the topic for Monday
and as you read the ext3 file system paper for Monday,
you know that's the thing you should be thinking about.
Okay any more final questions,
in fact anybody who has to leave, please feel free to leave,
but if you want to hang around and ask more questions, you know, please do so.
Oh, I have a question regarding cache size and the log size,
so you said that the cache size has to be a place as big as the log size,
but they seem to be the same size for this case,
so that means that if the log pins 30 buffers and then some other operation tries to do something,
it just fails because it it runs out of a free [spots] in the buffet.
No, maybe let's let's look at the,
okay so,
let me first check one thing.
Okay, let's go to bio.
Yeah, okay.
Let's actually first check NBUF is bigger than size of [match], [excitedly] buffer cache,
okay, so it's set up to something big.
So what happens actually if we can't find bget and find a buffer, actually it's panics.
And, so we we, there's no free slot in the buffer cache,
you know xv6 expense that's not particularly ideal,
in fact would be terrible and so you hope never to be in this situation
and hopefully picked numbers correctly basically is unlikely to happen.
But why can't we return an error.
Because that seems like the obvious thing to do,
like, is return an error to the caller and the caller, maybe returns back up to the file system interface
and just return minus one saying like oh this operation failed.
Why is that a problem?
So ready to think about this is that you know many file system operations are multi-step operations, right.
As we've seen now, in this lecture and in the previous lecture
and let's say, we did two writes and then the third write,
we run into this case, where we can actually do the write,
because there's no place in the block cache.
We have done two writes, right.
Can we just [bail] out of the file system call.
Okay I see right.
We cannot correct, because we might have updated to in the directory, directory block of some file,
if we might have to update the directory block in some directory,
and if we wanted to make this work,
what we would have to do is undo those changes, like any writes that we did before,
as part of that system call, we have to undo.
Okay.
That was painful, that's what we don't do it.
Does that make sense.
Okay so it's not a problem,
if they log the log pins everything and there's no more space for cache,
but it will just panic, okay.
Yeah, of course this panic never really happen, like there's a only a [corner] cases where this hopefully happens.
I guess you just,
okay, yeah that makes sense okay, thank you.
Any more questions?
I have a question about,
I guess following up my earlier one about the group commits,
I was trying to think of, like I think I kind of understand it a high level was trying to make sure
I understand concrete example, why it is important
and may is this an example that kind of demonstrates its,
like I guess I was thinking of a situation where you have say like this might be convoluted,
like one process generating a stream of numbers like one through n and then two processes consuming,
that maybe they're listening on the same pipe,
and say like n like stops an even number,
one process is consuming and printing out the odd numbers, one process is consuming part of the even numbers,
and if you didn't have group commits,
so like the correct behavior and say they're printing it for like their writing the same file.
Um.
And so the correct behavior would be at the end of at the end of all this,
you would expect the file to have like an even number, the last number,
but if you didn't have group commits,
it's possible that the second [to last] process actually gets committed after the last one and it actually see nine,
is just like a correct example, why this is important.
I think I have to think a little bit more carefully about it,
but that is definitely the flavour of the problem,
you might run into if you reorder system calls.
Okay, okay.
I have a great example in the lecture note,
if the lecture notes you know shell command that really you know behave weirdly if you didn't commit to,
this is not really an issue in some sense from group commit,
is really an issue that transactions need to be committed in order.
Mhm, I see, and group if he didn't have group commit, then.
Yeah, people might think like well what if you don't have group commit,
then there's a temptation to basically you know commit some later transaction,
because it's already finished, but the first one isn't finished yet,
and to create space,
but that's not a solution.
Okay, that makes sense,
where in the lecture notes this example of.
I think shell command, where were illustrated by ordering is important.
Okay.
It doesn't, it doesn't tie it directly to a group commits,
but it basically makes the point that ordering system calls is important.
I see, is this in the the like the text.