Alright.
The sort of underlying topic for today is
really getting multi-core, getting good multi-core performance,
getting good performance on multi-core hardware,
and that's actually very interesting and deep fascinating topic,
with many many different interesting aspects.
Today, we're just gonna bite off a fairly small piece,
and that's how to get a good performance for shared data in the kernel,
that's read much more often than it's written.
And it turns out there's many kinds of specific cases,
in which different ideas for getting good multi-core performance are useful.
We're gonna look at today is Linux's RCU,
which has been very successful,
for sort of read heavy data, read heavy kernel data.
The general sort of background here is that,
if you have modern machines
with four eight or sixteen or 64 or however many cores,
running in parallel and sharing memory,
the the kernel is really a parallel process, it's a parallel program,
and if you're going to get good performance,
you need to make sure that the kernel can run a lot of its work
as much as possible in parallel on different cores,
in order to get that much more,
if you can run the kernel parallel on eight cores,
all of them doing useful work,
you can get eight times the performance,
than if the kernel could only run a single core.
And, at a high level, this should clearly be possible,
if you have lots and lots of processes running on your computer,
the, first of all, the processes are running and executing in the kernel,
then we have very little to worry about,
they're likely to run in parallel
without any kernel having to do anything,
if the processes if you have many applications running,
and they're all making system calls a lot of the time,
different system calls made by different processes
just seem like they ought to be independent,
and should be able to proceed in many cases,
though certainly not all,
but should be able to proceed completely without interference,
like if two processes are forking,
or two processes are reading different pipes
or you know reading or writing different files,
there's no obvious reason why they should interfere with each other,
why they shouldn't be able to execute in parallel at n times the total throughput.
But the problem is the kernel has a lot of shared resources,
in order to, you know for other good reasons,
the kernel shares a lot of resources,
like memory and CPU and disk cache and inode cache,
and all this other stuff that's actually under the hood shared between different processes,
and that means that even if two processors are doing system calls,
two processes that have totally never heard of each other
and aren't trying to interact make system calls,
if those system calls happen to allocate memory or use disk cache,
more involve scheduling decisions,
they may well end up both using data structures in the kernel,
and therefore we need some story
for how they're both supposed to use the same data
without getting underfoot, without interfering with each other,
and there's been enormous effort over the years,
and making kernels, making all these cases and kernels run fast.
We've seen one of course that's oriented towards correctness namely spin locks,
spin locks are straightforward,
as such things go and easy to reason about,
but you know what spin lock does is prevent execution,
it prevents, its job is to prevent parallelism,
in cases where there might be a problem between two processes,
so spin locks are just directly away to decrease performance,
that's all they do.
Of course, they make it easy to reason about correctness,
but they absolutely prevent parallel execution,
and you know that's not always that desirable.
Okay, so again we're going to focus on read heavy data,
on the case in which
your data that's mostly read and relatively rarely written.
And the main example in use is a linked list, a singly linked list,
and so you can think of just a standard link to,
this diagram,
there's some sort of maybe global variable, that's a pointer, head pointer,
just a pointer and there's a bunch of list elements,
and each list element has some data
and I'll just say it's a string,
like you know "hello" is this sort of data in this element,
and each element also has a next pointer,
that points the next list element,
and then finally there's a pointer that points to zero to mark the end,
very straightforward.
And again we're gonna assume that,
most uses of this list that we're interested in are just reads,
you know the the kernel thread or whatever it is that's using this list,
is just scanning the list looking for something,
not trying to modify the list.
And occasional writers though,
you know all if there were zero writers ever,
we wouldn't need to have to worry about this at all,
because it'll be a completely static list, never changes,
we can read it freely,
but we're going to imagine that,
every once in a while,
somebody comes along and wants to write the list.
So that may mean that,
some other thread wants to change the data stored in a list element,
or maybe delete an element,
or maybe insert a new element somewhere.
So even though, it's we're aiming at a mostly reads,
we do have to worry about writes,
we need to make the reads safe in the face of writes.
Of course, in xv6,
we just have a lock protecting this list,
and a reader, that you know not only would writers,
in xv6, not only would writers have to acquire the lock,
but readers would have to acquire the lock too,
because we're going to rule out the situation,
in which while we're reading somebody's actually modifying the list,
because that could cause sort of the reader to see half updated value
or follow an invalid pointer or something.
So in xv6 we have locks,
but, that has a defect,
that if the common cases there's no writers,
it means that every time somebody comes along and reads,
in xv6, they grab an exclusive, like xv6 spin locks are exclusive,
even if you have just two readers,
only one of them can proceed at a time,
so what we'd like,
sort of one way to improve this situation,
would be to have a new kind of lock,
that allows multiple readers, but only one writer.
So I explore those next,
actually both because they're interesting,
because they they help motivate the need for RCU,
we'll talk about in a little while.
So there's, this notion called read write locks,
and the interface is a little more complicated than the spin locks we're used to,
we're going to imagine that there's one set of call,
that you call if you just want to read something,
so we're gonna imagine r_lock call and pass a lock
and then also an r_unlock call,
and readers call these.
And then there's a w_lock call and a w_unlock call,
and the semantics are that
you can either have multiple readers acquire the lock for reading,
so we do then would get parallelism,
or you can have exactly one writer have acquired the lock,
but you can never have a mix,
you can never have be in,
the locks rule out the possible,
read, read write locks rule out the possibility
of somebody having locked the lock for writing and also reading at the same time,
you're either one writer or lots of readers, but nothing else.
So that's the.
A question.
Yes.
This may be an implementation detail,
but what kind of mechanisms does this locking scheme put in place
to prevent someone writing, while they hold a read lock.
Nothing, nothing, it's just like xv6 locks, completely.
We're talking about kernel code written by trusted responsible developers
and so just like spin locks in xv6,
if the code is using locks incorrect, it's incorrect, there's no.
Okay.
And this is the way you know typical kernels are written,
you just have to assume that,
people developing the kernel are following their own rules.
Okay.
Okay, and again the reason why we care is that,
if we have a mostly read mostly data structure,
we'd love to have multiple readers be able to use it at the same time
to get genuine speedup from having multiple cores.
Alright, so, if there were no problem here,
this would just be the answer,
we wouldn't have needed to read today's paper,
but it turns out that,
if you dig into the details of what actually happens,
when you use read write locks,
especially for data that's actually read a lot,
there's some problems.
And in order to see what's going on,
we actually have to look at the implementation.
Linux indeed has a read/write lock implementation in it,
and this is a kind of simplified version of the Linux code.
The idea is that we have a struct rwlock,
which is like struct lock in xv6,
and it has a count in it,
if the count is 0,
that means that the lock is not held by anybody in any form,
if the count is -1,
that means that a writer has it locked,
and if the count is greater than 0,
that means that n readers have it locked,
and we need to keep track of them,
because we can only let a writer in,
if the number of readers descends to 0.
Okay, so somebody asked about addings.
No, I'm not sure if there's a question in the chat,
interrupt me if there is.
The read lock function, that's sit in a loop,
because if there's a writer,
we have to wait for the writer,
it looks,
it grabs a copy of the current n value,
if this less than 0, that means there's a writer,
and we just need to continue our loop, gonna spin,
waiting for the writer to go away,
otherwise we want to increment that value,
but we only want to increment it,
if it's still greater than or equal to 0,
so we can't, there's many things we can't do,
we can't, for example, just add one,
with standard n equals n plus one,
because if a writer sneaks in,
between when we check the value of n and when we actually try to increment it,
then we may actually go ahead and increment it,
at the same time, that some writer is setting it to -1,
which is wrong.
So we need to increment it,
only if it hasn't changed value since we checked it
and verified that is greater than or equal to 0,
and the way people do that is,
they take advantage of special atomic or interlocked instructions,
which you saw before,
for the, for implementation of spin locks in xv6.
And the interlocked instruction,
that's one that's particularly convenient to use as something called compare and swap,
the idea is the compare and swap takes three arguments,
the address of some location of memory that we want to act on,
the value that we think it holds
and the value that we'd like it to hold.
And the semantics of compare and swap are that,
the hardware checks,
the hardware first sort of basically sets an internal lock,
that makes only one compare and swap executed a time on a given memory location,
then the hardware checks that the current value of that location is indeed still x,
and if it still x,
sets it to this third argument, which is going to be x plus one,
and then the instruction yields one, its value,
if compare and swap observes that the current value isn't x,
then it doesn't change the value the memory location,
and it returns 0.
So this is basically an atomic,
if the location is x, set to x plus one.
It has to be atomic,
because there's really two things going on,
the hardware is checking the current value and setting it to a new value.
Any questions about compare and swap?
I have a question,
if there would be a reader and r_lock needs to continue,
would w_unlock reset the value back to x.
Um, w_unlock, if there's a writer,
w_unlock, which I'm afraid it shows set n to 0,
because there can only be one writer.
If there's what r_unlock does is
use another compare and swap to decrement n.
Okay, because, what happens,
if writer locks lock between when x is being computed and.
So, right here?
No, between the if and x somehow.
Okay, okay, it's, I'm not sure I understand exactly what time you're asking,
but it's absolutely good question,
what happens if w_lock is called somewhere during this sequence.
And for me the most dangerous time for w_lock to be called is
after this check, but before the compare and swap.
So, let's imagine that read lock has done,
as far as seeing that x, that x or l->n is 0.
Okay, so maybe we're right, we're right here,
and x is equal to 0.
We've already checked, the check is finished,
and then right at this time on another core,
some other thread calls w_lock,
and it actually gets its compare and swap in first.
So on the other core is trying to grab the write lock,
compare and swap is going to see if l->n is 0,
let's assume that n is 0, so this test is true,
and the compare and swap is on that other core
is going to set n to -1,
now the locks locked,
but we still think that n is 0 in this code,
even the locks locked.
And now we're gonna execute,
back on the reading core,
We're going to execute compare and swap,
but we're going to pass 0 here right,
this is the value we actually,
we're going to pass in the value we actually looked at,
not the current value of n.
And when we looked at it it was zero,
so we're going to pass 0 here,
and we'll telling compare and swap,
look only add one to,
only set it to 1, if its current value is 0.
But it's not 0, at this point, it's -1,
and so this compare and swap fails,
does not modify n, returns 0,
and so that means we'll go back to the top of this loop and try again,
of course now n is -1.
This may be related to the previous question a bit,
but, is it possible for an interrupt to occur,
when that x plus 1 is being computed in the CAS parameter or CAS parameter?
You mean before we actually execute CAS,
but while we're computing its arguments?
Right, so like you compute,
you pass in the x argument and that's okay,
but you before you compute the x plus 1
or while you're computing x plus 1,
an interrupt occurs.
Okay.
And the x plus 1 is wrong.
So, if an interrupt occurs while we're computing x plus 1,
that means we haven't,
CAS is actually an instruction,
it's a single machine instruction,
so for computing x plus 1,
that means we haven't called CAS yet.
If the interrupt happens and all kinds of things may happen,
we're going to get the same,
if we originally read zero here, right,
then interrupt or no interrupt,
we're gonna pass 1 as this third argument,
because interrupts not going to [reach out] and change,
this is a local, this x is a local variable for this code,
so interrupt context which anything is not gonna change x.
So that means we're going to pass 0 and 1 here,
and you know if n is still 0,
then we'll set it to one,
and that's that's what we want,
if it's not still 0,
then compare and swap won't change it.
Right, I guess you would have problems,
if you didn't set that local variable.
If you used l l->n here, l->n plus 1,
you would almost certainly be in big trouble,
because then n could change underfoot at any time,
that's why we actually grab a copy n,
grab a copy here in order to fix a specific value.
Yes.
Okay.
If two readers,
okay, so I covered the case
of whatever writer calls the same,
w_lock is called the same time as r_lock,
it's also interesting to wonder
what if r_lock is called at the same time.
So supposing the n starts at 0,
we know if two r_locks are called at the same time,
what we want is for n to end up with value 2,
and for both r_locks to return,
that's what we want,
because we want two readers to, be able to execute in parallel,
to use the data in parallel.
Okay, so, they're both gonna see 0 at this point.
So, at this point, both of them are going to have x equal to 0,
they're both gonna call compare and swap with 0 and 1.
Only one of those two compare and swap hopefully,
exactly one of those to compare and swaps will succeed,
whichever one,
you know compare and swap it's an atomic instruction,
the only one of them happens at a time on a given memory location,
so whichever will compare and swap is first we'll see,
that n is equal to 0, and will set it to 1,
the other cores simultaneous call to r_lock,
it's compare and swap will then execute
and it'll still pass zero and one here,
but n will now be equal to 1,
and so the compare and swap will fail for the second core and return 0,
the second core will go back to the top of this loop,
at this point it will be 1,
that's not less than zero,
so we'll go on to compare and swap,
and now it'll pass 1 and 2,
and now the second read lock will succeed,
both of them will have the lock.
So the first one succeeded, the first try,
the second one actually go back to the loop and try again.
Any questions?
Oh, sorry, so it is somehow possible that,
so a bunch of reads come,
and they they're reading their stuff,
and then a write also comes and it also wants to write,
but then some other reads also come after the write,
but then somehow the reads outrun the write,
and the write still has to wait somehow.
Yes, so so if the sequence is that,
a reader managed to acquire the lock,
one or more readers have the locks,
now n, you know each of them is called a compare and swap,
you know adds one to n for each reader,
so now n is greater than 0,
because there's multiple readers,
if a writer tries to acquire the lock at this point,
the writer's compare and swap, the compare value is 0,
so compare and swap will only change n to -1,
if its current value is 0.
But we know the current,
because there's multiple readers,
the current value of n is not 0,
and so the compare and swap will fail and returns zero,
then the writer will sit here in this loop,
basically waiting until n is equal to 0,
before it's compare and swap will succeed,
and return and give the lock to the writer.
So this certainly means the writer can be starved,
there's a lot of readers and may never be 0
and so the write may never succeed,
so that's a defect in this locking scheme.
Thank you.
I also have a question
about the the two readers scenario that I just mentioned,
it appears that in the worst case,
the reader that arrives second has to go through another iteration of the loop,
sounds somewhat wasteful,
I wonder if this generalizes to n writers.
It's certainly does.
They all have to get lost and start again.
You put your finger on why people don't like this scheme,
if there's a lot of simultaneous reader,
and so for for the reason you just mentioned,
r_lock, even if there's no writers at all,
if there's lots of readers, readers on many cores,
r_lock can be very very expensive,
and one thing you need to know about r_lock scheme,
which I think we've already mentioned in class is that,
on a multi-core system, every core has an associated cache,
we'll say L1 cache,
so each core has a bit of cache memory,
and whatever reads or writes something,
it's in the cache,
so there may be lots and lots of cores,
and there's some kind of interconnect network,
that allows the cores to talk to each other,
because of course if lots of cores have some data cached,
and one of the cores writes that data,
the writing core has to tell the other cores,
that they're not allowed to cache the data anymore,
it is called invalidation.
So what actually happens if you have n readers,
and people calling r_lock at about the same time on n cores.
They're all gonna read n, sorry this l->n value,
and load this memory location into their caches.
They're all gonna call compare and swap,
what the first one to actually call compare and swap is going to modify the data,
but in order to modify the data
has to invalidate all these other copies,
and so the compare and swap instruction that,
one has to send out an invalidate message over this little network
to each of the other n cores, right,
and then it returns all the other cores, the n minus 1 cores,
they have, their compare and swaps now actually have re-read
again requiring traffic over the network,
re-read this data, this memory location,
compared with x they have failed,
because they all call x with 0,
then the remaining n minus 1 readers go back to the top of loop,
and all n minus 1 of them again read the data,x
and again one of them writes it, right,
so on each, so there's going to be n times through the loop,
once for each core trying to acquire the lock,
each of those [trips] through the loop
involves order n messages on the network,
because at least every copy of the cached l->n has to be invalidated.
And that means that the total cost for n cores to acquire a particular lock,
even for reading is order n,
that means as you increase the number of cores for a popular piece of data,
the cost for everybody lock it just once goes up,
sorry, order n squared,
the total cost and time or messages sent over this interconnect is n squared.
And this is a very bad deal, right,
you would hope that,
if you needed to do something ten times,
you know ten different cores needed to do something,
especially given that they're just reading the list,
they're not modifying it,
you'd hope that they could really run in parallel,
that is the total [] clock time for 16 cores to read something,
should be the same as the total [] clock time for one core read something,
because that's getting parallelism means is that,
you can do things at the same time.
But here the more cores are try to read this,
the more expensive the lock acquisition is,
and so what's going on is that,
this style of locks has converted read only access to data,
you know the list is probably sitting in the cache already,
because nobody's modifying the list, right.
So the actual access to the list might only take a few dozen cycles,
but if the data is popular,
getting the lock can take hundreds or thousands of cycles,
because of this n squared effect.
And the fact that instead of it being cache x,
it's these accesses that have to go over the bus, this interconnect,
in order to invalidate and do these cache coherence operations.
So this these locks have turned very cheap read only access to data,
into an extremely expensive read write access to this data.
And will probably completely destroy any possible parallel performance,
if what you were doing,
if the actual data was fairly simple to read,
lock will dominate and destroy parallel performance.
So any questions about this performance story?
In a sense you know the bad performance of read write locks
is the reason for the existence of RCU,
because if this was efficient,
then there would be no need to do better than that right,
but it's terribly inefficient.
And it's there's two things going on,
one is the details of this,
so there needs to be a total of n squared trips through this loop,
if we have n cores,
sort of one way of looking at it.
The other way of looking at it is that,
we're writing,
you know regardless of the details of what's going on here,
these locks have turned a read only access,
which could be cached and extremely fast
into an access that one way or another involves a write,
one or more writes,
and writes are just much more expensive than reads,
if we're writing data that might be shared with other cores.
Because a read for data that's not modify,
it can be satisfied in a couple cycles out of your own cache,
a write, any write to data that may be cached by other cores,
has to involve communication between cores to invalidate other copies.
So no matter how you slice it,
anything that involves a write to share data is a disaster for performance,
if you otherwise could have been read only.
So the details of this loop,
are sort of less important than the fact that it did a write to share data.
So what we're looking for is a way
to be able to read data without writes, right,
we want to be able to scan that list without doing any writes,
what so ever, including any writes,
that might be required to do some kind of locking thing,
they were looking for really really read only access to data.
Okay.
So one possibility, that's a possibility,
but it's sort of a thought experiment is
we just have the readers not bother locking,
you know occasionally you get lucky
and it turns out that readers can read stuff,
and that only writers need to lock.
So we'll just do a quick experiment to see,
whether we could have a lock,
just have readers just read the list without locking it.
I suppose we have this list and it has some you know strings.
And, we're gonna read it,
okay, so nothing goes wrong if there's no writer, right,
just read list, it's not a problem.
So we have to imagine there's a writer,
and there's probably three cases,
if you read a list while some other cores modifying it,
so one case is that,
the writer is just changing the content,
that is not adding or deleting anyone is necessarily,
a writer is changing the string to be some other string.
So, one is the writers changing the content,
two is the writer is inserting a new list element,
and the third case is if the writer is deleting a list element.
And I want to examine these,
because we need a [story] for each of RCU
actually kind of has a [story] for each.
So, the danger,
so I'm just talking about what goes wrong,
if somebody's reading a list while another cores writing it,
if the writer wants to just change this string,
then the danger is that the reader will be actually reading the bytes of this string
or whatever else is in the list element,
while the writer is modifying the same bytes.
And so if we don't do anything special,
the reader will see some mixture of the old bytes and the new bytes,
and that's probably a disaster,
that's one case we have to worry about.
Another possibility is that the writer is inserting a new element,
of course what that means is that,
you know supposing the writer wants to insert the new element at the head,
the writers going to cook up some new element
going to change the head pointer to point to it,
I'm going to change the new element to point at the old first element, right,
so the danger here,
if a reader reads, reading list while writers inserting,
is that maybe you know if we really blow it,
the the writer may set the head pointer to point to the new element,
before the new elements initialized,
that is why it may be contains garbage for the string
or some illegal pointer as the next element.
So that's the thing that could go wrong for writer's inserting.
So let's, and the writer's deleting,
then, you know what it means to delete an element
is first to change let's say deleting the first element,
we change the head pointer to point to the second element,
and then call free on the first element
to return this to the free list,
and the danger here,
you know if the reader sees the new head pointer, that's fine,
they're just gonna go on to the second element,
so the first if the reader actually was looking at the first element
and then the writer freed it,
then the problem we have is
now the readers looking at element that's on the free list,
and could be allocated for some other use
and overwritten for some completely other use,
while the readers still looking at this element.
So from the reader point of view,
now all of a sudden elements filled with garbage
and said it was [expecting],
so that's the third case, we have to.
If we want to have lock,
we want have absolutely no locks for readers,
we have to worry about these three situations.
I'm not talking about writer versus writer problems here,
because I'm just assuming for this entire lecture,
that writers still use locks,
there's still some ordinary like xv6 style spin lock here,
and writers acquire this lock before doing anything,
but readers don't require any locks, whatsoever.
Questions about these dangers?
Okay.
The point is we can't just simply have readers read with no locks,
but it turns out we can and fix the specific problems,
and that takes us to RCU.
RCU has a couple of ideas in it that,
RCU is, by the way, it's as much a kind of approach to concurrency, concurrency control
as it is a particular algorithm,
it's a way of structuring approach structuring readers and writers.
So that they can get along with the readers not having to take locks.
The general game with read copy update is
we're going to fix those three situations,
in which readers might get into trouble if there's a concurrent writers,
and we're going to do it by making the writers a little bit more complicated.
So the writers going to end up somewhat slower,
they still need to lock plus follow some extra rules,
but the reward will be the readers will be dramatically faster,
because they can operate without locks
and without ever writing memory.
Okay, so the first big idea in RCU is that,
in that first trouble situation, we talked about before,
where the writer is updating a list element, the content of a list element,
we're going to actually outlaw that,
we're going to say writers are not allowed to modify the contents of a list elements,
instead if we have a linked list like this, with a couple of elements.
If a writer wanted to update the content of element 2,
instead of changing it in place, which wouldn't do,
it would actually cook up, it would call the allocator to allocate a new element,
it would initialize the element completely,
so whatever new content you know we wanted to put here,
instead the old content,
the writer would set the next pointer on this new element,
so that this new element is now completely correct looking,
and then in a single write to E1's next pointer,
the writer would switch E1 from pointing to the,
from pointing to the old version of E2,
to pointing to the new version of E2.
So the game is instead of updating things in place,
we're going to replace them with new versions of the same data.
And so so now a reader, you know readers got as far as E1
is just looking at E1's next pointer,
the reader's going to either see the old next pointer which points to E2
and that's fine,
because nobody was changing E2,
or the reader's going to see the new next pointer
and look at the new list element.
And either way since the writer initial fully initialized this list element,
before setting E1's next pointer,
either way, the readers going to see a correct next pointer, that points to E3.
So the point is the reader will never see a string,
that's in the process of being a content that's in the process of being modified.
There's any questions about this particular idea?
What about the, sorry.
Okay, I can go ahead,
will the the link between E2 and E3 be deleted,
or will it be left there
in case that are either somehow reached E2.
Now, we're just gonna leave it,
well I'll come to this, this excellent question,
and it's actually the main piece of complexity in RCU,
but for now we're just going to imagine that E2 is left alone for the moment.
The link from E2 to E3 we don't need to worry about it anyway right,
because that's a part of E2,
and like in normal implementations,
we just free that anyway,
like with no RCU involved,
we don't ever need to worry about that link, right.
But the danger is that,
that just before we changed this next pointer,
that some reader had followed the next pointer to E2.
So overall what we're worried about here is that,
some some reader on some cores actually right now reading E2,
so we'd better not free it.
Right right.
That's what I think that's all we're saying is
you better not free E2 right away,
just leave it alone.
As a piece of jargon,
the write,
the swap of e E1's next pointer from the old E2 to the new E2,
I in my head I call this a committing write,
there's a,
this is then part of the reason why this works is that,
with a single committing write, which is atomic,
writes to pointers on the machines we use are atomic,
in the sense that either the write to the pointer happen or didn't happen,
from the perspective of readers,
because they're atomic,
basically with one instruction,
with the one atomic store we can,
it's an ordinary store,
but it's indivisible,
we switch E1 from point to old,
the next point from pointing to the old one,
the new one that write is what sort of commits us to,
now using the second version.
This is a very basic technique,
a very important technique for RCU,
and what it means is that,
RCU is really mostly applicable to data structures,
for which you can have single committing writes.
So that means there's some data structures which are quite awkward in the scheme,
like a doubly linked list,
where every element is pointed to from two different pointers,
now we can't get rid of a list elements with a single committing write,
because there's two pointers to it,
we can't, on most machines we can't atomically
change two different memory locations at the same time,
so doubly lists are not so good for RCU.
A data structure that is good as a tree,
and if you have a tree of,
a tree of nodes like this,
then we can do,
suppose we want to change,
want to modify this value down here,
what we can do,
there's some head to the tree,
what we can do is
cook up a new a new version of this part of the tree here,
and with a single committing write to the head pointer,
switch to the new version of the tree,
and so the new version of the tree,
which will you know the writer will allocate, sort of create,
can actually share for, convenience share structure,
the unmodified part with the old tree,
and then with a single committing write,
we're going to change the head pointer to
a tree head pointer to point to the new version.
But for other data structures,
that don't look like the trees,
it's not so easy to use RCU.
Okay, that's the first idea.
Any other questions?
The second idea,
One of the problems with,
one of the potential problems with this scheme I just described,
and we're gonna cook up a new E2 [],
and what I said was oh well we'll initialize the content for E2 [],
and we'll you know set its next pointer, correctly,
and after that we'll set E1's next pointer to point to E2,
as you may recall from discussions of xv6,
by default, there's no after that on these machines,
the compiler and the hardware,
basically all compilers and many microprocessors reorder memory operations.
So, if you simply you know say we allocate a new element,
and we just wrote this C code, you know e->next equals you know E3,
and then E1->next equals e,
this is not going to work well,
it's not gonna work reliably,
it's gonna work fine when you test it,
but it won't work in real life all the time,
occasionally it will go wrong.
And the reason is that the compiler may end up reordering these writes
or the machine may end up reordering these writes
or the reading code which reads these various things,
the compiler or the machine, the microprocessor may end up reordering the reader's reads,
and of course if we set E1->next to point E2
before we initialize the content of E2,
so that it's string holds its next pointer, point off into space,
then some readers going to see this pointer,
follow with read garbage and crash.
So the second idea is that,
both readers and writers have to use memory barriers,
you know even though we're not locking or really because we're not locking,
read, the writers and the readers have to use a barrier,
and for writers the place the barrier has to go is before the committing write.
So we need a barrier here,
tells the hardware and the compiler look all the writes before this barrier,
please finish them before doing any writes after the barrier.
So that E2 is fully initialized,
before we set E1 to point to it.
And on the read side,
the reader needs to load E1->next into some temporary location or register,
so we'll just say register one equals E1->next,
then the reader needs a barrier,
and then the reader is going to look at r1->x,
it's content in r1->next.
And with this barrier, the reader says is
don't issue any of these loads until after we've completed this load.
So the reader's gonna look at E1->next
and either get the old E2 or the new E2,
and then the barrier says that,
only then are we going to start looking at,
only after we've grabbed this,
all these reads have to execute after this read.
And since the writer guaranteed to initialize the content
before committing the pointer to the new E2,
that means these reads,
if this pointer points to the new E2,
that means these reads are guaranteed to see the initialized content.
Okay, so we saw a little bit.
How can you, oh sorry,
I was just, I was confused about the reader,
so how, how can you read r1,
r1 like anything before you read r1.
I guess how how would they,
so yeah, I guess like if even if it rewarded that,
how, how did be able to read r1->x before it read r1->next?
You, I think you've stumped me.
Yeah, I mean what were you pointing out is that,
before you even know what the pointer is
you can't possibly actually issue the reads,
the, a possibility is that whatever this pointer points to,
maybe it's already cached on this core,
due to some maybe this memory had been
you know a minute ago used for something else, something totally else,
and we have an old version of this cache our core,
at the address at this address,
but for some previous use of the memory,
if this read was to use the old cache value,
I'm not sure this can happen,
just making this up for you.
But if this really could use the old cache value,
then we'd be in big trouble.
And I don't know if the machine would actually do that or whether.
Another possibility is that the compiler,
you know, the real answer is I don't know,
I should go off and think about what a specific example would be.
Okay, okay, I see, the cache version, makes sense, yeah.
I'm not actually completely sure it could could happen in real life.
That's a good question.
Okay, that's the second idea.
The third problem we have which something somebody raised before
is that the writer is going to swap the E1 pointer to point to the new E2,
but there could be readers, you know who started looking at follow this pointer,
just before we change the writer changed,
who are still looking at E2.
We need to free this list element someday,
but we'd better not free it while some readers still using it,
so we need to somehow wait
until the last reader has finished using E2,
before we can free it.
And that's the third and final main problem that RCU solves,
how long should a writer wait before it frees E2.
There's you could imagine a number of ways of doing this,
for example we could put a reference count in every list element
and have readers increment it,
and have writers wait,
reader's increment when they start using list element,
decrement it, when they're done using the list element,
and have the writer wait for the reference count on this element go to 0,
we would regret that instantly,
because the whole point of RCU is to allow reading without writing.
Because we know that if lots of readers are changing this reference count
is going to be terribly expensive to do the writes involved in maintaining a reference count,
so we absolutely don't want reference counts.
Another possibility would be to use a garbage collected language,
and in a garbage collected language,
you don't ever free anything explicitly,
instead the garbage collector does the bookkeeping required
to decide if any thread
for example any data structure has still has a reference to this element,
and the garbage collector once it proves this element can't possibly be ever used again,
only then will the garbage collector free this,
so that's another quite possibly reasonable scheme
for deciding when to free this list element.
You know Linux which uses RCU,
it's not written in a garbage collected language, so.
And we're not even sure that garbage collection would be would improve performance,
so we can't use a standard garbage collector here,
instead, RCU uses another sort of a trick,
that works well in the kernel for delaying freeze.
And so that idea is that,
the readers and writers have to each follow a rule,
that will allow writers to delay the freeze,
readers are not allowed to hold a pointer to RCU protected data across a context switch.
So a reader is not allowed to hold a pointer,
one of those list elements across a context switch.
So the readers, they cannot yield the CPU, in a RCU critical section.
And then what the writers do is,
they delay the free until every core as context switches at least once.
So this is easy enough,
this is actually also a rule for spin locks,
in a spin lock critical section, you can't yield the CPU,
but nevertheless you have to be a bit careful.
This is a little more involved,
but it's relatively clear,
when each each cores knows this context switching,
and so this is a pretty well defined point for the writer to have to wait for.
And just requires some implementation,
this also requires this may be a significant delay
and maybe a millisecond or a significant fraction of a millisecond
that the writer has to wait, before it's allowed to free that list element,
to be sure that no reader could possibly still be using it.
People have come up with a bunch of techniques for actually implementing this wait,
though most straightforward one the paper talks about is that,
the writing thread simply arranges with the scheduler
to have the writing thread be executed briefly on every one of the cores in the system.
And what that means is that
every one of the cores must have done a context switch during this process,
and since readers can't hold stuff across context switches,
that means that the writer is now waited long enough.
And so the way the actual writer code looks like is
the writing code does whatever modifications it's going to do to the data,
and then it calls this synchronize_rcu call,
which actually implements 2.
And then the writer freeze whatever the old element was.
And so that means that the writer is doing whatever it's doing,
you know at this point,
let's say it's doing the you know the E1->next is equal to the new list element.
And so you know this synchronize_rcu causes force a context switch on every core,
so any core that could have read,
any core that could have read the old value,
must have read it at this point,
must have read it at this point in time,
if after that point in time,
we've done a context switch on every core,
that means that no core that read the old value
could still have a pointer to that value at this point in time,
due to rule one,
and that means they were allowed to free the old value.
Any questions?
You may object that this synchronize_rcu
will take a significant perhaps fraction of a millisecond,
that's quite true.
Is that, so that's too bad,
one of the justifications is that writing for RCU protected data,
writing is going to be relatively rare,
so the fact that the writes take longer
may not will probably not affect overall performance very much,
for the situations in which the writer really doesn't want to wait,
there's another call,
that that defers even a wait call call_rcu.
And the idea is you pass it the, in the usual use case,
you pass it a pointer to the object you want to free,
and then a callback function that just calls free on this pointer,
and the rcu system basically stashes away,
the call_rcu stashes away these two values on list,
and then immediately returns and then does some bookkeeping,
typically involving basically looking at
the counts of how many contexts which have occurred on each core,
the system, sort of in the background after call_rcu returns
does some bookkeeping to wait until all cores context switch,
and then calls this callback function with this argument,
and so this is a way of avoiding the wait,
because this call returns instantly.
On the other hand, you're discouraged from using it,
because now this list that,
if if the kernel calls call_rcu a lot,
then the list that holds these values can get very long,
and it means that there may be a lot of memory that's not being freed,
all the data all the,
this, this list grows very long,
each list element of is has a pointer in it that should be free
to point to an object that should be freed.
So under extreme circumstances,
you can run a system,
if you're not careful a lot of calls to rcu call_rcu,
you can run a system out of memory,
because all the memory ends up on this list of deferred freeze.
So people don't like to use this, they don't have to.
Okay, to,
please ask questions so far, if you have questions.
So, this doesn't, this prevents us free,
that prevents us from freeing something that somebody's still using,
it doesn't prevent us from modified,
like having the readers see a half-baked version of something,
because it's being modified right.
Idea 1 prevented that, yeah.
Okay.
So they they get the idea, behind the idea 1 is that,
instead of updating a list element in place,
which would absolutely cause the problem you mentioned,
when the writers are not allowed to update RCU protected data in place,
instead they cook up a new data element,
and sort of swap it into the data structure with a single committing write.
Oh, and the swapping will be atomic,
so there's no problem.
Right, because that's a single pointer, right, which is atomic,
whereas overwriting a string is completely not atomic.
That makes sense.
Other questions?
Does condition 1 in idea 3 mean
we need to be careful about how much work we put inside those protected sections,
since it kind of hogs the core for that entire section.
Yes, yes, so this is, that's right,
so, readers in the rcu critical section,
while they're looking at the protected data,
they can't context switch,
and so you're, you know you want to keep those critical sections short,
now, and that's a consideration.
The way it plays out though is that,
the way RCU has been deployed
is typically there will be some piece of code in Linux,
that was protected with ordinary locks or read write locks,
and somebody you know for some workloads,
we'll see that lock is a terrible performance problem,
and they're going to replace the locking critical section with an RCU critical section,
although sometimes it's more involved than that.
And since locking critical sections were already,
it was extremely important to make them short,
because while you hold a lock,
there may be lots of other cores waiting for that lock,
so there's a lot of pressure to keep ordinary lock critical sections short,
because RCU critical sections are often
sort of revised lock critical sections,
that used to be like critical sections,
they tend to be short also.
And you know that means that,
you know not always,
but usually there there's not a,
not a direct worry about keeping RCU critical sections short.
Although it is a constraint,
the real constraint actually you're not allowed to hold pointers over,
pointers to RCU data over context switches.
And that's actually you can't,
for example read the disks and wait for the disk wait to complete,
while while holding on a pointer, onto a pointer to RCU protected data.
So it's not quite so much,
the the thing that usually comes up is not the length of the critical section,
so much as the prohibition against yielding CPU.
Okay.
Let's see, so just kind of firm up,
but I, all the stuff I just talked about,
here's the kind of what you would see
in a simple use of RCU.
So this is code,
you might see for reading a list, and rcu protected list,
and this is the code,
you might see on the write side,
for code that just wants to a particular case of replacing the first list element,
so the read side, there is actually this,
these read_lock and read_unlock calls,
those do almost nothing, almost nothing,
the only, the only little thing they do is set a flag, that says
or rcu_read_lock sets a flag, that says,
if a timer interrupt happens, please don't context switch,
because I'm in the middle of rcu critical section.
So that's all really does
set a flag that prohibits timer interrupt context switches,
interrupts may still happen, but it wont context switch,
and then read_unlock unset flag,
really it's counter of nested RCU critical sections.
So these two functions are extremely fast and do almost nothing.
And then this loop would sort of scan down the our list,
this is the call that insert the memory barrier,
so what RCU, this really boils down to just a couple of instructions,
it just reads, it grabs a copy of this pointer from memory,
issues a memory barrier and then returns that pointer.
And then we can look at the content
and go on to the next list element.
So the readers quite simple.
The writers a little more involved,
writers still,
you know the RCU doesn't help writers avoid interfering with each other,
so writers still have to have some way
of making sure only one writer modifies the list at a time.
In this case,
I'm just imagining we're going to use ordinary spin locks,
so the writer requires the lock.
If we're replacing the first list element,
we need to save a copy at the beginning,
because we're going to need to eventually free it,
so we save this copy of the oldest element,
now we're this code plays that trick I talked again about,
allocating a complete new list element
to hold this updated content.
We're gonna allocate a new list element,
we're gonna set its content,
we're gonna set the next pointer
to the next pointer in the old first list element as we're replacing it,
and then this rcu_assign_pointer issues a memory barrier,
so that all these these writes happened,
and then sets a pointer pointed to by this first argument to be equal to that,
so basically this just issues a memory barrier
and then sets head equal to e.
Now we can release the lock,
we still have a pointer to the old first list element,
call synchronize_rcu to make sure every CPU
that could have grabbed a pointer to the oldest element,
before we did the committing write has yielded the CPU
and therefore given up its pointer RCU protected data,
and now we could free the old list element.
Any questions?
Alright.
There RCU, one thing to note about this is that,
while in the reader,
while we're allowed to look at this list element inside the loop here,
one thing we're not allowed to do is return the list element,
so for example we using RCU,
we couldn't write a lookup a list lookup function,
that returned either the list element
or a pointer into data held in the list element,
like a string that was embedded in the list element.
Because then we'd be in, then we would no longer be in control,
you know it has to be the case,
that we don't look at RCU protected data outside,
this RCU critical section or we don't do a context switch,
if we just write a generic function that returns a list element,
then for all we know the caller,
maybe we can persuade the caller to follow some rules too,
but for all we know, the caller make context switch
or we run into trouble
either we call rcu_read_unlock before returning the list element,
which is illegal,
because now a timer interrupt could force a switch,
or we don't call rcu_read_unlock.
So use of RCU sort of does put some additional constraints on readers,
that wouldn't have existed before.
A question about that.
Yes.
So, are you saying in particular,
that if we had some form of like read element at index i method,
that there's no way to structure this,
so that it couldn't return the value held by the [] element i.
It could return a copy.
So what would work, you know if e->x is a string,
we could return a copy of this string,
and that's fine,
what would be a violation of RCU rules,
if we return a pointer to this very string sitting inside,
a pointer it would be a mistake to return a pointer into somewhat into e.
If the string is stored inside the list element,
we better not return this pointer that string,
because then, that will be,
you have to not context switch,
we're holding a pointer into RCU protected data,
and the you know the convention is
you know you just use that data within this critical section.
And so it would almost certainly be breaking the convention
or this setup would have to be much more complicated,
if we ended up returning pointers into the protected data.
Thank you.
The I just want to return briefly to the performance story,
it's, it's hard to characterize sort of what the performance is,
I mean in a sense,
the, let's see the the overall performance story is that
if you use RCU, reads are extremely fast,
they just proceed at whatever,
they've served no overhead above the ordinary overhead of looking at that data,
so if your list is a billion elements long,
yeah, reading list will take a long time,
but it's not because synchronization,
is just because you're doing a lot of work for readers.
So you can almost view RCU is having zero overhead for readers
and exceptions are minor,
rcu_read_lock, you know just a tiny amount of work
to set this flag saying no context switches,
and rcu_dereference issues a memory barrier,
which actually might slow you down by dozens, few dozen cycles,
but it's much cheaper than a lock.
The performance story for writers is much sadder,
you have to do all the stuff,
you always had to do using locks,
in fact you have to acquire and release locks in the writer,
and you have this potentially extremely expensive call
or time-consuming called synchronize_rcu.
In fact you can give up,
you know internally synchronize_rcu gives up the CPU,
so you don't doesn't spend necessarily.
But it may require a lot of elapsed time
waiting for every other core to context switch.
So depending on the mix of reason writes
and how much work was being done inside the read critical section,
the performance increase varies tremendously,
from a much much faster,
if these critical sections were short and there's few writes too,
perhaps even slower, if writes are very common.
And so when people apply RCU to kernel stuff,
actually you absolutely have to do performance tests against a bunch of workloads
in order to figure out whether using RCU is a win for you,
because, so depending on the workload.
I have a maybe a tangential question,
but we've seen that,
I guess when there's multiple cores being used,
there's some added complexity to our usual implementations,
and it's often the these atomic instructions kind of come to the rescue
and that's assuming there's one shared memory system,
but I wonder like
what happens if a machine is trying to maintain like multiple RAM systems,
how does it unify those.
The ordinary,
well, at a, at a at the level we're talking about,
the machine has one RAM system.
Okay, that's you know,
yeah, it's, for all those sort of ordinary computers,
you would buy that multiple cores,
you can pretty much program
as if there were just one RAM system shared among all the cores,
that's the logical model the hardware provides you,
at physical levels not like that often.
There's plenty of machines out there that have this physical arrangement,
we have a CPU chip,
so here's one CPU chip,
maybe with lots of cores on it, right.
And you get CPU chips with,
I don't know how many cores these days, say 32 cores,
let's say you want to build a 64 core machine,
you can only buy 32 core chips,
well you can make a board that has two sockets for chips on it,
so now we have two chips,
the fastest way to get at memory is
to have the memory more or less as directly attached to the CPU chip as possible,
so what you would do is you'd have like a very fat set of wires here,
to right next to the chip a bunch of RAM.
So it has direct access
and of course this chips going to want its own RAM also, right.
So so this is,
I'm just drawing a picture of what you would see,
if you opened up a PC with two processor chips and RAM.
But now we're faced with a problem,
what happens if a software over on this chip,
uses a memory location it's actually stored in this RAM.
So in fact there's also a interconnect between these two chips,
generally an extremely fast interconnect,
like gigabytes per second,
and the chips are smart enough
to know that certain physical memory locations are in this bank of RAM,
and other physical locations, physical memory addresses are in this bank of RAM,
of software here uses a physical address is over this one,
the chip is clever enough to send a message,
basically little network,
send a message over this chip,
look I need to read some RAM, please do it,
go read its RAM and send the result back.
You can buy four chip arrangements
with the same thing with a complex interconnect like this,
there's a huge amount of engineering going on
in order to map the straightforward shared RAM model
onto what sort of feasible to build with high performance in real life,
and fit in two or three dimensions.
Is that answer your question?
Yeah, yeah, that provides a lot of context, thank you.
Okay.
Yeah, any questions on the actual technique?
Alright so,
as, I'm sure you've got the sense of RCU is not universally applicable,
there's not,
you can't just take every situation in which using spin locks
and getting bad parallel performance
and convert it to RCU and get better performance,
because, the main reason it completely doesn't help writes makes them slower.
You know really only helps performance,
if if the reads outnumber the writes considerably.
It has this restriction that
you can't hold pointers to protect the data across sleep,
which just makes some kind of code quite awkward,
if you actually need to sleep,
you may then need to re-lookup whatever it is.
So you know to do another RCU critical section after the sleep completes,
in order to look again
for, for the data that you originally were looking at,
assuming it's still even exists,
so it just makes code a bit more complicated.
The data structures, the most straightforward way to apply it is,
the data structures that have a structure,
that's amenable to single committing writes for updates,
you can't modify things in place, so you have to replace stuff,
so you know list and trees,
but not more complex data structures,
the paper mentioned some more complicated ways like sequence locks,
to be able to update stuff in place,
despite readers that aren't using locks,
but they are getting more complicated
and the situations under which they actually improve performance are more restricted.
Another subtle problem is that,
readers can see stale data,
without any obvious bound on how long they can see stale data for,
because if some reader gets a pointer to a RCU protected object,
just before a writer replaces it,
the reader may still hold on to that data for quite a long time,
at least on the scale of modern computer instructions,
and a lot of the time, this turns out not to matter much,
but the paper mentioned some situations which I actually don't really understand,
in which people expect writes to actually take effect after the write completes,
and therefore, which readers see stale data is a bit of a surprise.
You may also,
as a separate topic,
wonder what happens if you have write heavy data,
like RCU is all about read heavy data,
but that's just one of many situations you might care about,
for getting parallel performance,
they also care about write heavy data.
Actually, in the extremes, in some extreme cases of write heavy data,
you can do quite well,
there's no technique I know of for write heavy data,
that's quite as universally applicable as RCU,
but there are still ideas for coping with data that's mostly written.
The most powerful idea is to restructure your data,
restructure the data structure, so it's not shared,
and sometimes you can do,
that sometimes the sharing is just completely gratuitous,
and you can get rid of it once you realize it's a problem.
But it's also often the case,
that the that while you do sometimes need to have shared data,
that the common case doesn't require different cores to write the same data,
even though they need to write some of the data a lot.
And you've actually seen that in the labs,
in the locking lab,
in the kalloc part of the lab,
you restructured the free list,
so that each core has a dedicated free list,
thus converting a write heavy data structure the free list
into one that was a semi-private per core,
so most of the times cores just have to,
they don't conflict with other cores,
because they have their own private free list
and the only time you have to look at other free lists is,
if your free list runs out.
There are actually many examples
of this way of dealing with write heavy data in the kernel,
thinking the allocator Linux is like this,
Linux's scheduling lists.
There's a separate set of threads for each core,
that the scheduler looks at most of the time,
and cores only have to look at each others scheduling list,
they run out of work to do.
Another example is statistics counters,
if you're counting something
and the counts go change a lot, but they're rarely read,
that is the counts are truly dominated by writes not reads,
you can restructure your counter,
so that each core has a separate counter,
and so each core just modifies its own counter,
when it needs to change the count,
and if you want to read something,
then you have to go out
and lock and read all the per core counters,
so that's a technique to make writes very fast.
Because the writers just modify the local per core counter,
but the reads are now very slow,
and you know, but if your counters are write heavy
as just the counters often are.
That could be a big win
shifting the work now to the reads.
So the point is there are techniques,
even though we didn't talk about that much,
there are also sometimes techniques that help for write intensive workloads.
To wrap up the RCU,
the stuff we read about in the paper
is actually a giant success story for Linux,
is used all over Linux to get at all kinds of different data,
because it just turns out that
read and read mostly data read intensive data, it's extremely common,
like cached file blocks, for example are mostly read,
so a technique that speeds up only reads is a really very widely applicable.
And RCU is particularly magic,
there's lots of other interesting concurrency techniques, synchronization techniques,
RCU is magic,
because it completely eliminates locking and writing for the readers,
so it's just a big breakthrough
compared to things like read write locks,
which were the previous state of the art.
And the key idea that really makes it work is the,
sort of garbage collection,
like deferring a freeze for what they call the grace period,
until all the readers are guaranteed to be finished using the data,
so you can all as well as the synchronization technique,
it's actually fair to view it as a very much,
so as a kind of a specialized garbage collection technique.
And that is all I have to say,
so I'm happy to take questions.
Oh, sorry, can you explain the stale data for readers,
so I don't understand why how that can happen,
because you you're reading your critical section,
and, you just get whatever data is there at that point,
and then you just.
It actually usually is not a problem,
but the reason why ever might come up,
well ordinarily, you know if you have code that says x equals 1,
and then you know print done,
gosh, it's pretty surprising,
if after this point,
someone reading the data, sees that value before you set it to 1.
Right, that's a maybe a bit of a surprise, right.
Well, there's a sense in which RCU allows that to happen, right,
if this is really what we're really talking about is,
you know list_replace whatever you know find the element that has 1
and change it to 2,
with using RCU, right,
after that finishes, we print, oh yeah we're done,
if there's some reader that was looking at the list, right,
they may have you know just gotten to the list element,
that held one, that we replaced with 2,
and then a good deal longer,
you know, and then they do the actual read of the list element,
you know they look at
whatever the content is in the list element after we've done this,
you know they're reading the list element,
only at this point later in time,
and they see the old value,
so if you're not prepared for this,
this is a little bit odd now.
I mean they, they may even do a memory barrier right,
I mean it's not a memory barrier issue, is just like.
And indeed, most of the time, it doesn't matter.
I see, so this is when this replace is very close,
so like they read somehow like starts before the replace,
but it is takes a while, and.
Yes, yeah, the reader if the reader is slower than the writer or something.
Now, you know, I think this mostly doesn't matter,
because after all, the reader and the writer were acting concurrently
and you know two things happen concurrently,
usually you, you would never have imagined
that you could have been guaranteed much about the exact order,
if the two operations were invoked concurrently.
The paper claims,
I mean, the paper as an example in which they said it matters,
it turned out to cause a real problem,
although I don't really understand why that was.
I see, this makes sense,
and my other question was,
it's called a RCU because of idea one, is that right.
Read copy update, yes,
I believe it's because of idea one,
that is that instead of modifying things in place,
you make a copy and you sort of copy
not the that's the real thing.
Right, this makes sense, thank you so much.
Yes.
So at the beginning of lecture
or towards the beginning we talked about the of n squared [runtime]
for the cache coherence protocols,
for updating the read write locks,
isn't this also a problem with spin locks, where.
Yeah, okay,
so so what is the reason,
why we didn't discuss that aspect.
Why we didn't.
Yeah or like,
is there a reason that that still exists
or are like what do spin locks do to address that.
Okay.
Locks are hideously expensive,
if there are standard spin locks, like xv6 has,
are extremely fast, if the lock is not particularly contended,
and terribly slow, if lots of cores try to get the same lock at the same time.
Okay, yeah, this is one of the things that makes life interesting,
and you know there's,
yeah, I mean there's there's locks that are a better scaling,
but worse,
they have better high load performance,
but worse low load performance.
Okay thanks.
But I'm not aware of a lock that is,
anyway, it's hard it's hard to get this stuff, right,
it's hard to get good performance on these machines.
Other questions?
This might be unrelated,
but can there ever be a lock of games between multiple different systems,
like like not just contained to one system,
maybe like multiple servers perhaps.
There are absolutely distributed systems,
in which there's a sort of locking,
in which that sort of universal locks spans multiple machines,
when places comes up in distributed databases
where the data you've met you display your data over multiple servers,
but if you have a transaction,
that uses data this you know different pieces of data on different servers,
you need gonna need to [collect] locks.
They were in,
you need to basically collect locks from multiple servers.
Another place that comes up,
although there's been a number of systems
that are essentially tried to mimic shared memory across independent machines,
with the machines,
if I use some memory that's in your machine,
then there's some infrastructure stuff
that causes my machine to talk to your machine
and ask for the memory,
and you know then the game is usually
to run existing parallel programs on a cluster of workstations
instead of on a big multi-core machine,
hoping this is going to be cheaper.
And you know something needs to be done about spin locks there
or whatever locking you're going to use.
And so people have invented various ways
to make the locking work out well in that case too.
You using techniques that are not often not quite the same as this,
although the pressure to avoid,
the pressure to avoid costs is even higher in that piece.
Anything else?
Thank you.
You're welcome.